<file1>
<first>
Sample Type / Medical Specialty:Office Notes

Sample Name:Chest Pain - Office Note(adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({}); | var addthis_config = {"data_track_clickback":true}; View this sample in Blog format on MedicalTranscriptionSamples.com (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({}); var addthis_config = {"data_track_clickback":true}; Sample Type / Medical Specialty: Office Notes
 Sample Name: Chest Pain - Office Note Description: Patient with a family history of premature coronary artery disease came in for evaluation of recurrent chest pain
 (Medical Transcription Sample Report)
 DISCHARGE DIAGNOSES: 1.  Chest pain.  The patient ruled out for myocardial infarction on serial troponins.  Result of nuclear stress test is pending.
 2.  Elevated liver enzymes, etiology uncertain for an outpatient followup.
 3.  Acid reflux disease.
 TEST DONE: Nuclear stress test, results of which are pending.
 HOSPITAL COURSE: This 32-year-old with family history of premature coronary artery disease came in for evaluation of recurrent chest pain, O2 saturation at 94% with both atypical and typical features of ischemia.  The patient ruled out for myocardial infarction with serial troponins.  Nuclear stress test has been done, results of which are pending.  The patient is stable to be discharged pending the results of nuclear stress test and cardiologist's recommendations.  He will follow up with cardiologist, Dr. X, in two weeks and with his primary physician in two to four weeks.  Discharge medications will depend on results of nuclear stress test.
 (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({}); (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({}); Keywords: office notes, chest pain, serial troponins, premature coronary artery disease, coronary artery disease, nuclear stress test, stress test,
 NOTE : These
            transcribed medical transcription sample reports and examples are provided by various users and
            are for reference purpose only. MTHelpLine does not certify accuracy and quality of sample reports.
            These transcribed medical transcription sample reports may include some uncommon or unusual formats;
            this would be due to the preference of the dictating physician. All names and dates have been
            changed (or removed) to keep confidentiality. Any resemblance of any type of name or date or
            place or anything else to real world is purely incidental.</first>
</file1>