<file1>
<first>
TITLE: Pemphigus
ABOUT: Pemphigus is a type of disease where the body’s immune system attacks healthy cells in the top layer of skin (epidermis). It causes blisters on the skin and in the mouth, nose, throat, eyes, and genitals. Some forms of pemphigus can cause death if not treated. Pemphigus causes blisters on the skin and in the mouth, nose, throat, eyes, and genitals. Your immune system makes antibodies, which attack viruses and harmful bacteria. With pemphigus, antibodies instead attack healthy cells in the skin or mucous membranes. As a result, Skin cells separate from each other. 
 Fluid collects between skin layers. 
 Blisters form and may cover a large area of skin. The cause of this immune system attack is not known. Pemphigus does not spread from person to person. It does not appear to be passed from parent to child. But some people’s genes put them more at risk for pemphigus. Early diagnosis is important, so see your doctor if you have long-lasting blisters on the skin or mouth. Pemphigus is rare, and your doctor may test for other diseases first. The doctor should do all of these tests. No single test is right all the time. A complete history and physical exam. 
 Remove a sample of a blister and look at with a microscope. 
 Do chemical tests on a skin sample to determine the type of pemphigus. 
 A blood sample to measure pemphigus antibody levels. Pemphigus is treated with medicines that: Control the immune system. 
 Treat infections. These medicines can have major side effects. Ask your doctor to tell you about them. Tell each doctor you see about the medicines you take. Doctors who treat pemphigus include: Dermatologists, who treat skin problems. 
 Dentists, who can tell you how to take care of your gums and teeth if you have blisters in your mouth.
SYMPTOMS:Pemphigus causes blisters on the skin and in the mouth, nose, throat, eyes, and genitals.
CAUSES:Your immune system makes antibodies, which attack viruses and harmful bacteria. With pemphigus, antibodies instead attack healthy cells in the skin or mucous membranes. As a result, Skin cells separate from each other. 
 Fluid collects between skin layers. 
 Blisters form and may cover a large area of skin. The cause of this immune system attack is not known. Pemphigus does not spread from person to person. It does not appear to be passed from parent to child. But some people’s genes put them more at risk for pemphigus.
TREATMENT:Pemphigus is treated with medicines that: Control the immune system. 
 Treat infections. These medicines can have major side effects. Ask your doctor to tell you about them. Tell each doctor you see about the medicines you take.
DIAGNOSIS:Early diagnosis is important, so see your doctor if you have long-lasting blisters on the skin or mouth. Pemphigus is rare, and your doctor may test for other diseases first. The doctor should do all of these tests. No single test is right all the time. A complete history and physical exam. 
 Remove a sample of a blister and look at with a microscope. 
 Do chemical tests on a skin sample to determine the type of pemphigus. 
 A blood sample to measure pemphigus antibody levels.
PREVENTION:Pemphigus is rarely fatal. Most people with pemphigus can control it with medicines. But pemphigus and its treatments can cause: Lost time at work. 
 Weight loss. 
 Loss of sleep. 
 Stress. Support groups can help you cope with the disease.
SPECIALIST:Doctors who treat pemphigus include: Dermatologists, who treat skin problems. 
 Dentists, who can tell you how to take care of your gums and teeth if you have blisters in your mouth.
EPIDEMIOLOGY:Pemphigus affects people of all races and cultures. Groups at higher risk are: People of Mediterranean descent. 
 Eastern European Jews. 
 People who live in the rainforests of Brazil. Men and women both get pemphigus at the same rate. It is most common in middle-aged and older adults. But it can occur in young adults and children.</first>
</diseases>