<file1>
<first>
TITLE: Arthritis
ABOUT: "Arthritis" literally means joint inflammation. Although joint inflammation is a symptom or sign rather than a specific diagnosis, the term arthritis is often used to refer to any disorder that affects the joints. Joints are places where two bones meet, such as your elbow or knee. There are different types of arthritis. In some diseases in which arthritis occurs, other organs, such as your eyes, heart, or skin, can also be affected. Fortunately, current treatments allow most people with arthritis to lead active and productive lives. Symptoms of arthritis can include: Pain, redness, heat, and swelling in your joints.  
 Trouble moving around. 
 Fever. 
 Weight loss. 
 Breathing problems. 
 Rash or itch. These symptoms may also be signs of other illnesses. There are probably many genes that make people more likely to have arthritis. Research has found some of these genes. If you have the gene linked with arthritis, something in your environment—such as a virus or injury—may trigger the condition. To diagnosis you with arthritis or another rheumatic disease, your doctor may: Ask you about your medical history. 
 Give you a physical exam. 
 Take samples for a laboratory test. 
 Take x-rays. There are many treatments that can help relieve pain and help you live with arthritis. You should talk to your doctor about the best treatments for you, which can include: Medications to relieve pain, slow the condition, and prevent further damage. 
 Surgery to repair joint damage or relieve pain. Doctors who diagnose and treat arthritis and other rheumatic disease include: A general practitioner, such as your family doctor. 
 A rheumatologist, who treats arthritis and other diseases of the bones, joints, and muscles.
SYMPTOMS:Symptoms of arthritis can include: Pain, redness, heat, and swelling in your joints.  
 Trouble moving around. 
 Fever. 
 Weight loss. 
 Breathing problems. 
 Rash or itch. These symptoms may also be signs of other illnesses.
CAUSES:There are probably many genes that make people more likely to have arthritis. Research has found some of these genes. If you have the gene linked with arthritis, something in your environment—such as a virus or injury—may trigger the condition.
TREATMENT:There are many treatments that can help relieve pain and help you live with arthritis. You should talk to your doctor about the best treatments for you, which can include: Medications to relieve pain, slow the condition, and prevent further damage. 
 Surgery to repair joint damage or relieve pain.
DIAGNOSIS:To diagnosis you with arthritis or another rheumatic disease, your doctor may: Ask you about your medical history. 
 Give you a physical exam. 
 Take samples for a laboratory test. 
 Take x-rays.
PREVENTION:There are many things you can do to help you live with arthritis and other rheumatic diseases, including: Take your medications when and how you’re supposed to. 
 Exercise to reduce joint pain and stiffness. It also helps with losing weight, which reduces stress on the joints. You should speak to your doctor about a safe, well-rounded exercise program. 
 Use heat and cold therapies to reduce joint pain and swelling. 
 Try relaxation therapy to help reduce pain by learning ways to relax your muscles. 
 Use splints and braces to support weakened joints or allow them to rest. You should see your doctor to make sure your splint or brace fits well. 
 Use assistive devices, such as a cane or shoe insert, to ease pain when walking. Other devices can help you open a jar, close zippers, or hold pencils.
SPECIALIST:Doctors who diagnose and treat arthritis and other rheumatic disease include: A general practitioner, such as your family doctor. 
 A rheumatologist, who treats arthritis and other diseases of the bones, joints, and muscles.
EPIDEMIOLOGY:</first>
</diseases>