<file1>
<first>
TITLE: Rheumatoid Arthritis
ABOUT: Rheumatoid arthritis is a disease that affects your joints. Joints are where two or more bones join together, such as at your knees, hips, or shoulders. Rheumatoid arthritis causes pain, swelling, and stiffness. If joints on one side of your body have rheumatoid arthritis, usually those joints on the other side do too. This disease often occurs in more than one joint. It can affect any joint in the body. If you have this disease, you also may feel sick and tired, and sometimes get fevers.   Symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis, which can range from mild to severe, include: Tender, warm, swollen joints. 
 Swollen joints on both sides of the body, such as in both your right and left wrist. 
 Swollen joints often in the wrist and finger joints closest to the hand. 
 Swollen joints sometimes in other joints, including the neck, shoulders, elbows, hips, knees, ankles, and feet. 
 Feeling tired and having low energy. 
 Fevers. 
 Pain and stiffness lasting for more than 30 minutes in the morning or after a long rest. 
 Symptoms that last for many years. Doctors don't know the exact cause of rheumatoid arthritis. They know that with this type of arthritis, a person's immune system attacks his or her own body tissues. The immune system normally attacks invaders to the body, such as a cold virus or bacteria. Researchers are learning many things about why and how this happens. Things that may cause rheumatoid arthritis are: Genes (passed from parent to child). 
 Environmental factors. 
 Hormones. Rheumatoid arthritis can be hard to diagnose because: There is no single test for the disease. 
 The symptoms can be the same as in other kinds of joint disease. 
 The full symptoms can take time to develop. To diagnose rheumatoid arthritis, doctors use medical history, a physical exam, x-rays and other imaging tests, and lab tests. Doctors have many ways to treat rheumatoid arthritis. Treatment may involve: Medicine. 
 Surgery. 
 Regular doctor visits. 
 Complementary therapies. The goals of treatment are to: Take away pain. 
 Reduce swelling. 
 Slow down or stop joint damage. 
 Help you feel better. 
 Help you stay active. Most people with rheumatoid arthritis take medicine. Drugs can be used for pain relief, to reduce swelling, and to stop the disease from getting worse. What a doctor prescribes depends on: Your general health. 
 How serious the rheumatoid arthritis is. 
 How serious the rheumatoid arthritis may become. 
 How long you will take the drug. 
 How well the drug works. 
 Possible side effects. There are many kinds of surgery for people with a lot of joint damage. Surgery may: Reduce your pain. 
 Help your joint work better. 
 Help you be able to do daily activities. Surgery is not for everyone. Talk with your doctor to decide what is best for you. Regular medical care is important so doctors can: See if the disease is getting worse. 
 See if drugs are helping. 
 Discuss any drug side effects. 
 Change treatment when needed. Special diets, vitamins, and other complementary therapies are sometimes suggested to treat rheumatoid arthritis.  Many of these treatments are not harmful, but they may not be well tested or have any real benefits. Ask your doctor about things you can do to manage your pain, such as exercise programs, support groups, and education classes. Before starting any complementary therapy, talk with your doctor to make sure it isn’t harmful. Several types of health care professionals may treat you, including:  Internist, who diagnoses and treats adults. 
 Rheumatologist, who treats arthritis and other disease of the bones, joints, and muscles. 
 Orthopaedists, who treat and perform surgery for bone and joint diseases. 
 Physical therapists, who help to improve joint function. 
 Occupational therapists, who teach ways to protect joints, reduce pain, perform activities of daily living, and conserve energy. 
 Dietitians, who teach ways to use a good diet to improve health and maintain a healthy weight.
SYMPTOMS:Symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis, which can range from mild to severe, include: Tender, warm, swollen joints. 
 Swollen joints on both sides of the body, such as in both your right and left wrist. 
 Swollen joints often in the wrist and finger joints closest to the hand. 
 Swollen joints sometimes in other joints, including the neck, shoulders, elbows, hips, knees, ankles, and feet. 
 Feeling tired and having low energy. 
 Fevers. 
 Pain and stiffness lasting for more than 30 minutes in the morning or after a long rest. 
 Symptoms that last for many years.
CAUSES:Doctors don't know the exact cause of rheumatoid arthritis. They know that with this type of arthritis, a person's immune system attacks his or her own body tissues. The immune system normally attacks invaders to the body, such as a cold virus or bacteria. Researchers are learning many things about why and how this happens. Things that may cause rheumatoid arthritis are: Genes (passed from parent to child). 
 Environmental factors. 
 Hormones.
TREATMENT:Doctors have many ways to treat rheumatoid arthritis. Treatment may involve: Medicine. 
 Surgery. 
 Regular doctor visits. 
 Complementary therapies. The goals of treatment are to: Take away pain. 
 Reduce swelling. 
 Slow down or stop joint damage. 
 Help you feel better. 
 Help you stay active. Most people with rheumatoid arthritis take medicine. Drugs can be used for pain relief, to reduce swelling, and to stop the disease from getting worse. What a doctor prescribes depends on: Your general health. 
 How serious the rheumatoid arthritis is. 
 How serious the rheumatoid arthritis may become. 
 How long you will take the drug. 
 How well the drug works. 
 Possible side effects. There are many kinds of surgery for people with a lot of joint damage. Surgery may: Reduce your pain. 
 Help your joint work better. 
 Help you be able to do daily activities. Surgery is not for everyone. Talk with your doctor to decide what is best for you. Regular medical care is important so doctors can: See if the disease is getting worse. 
 See if drugs are helping. 
 Discuss any drug side effects. 
 Change treatment when needed. Special diets, vitamins, and other complementary therapies are sometimes suggested to treat rheumatoid arthritis.  Many of these treatments are not harmful, but they may not be well tested or have any real benefits. Ask your doctor about things you can do to manage your pain, such as exercise programs, support groups, and education classes. Before starting any complementary therapy, talk with your doctor to make sure it isn’t harmful.
DIAGNOSIS:Rheumatoid arthritis can be hard to diagnose because: There is no single test for the disease. 
 The symptoms can be the same as in other kinds of joint disease. 
 The full symptoms can take time to develop. To diagnose rheumatoid arthritis, doctors use medical history, a physical exam, x-rays and other imaging tests, and lab tests.
PREVENTION:With rheumatoid arthritis, you can still lead a full life. Besides going to your doctor and therapists regularly, you can also do these activities to help reduce your symptoms. Look for ways to reduce stress on your joints. Some people find wearing a splint around a painful joint for a short time helps. Talk with your doctor to see if a splint may work for you. In addition, some special equipment can help such as a zipper puller or long-handled shoe horn. Keep a good balance between rest and activity. Try to take frequent breaks, especially when your symptoms are bothering you. Try to lower your stress by taking the time to relax, doing hobbies you enjoy, or joining a support group. Support groups can reduce your stress by helping you to: Learn about the disease. 
 Cope with your emotions about your symptoms. 
 Feel more control over the disease. 
 Build confidence. Eat a healthy diet which will help you manage your weight and get a variety of nutrients for overall health.
SPECIALIST:Several types of health care professionals may treat you, including:  Internist, who diagnoses and treats adults. 
 Rheumatologist, who treats arthritis and other disease of the bones, joints, and muscles. 
 Orthopaedists, who treat and perform surgery for bone and joint diseases. 
 Physical therapists, who help to improve joint function. 
 Occupational therapists, who teach ways to protect joints, reduce pain, perform activities of daily living, and conserve energy. 
 Dietitians, who teach ways to use a good diet to improve health and maintain a healthy weight.
EPIDEMIOLOGY:Anyone can get this disease, though it occurs more often in women. Rheumatoid arthritis often starts in middle age and is common in older people. But children and young adults can also get it.</first>
</diseases>