<file1>
<first>
TITLE: Shoulder Problems
ABOUT: Most shoulder problems happen when soft tissues in the joint and shoulder region break down. The symptoms of your shoulder problems will depend on the specific type of problem you are having. The signs and symptoms of dislocation in the shoulder include: Pain. 
 Swelling. 
 Numbness. 
 Weakness. 
 Bruising. 
 The arm appears out of position. The signs and symptoms of shoulder separation include: Pain and tenderness. 
 A bump in the middle of the top of the shoulder. The signs and symptoms of rotator cuff disease may be due to tendinitis or bursitis and may include a slow onset of pain: In the upper part of your arm. 
 When trying to sleep on your shoulder. 
 That travels down your arm. 
 That worsens when you lift your arm away from the body or over your head. The signs and symptoms of a torn rotator cuff include: Pain in the muscle in the top of the arm and the outer shoulder. 
 Increased pain when lifting the arm or extending it out and lowering the arm back down. 
 Weakness. 
 A popping or clicking noise when moving the shoulder. The signs and symptoms of a frozen shoulder include: Stiffness in the joint. 
 Tightness. 
 Unable to lift the arm. The signs and symptoms of a fracture include: Severe pain. 
 Redness. 
 Bruising. 
 The bones may appear out of position. The signs and symptoms of arthritis of the shoulder include: Pain. 
 Decrease in shoulder motion. Most shoulder problems happen when the soft tissues in the shoulder break down. This can happen when you: Repeat the same motion with your shoulder. 
 Age. 
 Use the shoulder too much, especially if you are older. 
 Perform manual labor. 
 Injure the shoulder, sometimes from playing sports or falling. Doctors diagnose shoulder problems by: Asking about your medical history. 
 Performing a physical exam. 
 Ordering tests, such as:
 X-rays. 
 Ultrasound. 
 Magnetic resonance imaging or MRI. Treatment for a shoulder dislocation may also include: Your doctor placing the ball of your upper arm back into the socket. 
 Wearing a sling or device to keep your shoulder in place. 
 Exercises to improve
 Range of motion. 
 Strengthen muscles. 
 Prevent injuries. 
 Surgery if you injure the tissues or nerves around the shoulder. Treatment for a shoulder separation may also include: A sling to keep your shoulder in place. 
 Exercise, after a time of rest. 
 Surgery if the tear is severe. Treatment for tendinitis and bursitis includes: Medicines such as aspirin and ibuprofen to help lower your pain and swelling 
 Ultrasound to warm deep tissues and improve blood flow to the area of your injury. 
 Injection of a corticosteroid drug if your shoulder is not getting better. 
 Surgery if after 6 to 12 months your shoulder is not better. Treatment for a rotator cuff tear may also include: Heat or cold to the sore area of your injury. 
 Medicines to help your pain and swelling. 
 Electrical stimulation of your muscles and nerves. 
 Ultrasound to warm deep tissues and improve blood flow to the area of your injury. 
 Injection of a cortisone medicine into your shoulder joint. 
 Surgery to repair the tear if you don’t see improvement with other treatments. Treatment for a frozen shoulder may also include: Medicines to help with pain and swelling. 
 Heat to the sore area. 
 Stretching exercises. 
 Nerve and muscle stimulation using a transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS). 
 Injection of a corticosteroid drug if your shoulder is not better. 
 Surgery if the shoulder does not improve with other treatments. Treatment for a fracture may include: A doctor putting the bones into a position to promote healing. 
 A sling or other device to keep the bones in place. 
 After the bone heals, exercise to strengthen the shoulder and restore movement. 
 Surgery. Treatment for arthritis may include: Medicines to help with pain and swelling. 
 Physical therapy. If you injure a shoulder, try the following: Rest. Don’t use your shoulder for 48 hours 
 Ice. Put an ice pack on your injured shoulder for 20 minutes, four to eight times per day. You can use a:
 Cold pack. 
 Ice bag. 
 Plastic bag filled with crushed ice wrapped in a towel. 
 Compression. Put even pressure or compression on the painful area to help reduce the swelling to your shoulder. A wrap or bandage will help hold your shoulder in place. 
 Elevation. If you are able, keep the injured area above the level of your heart. Using a pillow under your shoulder will help.
SYMPTOMS:The symptoms of your shoulder problems will depend on the specific type of problem you are having. The signs and symptoms of dislocation in the shoulder include: Pain. 
 Swelling. 
 Numbness. 
 Weakness. 
 Bruising. 
 The arm appears out of position. The signs and symptoms of shoulder separation include: Pain and tenderness. 
 A bump in the middle of the top of the shoulder. The signs and symptoms of rotator cuff disease may be due to tendinitis or bursitis and may include a slow onset of pain: In the upper part of your arm. 
 When trying to sleep on your shoulder. 
 That travels down your arm. 
 That worsens when you lift your arm away from the body or over your head. The signs and symptoms of a torn rotator cuff include: Pain in the muscle in the top of the arm and the outer shoulder. 
 Increased pain when lifting the arm or extending it out and lowering the arm back down. 
 Weakness. 
 A popping or clicking noise when moving the shoulder. The signs and symptoms of a frozen shoulder include: Stiffness in the joint. 
 Tightness. 
 Unable to lift the arm. The signs and symptoms of a fracture include: Severe pain. 
 Redness. 
 Bruising. 
 The bones may appear out of position. The signs and symptoms of arthritis of the shoulder include: Pain. 
 Decrease in shoulder motion.
CAUSES:Most shoulder problems happen when the soft tissues in the shoulder break down. This can happen when you: Repeat the same motion with your shoulder. 
 Age. 
 Use the shoulder too much, especially if you are older. 
 Perform manual labor. 
 Injure the shoulder, sometimes from playing sports or falling.
TREATMENT:Treatment for a shoulder dislocation may also include: Your doctor placing the ball of your upper arm back into the socket. 
 Wearing a sling or device to keep your shoulder in place. 
 Exercises to improve
 Range of motion. 
 Strengthen muscles. 
 Prevent injuries. 
 Surgery if you injure the tissues or nerves around the shoulder. Treatment for a shoulder separation may also include: A sling to keep your shoulder in place. 
 Exercise, after a time of rest. 
 Surgery if the tear is severe. Treatment for tendinitis and bursitis includes: Medicines such as aspirin and ibuprofen to help lower your pain and swelling 
 Ultrasound to warm deep tissues and improve blood flow to the area of your injury. 
 Injection of a corticosteroid drug if your shoulder is not getting better. 
 Surgery if after 6 to 12 months your shoulder is not better. Treatment for a rotator cuff tear may also include: Heat or cold to the sore area of your injury. 
 Medicines to help your pain and swelling. 
 Electrical stimulation of your muscles and nerves. 
 Ultrasound to warm deep tissues and improve blood flow to the area of your injury. 
 Injection of a cortisone medicine into your shoulder joint. 
 Surgery to repair the tear if you don’t see improvement with other treatments. Treatment for a frozen shoulder may also include: Medicines to help with pain and swelling. 
 Heat to the sore area. 
 Stretching exercises. 
 Nerve and muscle stimulation using a transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS). 
 Injection of a corticosteroid drug if your shoulder is not better. 
 Surgery if the shoulder does not improve with other treatments. Treatment for a fracture may include: A doctor putting the bones into a position to promote healing. 
 A sling or other device to keep the bones in place. 
 After the bone heals, exercise to strengthen the shoulder and restore movement. 
 Surgery. Treatment for arthritis may include: Medicines to help with pain and swelling. 
 Physical therapy. If you injure a shoulder, try the following: Rest. Don’t use your shoulder for 48 hours 
 Ice. Put an ice pack on your injured shoulder for 20 minutes, four to eight times per day. You can use a:
 Cold pack. 
 Ice bag. 
 Plastic bag filled with crushed ice wrapped in a towel. 
 Compression. Put even pressure or compression on the painful area to help reduce the swelling to your shoulder. A wrap or bandage will help hold your shoulder in place. 
 Elevation. If you are able, keep the injured area above the level of your heart. Using a pillow under your shoulder will help.
DIAGNOSIS:Doctors diagnose shoulder problems by: Asking about your medical history. 
 Performing a physical exam. 
 Ordering tests, such as:
 X-rays. 
 Ultrasound. 
 Magnetic resonance imaging or MRI.
PREVENTION:
SPECIALIST:
EPIDEMIOLOGY:Men, women, and children can have shoulder problems. They occur in people of all races and ethnic backgrounds.</first>
</diseases>