<file1>
<first>\nTITLE:Menopause



ABOUT: 
The menopause is when a woman stops having periods and is no longer able to get pregnant naturally.
Periods usually start to become less frequent over a few months or years before they stop altogether. Sometimes they can stop suddenly.
The menopause is a natural part of ageing that usually occurs between 45 and 55 years of age, as a woman's oestrogen levels decline. In the UK, the average age for a woman to reach the menopause is 51.
However, around 1 in 100 women experience the menopause before 40 years of age. This is known as premature menopause or premature ovarian insufficiency.
SYMPTOMS: Most women will experience menopausal symptoms. Some of these can be quite severe and have a significant impact on your everyday activities.
Common symptoms include:

hot flushes
night sweats
vaginal dryness and discomfort during sex
difficulty sleeping
low mood or anxiety
reduced sex drive (libido)
problems with memory and concentration
Menopausal symptoms can begin months or even years before your periods stop and last around four years after your last period, although some women experience them for much longer.
Read more about the
symptoms of the menopause
When to see your GP
It's worth talking to your GP if you have menopausal symptoms that are troubling you or if you're experiencing symptoms of the menopause before 45 years of age.
Your GP can usually confirm whether you are menopausal based on your symptoms, but a 
blood test to measure your hormone levels may be carried out if you're aged 40 to 45.
Blood tests may also be carried out to help diagnose suspected premature menopause if you’re under 40 and have menopausal symptoms.
Treatments for menopausal symptoms
Your GP can offer treatments and suggest lifestyle changes if you have severe menopausal symptoms that interfere with your day-to-day life, including:

hormone replacement therapy (HRT) – tablets, skin patches, gels and implants that relieve menopausal symptoms by replacing oestrogen
vaginal oestrogen creams, lubricants or moisturisers for vaginal dryness
cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) – a type of talking therapy that can help with low mood and anxiety
eating a 
healthy, balanced diet and
exercising regularly – maintaining a healthy weight and staying fit and strong can improve some menopausal symptoms
Your GP can refer you to a menopause specialist if your symptoms don't improve after trying treatment or if you're unable to take HRT.
Read more about
treating the menopause
What causes the menopause?
The menopause is caused by a change in the balance of the body's sex hormones, which occurs as you get older.
It happens when your ovaries stop producing as much of the hormone oestrogen and no longer release an egg each month.
Premature or early menopause can occur at any age, and in many cases, there's no clear cause.
Sometimes it's caused by a treatment such as surgery to remove the ovaries (oophorectomy), some 
breast cancertreatments,
chemotherapy or
radiotherapy, or it can be brought on by an underlying medical condition, such as
Down's syndrome or 
Addison's disease.

SYMPTOMS: 
Most women will experience some symptoms around the menopause. The duration and severity of these symptoms varies from woman to woman.
Symptoms usually start a few months or years before your periods stop, known as the perimenopause, and can persist for some time afterwards.
On average, most symptoms last around four years from your last period. However, around 1 in every 10 women experience them for up to 12 years.
If you experience the menopause suddenly rather than gradually – for example, as a result of cancer treatment – your symptoms may be worse.
Changes to your periods
The first sign of the menopause is usually a change in the normal pattern of your periods.
You may start having either unusually light or
heavy periods.
The frequency of your periods may also be affected. You may have one every two or three weeks, or you may not have one for months at a time.
Eventually, you'll stop having periods altogether.
Common menopausal symptoms
About 8 in every 10 women will have additional symptoms for some time before and after their periods stop.
These can have a significant impact on daily life for some women.
Common symptoms include:

hot flushes – short, sudden feelings of heat, usually in the face, neck and chest, which can make your skin red and sweaty
night sweats – hot flushes that occur at night
difficulty sleeping – this may make you feel tired and irritable during the day
a
reduced sex drive (libido)
problems with memory and concentration
vaginal dryness and pain, itching or discomfort during sex
headaches
mood changes, such as 
low moodor anxiety
palpitations – heartbeats that suddenly become more noticeable
joint stiffness, aches and pains
reduced muscle mass
recurrent
urinary tract infections (UTIs), such as
cystitis
The menopause can also increase your risk of developing certain other problems, such as
weak bones (osteoporosis).
See your GP if you're finding your symptoms particularly troublesome, as treatments are available.
Read about
how to manage symptoms of the menopause

TREATMENT: 
Not all women want treatment to relieve
symptoms of the menopause, but treatments are available if you find the symptoms particularly troublesome.
The main treatment for menopausal symptoms is 
hormone replacement therapy (HRT), although other treatments are also available for some of the symptoms.
Hormone replacement therapy (HRT)
HRT involves taking oestrogen to replace the decline in your body's own levels around the time of the menopause. This can relieve many of the associated symptoms.
HRT has been out of favour since the early 2000s because of a link with breast cancer, but 
new guidelinesfrom the National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) say that HRT is effective and should be offered to women with menopausal symptoms, after discussing the risks and benefits.
There are two main types of HRT:

combined HRT (oestrogen and progestogen) – for women with menopausal symptoms who still have their womb (oestrogen taken on its own can otherwise increase your risk of 
womb cancer)
oestrogen-only HRT – for women who have had their womb removed in a 
hysterectomy
HRT is available as tablets, skin patches, a gel to rub into the skin or implants.
HRT is extremely effective at relieving menopausal symptoms, especially hot flushes and night sweats, but there are a number of side effects, including breast tenderness, 
headachesand vaginal bleeding. It's also associated with an increased risk of 
blood clotsand
breast cancer in some women.
HRT is not advisable for some women, such as those who have had certain types of breast cancer or are at high risk of getting breast cancer.
Your GP can give you more information about the risks and benefits of HRT to help you decide whether or not you want to take it.
Read more about 
HRT
Hot flushes and night sweats
If you experience hot flushes and night sweats as a result of the menopause, simple measures may sometimes help, such as:

wearing light clothing
keeping your bedroom cool at night
taking a cool shower, using a fan or having a cold drink
trying to 
reduce your stress levels
avoiding potential triggers, such as spicy food, caffeine, smoking and alcohol
taking regular 
exerciseand 
losing weightif you're overweight
If the flushes and sweats are frequent or severe, your GP may suggest taking HRT.
If HRT isn't suitable for you, or you would prefer not to have it, your GP may recommend other medications that can help, such as clonidine (a
high blood pressure medicine) or certain
antidepressants.
These medications can cause unpleasant side effects, so it's important to discuss the risks and benefits with your doctor before starting treatment.
Mood changes
Some women experience mood swings, low mood and anxiety around the time of the menopause.
Self-help measures such as getting plenty of rest, taking regular exercise and doing relaxing activities such as
yoga and tai chi may help. Medication and other treatments are also available, including HRT and cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT).
CBT is a type of talking therapy that can improve low mood and feelings of anxiety. Your GP may be able to refer you for CBT on the NHS, or recommend self-help options such as online CBT courses. 
Antidepressants may help if you've been diagnosed with
depression.
Reduced sexual desire
It's common for women to lose interest in sex around the time of the menopause, but HRT can often help with this. If HRT isn't effective, you might be offered a testosterone supplement.
Testosterone is the male sex hormone, but it can help to restore sex drive in menopausal women. It’s not currently licensed for use in women, although it can be prescribed by a doctor if they think it might help.
Possible side effects of testosterone supplements include 
acneand unwanted hair growth.
Read more about 
loss of libidoand
female sexual problems
Vaginal dryness and discomfort
If your vagina becomes dry, painful or itchy as a result of the menopause, your GP can prescribe oestrogen treatment that's put directly into your vagina as a pessary, cream or vaginal ring.
This can safely be used alongside HRT.
You'll usually need to use vaginal oestrogen indefinitely, as your symptoms are likely to return when treatment stops. However, side effects are very rare.
You can also use over-the-counter vaginal moisturisers or lubricants in addition to, or instead of, vaginal oestrogen.
Read more about 
vaginal dryness 
Weak bones
Women who have been through the menopause are at an increased risk of developing 
osteoporosis (weak bones)as a result of the lower level of oestrogen in the body.
You can reduce your chances of developing osteoporosis by:

taking HRT – HRT can help to prevent osteoporosis, although this effect doesn't tend to last after treatment stops
exercising regularly – including weight-bearing and resistance exercises
eating a healthy diet that includes plenty of fruit, vegetables and sources of 
calcium, such as low-fat milk and yoghurt
vitamin D, which can help to keep your bones strong
stopping smoking and cutting down on alcohol
taking calcium and/or vitamin D supplements if you don't feel you're getting enough of these – discuss this with your GP
Read more about 
menopause and bone healthand
preventing osteoporosis
Premature menopause
Premature menopause, also known as premature ovarian insufficiency, is when a woman experiences the menopause before the age of 40.
The two main treatments for early menopause are HRT and the
combined contraceptive pill, as they both contain oestrogen and progestogen.
These treatments can help to relieve troublesome menopausal symptoms and reduce the risk of problems such as osteoporosis.
Your doctor will normally recommend continuing treatment until at least around the time of natural menopause (45 to 55 years of age).
Follow-up appointments
If you're having treatment for your menopausal symptoms, you'll need to return to your GP for a follow-up review after three months, and once a year after that.
During your reviews, your GP may:

make sure your symptoms are under control
ask about any side effects and bleeding patterns
check your weight and blood pressure
review the type of HRT you're taking and make any necessary changes
discuss when you could stop treatment and how this could be done
Many women will need treatment for a few years, until most of their menopausal symptoms have passed.
</first>
</diseases>