<file1>
<first>\nTITLE:New or worsening back pain



Overview


Back pain that develops suddenly can be disabling at first, but will usually ease over time.
What to do
If you've developed back pain, or back and leg pain, in the last 48 hours:

take painkillers - this can help your pain and help you move
apply heat or cold - this can also help your pain
keep active - try and keep moving, even if you have to go carefully at first
do some back exercises - working out any tension, or stiffness, in your back can help you to keep active
You should also follow this advice if you back pain has got worse.
When to see your GP
You should speak to your GP as soon as possible if you have back pain and:  

find it difficult to pass or control urine
feel numbness or altered sensation around your back passage or genitals - such as wiping after the toilet
have pins and needles around your back passage or genitals - such as wiping after the toilet  
If your GP surgery is closed, phone 111.
 

Lower back pain: Self-help guide
If you are experiencing pain in your lower back, complete our self-help guide to assess your symptoms and find out what to do next.
Self-help guide: Lower back pain


Sitting and standing
If you have back pain, you may find it difficult to get out of bed or get up from a chair or the floor. There are some simple techniques you can use to make this easier and more comfortable.
If you've tried these techniques but still find it too painful or difficult to get off the floor, speak to your GP. If your GP surgery is closed, phone 111.

Getting off the floor

Acute back pain can sometimes be so sudden and severe that you end up on the floor and in too much pain to move. If this happens, there are techniques you can use to get back on your feet safely and in relative comfort.
How to get up from the floor
To get up safely from lying face down:

Bend your stronger knee and slowly raise it and your upper body to a crawling position
Move towards a chair that can be used for support
Pause for breath
Support yourself on the chair with your arms
Move your stronger leg forward from a kneeling position
Lean forward and use the chair to support you as you straighten both legs, starting with the strongest

Getting out of a chair

Acute back pain can make using chairs especially painful and difficult. There are, however, techniques you can use to make getting in and out of chairs easier and less painful.
How to sit on a chair
To sit on a chair safely:

Feel the chair at the back of your legs
Brace your tummy muscles 
Use the arms of the chair to help you stand down
If the chair has no arms, push on your thighs for a bit of extra support
To help your back and make sitting more comfortable:

Try to get up and change position regularly 
Try to sit right back in the chair
Put a rolled up towel in the small curve at the bottom of your spine
How to get out of a chair
To get out of a chair safely:

Ease yourself forward to the edge of the chair
Brace your tummy muscles
Use the arms of the chair to help you stand up
If the chair has no arms, push on your thighs for a bit of extra support

Getting in and out of bed

Acute back pain can make getting in and out of bed difficult. It's common for people to get stuck in bed, which can do more harm than good. There are, however, techniques you can use to make getting in and out of bed easier and less painful.
How to get out of bed
To get out of bed safely:

Roll onto your tummy and edge yourself towards the edge of the bed
Let the leg nearest the edge drop towards the floor and start to push up with your hands
Walk your hands down the bed towards your hips and raise yourself up
Carefully bring your other leg towards the floor and stand up
Alternatively:

Roll onto the side you feel most comfortable
Support your body with the arm closest to the bed and  use your other arm to slowly start to raise yourself up
Carefully bring your other leg towards the floor and stand up
How to get into bed
To get into bed safely:

Feel the bed at the back of your legs
Brace your tummy muscles
Sit down slowly pushing your thighs for a bit of extra support
Support your body with the arm closest to the top of the bed and use your other arm to slowly lower yourself down
Roll onto the side you feel most comfortable
</first>
</diseases>