<file1>
<first>\nTITLE:Diabetic retinopathy



ABOUT: 
Diabetic retinopathy is a complication of
diabetes, caused by high blood sugar levels damaging the back of the eye (retina). It can cause blindness if left undiagnosed and untreated.
However, it usually takes several years for diabetic retinopathy to reach a stage where it could threaten your sight.
To minimise the risk of this happening, people with diabetes should:

ensure they control their blood sugar levels, blood pressure and cholesterol
attend diabetic eye screening appointments – annual screening is offered to all people with diabetes aged 12 and over to pick up and treat any problems early on
This page covers:
How diabetes can affect the eyes
Am I at risk of diabetic retinopathy?
Symptoms of diabetic retinopathy
Diabetic eye screening
Reduce your risk of diabetic retinopathy
Treatments for diabetic retinopathy
How diabetes can affect the eyes
The retina is the light-sensitive layer of cells at the back of the eye that converts light into electrical signals. The signals are sent to the brain and the brain turns them into the images you see.
The retina needs a constant supply of blood, which it receives through a network of tiny blood vessels. Over time, a persistently high blood sugar level can damage these blood vessels in three main stages:

tiny bulges develop in the blood vessels, which may bleed slightly but don’t usually affect your vision – this is known as background retinopathy
more severe and widespread changes affect the blood vessels, including more significant bleeding into the eye – this is known as pre-proliferative retinopathy
scar tissue and new blood vessels, which are weak and bleed easily, develop on the retina – this is known as proliferative retinopathy and it can result in some loss of vision
However, if a problem with your eyes is picked up early, lifestyle changes and/or treatment can stop it getting worse.
Read about the 
stages of diabetic retinopathy
Am I at risk of diabetic retinopathy?
Anyone with 
type 1 diabetesor 
type 2 diabetesis potentially at risk of developing diabetic retinopathy.
You're at a greater risk if you:

have had diabetes for a long time
have a persistently high blood sugar (blood glucose) level
have 
high blood pressure
have
high cholesterol
are pregnant
are of Asian or Afro-Caribbean background
By keeping your blood sugar, blood pressure and cholesterol levels under control, you can
reduce your chances of developing diabetic retinopathy.
SYMPTOMS: You won't usually notice diabetic retinopathy in the early stages, as it doesn't tend to have any obvious symptoms until it's more advanced.
However, early signs of the condition can be picked up by taking photographs of the eyes during 
diabetic eye screening.
Contact your GP or diabetes care team immediately if you experience:

gradually worsening vision
sudden vision loss
shapes floating in your field of vision (floaters)
blurred or patchy vision
eye pain or redness
These symptoms don't necessarily mean you have diabetic retinopathy, but it's important to get them checked out. Don't wait until your next screening appointment.
Diabetic eye screening
Everyone with diabetes who is 12 years old or over is invited for eye screening once a year.
Screening is offered because:

diabetic retinopathy doesn't tend to cause any symptoms in the early stages
the condition can cause permanent blindness if not diagnosed and treated promptly
screening can detect problems in your eyes before they start to affect your vision
if problems are caught early, treatment can help prevent or reduce vision loss
The screening test involves examining the back of the eyes and taking photographs. Depending on your result, you may be advised to return for another appointment a year later, attend more regular appointments, or discuss treatment options with a specialist.
Read more about
diabetic eye screening
Reduce your risk of diabetic retinopathy
You can reduce your risk of developing diabetic retinopathy, or help prevent it getting worse, by:

controlling your blood sugar, blood pressure and cholesterol levels
taking your diabetes medication as prescribed
attending all your screening appointments
getting medical advice quickly if you notice any changes to your vision
maintaining a healthy weight, eating a
healthy, balanced diet,
exercising regularly and
stopping smoking
Read more about
how to prevent diabetic retinopathy.
Treatments for diabetic retinopathy
Treatment for diabetic retinopathy is only necessary if screening detects significant problems that mean your vision is at risk.
If the condition hasn't reached this stage, the above advice on managing your diabetes is recommended.
The main treatments for more advanced diabetic retinopathy are:

laser treatment
injections of medication into your eyes
an operation to remove blood or scar tissue from your eyes
Read more about the
treatment of diabetic retinopathy

Stages of diabetic retinopathy

Diabetic retinopathy develops in stages over time.
If you're diagnosed with diabetic retinopathy after
diabetic eye screening, lifestyle changes and/or treatment can reduce the chances of the problem progressing.
The main stages of diabetic retinopathy are described below. You won’t necessarily experience all of these.
Stage one: background retinopathy
This means that tiny bulges (microaneurysms) have appeared in the blood vessels in the back of your eyes (retina), which may leak small amounts of blood. This is very common in people with 
diabetes.
At this stage:

your sight isn't affected, although you're at a higher risk of developing vision problems in the future
you don't need treatment, but you'll need to take care to prevent the problem getting worse – read more about
preventing diabetic retinopathy
the chances of it progressing to the stages below within three years is over 25% if both of your eyes are affected
Stage two: pre-proliferative retinopathy
This means that more severe and widespread changes are seen in the retina, including bleeding into the retina.
At this stage:

there's a high risk that your vision could eventually be affected
you'll usually be advised to have more frequent screening appointments every three or six months to monitor your eyes
Stage three: proliferative retinopathy
This means that new blood vessels and scar tissue have formed on your retina, which can cause significant bleeding and lead to retinal detachment (where the retina pulls away from the back of the eye).
At this stage:

there's a very high risk you could lose your vision
treatment will be offered to stabilise your vision as much as possible, although it won't be possible to restore any vision you've lost
Diabetic maculopathy
In some cases, the blood vessels in the part of the eye called the macula (the central area of the retina) can also become leaky or blocked. This is known as diabetic maculopathy.
If this is detected:

there's a high risk that your vision could eventually be affected
you may be advised to have more frequent specialised testing to monitor your eyes
you may be referred to a hospital specialist to discuss treatments that can help stop the problem getting worse
Read more about
treating diabetic retinopathy

TREATMENT: 
Diabetic retinopathy usually only requires specific treatment when it reaches an advanced stage and there's a risk to your vision.
It's typically offered if 
diabetic eye screening detects stage three (proliferative) retinopathy, or if you have symptoms caused by diabetic maculopathy.
At all stages, managing your diabetes is crucial.
Read about the 
stages of diabetic retinopathy for more information about what these terms mean.
Managing your diabetes
The most important part of your treatment is to keep your diabetes under control.
In the early stages of diabetic retinopathy, controlling your diabetes can help prevent vision problems developing.
In the more advanced stages, when your vision is affected or at risk, keeping your diabetes under control can help stop the condition getting worse.
Read about
what you can do to reduce the risk of diabetic retinopathy progressing
Treatments for advanced diabetic retinopathy
For diabetic retinopathy that is threatening or affecting your sight, the main treatments are:

laser treatment – to treat the growth of new blood vessels at the back of the eye (retina) in cases of proliferative diabetic retinopathy, and to stabilise some cases of maculopathy
eye injections – to treat severe maculopathy that's threatening your sight
eye surgery– to remove blood or scar tissue from the eye if laser treatment isn't possible because retinopathy is too advanced
Laser treatment
Laser treatment is used to treat new blood vessels at the back of the eyes in the advanced stages of diabetic retinopathy. This is done because the new blood vessels tend to be very weak and often cause bleeding into the eye.
Treatment can help stabilise the changes in your eyes caused by your diabetes and stop your vision getting any worse, although it won't usually improve your sight.
Laser treatment:

involves shining a laser into your eyes – you'll be given
local anaestheticdrops to numb your eyes; eye drops are used to widen your pupils and special contact lenses are used to hold your eyelids open and focus the laser onto your retina
normally takes around 20-40 minutes
is usually carried out on an outpatient basis, which means you won't need to stay in hospital overnight 
may require more than one visit to a laser treatment clinic
isn't usually painful, although you may feel a sharp pricking sensation when certain areas of your eye are being treated
Side effects
After treatment, you may have some side effects for a few hours. These can include:

blurred vision – you won't be able to drive until this passes, so you'll need to arrange for a friend or relative to drive you home, or take public transport
increased sensitivity to light – it might help to wear sunglasses until your eyes have adjusted
aching or discomfort – over-the-counter painkillers, such as
paracetamol, should help
Possible complications
You should be told about the risks of treatment in advance. Potential complications include:

reduced night or peripheral (side) vision – some people may have to stop driving as a result of this
bleeding into the eye or objects floating in your vision (floaters)
being able to "see" the pattern made by the laser on the back of your eye for a few months
a small, but permanent, blind spot close to the centre of your vision
Get medical advice if you notice that your sight gets worse after treatment.
Eye injections
In some cases of diabetic maculopathy, injections of a medicine called anti-VEGF may be given directly into your eyes to prevent new blood vessels forming at the back of the eyes.
The main medicines used are called ranibizumab (Lucentis) and aflibercept (Eylea). These can help stop the problems in your eyes getting worse, and may also lead to an improvement in your vision.
During treatment:

the skin around your eyes will be cleaned and covered with a sheet
small clips will be used to keep your eyes open
you'll be given local anaesthetic drops to numb your eyes
a very fine needle is carefully guided into your eyeball and the injection is given
The injections are usually given once a month to begin with. Once your vision starts to stabilise, they'll be stopped or given less frequently.
Injections of 
steroid medication may sometimes be given instead of anti-VEGF injections, or if the anti-VEGF injections don't help.
Risks and side effects
Possible risks and side effects of anti-VEGF injections include:

eye irritation or discomfort
bleeding inside the eye
floaters or a feeling of having something in your eye
watery or dry, itchy eyes
There's also a risk that the injections could cause 
blood clotsto form, which could lead to a 
heart attackor
stroke. This risk is small, but it should be discussed with you before you give your consent to treatment.
The main risk with steroid injections is increased pressure inside the eye.
Eye surgery
Surgery may be carried out to remove some of the vitreous humour from the eye. This is the transparent, jelly-like substance that fills the space behind the lens of the eye.
The operation, known as vitreoretinal surgery, may be needed if:

a large amount of blood has collected in your eye
there's extensive scar tissue that's likely to cause, or has already caused, retinal detachment
During the procedure, the surgeon will make a small incision in your eye before removing some of the vitreous humour, removing any scar tissue and using a laser to prevent a further deterioration in your vision.
Vitreoretinal surgery is usually carried out under local anaesthetic and sedation. This means you will not experience any pain or have any awareness of the surgery being performed.
After the procedure
You should be able to go home on the same day or the day after your surgery.
For the first few days, you may need to wear a patch over your eye. This is because activities such as reading and watching television can quickly tire your eye to begin with.
You will probably have blurred vision after the operation. This should improve gradually, although it may take several months for your vision to fully return to normal.
Your surgeon will advise you about any activities you should avoid during your recovery.
Risks and side effects
Possible risks of vitreoretinal surgery include:

developing a cataract
further bleeding into the eye
retinal detachment
fluid build-up in the cornea (outer layer at the front of the eye)
infection in the eye
There's also a small chance that you will need further retinal surgery afterwards. Your surgeon will explain the risks to you.

PREVENTION: 
You can reduce your risk of developing diabetic retinopathy, or help stop it getting worse, by keeping your blood sugar levels, blood pressure and cholesterol levels under control.
This can often be done by making healthy lifestyle choices, although some people will also need to take medication.
Healthy lifestyle
Adopting a few lifestyle changes can improve your general health and reduce your risk of developing retinopathy. These include:

eating a
healthy, balanced diet – in particular, try to cut down on 
salt,
fatand
sugar
losing weight if you're overweight – you should aim for a BMI of 18.5-24.9
exercising regularly – aim to do at least 150 minutes of
moderate-intensity activity, such as walking or cycling, a week; doing 10,000 steps a day can be a good way to reach this target
stopping smokingif you smoke
not exceeding the recommended alcohol limits – men and women are advised not to regularly drink more than 14 
alcohol unitsa week
You may also be prescribed medication to help control your blood sugar level (such as insulin or metformin), blood pressure (such as ACE inhibitors) and/or cholesterol level (such as
statins).
Know your blood sugar, blood pressure and cholesterol levels
It can be easier to keep your blood sugar levels, blood pressure and cholesterol levels under control if you know what level they are and monitor them regularly.
The lower you can keep them, the lower your chances of developing retinopathy are. Your diabetes care team can let you know what your target levels should be.
Blood sugar
If you check your blood sugar level at home, it should be 4 to 10mmol/l. The level can vary throughout the day, so try to check it at different times.
The check done at your GP surgery is a measure of your average blood sugar level over the past few weeks. You should know this number, as it is the most important measure of your diabetes control. 
It’s called HbA1c, and for most people with diabetes it should be around 48 mmol/l or 6.5%.
Read about 
treating type 1 diabetes and 
treating type 2 diabetes
Blood pressure
You can ask for a blood pressure test at your GP surgery, or you can buy a blood pressure monitor to use at home. Blood pressure is measured in millimetres of mercury (mmHg) and is given as two figures.
If you have diabetes, you'll normally be advised to aim for a blood pressure reading of no more than 140/80mmHg, or less than 130/80mmHg if you have diabetes complications, such as eye damage.
Read more about 
preventing high blood pressureand 
treating high blood pressure
Cholesterol
Your cholesterol level can be measured with a simple blood test carried out at your GP surgery. The result is given in millimoles per litre of blood (mmol/l).
If you have diabetes, you'll normally be advised to aim for a total blood cholesterol level of no more than 4 mmol/l.
Read more about 
preventing high cholesterol and 
treating high cholesterol
Regular screening
Even if you think your diabetes is well controlled, it's still important to attend your annual
diabetic eye screening appointment, as this can detect signs of a problem before you notice anything is wrong.
The earlier that retinopathy is detected, the greater the chance of effectively treating it and stopping it getting worse.
You should also contact your GP or diabetes care team immediately if you develop any problems with your eyes or vision, such as:

gradually worsening vision
sudden vision loss
shapes floating in your field of vision (floaters)
blurred vision
eye pain or redness
These symptoms don't necessarily mean you have diabetic retinopathy, but it's important to get them checked out straight away.
</first>
</diseases>