<file1>
<first>Alzheimer's Disease Patient Caregiver Guide
Tips for Caregivers of a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Caring for a person with
 Alzheimer's disease at home is a difficult task and can become overwhelming at times. Each day brings new challenges as the
 caregiver copes with changing levels of ability and new patterns of behavior. Research has shown that caregivers themselves often are at increased risk for
 depression and illness, especially if they do not receive adequate support from family, friends, and the community. One of the biggest struggles caregivers face is dealing with the difficult behaviors of the person they are caring for. Dressing, bathing, eating—basic activities of daily living—often become difficult to manage for both the person with
 Alzheimer's and the caregiver. Having a plan for getting through the day can help caregivers cope. Many caregivers have found it helpful to use strategies for dealing with difficult behaviors and stressful situations. Through trial and error you will find that some of the following tips work, while others do not. Each person with
 Alzheimer's is unique and will respond differently, and each person changes over the course of the disease. Do the best you can, and remind yourself to take breaks. Dealing with the Diagnosis of Alzheimer's Disease Finding out that a loved one has
 Alzheimer's disease can be stressful, frightening, and overwhelming. As you begin to take stock of the situation, here are some tips that may help: Ask the doctor any questions you have about
 Alzheimer's disease . Find out what treatments might work best to alleviate symptoms or address behavior problems. Contact organizations such as the Alzheimer's Association and the Alzheimer's Disease Education and Referral (ADEAR) Center for more information about the disease, treatment options, andcaregiving resources. Some community groups may offer classes to teach
 caregiving , problem-solving, and management skills. See "For More Information" below to contact the ADEAR Center and a variety of other helpful organizations. Find a support group where you can share your feelings and concerns. Members of support groups often have helpful ideas or know of useful resources based on their own experiences. Online support groups make it possible for caregivers to receive support without having to leave home. The Alzheimer's Association and other organizations sponsor support groups. Study your day to see if you can develop a routine that makes things go more smoothly. If there are times of day when the person with Alzheimer's is less confused or more cooperative, plan your routine to make the most of those moments. Keep in mind that the way the person functions may change from day to day, so try to be flexible and adapt your routine as needed. Consider using adult day care or respite services to ease the day-to-day demands of caregiving. These services allow you to have a break while knowing that the person with Alzheimer's is being well cared for. Begin to plan for the future. This may include getting financial and legal documents in order, investigating long-term care options, and determining what services are covered by health insurance and Medicare.
 Communicating with a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Trying to communicate with a person who has Alzheimer's disease can be a challenge. Both understanding and being understood may be difficult. Choose simple words and short sentences and use a gentle, calm tone of voice. Avoid talking to the person with Alzheimer's like a baby or talking about the person as if he or she weren't there. Minimize distractions and noise—such as the television or radio—to help the person focus on what you are saying. Make eye contact and call the person by name, making sure you have his or her attention before speaking. Allow enough time for a response. Be careful not to interrupt. If the person with Alzheimer's is struggling to find a word or communicate a thought, gently try to provide the word he or she is looking for. Try to frame questions and instructions in a positive way. Be open to the person's concerns, even if he or she is hard to understand. Bathing a Person with Alzheimer's Disease While some people with Alzheimer's disease don't mind bathing, for others it is a frightening, confusing experience. Advance planning can help make bath time better for both of you. Plan the bath or shower for the time of day when the person is most calm and agreeable. Be consistent. Try to develop a routine. Respect the fact that bathing is scary and uncomfortable for some people with Alzheimer's. Be gentle and respectful. Be patient and calm. Tell the person what you are going to do, step by step, and allow him or her to do as much as possible. Prepare in advance. Make sure you have everything you need ready and in the bathroom before beginning. Draw the bath ahead of time. Be sensitive to the temperature. Warm up the room beforehand if necessary and keep extra towels and a robe nearby. Test the water temperature before beginning the bath or shower. Minimize safety risks by using a handheld showerhead, shower bench, grab bars, and nonskid bath mats. Never leave the person alone in the bath or shower. Try a sponge bath. Bathing may not be necessary every day. A sponge bath can be effective between showers or baths.
 Dressing a Person with Alzheimer's Disease For someone who has Alzheimer's, getting dressed presents a series of challenges: choosing what to wear, getting some clothes off and other clothes on, and struggling with buttons and zippers. Minimizing the challenges may make a difference. Try to have the person get dressed at the same time each day so he or she will come to expect it as part of the daily routine. Encourage the person to dress himself or herself to whatever degree possible. Plan to allow extra time so there is no pressure or rush. Allow the person to choose from a limited selection of outfits. If he or she has a favorite outfit, consider buying several identical sets. Store some clothes in another room to reduce the number of choices. Keep only one or two outfits in the closet or dresser. Arrange the clothes in the order they are to be put on to help the person move through the process. Hand the person one item at a time or give clear, step-by-step instructions if the person needs prompting. Choose clothing that is comfortable, easy to get on and off, and easy to care for. Elastic waists and Velcro® enclosures minimize struggles with buttons and zippers. Eating: Getting a Person with Alzheimer's Disease to Eat Eating can be a challenge. Some people with Alzheimer's disease want to eat all the time, while others have to be encouraged to maintain a good
 diet . View mealtimes as opportunities for social interaction and success for the person with Alzheimer's. Try to be patient and avoid rushing, and be sensitive to
 confusion and
 anxiety . Aim for a quiet, calm, reassuring mealtime atmosphere by limiting noise and other distractions. Maintain familiar mealtime routines, but adapt to the person's changing needs. Give the person food choices, but limit the number of choices. Try to offer appealing foods that have familiar flavors, varied textures, and different colors. Serve small portions or several small meals throughout the day. Make healthy snacks, finger foods, and shakes available. In the earlier stages of
 dementia , be aware of the possibility of overeating. Choose dishes and eating tools that promote independence. If the person has trouble using utensils, use a bowl instead of a plate, or offer utensils with large or built-up handles. Use straws or cups with lids to make drinking easier. Encourage the person to drink plenty of fluids throughout the day to avoid
 dehydration . As the disease progresses, be aware of the increased risk of choking because of chewing and
 swallowing problems . Maintain routine dental checkups and daily
 oral health care to keep the mouth and
 teeth healthy.
 Activities for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease What to do all day? Finding activities that the person with Alzheimer's disease can do and is interested in can be a challenge. Building on current skills generally works better than trying to teach something new. Don't expect too much. Simple activities often are best, especially when they use current abilities. Help the person get started on an activity. Break the activity down into small steps and praise the person for each step he or she completes. Watch for signs of agitation or frustration with an activity. Gently help or distract the person to something else. Incorporate activities the person seems to enjoy into your daily routine and try to do them at a similar time each day. Try to include the person with Alzheimer's in the entire activity process. For instance, at mealtimes, encourage the person to help prepare the food, set the table, pull out the chairs, or put away the dishes. This can help maintain functional skills, enhance feelings of personal control, and make good use of time. Take advantage of adult day services, which provide various activities for the person with Alzheimer's, as well as an opportunity for caregivers to gain temporary relief from tasks associated with caregiving. Transportation and meals often are provided. Exercise for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Incorporating
 exercise into the daily routine has benefits for both the person with Alzheimer's disease and the caregiver. Not only can it improve health, but it also can provide a meaningful activity for both of you to share. Think about what kind of physical activities you both enjoy, perhaps
 walking ,
 swimming , tennis, dancing, or gardening. Determine the time of day and place where this type of activity would work best. Be realistic in your expectations. Build slowly, perhaps just starting with a short walk around the yard, for example, before progressing to a walk around the block. Be aware of any discomfort or signs of overexertion. Talk to the person's doctor if this happens. Allow as much independence as possible, even if it means a less-than-perfect garden or a scoreless tennis match. See what kinds of
 exercise programs are available in your area. Senior centers may have group programs for people who enjoy exercising with others. Local malls often have walking clubs and provide a place to exercise when the weather is bad. Encourage physical activities. Spend time outside when the weather permits. Exercise often helps everyone
 sleep better.
 Incontinence in a Person with Alzheimer's Disease As the disease progresses, many people with Alzheimer's begin to experience
 incontinence , or the inability to control their bladder and/or bowels. Incontinence can be upsetting to the person and difficult for the caregiver. Sometimes incontinence is due to physical illness, so be sure to discuss it with the person's doctor. Have a routine for taking the person to the bathroom and stick to it as closely as possible. For example, take the person to the bathroom every 3 hours or so during the day. Don't wait for the person to ask. Watch for signs that the person may have to go to the bathroom, such as restlessness or pulling at clothes. Respond quickly. Be understanding when accidents occur. Stay calm and reassure the person if he or she is upset. Try to keep track of when accidents happen to help plan ways to avoid them. To help prevent nighttime accidents, limit certain types of fluids—such as those with
 caffeine —in the evening. If you are going to be out with the person, plan ahead. Know where restrooms are located, and have the person wear simple, easy-to-remove clothing. Take an extra set of clothing along in case of an accident. Sleep Problems for Caregivers and a Person with Alzheimer's Disease For the exhausted caregiver,
 sleep can't come too soon. For many people with Alzheimer's disease, however, the approach of nighttime may be a difficult time. Many people with Alzheimer's become restless, agitated, and irritable around dinnertime, often referred to as "sundowning" syndrome. Getting the person to go to bed and stay there may require some advance planning. Encourage exercise during the day and limit daytime napping, but make sure that the person gets adequate rest during the day because
 fatigue can increase the likelihood of late afternoon restlessness. Try to schedule physically demanding activities earlier in the day. For example, bathing could be done in the morning, or the largest family meal could be served at midday. Set a quiet, peaceful tone in the evening to encourage sleep. Keep the lights dim, eliminate loud noises, even play soothing music if the person seems to enjoy it. Try to keep bedtime at a similar time each evening. Developing a bedtime routine may help. Limit
 caffeine . Use night-lights in the bedroom, hall, and bathroom if the darkness is frightening or disorienting.
 Hallucinations and Delusions in a Person with Alzheimer's Disease As the disease progresses, a person with Alzheimer's disease may experience
 hallucinations and/or
 delusions . Hallucinations are when the person sees, hears, smells, tastes, or feels something that is not there. Delusions are false beliefs that the person thinks are real. Sometimes hallucinations and delusions are signs of physical illness. Keep track of what the person is experiencing and discuss it with the doctor. Avoid arguing with the person about what he or she sees or hears. Try to respond to the feelings he or she is expressing. Comfort the person if he or she is afraid. Try to distract the person to another topic or activity. Sometimes moving to another room or going outside for a walk may help. Turn off the television set when violent or disturbing programs are on. The person with Alzheimer's may not be able to distinguish television programming from reality. Make sure the person is safe and does not have access to anything he or she could use to harm anyone. Discuss with the doctor any illness the person has had or medicines he or she is taking. Sometimes an illness or medicine may cause hallucinations or delusions. Wandering: A Problem for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Keeping the person safe is one of the most important aspects of caregiving. Some people with Alzheimer's disease have a tendency to wander away from their home or their caregiver. Knowing how to limit wandering can protect a person from getting lost. Make sure that the person carries some kind of identification or wears a medical bracelet. Consider enrolling the person in the
 Alzheimer's Association Safe Return program if the program is available in your area. If the person gets lost and is unable to communicate adequately, identification will alert others to the person's medical condition. Notify neighbors and local authorities in advance that the person has a tendency to wander. Keep a recent photograph or videotape of the person with Alzheimer's to assist police if the person becomes lost. Keep doors locked. Consider a keyed deadbolt or an additional lock up high or down low on the door. If the person can open a lock because it is familiar, a new latch or lock may help. Install an "announcing system" that chimes when the door opens.
 Home Safety for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Caregivers of people with Alzheimer's disease often have to look at their homes through new eyes to identify and correct safety risks. Creating a safe environment can prevent many stressful and dangerous situations. The ADEAR Center offers the booklet, Home Safety for People with Alzheimer's Disease, which lists many helpful tips. See "For More Information" to contact the ADEAR Center. Install secure locks on all outside windows and doors, especially if the person is prone to wandering. Remove the locks on bathroom doors to prevent the person from accidentally locking himself or herself in. Use childproof latches on kitchen cabinets and anyplace where cleaning supplies or other chemicals are kept. Label medications and keep them locked up. Also make sure knives, lighters and matches, and guns are secured and out of reach. Keep the house free from clutter. Remove scatter rugs and anything else that might contribute to a fall. Make sure lighting is good both inside and outside the home. Be alert to and address kitchen-safety issues, such as the person forgetting to turn off the stove after cooking. Consider installing an automatic shut-off switch on the stove to preventburns or fire. Be sure to secure or put away anything that could cause danger, both inside and outside the home. Driving: Decisions for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Making the decision that a person with Alzheimer's is no longer safe to drive is difficult, and it needs to be communicated carefully and sensitively. Even though the person may be upset by the loss of independence, safety must be the priority. Look for clues that safe driving is no longer possible, including getting lost in familiar places, driving too fast or too slow, disregarding traffic signs, or getting angry or confused. Be sensitive to the person's feelings about losing the ability to drive, but be firm in your request that he or she no longer do so. Be consistent—don't allow the person to drive on "good days" but forbid it on "bad days." Ask the doctor to help. The person may view the doctor as an authority and be willing to stop driving. The doctor also can contact the Department of Motor Vehicles and request that the person be reevaluated. If necessary, take the car keys. If just having keys is important to the person, substitute a different set of keys. If all else fails, disable the car or move it to a location where the person cannot see it or gain access to it. Ask family or friends to drive the person or find out about services that help people with disabilities get around their community.
 Visiting the Doctor with a Person with Alzheimer's Disease It is important that the person with Alzheimer's disease receive regular medical care. Advance planning can help the trip to the doctor's office go more smoothly. Try to schedule the appointment for the person's best time of day. Also, ask the office staff what time of day the office is least crowded. Let the office staff know in advance that this person may be confused because of Alzheimer's disease. Ask them for help to make the visit go smoothly. Don't tell the person about the appointment until the day of the visit or even shortly before it is time to go. Be positive and matter-of-fact. Bring along something for the person to eat and drink and any materials or activities that he or she enjoys. Have a friend or another family member go with you on the trip, so that one of you can be with the person while the other speaks with the doctor. Take a brief summary listing the person's medical history, primary care doctor, and current medications. Coping with Holidays for Caregivers and a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Holidays are bittersweet for many Alzheimer's disease caregivers. The happy memories of the past contrast with the difficulties of the present, and extra demands on time and energy can seem overwhelming. Finding a balance between rest and activity can help. Keep or adapt family traditions that are important to you. Include the person with Alzheimer's as much as possible. Recognize that things will be different, and be realistic about what you can do. Encourage friends and family to visit. Limit the number of visitors at one time, and try to schedule visits during the time of day when the person is at his or her best. Avoid crowds, changes in routine, and strange places that may cause confusion or agitation. Do your best to enjoy yourself. Try to find time for the holiday things you like to do. Ask a friend or family member to spend time with the person while you are out. At larger gatherings such as weddings or family reunions, try to have a space available where the person can rest, be alone, or spend some time with a smaller number of people, if needed.
 Visiting a Person with Alzheimer's Disease Visitors are important to people with Alzheimer's. They may not always remember who the visitors are, but the human connection has value. Here are some ideas to share with someone who is planning to visit a person with the disease. Plan the visit for the time of day when the person with Alzheimer's is at his or her best. Consider bringing along an activity, such as something familiar to read or photo albums to look at, but be prepared to skip it if necessary. Be calm and quiet. Avoid using a loud tone of voice or talking to the person as if he or she were a child. Respect the person's personal space and don't get too close. Try to establish eye contact and call the person by name to get his or her attention. Remind the person who you are if he or she doesn't seem to recognize you. Don't argue if the person is confused. Respond to the feelings you hear being communicated, and distract the person to a different topic if necessary. Remember not to take it personally if the person doesn't recognize you, is unkind, or responds angrily. He or she is reacting out of confusion. Choosing a Nursing Home for a Person with Alzheimer's Disease For many caregivers, there comes a point when they are no longer able to take care of their loved one at home. Choosing a residential care facility—a group home, assisted living facility, or
 nursing home—is a big decision, and it can be hard to know where to start. It's helpful to gather information about services and options before the need actually arises. This gives you time to explore fully all the possibilities before making a decision. Determine what facilities are in your area. Doctors, friends and relatives, hospital social workers, and religious organizations may be able to help you identify specific facilities. Make a list of questions you would like to ask the staff. Think about what is important to you, such as activity programs, transportation, or special units for people with Alzheimer's disease. Contact the places that interest you and make an appointment to visit. Talk to the administration, nursing staff, and residents. Observe the way the facility runs and how residents are treated. You may want to drop by again unannounced to see if your impressions are the same. Find out what kinds of programs and services are offered for people with Alzheimer's and their families. Ask about staff training in
 dementia care, and check to see what the policy is about family participation in planning patient care. Check on room availability, cost and method of payment, and participation in Medicare or Medicaid. You may want to place your name on a waiting list even if you are not ready to make an immediate decision about long-term care. Once you have made a decision, be sure you understand the terms of the contract and financial agreement. You may want to have a lawyer review the documents with you before signing. Moving is a big change for both the person with Alzheimer's disease and the caregiver. A social worker may be able to help you plan for and adjust to the move. It is important to have support during this difficult transition.
 For More Information on Alzheimer's Disease Many organizations offer information for caregivers. To learn more about support groups, services, research, and additional publications, you may wish to contact the following: Alzheimer's Disease Education &amp; Referral (ADEAR) Center
 P.O. Box 8250
 Silver Spring, MD 20907-8250
 1-800-438-4380
 Web address:
 www.nia.nih.gov/
 Alzheimers The National Institute on
 Aging 's ADEAR Center offers information and publications for families, caregivers, and professionals on diagnosis, treatment, patient care, caregiver needs, long-term care, education and training, and research related to Alzheimer's disease. Staff members answer telephone, email, and written requests and make referrals to local and national resources. The ADEAR website offers free, online publications in English and Spanish; email alert and online Connections newsletter subscriptions; an Alzheimer's disease
 clinical trials database; the Alzheimer's Disease Library database; and more. Alzheimer's Association
 225 North Michigan Avenue
 Suite 1700
 Chicago, IL 60601-7633
 1-800-272-3900
 Web address: www.alz.org The Alzheimer's Association is a national, nonprofit association with a network of local chapters that provide education and support for people diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease, their families, and caregivers. The Association also supports research on Alzheimer's. Alzheimer's Foundation of America
 322 Eighth Avenue, 7th Floor
 New York, NY 10001
 1-866-232-8484 (toll-free)
 www.alzfdn.org The Alzheimer's Foundation of America provides care and services to individuals confronting dementia and to their caregivers and families through member organizations dedicated to improving quality of life. Services include a toll-free hotline, consumer publications and other educational materials, and conferences and workshops. Children of Aging Parents
 P.O. Box 167
 Richboro, PA 18954
 1-800-227-7294
 Web address: www.caps4caregivers.org This nonprofit group provides information and materials for adult children caring for their older parents. Caregivers of people with Alzheimer's disease also may find this information helpful. Eldercare Locator
 1-800-677-1116
 Web address: www.eldercare.gov Eldercare Locator is a nationwide directory-assistance service helping older people and their caregivers locate local support and resources. It is funded by the U.S. Administration on
 Aging (AoA). AoA's website at www.aoa.gov offers information about caregiving, working with and providing services to people with Alzheimer's, and where to look for support and assistance. Family Caregiver Alliance
 180 Montgomery Street
 Suite 1100
 San Francisco, CA 94104
 1-800-445-8106
 Web address: www.caregiver.org Family Caregiver Alliance is a nonprofit organization that offers support services and information for people caring for adults with Alzheimer's,
 stroke , traumatic brain injuries, and other cognitive disorders. Programs and services include an information clearinghouse for FCA's publications. The National Institute on Aging Information Center
 P.O. Box 8057
 1-800-222-2225
 1-800-222-4225 (TTY)
 Web address: www.nia.nih.gov The NIA Information Center offers a variety of information about health and aging. To order publications in English or Spanish or to sign up for regular email alerts, visit www.nia.nih.gov/HealthInformation. Visit NIHSeniorHealth (www.nihseniorhealth.gov), a senior-friendly website from NIA and the National Library of Medicine. This website has health information for older adults. Special features make it simple to use. For example, you can click on a button to have the text read out loud or to make the type larger. National Family Caregivers Association
 10400 Connecticut Avenue, Suite 500
 Kensington, MD 20895-3944
 1-800-896-3650 (toll-free)
 www.thefamilycaregiver.org The National Family Caregivers Association helps educate and support people who care for loved ones with chronic illness, disability, or the frailties of old age. The Association offers an online library of information and educational materials, workshops, and other resources. National Hospice and Palliative Care Organization
 1731 King Street, Suite 100
 Alexandria, VA 22314
 1-800-658-8898 (toll-free)
 www.nhpco.org This nonprofit organization works to enhance the quality of life for people who are terminally ill. It provides information, resources, and referrals to local
 hospice services and offers publications and online resources. The Simon Foundation for Continence
 P.O. Box 815
 Wilmette, IL 60091
 1-800-237-4666
 Web address: www.simonfoundation.org The Simon Foundation for Continence helps individuals with incontinence, their families, and the health professionals who provide their care. The Foundation provides books, pamphlets, tapes, self-help groups, and other resources. Well Spouse Association
 63 West Main Street, Suite H
 Freehold, NJ 07788
 1-800-838-0879
 Web address: www.wellspouse.org This nonprofit membership organization gives support to spouses and partners of the chronically ill and/or disabled. It offers support groups and a newsletter. The National Institute on Aging gratefully acknowledges the following Alzheimer's Disease Centers for their valuable contributions of information in preparation of this Caregiver Guide: Duke University Joseph and Kathleen Bryan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center The Johns Hopkins University Alzheimer's Disease Center
</first>
</file1>