<file1>
<first>Khat
What is Khat and what are the street names for Khat? Street terms for Khat: (pronounced Cot) Abyssinian tea, African salad, oat, 
kat, chat, and catha. Also referred to as qat in Yemen, tschat in Ethiopia, and 
miraa in Kenya. What does Khat look like? Khat is a flowering evergreen shrub native to East Africa and the 
 Arabian Peninsula. Khat that is sold and abused is usually 
just the leaves, twigs, and shoots of the Khat shrub. How is Khat used? Khat is typically chewed like
 tobacco . The fresh 
leaves, twigs, and shoots of the Khat shrub are chewed, and then retained in the 
cheek and chewed intermittently to release the active drug. Dried plant material can be made into tea or a chewable paste. Khat can also be smoked and 
even sprinkled on food. What are the health side effects of Khat use? Common side effects include
 anorexia , 
 tahycardia,
 hypertension ,
 insomnia , and gastric disorders. Chronic Khat abuse can result in symptoms such as physical exhaustion, violence, and 
 suicidal
 depression . Widespread frequent use of Khat impacts productivity because it tends to 
 reduce worker motivation. Khat can induce
 manic behaviors,
 hyperactivity , and
 hallucinations . There are reports of Khat-induced psychosis. Who uses Khat? The use of Khat is an established cultural tradition 
for many social situations in the areas of primary cultivation: East Africa and 
the Arabian Peninsula. Several million people may currently be using Khat 
worldwide. The largest concentrations of users are in the regions surrounding 
the Middle East. How does Khat get to the United States? Khat, while illegal in the United 
States, is legal in much of Europe, East Africa, and the Arabian Peninsula. Individuals of East African and Middle Eastern descent are mot often responsible 
for the importation, distribution, possession, and use of Khat in the United 
 States. Khat is usually shipped already packaged in bundles, and wrapped in
 plastic bags 
 or banana leaves to retain moisture and freshness. Khat is 
generally smuggled in passenger luggage, overnight express mail, or shipped as 
air cargo and falsely labeled as "vegetables." How much does Khat cost? Exactly prices are not known, but Khat is a 
relatively costly drug.
</first>
</file1>