<file1>
<first>Kawasaki Disease

ABOUT: Kawasaki disease is a syndrome of unknown cause that mainly strikes young children. Kawasaki disease symptoms and signs include
 fever and redness of the eyes , hands,
 feet , mouth, and tongue. The disease can be treated with high doses of
 aspirin (salicylic acid) and gamma globulin. Kawasaki disease symptoms usually resolve within a month or two, but the disease should be considered a "lifelong disease" because monitoring for late-onset heart artery changes is necessary. Some children with Kawasaki disease suffer coronary artery lesions. What is Kawasaki disease, and how do doctors diagnose it? Kawasaki disease is an uncommon illness in children that is characterized by high
 fever of at least five days&amp;#39; duration together with at least four of the following five findings: The above criteria are used to make a diagnosis of Kawasaki disease. The terminology "incomplete Kawasaki disease" is sometimes used for patients who are diagnosed with only some features of classical Kawasaki disease. Most patients are under 5 years of age with a peak incidence at 18 months of age. It is the most common acquired
 heart disease in children.
 What is mucocutaneous lymph node syndrome? Mucocutaneous lymph node syndrome is the original name for Kawasaki disease. The original name was quite descriptive because the disease is characterized by the typical changes in the mucous membranes that line the lips and mouth and by the enlarged and tender
 lymph nodes . Kawasaki disease is also termed infantile polyarteritis. 
CAUSES:  The cause is not known. Microorganisms and toxins have been suspected, but none has been identified to date. It is common for Kawasaki disease to occur after a preceding infection, such as
 tonsillitis ,
 ear infection ,
 pneumonia , urine infection, or gastrointestinal infection. Genetic factors (genetic variants in some patients) and the immune system seem to play roles in the disease, which is characterized by immune activation. The disease is more common in those of Japanese or Korean descent. Who develops Kawasaki disease? Kawasaki disease typically affects children under 5 years of age. Only rarely does it affect children over 8 years of age, in which case it is sometimes referred to as atypical Kawasaki disease. 
SYMPTOMS:  The usual symptoms and signs of Kawasaki disease include prolonged fever, reddening of the eyes without pus (
 pinkeye ), cracked and inflamed lips and mucous membranes of the mouth with an inflamed strawberry tongue, ulcerative
 gum disease (
 gingivitis ), swollen lymph nodes in the neck (cervical
 lymphadenopathy ), joint pain often on both sides of the body, irritability, cough and
 runny nose , and a
 rash that is raised and bright red, with cracking and
 peeling skin (desquamation), especially on the palms and soles. The rash appears in a glove-and-sock fashion over the skin of the hands and feet. The rash becomes hard, swollen (edematous), and then peels off.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Most of the common symptoms described above will resolve without complications, even if untreated. Less common findings include inflammation of the lining of the heart (
 pericarditis ), joints (
 arthritis ), or covering of the brain and spinal cord (
 meningitis ), and the other heart problems listed below in the section on serious complications. The outlook (prognosis) for an individual affected is primarily determined by the seriousness of any heart complications. What is the difference between Kawasaki disease and Kawasaki syndrome? They are the same. Kawasaki disease is also referred to as Kawasaki syndrome. It was first described in the late 1960s in Japan by the renowned pediatrician Tomisaku Kawasaki. Is Kawasaki disease
contagious? No. Kawasaki disease is not believed to be a
 contagious illness. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Children with Kawasaki disease can develop inflammation of the arteries of various parts of the body. This inflammation of the arteries is called
 vasculitis . Arteries that can be affected include the arteries that supply blood to the heart muscle (the coronary arteries). Vasculitis can cause weakening of the blood vessels and lead to areas of vessel widening (aneurysms). The weakening occurs because of destruction of the elastic tissue in the walls of the blood vessels. Coronary artery aneurysms occur because of such injury to the blood vessels in Kawasaki disease. Because of the potential for heart injury and coronary artery aneurysms, special tests are performed to examine the heart. Children are typically evaluated with an
 electrocardiogram (
 EKG ) and an
 ultrasound test of the heart (
 echocardiogram ). Monitoring for this problem is crucial throughout life as it can develop as a late aftereffect of Kawasaki disease. Other arteries that can become inflamed include the arteries of the
 lungs , neck, and abdomen. These effects can lead to
 breathing problems,
 headaches , and
 abdominal pain , respectively. Blood tests to measure the degree of inflammation (such as
 C-reactive protein , or CRP, and erythrocyte
 sedimentation rate , or ESR) are often used to monitor the activity of the disease.
 
TREATMENT:  Children affected by Kawasaki disease are hospitalized. Kawasaki disease is treated with high doses of aspirin (salicylic acid) to reduce inflammation and to mildly thin the blood to prevent
 blood clot formation. Also used in treatment is gamma globulin administered through the vein (intravenous immunoglobulin or IVIG), together with fluids. This treatment has been shown to decrease the chance of developing coronary aneurysms in the coronary arteries, especially when used early in the illness. Sometimes cortisone medications are given. Persisting
 joint pains are treated with anti-inflammatory
 drugs , such as
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ) or
 naproxen (
 Aleve ). Plasma exchange (plasmapheresis) has been reported as effective in patients who were not responding to aspirin and gamma globulin. Plasmapheresis is a procedure whereby the patient&amp;#39;s plasma is removed from the blood and replaced with protein-containing fluids. By taking out portions of the patient&amp;#39;s plasma, the procedure also removes antibodies and proteins that are felt to be part of the immune reaction that is causing the inflammation of the disease. Kawasaki disease that is not responding to the traditional cornerstones of treatment, aspirin and gamma globulin infusions, can be deadly. Treatments being investigated include
 doxycycline , statin drugs (
 Lipitor ,
 Mevacor , others),
 anakinra (
 Kineret ), and
 cyclosporine (
 Neoral ).
 What is the prognosis for children with Kawasaki disease? Kawasaki disease is typically self-limited and generally resolves on its own after four to eight weeks, and with early treatment, full recovery is usual. However, the outcome is not so favorable in every child. Rarely, Kawasaki disease can cause death from
 blood clots forming in abnormal areas of widening (aneurysms) of the heart arteries (coronary arteries) and
 myocarditis (inflammation of heart muscle). Aneurysms of the arteries to the heart (coronary arteries) can occur early or late, even when the children are adults so follow-up is recommended for those patients diagnosed with the disease. Those children with larger aneurysms have a worse prognosis because of this risk. Such aneurysms can lead to blood clots,
 heart attacks (
 myocardial infarction ), and
 internal bleeding . Those whose echocardiograms do not demonstrate widening of the coronary arteries throughout life do best. Those with any signs of
 aneurysm changes require very close monitoring. Children less than 6 months of age and those with high levels of inflammation on blood testing are at highest risk. The earlier the diagnosis is made and treatment is begun the better the outcome. Researchers are searching for methods of detecting which children are at risk for the development of aneurysms of the coronary arteries. Further research is under way to investigate a variety of criteria for atypical variants of Kawasaki disease that do not have classical presentations. 
PREVENTION:  Because the cause of Kawasaki disease has not been determined, there are no measures known that can prevent the disease. Early evaluation and treatment can decrease the chance for long-term problems and/or complications.
</first>
</file1>