<file1>
<first>Kleine-Levin Syndrome
What is Kleine-Levin syndrome? Kleine-Levin syndrome is a rare disorder that primarily affects adolescent 
males (approximately 70 percent of those with Kleine-Levin syndrome are male). What are the symptoms of Kleine-Levin syndrome? It is characterized by recurring but reversible periods of excessive
 sleep (up 
to 20 hours per day). Symptoms occur as "episodes," typically lasting a few days 
to a few weeks. Episode onset is often abrupt, and may be associated with
 flu -like symptoms. Excessive food intake, irritability, childishness, 
disorientation,
 hallucinations , and an abnormally uninhibited sex drive may be 
observed during episodes. Mood can be
 depressed as a consequence, but not a 
cause, of the disorder. Affected individuals are completely normal between 
episodes, although they may not be able to remember afterwards everything that 
happened during the episode. It may be weeks or more before symptoms reappear. 
Symptoms may be related to malfunction of the hypothalamus and thalamus, parts 
of the brain that govern appetite and
 sleep . Is there any treatment for Kleine-Levin syndrome? There is no definitive treatment for Kleine-Levin syndrome and watchful 
waiting at home, rather than pharmacotherapy, is most often advised. Stimulant 
pills, including amphetamines,
 methylphenidate , and
 modafinil , are used to treat 
sleepiness but may increase irritability and will not improve cognitive 
abnormalities. Because of similarities between Kleine-Levin syndrome and certain 
mood disorders,
 lithium and
 carbamazepine may be prescribed and, in some cases, 
have been shown to prevent further episodes. This disorder should be 
differentiated from cyclic re-occurrence of sleepiness during the
 premenstrual period in teen-aged girls, which may be controlled with
 birth control pills . It 
also should be differentiated from
 encephalopathy , recurrent
 depression , or 
psychosis.
 What is the prognosis for Kleine-Levin syndrome? Episodes eventually decrease in frequency and intensity over the course of 
eight to 12 years. What research is being done on Kleine-Levin syndrome? NINDS supports a broad range of clinical and basic research on diseases 
causing
 sleep disorders in an effort to clarify the mechanisms of these 
conditions and to develop better treatments for them. Clinical trials on Kleine-Levin syndrome NIH Patient Recruitment for Kleine-Levin Syndrome
 Clinical Trials At NIH Clinical Center Throughout the U.S. and Worldwide For more information National Sleep Foundation
 1522 K Street NW
 Suite 500
 Washington, DC 20005
 [email protected] http://www.sleepfoundation.org
 Tel: 202-347-3471
 Fax: 202-347-3472 National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD)
 P.O. Box 1968
 (55 Kenosia Avenue)
 Danbury, CT 06813-1968
 [email protected] http://www.rarediseases.org
 Tel: 203-744-0100 Voice Mail 800-999-NORD (6673)
 Fax: 203-798-2291
</first>
</file1>