<file1>
<first>Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD)

ABOUT: Anxiety disorders are the most common category of psychiatric diagnoses. The most common anxiety disorders are specific
 phobias . Besides
 generalized anxiety disorder , other anxiety disorders include
 separation anxiety , selective mutism,
 social anxiety disorder (
 social phobia ),
 panic disorder , and
 agoraphobia . Anxiety disorders can also be caused by a medical illness or other medical conditions (
 anxiety disorder due to another medical condition). Use of or withdrawal from certain medications or substances can also cause an anxiety disorder (substance/medication-induced anxiety disorder). Signs and symptoms of anxiety may be physical (racing heart,
 shortness of breath ,
 sweating ), emotional (panic, feeling worried,
 stress ), behavioral (nervous habits, compulsions), and cognitive (racing thoughts, worries, obsessions). Many of these signs and symptoms are similar to the body&amp;#39;s normal "fight-or-flight" response to danger. Children and adolescents may have symptoms of anxiety either similar to or quite different from those of adults, depending on the specific diagnosis and age of the individual. There also seem to be gender-related differences in how many men and women experience and show anxiety. While
 obsessive-compulsive disorder (
 OCD ) used to be classified as an anxiety disorder, it is now grouped with other compulsive disorders. Posttraumatic stress disorder (
 PTSD ) has been reclassified as a
 trauma -related disorder instead of an anxiety disorder. Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) is an anxiety disorder that is characterized by excessive worries that interfere with the person&amp;#39;s life in some way. GAD is quite common, affecting millions of people. While there is no single cause of GAD, there are many factors that increase the risk of developing this disorder. If a medical or
 mental health professional suspects that you have GAD, you will likely undergo an extensive medical interview and physical examination. GAD usually requires treatment for it to resolve. Treatment of GAD usually involves some combination of lifestyle changes,
 psychotherapy , and/or medication. It is important for the individual with an anxiety disorder to work closely with their prescribing doctor to decide whether treatment with medications is an appropriate intervention, and if so, which medication should be administered. Various lifestyle choices and family interventions can also help prevent and decrease anxiety. There are many support groups and resources for people who suffer from generalized anxiety disorder (GAD).
 What is anxiety? Anxiety can be described as the response to a future or possible threat. Anxiety is closely related to fear, which is the response to a real or perceived immediate threat. Fear and anxiety are normal evolved responses in both humans and animals, and physical responses are linked to the "fight-or-flight" system. The autonomic nervous system controls the fight-or-flight response in the body, and this response generally includes dilation of the pupils in the eyes, increased heart rate, and increased
 respiration /
 breathing . Anxiety responses can include increased vigilance (paying attention to one&amp;#39;s surroundings) and muscle tension. Anxiety can be constructive, such as improving performance on a test, sporting event, or public speaking. Although these are normal responses and often helpful responses to danger, anxiety can cause problems when it is turned on too easily, not turned off when danger is absent, or when the response is too strong. Excessive anxiety that causes distress or impairment, that interferes with normal function, or causes avoidance of important activities and people in life, is considered an anxiety disorder.
 What are the types of anxiety disorders? Anxiety disorders are differentiated based on the type of object or situation that causes fear, anxiety, or avoidance as well as the thought patterns associated with the fear or anxiety. To be considered an anxiety disorder, the fear or anxiety also has to be persistent (lasting usually six months or more), and not a normal developmental phase (for example, a young child being afraid of being away from their parent). Anxiety disorders commonly start in childhood but persist into adulthood. The most common anxiety disorders are specific
 phobias . Specific phobias are an excessive fear of a specific object or situation, such as spiders (
 arachnophobia ), heights (
 acrophobia ), flying, or closed spaces (
 claustrophobia ). Most people are aware that their fears (phobias) are excessive, but they often feel powerless to control them. Sometimes a
 phobia may start after a traumatic event (for example, being stuck in a small space; seeing someone injured by an animal), but the symptoms are related to the fear and not related to re-experiencing the trauma (for example, the symptoms don&amp;#39;t better fit a
 post-traumatic stress disorder [
 PTSD ] diagnosis). In social anxiety disorder (social phobia or performance anxiety), people are excessively fearful or anxious about social interactions or situations that may involve being observed or scrutinized. Self-consciousness about being observed by others, or performing in front of others, is normal. However, social anxiety is much more extreme and gets in the way of completing normal (and often necessary) activities successfully. Social phobia may be limited to performance situations (such as speaking, singing, acting, etc., in front of others), or it may be more general and related to many (or all) situations around other people. Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) is characterized by persistent and excessive anxiety and worry about many different areas that are hard to control. Other anxiety disorders include separation anxiety disorder, selective mutism, agoraphobia (fear of being outside of the home in various situations), and panic disorder (recurring unexpected
 panic attacks and fear of having more panic attacks). Anxiety disorders may also be caused by
 drugs , medications, or other substances (including
 stimulants ,
 caffeine , and
 corticosteroids ). Stimulant medications and herbal preparations include common
 over-the-counter drugs such as
 cold medicine and decongestants, ephedra- or
 ephedrine -containing products,
 diet pills, or energy
 drinks . Prescription stimulants are sometimes used to treat
 ADHD /
 ADD (
 attention deficit hyperactivity disorder or
 attention deficit disorder ) and include
 methylphenidate (
 Ritalin ,
 Concerta ), amphetamine salts (
 Adderall ),
 lisdexamfetamine (
 Vyvanse ), and others. Withdrawal from alcohol and certain drugs (including
 benzodiazepines [medicines sometimes used to treat acute anxiety, such as
 alprazolam (
 Xanax ),
 lorazepam (
 Ativan ), or
 clonazepam (
 Klonopin ),
 barbiturates , or newer
 seizure medications such as
 gabapentin (
 Neurontin )]) can also cause anxiety-like symptoms. When a medication or drug is the primary cause of the anxiety, it is diagnosed as a medication or substance-induced anxiety disorder. Medical illnesses or conditions (such as thyroid conditions, breathing problems [such as
 asthma or
 COPD (
 chronic obstructive pulmonary disease ), or rare adrenal gland tumors (
 pheochromocytoma )]) can also cause anxiety disorders and/or anxiety-like symptoms. With the introduction of the
 Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (
 DSM-5 ), some diagnoses that used to be considered anxiety disorders have been recategorized into new sections. Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) is now grouped with other compulsive disorders, like hoarding and
 trichotillomania (hair pulling). Similarly,
 post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) has been reclassified with other trauma-related disorders. OCD and PTSD often have anxiety-related symptoms, and some treatments overlap with those for anxiety disorders.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Common symptoms and signs of anxiety disorder can include restlessness or feeling edgy; becoming tired easily,
 fatigue ; trouble concentrating, that may also appear as memory or attention problems; feeling as if the mind is going "blank"; irritability; muscle tension; headaches ; sleep problems (trouble falling or staying asleep or having
 sleep that is not restful). Anxiety that is associated with specific (specific or simple phobia) or social fears (social phobia) may also result in avoidance of certain situations or an elevation of symptoms to trigger a
 panic attack . Panic attacks are sudden episodes of intense fear and/or physical discomfort that reach a peak within minutes. Specific signs and
 symptoms of panic attack include both physical and emotional symptoms such as: palpitations (feelings of rapid and/or irregular heartbeats); chest pain ,
 chest tightness or other discomfort, feeling like one is having a
 heart attack ; shortness of breath or trouble breathing; sweating of the palms; nausea or other stomach upset; trembling or shaking; feeling dizzy, unsteady, lightheaded, or faint; derealization (feelings of unreality) or depersonalization (feeling detached from oneself); fear of losing control or going insane; numbness or tingling sensations; chills or
 hot flashes ; feeling like one is choking; a sense of impending doom; feeling like one is dying. Many anxiety disorders first develop in childhood or adolescence. Although some may resolve, many persist into adulthood. Some anxiety symptoms are related to childhood development. For example, separation anxiety is normal in young children. However, when the fear of being away from their parent persists or interferes with normal development, separation anxiety disorder is diagnosed. Separation anxiety may start after a traumatic event, such as the death of a loved one. However, if the fear is more about the trauma, and not specifically separation from the child&amp;#39;s caregivers, an
 acute stress disorder or
 posttraumatic stress disorder diagnosis may be more appropriate. Selective mutism refers to an inability to speak in social situations where there is an expectation to speak (such as school), but they are still able to speak in other settings. When this pattern persists and causes problems with school, work, or other performance, selective mutism is diagnosed. The similarities and differences in symptoms of anxiety in adults compared to children and adolescents depend on the specific condition that is causing the anxiety. For example, symptoms of social phobia or specific phobia are quite similar in children and
 teens compared to adults except that children and teens are less likely to recognize that their thoughts or behaviors are irrational. Symptoms of anxiety in children and teens tend to be consistent with how they express feelings in general. For example, younger children are less able to express feelings verbally compared to older children, and thus tend to express anxiety by complaining of physical symptoms like stomach upset or
 headaches . They are also more likely to cry, have tantrums, or become clingy. In contrast to younger children, teens tend to express symptoms of anxiety similarly to adults. However, adolescents are more likely than adults to exhibit anxiety by becoming irritable or angry. Anxious teens are also more likely to have wide
 mood swings from normal (euthymic) to anxious, angry, and irritable. Anxiety disorders are diagnosed in women about twice as often as in men. It is difficult to determine if women are more susceptible to anxiety disorders, or if men are less likely to acknowledge or report symptoms and are thus diagnosed less often. Similarly, differences in how men and women experience or recognize anxiety symptoms may also influence anxiety disorder diagnoses. Studies indicate that men seem to experience effects of anxiety differently compared to women. Specifically, men tend to exhibit more psychological symptoms of anxiety, like tension, irritability, and a sense of impending doom. In contrast, women tend to develop more physical symptoms like
 chest pain ,
 palpitations ,
 insomnia , shortness of breath, and
 nausea . Further, it seems that women with such physical symptoms of anxiety are more at risk for developing heart problems.
 When should people seek treatment for anxiety? Everyone experiences some symptoms of anxiety, but most often, this occurs in very serious situations. When the symptoms are triggered by normal events that aren&amp;#39;t dangerous, or they don&amp;#39;t settle down in a reasonable amount of time, you may have an anxiety disorder. Similarly, if the anxiety symptoms are getting in the way of your daily life, consider seeking a formal evaluation, and possible treatment, for an anxiety disorder. Not treating an anxiety disorder can impair your overall well-being, cause self-doubt, and may increase your risk of
 depression ,
 substance abuse , and even
 suicide . What is generalized anxiety disorder (GAD)? Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) is an anxiety disorder that is characterized by multiple and/or nonspecific worries. GAD often starts early in life, and people with this diagnosis will often describe being anxious, or being a "worrier," for most of their life. The fear associated with GAD interferes with the person&amp;#39;s ability to
 sleep , think, or function in some other way. Symptoms of anxiety are even described in the word itself. Specifically, the word anxiety comes from the Latin word
 anxietas , which means to choke or upset. The symptoms therefore include emotional or behavioral symptoms as well as ways of thinking that are responses to feeling as if one is in danger. How common is generalized anxiety disorder? GAD is quite common. In fact, it is the most common anxiety disorder seen by most primary care doctors. Up to 9% of people will develop GAD over the course of their lifetime. That translates to millions of GAD sufferers. During any given year in the U.S., up to 0.9% of adolescents (about one in 100) and 2.9% of adults (about one in 30) will have GAD. The prevalence of GAD peaks in middle age and declines in later years. Women are about twice as likely to develop GAD as men. Individuals from developed countries are more likely to report symptoms of GAD than those from non-developed countries.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  When people receive a GAD diagnosis, they commonly have (or had) other anxiety disorders. Individuals with GAD very commonly will also have major
 depressive episodes (unipolar
 depression ; "
 clinical depression ") during their life. GAD is not associated with an increased risk of having a substance use disorder,
 bipolar disorder , or a psychotic disorder. However, some symptoms of GAD are very common in other disorders, including PTSD, panic disorder,
 bipolar disorder , and
 psychotic disorders (such as
 schizophrenia ). However, part of a complete mental health evaluation should be confirming that the diagnosis of GAD is not better explained by another diagnosis.
 
CAUSES:  While there is no single cause of GAD, some people are more at risk for developing anxiety than others. Women tend to develop this condition and most other anxiety disorders more often than men, and individuals with a family history of anxiety and
 depression are more at risk for having GAD. Genetic factors (for example, a family history of anxiety and/or
 depression ) are thought to explain about one-third of the risk for GAD. Younger adults are more likely to have GAD or social anxiety disorder compared to older adults. Other risk factors for developing social anxiety disorder include being of Native-American ethnicity and having a low income. Being of Asian, Hispanic, or black ethnicity, as well as residing in a more populated region, seems to reduce the risk of social anxiety disorder. Inhibited temperament, parental anxiety, and having family and friends who somehow support avoidant coping mechanisms are risk factors for developing an anxiety disorder. Adolescents who smoke tobacco have been found to be at risk for developing anxiety. In children, girls, particularly those who begin
 puberty early, seem to be more likely to develop anxiety than their age peers of both genders. Life
 stress , involving health problems and family disagreements, has been found to be associated with developing an anxiety disorder. Certain other life stresses put people at risk for developing anxiety, as well. For example, in a study of African-American, Afro-Caribbean, and non-Hispanic white individuals, non-race-based discrimination was found to be a risk factor for developing anxiety in each of those groups while race-based discrimination was found to increase the likelihood of only the African-American people in developing anxiety.
 How do health care professionals diagnose generalized anxiety disorder (GAD)? According to the
 DSM-5 , the diagnosis GAD requires the following criteria, which must be present at least six months for more than half of the time: Excessive anxiety and worry. Worry is about a number of events or activities (for example, work or school performance, relationships, social functioning; worry not limited just to one topic). The worry is difficult to control. The anxiety and worry are associated with at least three of the following symptoms:
 Restlessness or feeling keyed up or on edge Easily fatigued Difficulty concentrating or mind going blank Irritability Muscle tension Sleep disturbance (difficulty falling or staying asleep; or restless, unsatisfying sleep) The anxiety, worry, and/or physical symptoms cause significant distress and/or impairment. Impairment may be in social, occupational, or other important aspects of life. The anxiety and worry are not better explained by a medical condition, a substance (drug of abuse or medication). They are also not better explained by a different psychiatric diagnosis. If a health care professional suspects that you have GAD, you will likely undergo an extensive medical interview and physical examination. As part of this examination, you may be asked a series of questions from a standardized questionnaire or self-test to help assess your risk of anxiety. The answers to these questions will help assess whether you meet the diagnostic criteria for GAD (as described above). Because anxiety may be associated with a number of other medical illnesses or can be a side effect of various medications, routine laboratory tests are often performed during the initial evaluation to rule out other causes of your symptoms. Occasionally, an X-ray, scan, or other imaging study may be needed. 
TREATMENT:  Many health care professionals may help determine the diagnosis and recommend treatment for individuals with GAD; these include licensed mental health therapists, family physicians, or other primary care professionals, specialists whom you see for a medical condition, emergency physicians, psychiatrists, psychologists, psychiatric nurses, and social workers. 
TREATMENT:  There are a variety of treatments available for controlling anxiety, including several effective anti-anxiety medications and specific forms of psychotherapy. In terms of medications,
 buspirone (BuSpar) is known to be quite effective for treating GAD. However, it seems to be less effective in managing many other disorders that often co-occur (are comorbid) with GAD. Therefore, specific members of the serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SRI) and the serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (SNRI) classes of drugs, which are also approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for effective treatment of GAD, are prescribed more often. Examples of SRI medications include
 fluoxetine (
 Prozac ),
 sertraline (
 Zoloft ),
 paroxetine (
 Paxil ),
 citalopram (
 Celexa ), and
 escitalopram (
 Lexapro ). Examples of SNRI medications are
 duloxetine (
 Cymbalta ),
 venlafaxine (
 Effexor ), and
 desvenlafaxine (
 Pristiq ). Some of the newer
 antidepressants work in a similar way to SRI and SNRI medications but do not yet have an FDA approval for treatment of GAD. Some of these newer medications are
 mirtazapine (
 Remeron ), levomilnacipran (Fetzima), vilazodone (Viibryd), and
 vortioxetine (
 Brintellix ). Benzodiazepine medications like clonazepam (Klonopin) and lorazepam (Ativan) are
 sedatives sometimes used for treating anxiety. They may be more effective for short-term use (for example, weeks to months), or occasional use in stopping severe anxiety symptoms, like those that occur in panic attacks, rather than the ongoing worry that is usually associated with GAD. Although alprazolam (Xanax) is often used to treat panic attacks, its short duration of action can sometimes result in having to take it several times per day, increasing the risk of tolerance and
 addiction . Another benzodiazepine,
 diazepam (
 Valium ), tends to be used less often due to concerns about its long duration of action and addiction potential. Use of benzodiazepines is somewhat controversial; many doctors are reluctant to use them because of the risk of abuse and dependence, and/or withdrawal. There is also some clinical research that suggests PTSD and anxiety disorders may be harder to control later if benzodiazepines are used. Because of the link between the autonomic nervous system and the fight-or-flight response in anxiety, medications that block this response may be helpful. One example is the
 beta-blocker family of medications usually used for
 high blood pressure .
 Beta-blockers stop some of the effects of epinephrine (adrenaline) that also is involved in anxiety and fear responses. Beta-blockers such as
 propranolol (
 Inderal ) are sometimes used to decrease episodic anxiety (for example, performance anxiety or test anxiety), and may also relieve some of the physical symptoms associated with a
 panic attack . In addition to these medications, a variety of other medication classes are sometimes used to help treat anxiety. Although they don&amp;#39;t have a specific approval for treating anxiety from the FDA, people may discuss the risks and benefits with their prescribing doctor and decide which medications may be right for them. Gabapentin (Neurontin) is a medication developed as a
 seizure medication but has been found to help some individuals with severe anxiety symptoms. Gabapentin may be a less addictive option compared to benzodiazepines. Older sedating anti-histamine medications, such as
 hydroxyzine (
 Vistaril ), are another nonaddictive type of medication that may be useful for panic attacks or severe episodes of anxiety. When anxiety disorders are difficult to treat, or an individual has side effects with an SRI/SNRI, they may decide with their doctor to try one of the newer antipsychotic (neuroleptic) medications. This class includes
 risperidone (
 Risperdal ),
 olanzapine (
 Zyprexa ),
 quetiapine (
 Seroquel ),
 aripiprazole (
 Abilify ),
 ziprasidone (
 Geodon ), paliperidone (Invega), and lurasidone (
 Latuda ). There are a number of
 clinical trials showing some reduction of anxiety symptoms from these medications. However, they also have significant possible side effects and require ongoing monitoring by the patient and their doctor. Zolpidem (
 Ambien ) and
 trazodone (
 Desyrel ) have been found helpful in treating the
 insomnia that can often be a symptom of anxiety. Before SRIs and SNRIs became available, older
 antidepressant medications including the tricyclic antidepressant (TCA) and monoamine oxidase inhibitor (
 MAOI ) classes were often used to treat anxiety disorders. Although both of these medication classes have been found to be effective in treating anxiety disorders, the newer classes of medications (SRIs and SNRIs) have been proven to be safer and better tolerated. Therefore, TCAs and
 MAOIs are used much less often than they used to be. When used in the appropriate person with close monitoring, these medications can be quite effective as part of treatment for panic disorder.
 What are the side effects of anxiety medications? All medications, prescribed or over the counter, carry a risk of side effects, and it is important for the person with an anxiety disorder to work closely with their prescribing doctor to decide whether treatment with medications is an appropriate intervention and if so, which medication should be administered. The kinds of side effects caused by a medication are highly specific to the medication itself and each medication class as a whole. The person being treated should therefore discuss potential medications with their treating physician and be closely monitored for the possibility of side effects that can vary from minor to severe and can uncommonly even be life threatening. The degree of risk from medications to the fetus of a
 pregnant woman is often not fully known. Some anxiety medications do have known risks for a fetus. Many pregnant women also have strong beliefs or fears about taking medication while pregnant. For each of these reasons, the decision of whether or not to take a medication for anxiety should be made by the woman with her prescribing physician (the woman&amp;#39;s obstetrician, or in consultation with her obstetrician). Treatment for anxiety can be individualized and may include psychotherapy alone or combined with medications. Similarly, women who are trying to become pregnant, or who may become pregnant, should consult with their doctor about what treatment choices are best for them. For people who may be wondering how to treat anxiety without prescribed medications, natural remedies available over the counter may be an option. Alternative and complementary treatment methods such as hypnosis,
 acupuncture , and herbal
 supplements (such as
 kava ,
 valerian , or passionflower) have been found to be helpful for some people with some anxiety disorders, but the research data are still considered to be too limited for many physicians to recommend them. Also, care should be taken when taking any
 dietary supplements , since dietary
 supplements and "natural" remedies are not regulated in terms of quality, content, or effectiveness. The psychotherapy component of treatment for anxiety disorders is at least as important as the medication treatment. In fact, research shows that counseling alone or the combination of medication and psychotherapy treatment are more effective than medication alone in overcoming anxiety for both adults and children. It has also been found to be potentially effective for people with
 autism in addition to anxiety. The most common type of therapy used to treat anxiety is cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT). This form of therapy seeks to help those with an anxiety disorder identify and decrease the irrational thoughts and behaviors that reinforce anxiety symptoms and can be administered either individually, in group therapy, and even in partner-assisted therapy. Recently, there have also been more online options for CBT available to treat both anxiety and depression. CBT that seeks to help the anxiety sufferer decrease the tendency to pay excessive attention to potential threats has also been found to be helpful. Behavioral techniques that are often used to decrease anxiety include relaxation techniques and gradually increasing exposure to situations that may have previously precipitated anxiety in the individual. Another name for this type of psychotherapy is exposure therapy. Helping the anxiety sufferer to understand and how to handle the emotional forces that may have contributed to developing symptoms (anxiety-focused psychodynamic psychotherapy) has also been found to be effective in teaching an individual with panic disorder how to prevent an anxiety attack or to decrease or stop a panic attack once it starts. Other commonly available psychotherapy approaches can also improve symptoms of anxiety. Therapies focused on well-being, including mindfulness-based individual or group therapies, are a widely available option. Often, a combination of psychotherapy and medications produces good results. Improvement is usually noticed in a fairly short period of time, about two to three months, although a full response (or remission of symptoms) usually takes longer. Thus, appropriate treatment for anxiety can prevent symptoms or at least substantially reduce their severity and frequency, bringing significant relief to many people with anxiety. There are also self-care measures that people with anxiety can do to help make treatment more effective. Since substances like
 caffeine , alcohol, and illicit drugs can worsen anxiety, those things should be avoided. Other tips to prevent or manage anxiety symptoms include engaging in
 aerobic exercise and stress-management techniques like deep breathing,
 massage therapy, and
 yoga , since these self-help and well-being activities have also been found to help decrease the frequency and severity of symptoms. Although many people breathe into a paper bag when afflicted by the
 hyperventilation that can be associated with panic, the benefit received may be the result of the individual believing it will remedy the symptoms (placebo effect). Also, breathing into a paper bag when one is having trouble breathing can make matters worse when the hyperventilation is the result of conditions of oxygen deprivation, as occurs with an
 asthma attack or a heart attack. People with an anxiety disorder may also need treatment for other emotional problems. Depression has often been associated with anxiety, as have alcohol and
 drug abuse . Recent research also suggests that
 suicide attempts are more frequent in people with an anxiety disorder. Fortunately, these problems associated with panic disorder can be overcome effectively, just like panic disorder itself. Sadly, many people with anxiety do not seek or receive treatment.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  There are many possible complications associated with anxiety. Mothers who struggle with anxiety during
 pregnancy are more likely to have
 babies who are of low birth weight. Children with anxiety often also suffer from depression, behavioral problems like
 attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (
 ADHD ), or oppositional defiant disorder (ODD), as well as substance abuse. They are at risk for having anxiety as adults, as well as attempting suicide and becoming psychiatrically hospitalized. In terms of achievement, children and teens with anxiety experience a higher rate of failing in school and having low-paying jobs as adults. 
PREVENTION:  Just as inhibited temperament, parental anxiety, and family and friends supporting avoidant coping mechanisms are risk factors for developing an anxiety disorder, encouraging the use of healthier ways to deal with stress can be of great help in the
 prevention of anxiety. Educating parents on how anxiety fits into their understanding of childhood development and the role of overprotecting parents in developing anxiety disorders have been found to help prevent anxiety disorders in children. Maintaining a healthy lifestyle, including a regular
 exercise program, eating a balanced
 diet , and getting adequate sleep can be key to minimizing and perhaps preventing anxiety.
 What is the prognosis of generalized anxiety disorder? Generalized anxiety disorder is often longstanding or lifelong, particularly without treatment. It can significantly interfere with the lives of individuals who have it and usually requires treatment for it to resolve. Therefore, people with generalized anxiety disorder are usually thought to need treatment for at least a year to prevent its recurrence, and some individuals may need to stay in treatment over the long term. Are there support groups for those with generalized anxiety disorder? The following are examples of support groups for anxiety disorders: ABIL, Inc. (Agoraphobics Building Independent Lives)
 [email protected] A.I.M. (Agoraphobics in Motion)
 [email protected] Association for Anxiety and Depression in America (ADAA) has an online listing of support groups by region:
 http://www.adaa.org/supportgroups Freedom From Fear
 http://www.freedomfromfear.org Phobics Anonymous
 619-322-COPE
 Where can people find additional information on generalized anxiety disorder? Reliable information about GAD, other anxiety disorders and psychiatric diagnoses can be found at National Alliance for Mental Illness (NAMI) and National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH). American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry
 http://www.aacap.org American Counseling Association
 http://www.counseling.org American Psychiatric Association
 http://www.psych.org American Psychological Association
 http://helping.apa.org Anxiety Disorders Association of America
 http://www.adaa.org/ National Anxiety Foundation
 3135 Custer Dr.
 Lexington, KY 40517-4001
 606-272-7166 National Association of Social Workers
 http://www.naswdc.org National Mental Health Association
 http://www.nmha.org National Panic/Anxiety Disorder News, Inc.
 http://www.npadnews.com</first>
</file1>