<file1>
<first>Appendectomy
What is appendicitis? Appendicitis is a condition in which the
 appendix becomes inflamed. The appendix is a finger or worm-shaped pouch that projects out from the cecum (the beginning of the colon). In most individuals, the appendix becomes inflamed because its tissues become infected with bacteria, and pus may develop within the lumen of the appendix. Mechanical blockage of the appendix by hard stool, a foreign body, or thick mucus may also lead to
 bacterial infections . The signs and
 symptoms of appendicitis may include aching
 pain that begins around the umbilicus (belly button) and then shifts to the lower right abdomen. The
 pain may be sharp and can increase by movements such as
 walking or
 coughing . Many individuals may develop
 nausea ,
 vomiting ,
 loss of appetite ,
 fever ,
 constipation , inability to pass
 gas , and abdominal swelling. Individuals may also develop
 diarrhea . A common sign of
 appendicitis is deep tenderness at the McBurney&amp;#39;s point (the location of McBurney&amp;#39;s point is about 2/3 the distance starting from the umbilicus to the right anterior superior iliac spine); however, young children and
 pregnant females may experience pain elsewhere in the abdomen.
 What is appendectomy? Appendectomy is the surgical removal of the appendix. This procedure is most 
often performed as an emergency operation. In some patients undergoing abdominal 
surgery for another reason, may have their appendix removed prophylactically so 
that
 appendicitis does not develop in the future; this option can be discussed 
with your surgeon. How do I prepare for an appendectomy? The majority of appendectomy operations are typically emergency surgeries so the patient needs to follow the instructions given by the surgeon. In general, the patient is advised not to eat food, although with the symptoms, they are usually not hungry anyway. The patient may be treated with medications to reduce or eliminate
 nausea and
 vomiting ; IV antibiotics may also be initiated before surgery. How is an appendectomy performed? Appendectomy is most often done in the operating room after the patient's 
skin has been shaved to remove hair and swabbed with a germ killing solution; 
sterility precautions are taken to prevent infection. The appendix may be 
removed by an open method or the 
laparoscopic technique. The open method 
requires a 2 to 3 inch incision in the lower right–hand side of the abdomen to 
remove the appendix, while the laparoscopic method uses several small incisions 
in the abdomen and the use of a laparoscope to visualize and then remove the appendix. What is the recovery time for an appendectomy? The recovery time for an appendectomy is variable and depends on the type of 
the procedure, type of anesthesia, and any complications that may have developed. 
For example, laparoscopic appendectomy may be done on an outpatient basis so 
that the patient can be discharged to recover at home, while an open 
method may require an overnight stay or an even longer time to be discharged 
to go home. Normal activities can resume in a few days but full recovery may take 4 
to 6 
weeks during which time strenuous activity should be avoided.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  Wound infection is the most common complication of an appendectomy. Abscess formation in the area of the removed appendix or surgical incision site may also occur.  Other relatively infrequent or rare complications may include ileus (lack of intestinal peristalsis), surgical injuries to internal organs or structures,
 gangrene of the bowel, peritonitis (infection in the peritoneal cavity) and bowel obstruction. Are there long-term consequences of removing the appendix? For most individuals there are no long-term consequences of removing the 
appendix. However, some individuals may have an increased risk of developing an
incisional
 hernia , stump appendicitis (infections due to a retained portion of 
the appendix), and bowel obstruction.
</first>
</file1>