<file1>
<first>Arsenic Poisoning

ABOUT: Arsenic is an element (metalloid) that can combine with organic and inorganic substances. Inorganic arsenic is arsenic alone or combined with inorganic substances that are very toxic to most biologic systems, including humans. Organic arsenic is arsenic combined with organic substances and may be non-toxic or far less toxic to many biologic systems than inorganic arsenic. Symptoms of arsenic poisoning vary with the type and
 concentration of the poison. Inorganic arsenic may cause abdominal pains, destruction of
 red blood cells (
 hemolysis ),
 shock , and death quickly. Lower concentrations of inorganic arsenic and organic arsenic cause far less severe symptoms. Diagnosis of arsenic poisoning is made by determining inorganic and organic levels of arsenic in the blood and urine. Treatment of arsenic poisoning in acute toxic poisonings needs to begin quickly; treatment involves removal of arsenic by
 dialysis , chelating agents, replacement of red blood cells, and if ingested, bowel cleansing. Acute toxic inorganic arsenic poisoning has only a fair to poor outcome. Chronic poisoning has a better outcome. Arsenic is found in groundwater, many chemicals, and foods. If arsenic is in the organic form, it is likely nontoxic or weakly toxic to humans, but inorganic arsenic can also be found in similar locations and materials and in high concentrations in industrial processes. In 2013, the FDA made recommendations that less than 10 parts per billion of arsenic was acceptable for levels in apple juice. Levels for arsenic have yet to be FDA approved for rice (still under study), although groundwater levels that provide arsenic to rice are FDA set at less than 10 parts per billion.
 What is arsenic? Arsenic is a grey-appearing chemical element (atomic number 33, symbol As in 
the periodic table) also termed a metalloid. Arsenic can exist in a metallic 
state in three forms (yellow, black, and gray; with gray predominating) and in 
ionic forms. Arsenic is considered to be a heavy metal, and arsenic toxicity 
shares some features with poisonings by other heavy metals. Historically, 
arsenic has been used as a medicinal agent, a pigment, a pesticide, and an agent 
with intent to harm (use with criminal intent). Up until 2003, arsenic (in the 
form of chromated copper arsenate) was used in the US as a treatment to prevent 
insect infestation of wood used in building. In 2003 the use of this compound 
was banned by the US Environmental Protection Agency. Arsenic is mixed with 
copper or lead to strengthen alloys containing these materials. Arsenic and some 
of its compounds react with proteins, mainly the thiol portions, and uncouples 
the process of oxidative phosphorylation, thus inactivating most cellular 
functions. Consequently, arsenic and some of the substances it combines with are 
deadly poisons to most biologic systems, except for a few bacterial species. 
Arsenic is used in making insecticides and weed killers. Arsenic is also thought 
to be carcinogenic, meaning that it has the potential to 
cause
 cancer . Arsenic 
can be found as a contaminant in food and water sources. Shellfish and other 
seafood, as well as fruits, vegetables, and rice; are the foods most commonly 
contaminated. Arsenic poisoning typically occurs as a result of industrial 
exposure, from contaminated wine or illegally distilled spirits, or in cases of 
malicious intent.
 What is inorganic arsenic? Inorganic arsenic is metallic or a metalloid element that forms a number of poisonous compounds. In industry, it can be found in a gaseous form termed arsine
 gas that is very toxic when inhaled. Inorganic arsenic is found in nature at low levels mostly compounded with oxygen, chlorine, and sulfur. These are called inorganic arsenic compounds. Inorganic arsenic compounds are much more poisonous to most biologic systems (animals, plants, humans) than organic arsenic (see below). Inorganic arsenic occurs in nature in the soil, copper and lead ore deposits, and water, but usually in low concentrations. However, it can become more concentrated when industrial processes use it to make wood preservatives, metal compounds, or organic arsenic-containing compounds such as insecticides, weed killers, and other compounds. If such compounds are burned, inorganic arsenic can be released into the air and later settle on the ground or in water and either remain in the inorganic form or combine with organic material. What is organic arsenic? Organic arsenic is any compound that is made from a chemical combination of 
the element arsenic with any organic compound (compounds containing a large 
amount of carbon). These are often termed arsenical organic compounds. Most 
frequently organic arsenic is a component used in making insecticides and weed 
killers and other compounds. Organic arsenic usually is not poisonous to humans 
but may be poisonous to humans in high concentrations. In general, organic 
arsenic is usually far less poisonous than inorganic arsenic. 
SYMPTOMS:  People can be exposed to arsenic by inhaling it, by consuming contaminated 
foods, water, or
 beverages , or by skin contact. We are normally exposed to trace 
amounts of arsenic in the air and water, and in foods. People may be exposed to 
higher levels if they live near industrial areas that currently or formerly 
contained arsenic compounds. Areas with known high concentrations of arsenic in 
the drinking water are also associated with greater exposure. Acute or immediate symptoms of a toxic level of exposure to arsenic may 
include the following: Vomiting Abdominal pain Diarrhea Dark urine (termed black water urine) Dehydration Cardiac problems Hemolysis (destruction of red blood cells) Vertigo Delirium Shock Death Long-term exposures to arsenic lower than toxic levels can lead to skin 
changes (darkening or discoloration, redness, swelling and hyperkeratosis (skin
 bumps that resemble
 corns or
 warts ). Whitish lines (Mees' lines) may appear in 
the fingernails. Both sensory and motor nerve defects can develop. Additionally,
 liver and kidney function may be affected. Arsenic exposure over the long-term has also been associated with the 
development of certain cancers, and arsenic has been classified as a carcinogen 
by the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). Studies of people in parts of 
Southeast Asia and South America where there has been a high level of arsenic in 
the drinking water have reported an increased risk of developing cancers of the 
bladder, 
kidney, 
lung, and 
skin. Organic arsenic compounds are not as toxic as 
inorganic compounds and are not believed to be linked to
 cancer .
 
DIAGNOSIS:  The history of the patient is very important as exposures are most often from 
industrial accidents so other people (coworkers, rescue personnel) may be 
exposed and not realize they may have some risk also. People exposed to toxic 
levels of arsenic may have breath and urine that smells like
 garlic as a clue to 
their diagnosis. Most doctors that suspect arsenic (or other metal or metalloid 
poisonings) will request lab studies such as 
blood cell counts and
serum
 electrolytes such as calcium and magnesium; if there is evidence of hemolysis 
(blood cell destruction), a type and screening for a potential
 blood transfusion is done.  There are rapid urine "spot" tests available to diagnose elevated 
levels of arsenic, but they usually don't distinguish between organic and 
inorganic arsenic. The patient's blood and urine will be sent for analysis for 
arsenic; a result of &gt; 50 micrograms/L is considered elevated, but acute toxic 
exposures may result in levels 5 to 100 times or more than those which are 
considered "elevated." A speciation test (determines levels of inorganic versus 
organic arsenic) is required in all cases in which total urine arsenic is 
elevated since inorganic arsenic is so toxic. 
Electrocardiograms (
 ECG ,
 EKG ) and 
nerve conduction tests 
are often done in any type of suspected arsenic exposure. Tests for other toxins 
or toxic overdoses (for example,
 Tylenol ingestion) may also be done.
 How is arsenic poisoning treated? Acute toxic inorganic arsenic exposure and arsine gas exposure can rapidly result in death, and there are only a few ways to possibly save the patient&amp;#39;s life.
 Hemodialysis can remove arsenic from the bloodstream, but only before it binds to the tissues so there is only a short time window for this treatment to work. Similarly, arsine binds to and causes rapid destruction of red blood cells, so blood transfusions and exchange transfusions may help the patient. In addition, if the arsenic was ingested, stomach or bowel irrigation may be attempted, but there is no good data to indicate these will be successful. Consultation with a nephrologist and a toxicologist as soon as possible is recommended; other consultants may need to be called (hematologist, psychiatrist, or others). Chelation therapy (the use of
 drugs that selectively bind and effectively inactivate substances) is usually begun quickly through an intravenous line. The drug and the bound arsenic is then excreted through the urine. The chelation drug of choice is Dimercaprol (also termed BAL in oil);
 Succimer (DMSA) has also been used successfully, and Dimerval (DMPS) may also work as a chelator, but it is not readily available in the US. What is the prognosis (outcome) of arsenic poisoning? If the patient survives an acute toxic exposure, most will develop some 
degree of nerve damage to the peripheral nerves (sensory and motor 
disturbances); many survivors may have cardiac, liver, renal, and skin problems; 
the prognosis is fair to poor. Chronic poisoning and organic arsenic exposure 
have better outcomes with fewer and less severe problems. In what foods (
rice), products (
apple juice), or liquids (
water) is arsenic found, where it is used, and what are safe limits? People may be exposed through work in a metal foundry, mining, glass production, the semiconductor industry, in criminal attempts at murder by poisoning,
 suicide attempts, and as a biological warfare agent. Arsenic has been found to contaminate such common items as wine, glues, and pigments. Arsenic is commonly found in many foods both in its relatively nontoxic organic form, and also in the more toxic inorganic form. Consequently, such foods need to be tested for both inorganic and organic arsenic levels. Arsenic has been reported in milk and dairy products, beef, pork, poultry, and cereal. Arsenic is also often found in rice, representing a potentially serious source of exposure in certain at-risk populations (especially children). Many water sources in the world have high levels of arsenic in them, both due to normal arsenic leaching out of the ground and from mining and industrial waste. Recent examples of concerns about arsenic have surfaced because of its presence in apple juice. In most studies, various sources of apple juice tested by government and consumer labs have found that most (over 95% tested) contain a very small amount of arsenic (less than 10 parts per billion) and are safe to drink (in contrast to a TV show that raised alarms about consuming apple juice). However, the FDA qualified their findings by indicating in July 2013, new standards would apply and any juice that contained 10 or more parts per billion (the same level set for safe groundwater) would not be permitted to be sold in the US. This is lower than the previous approved level of less than 23 parts per billion approved in 2008. Nonetheless, other groups suggest that only juice containing less than 3 parts per billion be FDA approved. Two other sources of arsenic, especially of some concern for children, is arsenic in groundwater and subsequently, in rice that is grown in such groundwater. Rice is a common food for children but to date, there are no regulations about the levels of arsenic that are considered safe for consumption. The FDA and the EPA are currently collecting data to make a recommendation about safe levels but many groups are pushing the FDA to act soon. The groups claim some private laboratories have detected that a single adult serving of some commercially available rice can give about 1.5 times the amount of permissible arsenic in one liter of water (under 10 parts per billion), so action on permissible arsenic levels should be done quickly. In 2013, the CDC recommends only about 2 cups of cooked rice per individual (adult) per week.
</first>
</file1>