<file1>
<first>Sjögren's Syndrome
Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome facts Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is an autoimmune disease of salivary and tear glands. Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome involves inflammation of glands and other tissues of the body. Most patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome are female. Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome can be complicated by infections of the eyes,
 breathing passages, and mouth. Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is typically associated with antibodies against a variety of body tissues (autoantibodies). A health care professional can diagnose Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome with a saliva-gland biopsy. Treatment of patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is directed toward relieving symptoms and complications in the particular areas of the body that are involved, such as the eyes, mouth, and vagina. What is Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is an autoimmune disease characterized by dryness of the mouth and eyes. Autoimmune diseases feature the abnormal production of extra antibodies in the blood that are directed against various tissues of the body. The misdirected immune system in autoimmunity tends to lead to inflammation of tissues. This particular autoimmune illness features inflammation and dysfunction in glands of the body that are responsible for producing tears and saliva. Inflammation of the glands that produce tears (lacrimal glands) leads to decreased water production for tears and
 dry eyes . Inflammation of the glands that produce the saliva in the mouth (salivary glands, including the parotid glands) leads to decreased saliva production and
 dry mouth and dry lips. Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome with gland inflammation (resulting in
 dry eyes and mouth, etc.) that is not associated with another connective tissue disease is referred to as primary Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome that is also associated with a connective tissue disease, such as
 rheumatoid arthritis ,
 systemic lupus erythematosus , or
 scleroderma , is referred to as secondary Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. Dryness of eyes and mouth, in patients with or without Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, is sometimes referred to as sicca syndrome.
 What causes Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? While the exact cause of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is not known, there is growing scientific support for genetic (
 inherited ) factors. The genetic background of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome patients is an active area of research. The illness is sometimes found in other family members. It is also found more commonly in families that have members with other autoimmune illnesses, such as
 systemic lupus erythematosus , autoimmune
 thyroid disease , type I
 diabetes , etc. Most patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome are female. What are risk factors for developing Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? The main risk factor for the development of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is being a member of a family that is already characterized as having autoimmune illnesses. This does not mean that it is predictable that a member of a family with known autoimmunity will develop the disease, only that is more likely than if there were no family members with known autoimmunity. Accordingly, it is likely that certain genes that are inherited from ancestors can predispose one to the development of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. It should also be noted that Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome can also be sporadic and occur in a person from a family with no known autoimmunity.
 What are Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome symptoms and signs? Symptoms of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome can involve the glands, as above, but there are also possible effects of the illness involving other organs of the body (extraglandular manifestations). When the tear gland (lacrimal gland) is inflamed from Sjögren&amp;#39;s, the resulting eye dryness can progressively lead to symptoms such as eye irritation, decreased tear production, a "gritty" sensation, eye infection, and serious
 abrasion of the dome of the eye (
 cornea ). Dry eyes can lead to infections of the eyes and inflammation of the eyelids (
 blepharitis ). The condition of having dry eyes is medically referred to as xerophthalmia. When the eyes become inflamed from dryness, it is referred to as keratoconjunctivitis sicca. Inflammation of the salivary glands can lead to the following symptoms and signs: mouth dryness, swallowing difficulties, dental decay, cavities , gum disease , mouth sores and swelling, hoarseness or impaired voice, abnormality of taste or loss of taste, dry
 cough , and stones and/or infection of the parotid gland inside of the cheeks. Dry lips often accompany the mouth dryness.
 Dry mouth is a condition medically referred to as
 xerostomia . Other glands that can become inflamed, though less commonly, in Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome include those of the lining of the breathing passages (leading to lung infections) and the vagina (sometimes causing a woman
 pain during intercourse or recurrent vaginal infections). Extraglandular (outside of the glands) problems in Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome include
 fatigue ,
 joint pain or inflammation (
 arthritis ),
 Raynaud&amp;#39;s phenomenon , lung inflammation,
 lymph node enlargement, and kidney, nerve, joint
 pain , and muscle disease with
 muscle pain and
 weakness . A rare serious complication of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is inflammation of the blood vessels (
 vasculitis ), which can damage the tissues of the body that are supplied by these vessels. A common disease that is occasionally associated with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is autoimmune
 thyroiditis (
 Hashimoto&amp;#39;s thyroiditis ), which can lead to abnormal
 thyroid hormone levels detected by
 thyroid blood tests .
 Heartburn and
 difficulty swallowing can result from
 gastroesophageal reflux disease (
 GERD ), another common condition associated with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. A rare and serious disease that is uncommonly associated with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is
 primary biliary cirrhosis , an autoimmune disorder of the
 liver that leads to scarring of the liver tissue. A small percentage of patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome develop
 cancer of the lymph glands (
 lymphoma ). This usually develops only after many years with the illness. Unusual lymph node swelling should be reported to the physician.
 How do health care professionals diagnose Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? The diagnosis of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome involves noting criterion such as dryness of the eyes and mouth. Significant dryness of the eyes can be determined in the doctor&amp;#39;s office by testing the eye&amp;#39;s ability to wet a small testing paper strip placed under the
 eyelid (Schirmer&amp;#39;s test using Schirmer tear test strips). More sophisticated testing can be done by an eye specialist (ophthalmologist). Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome salivary glands can become larger and harden or become tender. Salivary-gland inflammation can be detected by radiologic nuclear medicine salivary scans. Also, the diminished ability of the salivary glands to produce saliva can be measured with salivary flow testing. The diagnosis is strongly supported by abnormal findings of a biopsy of salivary-gland tissue. The glands of the lower lip are occasionally used for a biopsy sample of the salivary-gland tissue in the diagnosis of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. The lower lip salivary-gland biopsy procedure is performed under local anesthesia with the surgeon making a tiny incision on the inner part of the lower lip to expose and remove a sample of the tiny salivary glands within. Patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome typically produce a variety of extra antibodies against body tissues (autoantibodies). These can be detected through blood testing and include antinuclear antibodies (ANA), which are present in nearly all patients. Typical antibodies that are found in most, but not all patients, are SS-A and SS-B antibodies (Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome A and B antibodies, also known as anti-Ro and anti-La antibodies),
 rheumatoid factor , thyroid antibodies, and others. Low red blood count (
 anemia ) and abnormal blood levels of markers of inflammation (
 sedimentation rate ,
 C-reactive protein ) are seen.
 What is the
treatmentfor Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? Will changes to one&amp;#39;s diet improve Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome symptoms and signs? The treatment of patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is directed toward the particular areas of the body that are involved and prevention of complications such as infection. There is no cure for Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome. Dryness of the eyes can be helped by artificial tears, using eye-lubricant ointments at night, and minimizing the use of hair dryers. When dryness becomes more significant, the ophthalmologist can plug the tear duct closed so that tears cover the eye longer.
 Cyclosporine eyedrops (
 Restasis ) are approved medicated eyedrops that can reduce the inflammation of the tear glands, thereby improving their function. Signs of eye infection (
 conjunctivitis ), such as pus or excessive redness or pain, should be evaluated by the doctor. Dietary addition of
 flaxseed oil may also benefit eye dryness.
 Vitamin D supplementation may be beneficial, especially in those who have insufficient
 vitamin D blood levels. The
 dry mouth can be helped by drinking plenty of fluids, humidifying air, and good dental care to avoid dental decay. The glands can be stimulated to produce saliva by sucking on sugarless lemon drops or
 glycerin swabs. Additional treatments for the symptom of dry mouth are prescription medications that are saliva
 stimulants , such as
 pilocarpine (
 Salagen ) and
 cevimeline (
 Evoxac ). These medications should be avoided by people with certain heart diseases,
 asthma , or
 glaucoma . Artificial saliva preparations can ease many of the problems associated with dry mouth. Many of these types of agents are available as
 over-the-counter products , including
 toothpaste , gum, and mouthwash (Biotene).
 Numoisyn Liquid and lozenges are also available for the treatment of dry mouth.
 Vitamin E oil has been used with some success. Infections of the mouth and
 teeth should be addressed as early as possible in order to avoid more severe complications. Diligent dental care is very important. Moist, warm compresses can be massaged onto the parotid glands to help relieve swelling and pain. Saltwater (saline) nasal sprays can help dryness in the passages of the nose. A woman should consider vaginal lubricant for sexual intercourse if
 vaginal dryness is a problem. Hydroxychloroquine (Plaquenil) has been helpful for some manifestations of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, particularly
 fatigue , and muscle and
 joint pains . Serious complications of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, such as vasculitis, can require immune-suppression medications, including cortisone (
 prednisone and others) and/or
 azathioprine (Imuran) or
 cyclophosphamide (
 Cytoxan ). Infections, which can complicate Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, are addressed with appropriate antibiotics.
 Cancer of the
 lymph nodes (lymphoma), a rare complication of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, is treated independently.
 What are
complicationsof Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? It is not uncommon for people with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome to have complications of infections. Infections that are common in these patients include dental infections, eye infections,
 sinusitis ,
 bronchitis , and
 vaginitis . Close monitoring and early treatment of these infections are keys to optimal outcomes. Some people with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome can develop inflammation of the parotid gland in the cheeks. This can lead to dryness of the ducts that drain the gland and stones can form that block these drainage tubes. This can be serious and require aggressive antibiotics and surgery. A small percentage of patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome develop
 cancer of the lymph glands (lymphoma). This usually develops only after many years with the illness. Unusual lymph node swelling should be reported to the physician. A rare and serious disease that is uncommonly associated with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is primary biliary
 cirrhosis , an autoimmune disease of the liver that leads to scarring of the liver tissue. Another rare serious complication of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is inflammation of the blood vessels (vasculitis), which can damage the tissues of the body that are supplied by these vessels. Is it possible to prevent Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? Because Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is felt to be inherited, there is no particular way to prevent developing the disease. However, preventing complications of Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome, such as infection, eye irritation, etc., can be achieved using the methods described above. What is the
prognosisfor patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? With proper attention to eye and oral care, the outlook for patients with Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome is generally excellent. Eye dryness can lead to serious injury to the eye, particularly the cornea, and this should be avoided by consultation with an eye specialist. Mouth dryness can lead to dental decay and parotid gland infection and parotid stones. Optimal oral hygiene is essential. The serious complications of primary biliary cirrhosis and lymphoma can dramatically affect prognosis and are monitored for in routine regular office visits.
 What types of doctors treat Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome? Doctors that treat Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome include general medicine physicians including general practitioners, family medicine doctors, and internists, as well as specialists including
 rheumatologists , ophthalmologists, and otolaryngologists (ENT physicians). Conclusion Sjögren syndrome is an area of active immunology research. Many new treatments will be available in the near future. Research has suggested that
 rituximab (
 Rituxan ) may be beneficial for many features of Sjögren syndrome. Sjögren syndrome is named after a Swedish ophthalmologist, Henrik Sjögren. In the early 1900s, Sjögren called the syndrome "keratoconjunctivitis sicca." The name sicca syndrome is technically now used only to describe the combination of dryness of the mouth and eyes, regardless of cause. The term
 sicca refers to the dryness of the eyes and mouth.</first>
</file1>