<file1>
<first>Joint Replacement Surgery of the Hand
What happens in joint replacement surgery? Joint replacement surgery involves replacing a destroyed joint 
with an artificial joint. In knee or
 hip replacement surgery, the 
artificial joint is made out of metal and
 plastic .  In the case of 
joint replacement in the hand, the new joint is most commonly 
composed of silicone rubber or the patient's own tissues such as a portion of
tendon. Joint replacement surgery, also known as arthroplasty, is very 
common. Each year, orthopedic surgeons perform thousands of joint 
replacement surgeries in the U.S.  (Most of these procedures are performed on the large weight-bearing joints such as the hips and knees.) 
Joint replacement surgery in the hand is typically used in treating 
severe
 arthritis that involves the small joints of the hand. The hips and knees receive continuous
 stress from
 walking ,
 running , sporting activity, or injury and are more commonly affected 
by the wearing of cartilage (
 degenerative arthritis ) than the  hand 
joints.  However, the joints of the hand do experience
 stress in 
everyday use, and because the hand joints are smaller, these stresses 
are concentrated over a smaller surface area. The high ratio of 
stress to surface area can cause the smooth joint cartilage to wear 
over the years.  As the cartilage degenerates, the underlying bone 
becomes exposed.  When the deteriorated joint moves, bone rubs upon 
bone causing
 pain , swelling, limiting motion, and frequently causing 
a grinding or popping sensation.  Furthermore, forms of arthritis 
that are caused by inflammation of the tissues lining the joint 
frequently affect the small joints of the hands and wrists to cause 
joint destruction.  Examples include
 rheumatoid arthritis and
 psoriatic arthritis .
 
SYMPTOMS:  The most common symptoms of arthritis of the hands include
 pain , 
stiffness, and swelling over the joints. The pain is usually worsened 
when the joint is moved.  Moreover, motion of the joint is frequently 
limited due to pain and joint contractures.  Symptoms can lead to 
difficulty with daily living activities including tying shoes, 
buttoning buttons, opening jars, or turning a key in a lock. Physical signs of arthritis of the hand include changes in the 
appearance of the joints.  The joints most commonly affected by 
degenerative arthritis are those at the ends of the fingers.  Swelling 
and
 bumps , or nodes, can occur at the small joints at the area of the 
base of the nail.  These
 bumps are called Heberden nodes and can 
become extremely painful.  The joint at the base of the thumb can 
also become swollen with
 bone spurs and cause pain and deformity.  
The joint destruction also leads to severe pain when pinching the 
fingers together and gripping forcefully.  Joint motion limitation 
can also decrease the ability to grip. Wrist arthritis can cause pain with motion of the wrist or 
grasping and lifting.  Wrist range of motion is frequently limited by 
the arthritis.  Patients typically experience relief when the wrist 
is stabilized by a splint. Rheumatoid arthritis frequently causes swelling, pain, and 
stiffness in the wrists, as well as the small joints in the middle 
and at the base of the fingers. This disease frequently causes hand 
deformities.  Tissue lumps called rheumatoid nodules can form over 
the joints of the hand and wrist.  The joints of the fingers and 
thumb can become deformed and contracted by the destruction of the 
supporting ligaments, so that grasping and pinching movements are not 
possible.
 How are patients with hand joint abnormalities evaluated? The diagnosis of hand joint problems typically involves 
evaluating symptoms, physical examination, and the x-ray appearance of 
the joints.  Blood testing is sometimes also helpful in the 
assessment process.  Joint replacement surgery becomes a treatment 
option when significant joint destruction and/or deformity are 
present. What are the different surgical options? Surgical options include The optimal surgical treatment of arthritis of the hand and wrist 
varies from patient to patient and is based on many factors.  These 
factors include the patient's age, hand dominance, employment, level 
of pain, functional goals, and underlying disease. When is surgical cleaning of the joint the best alternative? Surgical cleaning of the joint, or salvage procedure, is usually 
performed in cases of early "wear and tear" arthritis where there are 
painful bone spurs or, in cases of
 rheumatoid arthritis , where there 
is a large amount of inflamed tissue.  Removal of bone spurs is 
especially helpful when the arthritis involves the joints at the ends 
of the fingers (distal interphalangeal or DIP joints). What is a joint fusion? When is it the best surgical 
option? Fusion of a joint involves removing the joint and 
surgically "fusing" the bone ends so that the two bones effectively 
become one solid bone.  This procedure terminates all motion at that 
joint and thus eliminates the pain. The benefit of fusion is pain 
relief and the downside is elimination of motion at the fused joint, 
which can hinder function. This surgical option is reserved for 
patients with advanced arthritis. Joint fusion is usually the best surgical option in patients who 
are younger and very active. Younger patients may not be candidates 
for joint replacement because of the increased stress demand on the 
joints which accompany higher activity levels.  This increased stress 
demand can quickly wear out an artificial joint.
 When is joint replacement surgery the best surgical option? Joint replacement surgery in the hand is an excellent option for 
treating arthritis of the hand in older, low-activity patients and 
for those with rheumatoid arthritis. Joint replacement surgery can 
provide pain relief, increase finger range of motion, and improve 
hand function. How do the surgical options vary with the different joints of 
the hands and wrists? Hand joint replacement surgery options differ according to the 
specific joint(s) involved. 1.
 DIP joint (joint closest to the fingertip) : This joint is 
not a good candidate for joint replacement.  The bones are very small 
and do not hold the implant very well. The best treatment option for 
advanced arthritis at this joint is fusion.  Hand function is only 
minimally compromised by lack of motion at this joint after a fusion 
procedure, while pain is relieved. 2.
 PIP joint (second joint from the fingertip) : Joint 
replacement is commonly performed in the PIP joint.  Hand function, 
especially power grasp, can be hindered by fusion of this joint.  The 
small and ring fingers are the best candidates for joint replacement 
as they are the most important for power grasp.  The index finger is 
not a good candidate for a PIP joint replacement, as it must 
withstand sideways forces which accompany movements such as key 
turning and fine manipulation of objects.  These forces cause excess 
stress on the joint implant and can lead to early implant breakage. There have been numerous false (prosthetic) joints designed for PIP 
joint replacement, but only one has stood the test of time.  The only 
nonexperimental PIP joint replacement is the silicone 
interpositional arthroplasty.  These joints are made of silicone 
rubber and have a flexible hinge in the middle and stems at the ends 
which insert into the shaft of the bone, providing stability.  The 
most frequently used silicone joint implants are termed the Swanson 
implant and the Sutter implant. The best results with PIP joint replacement are in patients with 
rheumatoid arthritis and in older, lower-activity patients. 3.
 MCP joint (third joint from the fingertip) :
 Osteoarthritis rarely affects the MCP joints.  The most common need for joint 
replacement in this joint is destruction from rheumatoid arthritis.  
Silicone joint replacement of the MCP joint has been used since the 
1960s and has produced excellent long-term results. 4.
 Thumb basal joint (where the thumb meets the wrist) : This 
joint is exposed to very high stresses with normal activities.  
Forces felt at the tip of the thumb are multiplied 12 times in 
their effect to the thumb base, thus predisposing this joint to 
wear.  Arthritis of this joint is very common, especially in women, 
and frequently requires joint replacement.  Attempts at silicone 
replacement of this joint have not been as successful as hoped due to 
implant failure and bone destruction.  Thus, the most common joint 
replacement procedure for the thumb base is done with natural 
material.  The procedure is termed the ligament reconstruction-tendon 
interposition procedure (LRTI).  This procedure uses the patient's 
own tendon to stabilize the thumb and resurface the joint.  LRTI 
provides stability and pain relief. Long-term results have been 
excellent.  This has also been called the tendon roll or "anchovy" 
procedure because the tendon used is curled to form the new joint 
cushion. 5.
 Wrist joint : Most patients with wrist arthritis are best 
treated with surgical joint cleaning or fusion and not joint 
replacement.  Most wrist-joint prostheses on the market are currently 
investigational and for use in extremely low activity patients with
 osteoarthritis or rheumatoid arthritis. Summary Arthritis of the hand and wrist is a very common and complex 
problem with many nonsurgical and surgical treatment options.  
Deciding which alternative is best can require the skills of the primary 
doctor, the arthritis specialist (
 rheumatologist ), and/or an 
orthopedic surgeon.
 Joint Replacement Surgery of the Hand At A Glance Joint replacement surgery involves replacing a destroyed joint with an artificial joint. This procedure is typically employed in treating severe arthritis involving certain joints. Surgical options for treatment of arthritis of the hand include cleaning of the abnormal cartilage and bone, fusion, and replacement surgery.
</first>
</file1>