<file1>
<first>Asthma
What should I know about Asthma? What is the medical definition of asthma? Asthma is a complex clinical syndrome of chronic
 airway inflammation characterized by recurrent, reversible, airway obstruction. Airway inflammation also leads to airway hyperreactivity, which causes airways to narrow in response to various stimuli. 
RISKS:  Asthma is a common chronic condition, affecting approximately 8%-10% of Americans, or an estimated 23 million Americans as of 2008. Asthma remains a leading cause of missed work days. It is responsible for 1.5 million emergency department visits annually and up to 500,000 hospitalizations. Over 3,300 Americans die annually from asthma. Furthermore, as is the case with other
 allergic conditions, such as
 eczema (
 atopic dermatitis ),
 hay fever (
 allergic rhinitis ), and food
 allergies , the prevalence of asthma appears to be on the rise. Asthma vs. COPD: What are the differences? Asthma is characterized by reversible airway narrowing, whereas
 COPD (
 chronic obstructive pulmonary disease ) typically has fixed airway narrowing. Some
 symptoms of COPD are similar to asthma, including
 wheezing ,
 shortness of breath , and
 cough . The
 cough in
 COPD can be more productive of mucus than asthma, and patients with severe
 COPD may need oxygen supplementation. COPD is very often a result of
 cigarette smoke exposure, either direct or secondhand, although severe asthma can evolve to COPD over time. Medications used to treat COPD include inhaled
 corticosteroids ,
 bronchodilators , inhaled
 corticosteroid /
 bronchodilator combinations, long-acting muscarinic antagonists, and oral steroids. There is a newly described syndrome called asthma/COPD overlap syndrome that displays characteristics of both asthma and COPD. This is an area of medicine that needs further study. 
CAUSES:  Asthma results from complex interactions between an individual&amp;#39;s inherited genetic makeup and their interactions with the environment. The factors that cause a genetically predisposed individual to become
 asthmatic are poorly understood. The following are risk factors for asthma: Family history of allergic conditions Personal history of hay
 fever (allergic
 rhinitis ) Viral respiratory illness, such as
 respiratory syncytial virus (RSV), during childhood Exposure to cigarette smoke Obesity Lower socioeconomic status What are the different
typesof asthma? The many potential triggers of asthma largely explain the different ways in which asthma can present. In most cases, the disease starts in early childhood from 2-6 years of age. In this age group, the cause of asthma is often linked to exposure to allergens, such as dust mites, tobacco smoke, and viral respiratory infections. In very young children, less than 2 years of age, asthma can be difficult to diagnose with certainty. Wheezing at this age often follows a viral infection and might disappear later, without ever leading to asthma. Asthma, however, can develop again in adulthood.
 Adult-onset asthma occurs more often in women, mostly middle-aged, and frequently follows a respiratory tract infection. The triggers in this group are usually nonallergic in nature. Your doctor may refer to asthma as being "extrinsic" or "intrinsic." A better understanding of the nature of asthma can help explain the differences between them. Extrinsic, or allergic asthma, is more common and typically develops in childhood. Approximately 70%-80% of children with asthma also have documented
 allergies . Typically, there is a family history of
 allergies . Additionally, other allergic conditions, such as nasal allergies or
 eczema , are often also present. Allergic asthma often goes into remission in early adulthood. However, in many cases, the asthma reappears later. Intrinsic asthma represents a small amount of all cases. It usually develops after the age of 30 and is not typically associated with allergies. Women are more frequently affected and many cases seem to follow a respiratory tract infection. Obesity also appears to be a risk factor for this type of asthma. Intrinsic asthma can be difficult to treat and symptoms are often chronic and year-round. 
SYMPTOMS:  The classic signs and
 symptoms of asthma are shortness of breath, cough (often worse at night), and wheezing (high-pitched whistling sound produced by turbulent airflow through narrow airways, typically with
 exhalation ). Many patients also report chest tightness. It is important to note that these symptoms are episodic, and individuals with asthma can go long periods of time without any symptoms. Common triggers for asthmatic symptoms include exposure to allergens (pets, dust mites, cockroach, molds, and pollens),
 exercise , and viral infections. Tobacco use or exposure to
 secondhand smoke complicates asthma management. Many of the symptoms and signs of asthma are nonspecific and can be seen in other conditions as well. Symptoms that might suggest conditions other than asthma include new symptom onset in older age, the presence of associated symptoms (such as chest discomfort,
 lightheadedness ,
 palpitations , and
 fatigue ), and lack of response to appropriate
 medications for asthma . The physical exam in asthma is often completely normal. Occasionally, wheezing is present. In an asthma exacerbation, the respiratory rate increases, the heart rate increases, and the work of
 respiration increases. Individuals often require accessory muscles to breathe, and breath sounds can be diminished. It is important to note that the blood oxygen level typically remains fairly normal even in the midst of a significant asthma exacerbation. Low blood oxygen level is therefore concerning for impending respiratory failure. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of asthma begins with a detailed history and physical examination. Primary-care providers are familiar with the diagnosis of asthma, but specialists such as allergists or pulmonologists may be involved. A typical history is an individual with a family history of allergic conditions or a personal history of allergic rhinitis who experiences
 coughing , wheezing, and difficulty
 breathing , especially with
 exercise or during the night. There may also be a propensity toward
 bronchitis or respiratory infections. In addition to a typical history, improvement with a trial of appropriate medications is very suggestive of asthma. In addition to the history and exam, the following are diagnostic procedures that can be used to help with the diagnosis of asthma: Lung function testing with spirometry: This test measures lung function as the patient breathes into a tube. If lung function improves significantly following the administration of a bronchodilator, such as
 albuterol , this essentially confirms the diagnosis of asthma. It is important to note, however, that normal lung function testing does not rule out the possibility of asthma. Measurement of exhaled nitric oxide (FeNO): This can be performed by a quick and relatively simple breathing maneuver, similar to spirometry. Elevated levels of exhaled nitric oxide are suggestive of "allergic" inflammation seen in conditions such as asthma. Skin testing for common aeroallergens: The presence of sensitivities to environmental allergies increases the likelihood of asthma. Of note, skin testing is generally more useful than blood work (in vitro testing) for environmental allergies. Testing for food allergies is not indicated in the diagnosis of asthma. Other potential but less commonly used tests include provocation testing such as a methacholine challenge, which tests for airway hyperresponsiveness. Hyperresponsiveness is the tendency of the breathing tubes to constrict or narrow in response to irritants. A negative methacholine challenge makes asthma much less likely. Specialists sometimes also measure sputum eosinophils, another marker for "allergic" inflammation seen in asthma. Chest imaging may show hyperinflation, but is often normal in asthma. Tests to rule out other conditions, such as cardiac testing, may also be indicated in certain cases. Blood testing can sometimes help differentiate between different types of asthma. Helpful blood tests include checking for the level of allergic antibody (IgE) or specialized white blood cells called eosinophils, which are often associated with allergic or extrinsic asthma. 
TREATMENT:  Are there
home remediesfor asthma? As per widely used guidelines, the treatment goals for asthma are to: adequately control symptoms, minimize the risk of future exacerbations, maintain normal lung function, maintain normal activity levels, and use the least amount of medication possible with the least amount of potential side effects. Inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) are the most effective anti-inflammatory agents available for the chronic treatment of asthma and are first-line therapy per most asthma guidelines. It is well recognized that ICS are very effective in decreasing the risk of asthma exacerbations. Furthermore, the combination of a long-acting bronchodilator (LABA) and an ICS has a significant additional beneficial effect on improving asthma control. The most commonly used
 asthma medications include the following: Short-acting bronchodilators (albuterol [Proventil, Ventolin, ProAir, ProAir RespiClick, Maxair,
 Xopenex ]) provide quick relief and can be used in conjunction for exercise-induced symptoms. Inhaled steroids (
 budesonide [
 Pulmicort Turbuhaler ,
 Pulmicort Respules ], fluticasone [Flovent, Arnuity Ellipta], beclomethasone [
 Qvar ],
 mometasone [Asmanex], ciclesonide [Alvesco], flunisolide [
 Aerobid , Aerospan]) are first-line anti-inflammatory therapy. Long-acting bronchodilators (
 salmeterol [
 Serevent ], formoterol [
 Foradil ], vilanterol) can be added to ICS as additive therapy. LABAs should never be used alone for the treatment of asthma. Leukotriene modifiers (
 montelukast [
 Singulair ],
 zafirlukast [
 Accolate ],
 zileuton [
 Zyflo ]) can also serve as anti-inflammatory agents. Anticholinergic agents (ipratropium [
 Atrovent , Atrovent HFA], tiotropium [Spiriva], umeclidinium [Incruse Ellipta]) can help decrease sputum production. Anti-IgE treatment (
 omalizumab [
 Xolair ]) can be used in allergic asthma. Anti-IL5 treatment (mepolizumab [Nucala], reslizumab [Cinqair]) can be used in eosinophilic asthma. Chromones (
 cromolyn [
 Intal ,
 Opticrom ,
 Gastrocrom ], nedocromil [
 Alocril ]) stabilize mast cells (allergic cells) but are rarely used in clinical practice. Theophylline (
 Respbid ,
 Slo-Bid ,
 Theo-24 ) also helps with bronchodilation (opening the airways) but is rarely used in clinical practice due to an unfavorable side-effect profile. Systemic steroids (
 prednisone [
 Deltasone ,
 Liquid Pred ],
 prednisolone [
 Flo-Pred ,
 Pediapred ,
 Orapred , Orapred ODT],
 methylprednisolone [
 Medrol ,
 Depo-Medrol ,
 Solu-Medrol ],
 dexamethasone [DexPak]) are potent anti-inflammatory agents that are routinely used to treat asthma exacerbations but pose numerous unwanted side effects if used repeatedly or chronically. Numerous additional monoclonal antibodies are also currently being studied and will likely be available within the next couple of years. Immunotherapy or
 allergy shots have been shown to decrease medication reliance in allergic asthma. There are no home remedies that have proven benefit for asthma. There is often concern about potential long-term side effects of inhaled corticosteroids. Numerous studies have repeatedly shown that even long-term use of inhaled corticosteroids has very few if any sustained, clinically significant side effects, including changes in bone health, growth, or weight. However, the goal always remains to treat all individuals with the least amount of medication that is effective. Patients with asthma should be routinely reassessed for any appropriate changes to their medical regimen. Asthma medications can be administered via inhalers either with or without a spacer or nebulized solution. It is important to note that if an individual has proper technique with an inhaler, the amount of medication deposited in the
 lungs is no different than that when using a nebulized solution. When prescribing asthma medications, it is essential to provide the appropriate teaching on proper delivery technique. Smoking cessation and/or minimizing exposure to
 secondhand smoke are critical when treating asthma. Treating concurrent conditions such as allergic rhinitis and
 gastroesophageal reflux disease (
 GERD ) may also improve asthma control.
 Vaccinations such as the annual
 influenza vaccination and
 pneumonia vaccination are also indicated. Although the vast majority of individuals with asthma are treated as outpatients, treatment of severe exacerbations can require management in the emergency department or inpatient hospitalization. These individuals typically require use of supplemental oxygen, early administration of systemic steroids, and frequent or even continuous administration of bronchodilators via a nebulized solution. Individuals at high risk for poor asthma outcomes are referred to a specialist (pulmonologist or allergist). The following factors should prompt consideration or referral: History of ICU admission or multiple hospitalizations for asthma History of multiple visits to the emergency department for asthma History of frequent use of systemic steroids for asthma Ongoing symptoms despite the use of appropriate medications Significant allergies contributing to poorly controlled asthma What should someone do when experiencing an asthma attack? Patients experiencing acute
 asthma symptoms should first use their rescue inhaler (albuterol). If asthma symptoms are worsening and use of albuterol is increasing, then asthma patients should have a medical evaluation. A course of oral steroids may be indicated and an adjustment in asthma maintenance therapy may be needed. If symptoms are rapidly progressive, asthma patients should seek emergency medical care. What is an asthma action plan? Patient education is a critical component in the successful management of asthma. An asthma action plan provides an individual with specific directions for daily asthma management and for adjusting medications in response to increasing symptoms or decreasing lung function, as usually measured by a peak flow meter. What is the prognosis for asthma? The prognosis for asthma is generally favorable. Children experience complete remission more often than adults. Although adults with asthma experience a greater rate of loss in their lung function as compared to age-controlled counterparts, this decline is usually not as severe as seen in other conditions, such as
 chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or
 emphysema . Asthma in the absence of other comorbidities does not appear to shorten life expectancy. Risk factors for poor prognosis from asthma include a history of hospitalizations, especially ICU admissions or
 intubation , frequent reliance on systemic steroids, significant medical comorbidities. The airway narrowing in asthma may become fixed over time and can resemble COPD or emphysema. The other main complication of asthma is due to side effects from oral steroid use, which can include bone loss (
 osteoporosis ),
 weight gain , and glucose intolerance. 
PREVENTION:  With the increasing prevalence of asthma, numerous studies have looked for risk factors and ways to potentially prevent asthma. It has been shown that individuals living on farms are protected against wheezing, asthma, and even environmental allergies. The role of air pollution has been questioned in both the increased incidence of asthma and in regards to asthma exacerbations. Climate change is also being studied as a factor in the increased incidence of asthma. Maternal
 smoking during pregnancy is a risk factor for asthma and poor outcomes. Tobacco smoke is also a significant risk factor for the development and progression of asthma. Treatment of environmental allergies with
 allergen immunotherapy, or
 allergy shots, has been shown to decrease a child&amp;#39;s risk of developing asthma. The development of asthma is ultimately a complex process influenced by many environmental and genetic factors, and currently there is no proven way to decrease an individual&amp;#39;s risk of developing asthma.</first>
</file1>