<file1>
<first>Microscopic Colitis (Lymphocytic Colitis and Collagenous Colitis)
What is colitis? Colitis means inflammation of the colon. The colon, also 
known as the
 large intestine or large bowel, 
constitutes the last part of the digestive tract. The colon is a long, muscular 
tube that receives digested food from the small intestine. It removes water 
from the undigested food, stores the undigested food, and then eliminates it from the body through 
bowel movements. The rectum is the last part of the colon adjacent to the anus. The common
 symptoms of colitis include: abdominal pain , diarrhea , and sometimes,
 rectal bleeding . There are many different types of colitis 
with different causes. Some examples of colitis include: infectious colitis caused by bacteria (such as
 shigella ,
 Campylobacter ,
 E. 
coli , and
 C. 
  difficile ) infectious colitis caused by a virus (such as
 cytomegalovirus [
 CMV ]) radiation colitis (such as following 
 treatment with 
  radiation for
 prostate cancer ) ischemic colitis (such as blockage of an artery in 
  the colon by a blood 
 clot. If the
 blood clot interrupts the flow of blood to a segment of the colon, the result is 
 inflammation of that segment and, sometimes, even death [
 gangrene ] of the 
  segment) Crohn's disease and
 ulcerative colitis (two related 
  conditions that are caused by abnormalities of the body's immune system in which the body  inappropriately makes antibodies and 
chemicals that attack the colon).
 Crohn's disease and
 ulcerative colitis are 
 also referred to as
 inflammatory bowel disease (
 IBD ). Infectious, radiation, ischemic, ulcerative, and Crohn's colitis all have 
visible abnormalities of the inner lining of the colon. These abnormalities 
include
 edema (swelling of the lining), redness, bleeding from the lining with 
gentle rubbing (friability), and ulcers. These abnormalities can be seen during
 colonoscopy (examination of the 
entire colon using a long flexible viewing tube) or
 flexible sigmoidoscopy (examination of the rectum and the sigmoid colon - the segment of the colon closest to the rectum). Edema and inflammation of the colon's lining interferes 
with the absorption of water from the undigested food, and the unabsorbed water 
exits the rectum as
 diarrhea . Pus and fluid also are secreted into the colon and 
add to the
 diarrhea . The redness, bleeding from the lining with gentle rubbing 
(friability), and ulcerations in the lining of the colon contribute to the rectal 
bleeding.
 What diseases are not colitis? Individuals with
 irritable bowel syndrome (
 IBS ) do not have 
colitis, even though this condition is sometimes referred to as having "
 spastic colitis ." 
These individuals may have symptoms that mimic colitis such as diarrhea, abdominal
 pain , and mucus in stool. Nevertheless, there is no inflammation of the colon 
in patients with
 IBS . The cause of symptoms in 
IBS is not clearly known; it may be caused by either abnormal motility (abnormal 
contractions) of the intestinal muscles or abnormally sensitive nerves in the
 intestines (visceral hypersensitivity). What is microscopic colitis? Microscopic colitis refers to inflammation of the colon 
that is only visible when the colon's lining is examined under a microscope. The 
appearance of the inner colon lining in microscopic colitis is normal by visual 
inspection during colonoscopy or flexible sigmoidoscopy. The diagnosis of 
microscopic colitis is made when a doctor, while performing colonoscopy or 
flexible sigmoidoscopy, takes biopsies (small samples of tissue) of the normal-appearing lining, and 
then 
examines the biopsies under a microscope. There are two types of microscopic colitis: 1) lymphocytic colitis and 
2) collagenous colitis. Some experts believe that lymphocytic colitis and 
collagenous colitis represent different stages of the same disease. The inflammation and the collagen probably interfere with absorption of water 
from the colon, resulting in the diarrhea.
 
CAUSES:  The cause(s) of microscopic colitis is unknown. Some experts suspect that 
microscopic colitis is an autoimmune disorder similar to the autoimmune 
disorders that cause chronic
 ulcerative colitis and
 Crohn's disease . One study has implicated long term (longer than 6 months) use of 
 nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
 drugs (
 NSAIDs ) as a cause of microscopic colitis. 
Some individuals' diarrhea improves after stopping the NSAIDs. Several other 
drugs have also been incriminated as a cause of microscopic colitis. The most 
common are
 proton pump inhibitors (
 PPIs ) such as
 lansoprazole (
 Prevacid ,
 Prevacid SoluTab ),
 omeprazole (
 Prilosec ,
 Zegerid ), and
 esomeprazole (
 Nexium );
the Statin
 simvastatin (
 Zocor ); H2 blocker
 ranitidine (
 Zantac ); SSRI
 sertraline Zoloft ); and P2Y12 inhibitor
 ticlopidine (Tilcid). 
SYMPTOMS:  The primary symptom of microscopic colitis is chronic, 
watery diarrhea. Individuals with microscopic colitis can have diarrhea for months 
or years before the diagnosis is made. Typically, the symptoms begin very 
gradually and are intermittent in nature with periods when the person feels 
well, followed by bouts of chronic diarrhea. This chronic diarrhea of microscopic 
colitis is different from the acute diarrhea of infectious colitis, which typically lasts only days 
to weeks. Some individuals with microscopic colitis also may experience mild abdominal 
cramps and
 pain .
 Blood in the stool is unusual.
 
RISKS:  The prevalence of microscopic colitis in the U.S. is not clearly known. Microscopic colitis most commonly occurs in the middle aged and elderly patients and is more common among women than men. When should I seek medical care for microscopic colitis? A person should seek medical care if the diarrhea lasts for more than 2 weeks or is accompanied with symptoms such as
 weight loss ,
 fatigue , and
 abdominal pain . 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of microscopic colitis is made by performing biopsies from different regions of the colon during colonoscopy or sigmoidoscopy. The abnormalities of the colon&amp;#39;s lining in microscopic colitis occur in a patchy distribution (areas of normal lining may coexist adjacent to areas of abnormal lining). For this reason, multiple biopsies should be taken from several different regions of the colon in order to accurately make a diagnosis. The patchy nature of microscopic colitis also is the reason why flexible sigmoidoscopy often is inadequate in diagnosing the condition because the abnormalities of microscopic colitis may be absent from the sigmoid colon (the colonic segment that is closest to the rectum and is within the reach of a sigmoidoscope) in some of the patients with microscopic colitis. Thus, biopsies of other regions of the colon accessible only with colonoscopy may be necessary for diagnosing microscopic colitis.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of microscopic colitis has not been standardized because there 
have not been adequate large scale, 
prospective, placebo controlled treatment 
trials. The following strategies are safe and may relieve diarrhea in some 
patients: Avoid nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) 
 and the other drugs mentioned under causes of microscopic colitis. Trial of lactose elimination (just to eliminate the 
  possibility that intolerance to lactose 
 in milk is aggravating the 
  diarrhea) Antidiarrhea agents such as
 loperamide (
 Imodium ) or
 diphenoxylate and atropine (
 Lomotil ) Bismuth subsalicylate 
 (
 Pepto-Bismol ) budesonide (Entocort 
 EC)
 5-ASA (
 mesalamine ) compounds such as
 Asacol ,
 Pentasa , or
 Colazal Controlled trials showed that budesonide 
(Entocort, a poorly absorbed steroid) is effective in controlling diarrhea in 
more than 75% of the patients with collagenous colitis, but the diarrhea tends 
to recur soon after 
stopping Entocort. Though data supporting their use is lacking, some doctors may use 
medications that potently suppress the immune system such as
 azathioprine (Imuran, Azasan) and 6-
 mercaptopurine in patients with severe microscopic colitis that is unresponsive to other 
treatments. 
PREVENTION:  Since the cause of microscopic colitis is not known, no advice can be 
provided about preventing this disease. What is the
prognosisof microscopic colitis? The long term prognosis (course) of microscopic colitis is not clear. In 
approximately two-thirds of the patients with microscopic colitis, the diarrhea 
resolves spontaneously after several years. The remaining one-third of the 
patients with microscopic colitis experience persistent or intermittent diarrhea 
and/or
 abdominal pain for many years (possibly 
indefinitely) as there is no cure for the condition.
</first>
</file1>