<file1>
<first>Restless Leg Syndrome (Symptoms, Causes, Treatment Medications, Home Remedies)

ABOUT: What is restless leg syndrome (RLS)? Restless leg syndrome (RLS,
 restless legs syndrome ) is a common cause of painful legs. The
 leg pain of restless leg syndrome typically eases with motion of the legs and becomes more noticeable at rest. Restless leg syndrome also features worsening of symptoms and leg
 pain during the early evening or later at night. Restless leg syndrome is often abbreviated RLS; it has also been termed shaking leg syndrome. Nighttime involuntary jerking of the legs during
 sleep are also known as periodic leg/limb movement disorder.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Many different symptoms are described by people with restless leg syndrome, for example: leg
 pain , cramps, tingling, itchy , burning, and aching. The characteristic nighttime worsening of symptoms in persons with restless legs syndrome frequency leads to
 insomnia . Because of lack of
 sleep , children and some adults may be very drowsy, irritable, and aggressive during daytime hours. Restless leg syndrome usually begins slowly. Over time, the legs become more affected. Less frequently, restless leg syndrome can affect the arms. Is restless leg syndrome common during pregnancy? Restless leg syndrome is relatively common during pregnancy, especially in the second half of pregnancy. While most medications used to treat restless leg syndrome have not been adequately studied in
 pregnant women, the non-medication treatments and techniques described above can be very helpful. Furthermore, avoiding caffeine, warm compresses,
 massage , and regular exercising according to the doctors&amp;#39; suggestions can be helpful.
 
CAUSES:  The cause of restless leg syndrome is unknown in most people. However, restless leg syndrome has been associated with pregnancy , obesity , smoking , iron deficiency and anemia, nerve disease, polyneuropathy (which can be associated with
 hypothyroidism , heavy metal toxicity, toxins, and many other conditions), other hormone diseases such as
 diabetes , and kidney failure (which can be associated with vitamin and mineral deficiency). Some
 drugs and medications have been associated with restless leg syndrome including: caffeine, alcohol, H2-histamine blockers (such as ranitidine [
 Zantac ] and cimetidine [
 Tagamet ]), and certain
 antidepressants (such as amitriptyline [
 Elavil , Endep]). Occasionally, restless leg syndrome run in families. Recent studies have shown that restless leg syndrome appears to become more common as a person ages. Also, poor venous circulation of the legs (such as with
 varicose veins ) can cause restless leg syndrome.
 How do you know if you have restless leg syndrome? The National Institutes of Health says that four criteria must be met for the diagnosis of RLS in a person (adult or child): A strong urge to move your legs. This urge often, but not always, occurs with unpleasant feelings in your legs. When the disorder is severe, you also may have the urge to move your arms. Symptoms that start or get worse when you&amp;#39;re inactive. The urge to move increases when you&amp;#39;re sitting still or lying down and resting. Relief from moving. Movement, especially walking, helps relieve the unpleasant feelings. Symptoms that start or get worse in the evening or at night. 
TREATMENT:  Is there a cure? Treatment of restless leg syndrome is first directed toward any underlying illness, if known. For example: Blood testing to reveal underlying
 iron deficiency anemia may reveal the underlying cause. If
 varicose veins are thought to be the cause, then surgery to repair the circulation may be considered. Reduction or elimination of caffeine,
 nicotine , and alcohol from a person&amp;#39;s
 diet can be very helpful. Stopping
 smoking can significantly diminish or prevent symptoms. Getting
 better sleep and
 exercise can help some persons affected by restless legs. Pregnant women who do not sleep well at night and other people with
 sleep disorders may develop RLS. There is no cure for restless leg syndrome; however, the condition usually responds well to home remedies and medications. The outlook is excellent for people with restless leg syndrome as long as it does not weaken or damage the function of the legs.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Medications used to treat restless leg syndrome include: natural
 supplements (such as iron), carbidopa -levodopa (
 Sinemet ), opioids (such as
 hydrocodone , or tramadol [
 Ultram ] for intermittent symptoms), carbamazepine (
 Tegretol , Tegretol XR,
 Equetro , Carbatrol), clonazepam (
 Klonopin ), diazepam (
 Valium ), triazolam (
 Halcion ), temazepam (
 Restoril ), baclofen (
 Lioresal ) bromocriptine , clonidine (Catapres,
 Catapres-TTS ,
 Jenloga ), gabapentin (
 Neurontin ), gabapentin enacarbil (
 Horizant ER), ropinirole (
 Requip ), and pramipexole (
 Mirapex ).
 6 natural home remedies for restless leg syndrome symptoms Other treatments that have been helpful for some people with restless leg syndrome include: Some of these natural remedies to reduce symptom of restless leg syndrome and may cause side effects. Discuss any problems or side effects you have after using home remedies or alternative treatments for restless leg syndrome with your doctor. Can other conditions mimic restless leg syndrome? There are many conditions which can mimic restless leg syndrome including: Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, fibromyalgia , muscle diseases, joint conditions, nerve problems such as
 peripheral neuropathy caused by
 diabetes (
 diabetic neuropathy ), and circulation difficulties. In children, restless leg syndrome is often misdiagnosed as "growing pains."
</first>
</file1>