<file1>
<first>Lichen Planus

ABOUT: Lichen planus is a chronic recurrent skin disease of unknown cause with no established cure. Lichen planus generally affects adults and can involve any portion of the skin and lining tissue (mucous membranes) of the mouth and/or vagina, but it has a predilection for the wrists, ankles, and oral and genital tissues. Lichen planus is characteristically
 itchy . Lichen planus may spontaneously resolve. Lichen planus is managed with a variety of topical and oral medications. What is lichen planus? Lichen planus is a chronic recurrent inflammatory disorder of the skin and mucous membranes. It is characterized by small, flat-topped, polygonal
 bumps that may coalesce into rough, scaly plaques on the skin. There may also be involvement of the lining tissue (mucous membranes) of the mouth and/or vagina. Lichen planus is a poorly understood skin condition. Its name is descriptive in that to some it resembles a simple plant, a lichen, which grows on rocks and tree bark, while
 planus is Latin for flat. 
CAUSES:  The cause of lichen planus is unknown. In certain locales, patients with extensive lichen planus seem to be more likely to have a
 hepatitis C virus infection of the
 liver . However, it seems unlikely that the virus is the cause of lichen planus in such situations. Some
 drugs , such as those containing arsenic, bismuth, or gold, can produce an eruption which appears identical to lichen planus. Exposure to certain chemicals used in the development of color photographs can also produce a similar
 rash . The long-term use of the drugs quinacrine or
 quinidine (
 Quinidine Gluconate ,
 Quinidine Sulfate ), may produce hypertrophic lichen planus of the lower legs. Lichenoid eruptions can occur in
 graft-versus-host disease in people who have received bone marrow transplants. Tissue examination by a pathologist (biopsy) is frequently necessary to distinguish such lichenoid drug eruptions from classical lichen planus. Of course, stopping the offending drug is associated with resolution of the eruption.
 How is the rash of lichen planus different from that of most other common rashes? Lichen planus can be distinguished from
 eczema ,
 psoriasis , and other common
 rashes purely on the basis of its clinical appearance in that lesions are small bumps or aggregations of bumps that are flat-topped, shiny, polygonal, and purple to grey in color. They tend to occur at the wrists and elbows and ankles. Individual
 papules contain thin white lines called Wickham&amp;#39;s striae. When lichen planus involves mucosal tissues, such as the lips or cheeks, these white filmy, web-like lines are easy to detect. It is not unusual for lichen planus to appear at sites of
 trauma , especially along lines of scratches (excoriations). 
SYMPTOMS:  Lichen planus
 itching varies from mild to severe. The onset of lichen planus can be sudden or gradual. The first attack may last for weeks or months, and recurrences may happen for years. The bumps at first are 2 mm-4 mm in diameter, with angular borders and a violet color. An excess of pigment (
 hyperpigmentation ) may develop in the affected skin as the lesions persist. If lichen planus involves the
 scalp , it can permanently damage the hair follicles, producing a patch of bald skin called lichen planopilaris. If lichen planus involves the finger or toenails, scarring often occurs, producing permanently malformed nails. Ulcerative lichen planus may occur if oral or vaginal lining tissue (mucosa) are involved. What does lichen planus look like? The appearance of lichen planus depends on whether the skin or the lining (mucous membranes) inside the mouth or vagina are affected: Skin involvement : The usual skin involvement with lichen planus consists of flat-topped lilac or violet to brown spots a few millimeters in diameter on the skin. These spots tend to be located on the inner wrists, forearms, the lower legs just above the ankles, and the lower part of the back. A variant of this disease is called
 hypertrophic lichen planus . This condition appears as thick, reddish-brown lesions that are covered with scales. These spots tend to be on the shins, but they can occur anywhere on the body. This is an especially
 itchy and persistent (chronic) variant of lichen planus. Atrophic lichen planus produces slightly depressed lesions that otherwise resemble typical lichen planus. Mucous membranes : Lichen planus of the mucous membranes of the mouth and genitals is common. It appears as a white, lacy
 rash on the inside of the cheeks or the vagina and may not cause symptoms. The oral rash often occurs prior to any skin involvement. More troublesome, although rare, is erosive lichen planus, which can be quite sore and uncomfortable. This erosive form typically causes the patient to complain of the shallow and often quite painful, recurrent ulcers in the mouth or genitals. Lichen planus of the female genitalia can involve the external vulvar mucosa and the internal vaginal mucosa. There is an association with
 cancer in these areas, so both the oral and vaginal tissues need to monitored by a medical professional. Nail malformation may be produced by lichen planus. Lichen planus may involve the scalp, producing a permanent, scarring type of balding.
 
TREATMENT:  Most dermatologists, gynecologists, and some oral surgeons diagnose and treat lichen planus. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Usually, lichen planus is relatively straightforward to diagnose. Physicians can make the diagnosis in typical cases simply by looking at the rash. If necessary, a
 skin biopsy may be done to help confirm the diagnosis because, under the microscope, lichen planus is distinctive in appearance. Because there are a number of other lichenoid eruptions that resemble lichen planus a biopsy confirmation is frequently necessary. Persistent oral or vaginal lichen planus, with spots that thicken and grow together, can sometimes be difficult to distinguish clinically from whitish
 precancerous plaques called
 leukoplakia . A biopsy can be helpful in this situation. There seem to be a few patients in whom ulcerative lichen planus precedes the development of
 oral cancer . Are there
home remediesfor lichen planus? Although there is little objective evidence of its benefits,
 green tea has been suggested as a treatment for lichen planus. It is likely to be a safe approach.
 
TREATMENT:  Most lichen planus is relatively mild. Affected individuals who do not have symptoms do not need treatment. Ultimately, there is no agreed-upon cure for this condition. If the
 itch or appearance of the rash are unpleasant, topical
 corticosteroid creams or topical calcineurin inhibitors like
 tacrolimus or
 pimecrolimus may be of help. For localized, itchy, thick lesions, injections of
 corticosteroids directly into the plaque may helpful.
 Antihistamines may blunt the
 itch , particularly if it is only moderate. This effect is in part due to the sedative effect of antihistamines. For oral lesions, topical steroids (cortisone) in special oral preparations are available. In more severe lichen planus, physicians may recommend oral medications or therapy with ultraviolet light. Oral medications may include a course of oral
 prednisone or
 acitretin or
 griseofulvin . Occasionally, other immunosuppressive agents may be employed. However, the
 itching may return after the drug has been discontinued. A low-dose oral corticosteroid every other morning may be also prescribed. For painful lesions within the mouth, special mouthwashes containing a painkiller (such as
 lidocaine ) before meals may provide some relief. Any drug or chemical suspected of being the cause of the lichen planus should be discontinued. What is the long-term prognosis of lichen planus? Lichen planus usually goes away by itself in time. Some drugs can produce
 rashes that are similar in appearance to lichen planus. These rashes can be distinguished from lichen planus in that they go away when the offending drug is stopped.
 
PREVENTION:  Since the cause of lichen planus is unknown, there are no reliable options to prevent it.
</first>
</file1>