<file1>
<first>Liver Cancer (Hepatocellular Cancer) Prevention
Key points Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may help prevent
 cancer . The following risk factors may increase the risk of
 liver cancer :
 Hepatitis B and C Cirrhosis Aflatoxin The following protective factor may decrease the risk of
 liver cancer :
 Hepatitis B vaccine Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to prevent
 cancer . New ways to prevent liver cancer are being studied in clinical trials. Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may help prevent 
cancer. Avoiding
 cancer risk factors may help prevent certain
 cancers . Risk factors 
include
 smoking , being
 overweight , and not getting enough
 exercise . Increasing 
protective factors such as quitting
 smoking and exercising may also help prevent 
some cancers. Talk to your doctor or other health care professional about how 
you might lower your risk of cancer.
 The following risk factors may increase the risk of liver cancer: Having chronic
 hepatitis B or chronic
 hepatitis C increases the risk of 
developing liver cancer. The risk is even greater for people with both
 hepatitis B and C. Also, the longer the
 hepatitis infection lasts (especially hepatitis 
C), the greater the risk. In a study of patients with chronic
 hepatitis C , those who were treated to 
lower their iron levels by having blood drawn and eating a low-iron
 diet were 
less likely to develop liver cancer than those who did not have this treatment. The risk of developing liver cancer is increased for people who have 
cirrhosis, a disease in which healthy liver tissue is replaced by
 scar tissue . 
The
 scar tissue blocks the flow of blood through the liver and keeps it from 
working as it should. Chronic
 alcoholism and chronic
 hepatitis C are the most 
common causes of cirrhosis. The risk of developing liver cancer may be increased by eating foods that 
contain aflatoxin (poison from a fungus that can grow on foods, such as grains 
and nuts, that have not been stored properly).
 The following protective factor may decrease the risk of liver cancer: Preventing hepatitis B infection (by being vaccinated for hepatitis B) has 
been shown to lower the risk of liver cancer in children. It is not yet known if 
it lowers the risk in adults. Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to prevent cancer. Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to lower the risk of 
developing certain types of cancer. Some cancer prevention trials are conducted 
with healthy people who have not had cancer but who have an increased risk for 
cancer. Other prevention trials are conducted with people who have had cancer 
and are trying to prevent another cancer of the same type or to lower their 
chance of developing a new type of cancer. Other trials are done with healthy 
volunteers who are not known to have any risk factors for cancer. The purpose of some cancer prevention clinical trials is to find out whether 
actions people take can prevent cancer. These may include eating fruits and 
vegetables, exercising, quitting
 smoking , or taking certain medicines,
 vitamins ,
 minerals , or food
 supplements . New ways to prevent liver cancer are being studied in clinical trials. Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information 
about clinical trials can be found in the
 Clinical Trials section of the NCI website.
</first>
</file1>