<file1>
<first>Alternative Treatment for MS (Complementary and Alternative Medicine or CAM for MS)
Alternative treatment (CAM) for 
ABOUT: Fatigue and muscle
 spasticity are 
 the
 symptoms of MS that are best addressed by complementary or alternative 
 treatment or medicine (
 CAM ). Complementary or alternative treatments or therapies that have been 
 shown to be helpful in helping reduce
 fatigue include:
 Yoga , exercise , (including
 swimming and
 walking ), magnet therapy, and gingko biloba
 supplements . Massage therapy and
 acupuncture have been reported by some to provide relief for spasticity. Ongoing studies are being conducted to look at the potential benefits of
 medical  marijuana on
 MS symptoms ; to include
 chronic pain and spasticity.
 Marinol and Sativex, two FDA approved forms of
 medical marijuana (medical 
cannabis) may be beneficial in improving spasticity or bladder frequency. People who desire CAM therapies 
 generally feel that conventional treatments are not effective in controlling 
 their symptoms or that the side effects are not acceptable. Most CAM therapies are not covered 
 by insurance. It is important to discuss the use 
 of CAM therapies with your health-care professional, since some CAM therapies 
 may interact adversely with medications. CAM has not been shown to have 
 significant effects on the progression of
 MS over time. 
TREATMENT:  CAM (
 complementary and alternative medicine ) is care provided in addition 
(integrative medicine) to 
or instead of traditional or standard medical practices. This group of therapies 
is wide-ranging, and includes: acupuncture , herbal
 supplements , dietary 
modifications, magnets, reflexology, and much more. Some people who seek out alternative medicine feel that conventional therapy has 
not successfully controlled their symptoms, or that the potential side effects 
associated with traditional therapy aren't acceptable. Others find that adding 
complementary medicine to their program allows improved control of symptoms.
 When complementary medicine is added to traditional routes, it is referred to as 
integrative medicine. Recent studies through the US Centers for Disease Control and
 Prevention (CDC), specifically the National Health Interview Survey, suggest that as many 
as 38% of residents within the United States seek out CAM. Many therapies that are considered within the group of complementary and 
alternative medicines haven't been studied extensively or investigated in 
comparison to conventional treatment options. What is of multiple sclerosis (MS)? Multiple sclerosis (
 MS ) is a disease that causes
 demyelination of the brain 
and spinal cord, or a loss of the covering around axons. When this occurs, the 
axons (the parts of the nerve cells that transmit impulses to other cells) don't 
work well. As more areas of the central nervous system are affected by the loss 
of myelin, different symptoms develop.
 
SYMPTOMS:  The
 specific symptom seen in MS is related to 
the area of injury in the brain or spinal cord. Examples of symptoms of
 MS include: a numbness, burning ors tingling feeling, or
 weakness in certain areas of 
 the body; the weakness might be mild or severe enough to cause
 paralysis of 
 one side of the body; bladder and bowel symptoms such as
 incontinence , difficulty in starting 
 to urinate, a strong and/or frequent urge to urinate, even loss of control of 
 the bladder or an inability to empty the bladder; eye problems such as eye discomfort,
 double vision , uncontrollable eye 
 movements,
 optic neuritis , and
 vision loss ; difficulty moving the arms or legs, difficulty walking, or problems with 
 coordination and fine motor skills; sexual problems 
 in men and a
 vaginal dryness (decrease in vaginal 
 lubrication in women); Nerve and brain problems such as
 dizziness ,
 depression ,
 memory loss , 
 balance problems, poor judgment, and
 memory loss ; and as MS progresses, some patients are left with muscle spasticity, which is an 
involuntary painful contraction of some muscles.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Fatigue and spasticity seem to respond best to CAM. Therapies that have been 
shown to be of some benefit for fatigue have included: exercise , for example, yoga, ,swimming, walking, and other types of 
 regular exercise; magnet therapy; and gingko biloba 
supplements. Spasticity has reportedly been reduced with the use of acupuncture 
and massage therapy. A sense of tingling (paresthesias) have been reportedly 
improved with reflexology. Symptoms including
 depression , memory loss,
 urinary incontinence , and 
progression of MS itself (including relapses, disease extent as measured on
 MRI ), and disability have had limited improvement when treated with CAM. Therapies tested in an effort to improve these symptoms have included: a
 low-fat
 diet , bee venom, hypnosis, multiple different amino acids, alpha lipoic acid, and hyperbaric oxygen therapy. None of these treatments led to any significant 
benefit in the studied symptoms.
 What about medical marijuana (cannabis) for MS symptoms? There have been a number of studies 
looking at the potential benefits of medical
 marijuana (cannabis) on MS 
symptoms, including spasticity and
 chronic pain . There is some suggestion that 
FDA approved forms of medical cannabis (Marinol or Sativex) may be beneficial in 
improving spasticity or bladder frequency. However, there are no reports that 
ingested or inhaled medical marijuana is beneficial for conditions associated with MS. 
The
 National Multiple Sclerosis Society has more information about medical 
marijuana for
 MS symptoms (http://www.nationalmssociety.org/Treating-MS/Complementary-Alternative-Medicines/Marijuana) Who is eligible to pursue treatment with CAM? Anyone can participate CAM therapy. 
However, it is important to recognize that most of these therapies are not 
covered by insurance, and may be an "out of pocket" cost for patients with MS. Patients who decide to pursue CAM need to share this information with their 
physicians, as some supplements may interact with convention medication and lead 
to side effects. How much does CAM cost? The costs of CAM can vary widely; regular exercise and yoga can be low or 
no-cost options, while massage therapy, acupuncture, and some supplements can be 
quite expensive. Every patient must have a good relationship with treating 
health-care professionals of traditional and non-traditional therapies to best 
understand potential costs.
 
RISKS:  Side effects of CAM vary depending on the treatment. Patients who have 
selected various supplements or dietary measures may experience:
 hot flashes (flushing), or gastric disturbances, such as
 nausea or
 constipation . Some supplements can 
increase the risk of bleeding (gingko biloba) or interact with traditional 
medications. Infections may occur when the 
 skin is punctured, such as with 
acupuncture. Some patients expect CAM to be able to out-perform 
conventional treatments, despite a lack of scientific evidence. If this doesn't 
occur, patients may feel discouraged. It is important to discuss any potential or ongoing use of CAM with your 
health-care professional, who may need to adjust your current therapies to 
prevent any adverse effects caused by interactions between the two types of 
therapies. What different types of CAM were studied in the National Health Interview 
Survey? Different types of complementary and alternative medicines that were studied in the National Health Interview Survey from 2002 through 2012 
include: Acupuncture Ayurveda Biofeedback Chelation therapy Chiropractic care Energy healing therapy/Reiki Special diets :
 Vegetarian , Vegan, Macrobiotic, others Folk medicine Guided imagery Homeopathic treatment Hypnosis Massage Meditation Movement therapies: Alexander technique, Feldenkrais,
 Pilates Naturopathy Nonvitamin and nonmineral
 dietary supplements Osteopathic manipulation Progressive relaxation Qi gong Tai chi Traditional healers: Botanica, Curandero, Espiritista, Yerbera, Medicine 
 man, Shaman, others Yoga
</first>
</file1>