<file1>
<first>Electromyogram (EMG)
What is an electromyogram? An electromyogram (EMG) is a test that is used to record the electrical activity of muscles. When muscles are active, they produce an electrical current. This current is usually proportional to the level of the muscle activity. An EMG is also referred to as a myogram. EMGs can be used to detect abnormal electrical activity of muscle that can occur in many diseases and conditions, including muscular dystrophy, inflammation of muscles, pinched nerves, peripheral nerve damage (damage to nerves in the arms and legs),
 amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (
 ALS ),
 myasthenia gravis ,
 disc herniation , and others. Why is an EMG test done? An EMG is often performed when patients have unexplained muscle
 weakness . The EMG helps to distinguish between muscle conditions in which the problem begins in the muscle and muscle weakness due to nerve disorders. The EMG can also be used to detect true weakness, as opposed to weakness from reduced use because of
 pain or lack of motivation. EMGs can also be used to isolate the level of nerve irritation or injury. How is an intramuscular EMG done? A needle is inserted through the skin into the muscle. The electrical activity is detected by this needle (which serves as an electrode). The activity is displayed visually on an oscilloscope and may also be detected audibly with a speaker. Since skeletal muscles are often large, several needle electrodes may need to be placed at various locations to obtain an informative EMG. After placement of the electrode(s), the patient may be asked to contract the muscle (for example, to bend the leg). The presence, size, and shape of the wave form (the action potential) produced on the oscilloscope provide information about the ability of the muscle to respond to nervous stimulation. Each muscle fiber that contracts produces an action potential. The size of the muscle fiber affects the rate (how frequently an action potential occurs) and the size (the amplitude) of the action potential.
 Is an EMG painful? Yes. There is some discomfort at the time the needle electrodes are inserted. They feel like shots (intramuscular injections), although nothing is injected during an EMG. Afterwards, the muscle may feel a little sore for up to a few days. How do you prepare for an intramuscular EMG? For adults, no special preparation is needed. For infants and children, the physical and psychological preparation depends on the child&amp;#39;s age, behavior, and prior experience. (For instance, has the child been traumatized by another medical or dental procedure?) What other test is done during an intramuscular EMG? A nerve conduction velocity (NCV) test is often done at the same time as an EMG. In this test, the nerve is electrically stimulated while a second electrode detects the electrical impulse &amp;#39;down-stream&amp;#39; from the first. This is usually done with surface patch electrodes (they are similar to those used for an
 electrocardiogram ) that are placed on the skin over the nerve at various locations. One electrode stimulates the nerve with a very mild electrical impulse. The resulting electrical activity is recorded by the other electrodes. The distance between electrodes and the time it takes for electrical impulses to travel between electrodes are used to calculate the speed of impulse transmission (nerve conduction velocity). A decreased speed of transmission indicates nerve disease. The NCV test can be used to detect true nerve disorders (such as neuropathy) or conditions whereby muscles are affected by nerve injury (such as
 carpal tunnel syndrome ). Normal body temperature must be maintained for the NCV test, because low body temperatures slow nerve conduction. Previous contributing authors and editors: Medical Author: Frederick Hecht, MD, FAAP, FACMG
 Medical Editor: Barbara K. Hecht, Ph.D.
</first>
</file1>