<file1>
<first>Melanosis Coli (Pseudomelanosis Coli)
What is melanosis coli? Melanosis coli is a condition usually associated with 
chronic
 laxative use in which dark pigment is deposited in 
the lamina propria 
(one of the lining layers) of the
 large intestine (colon). The pigment deposition results in a characteristic dark brown to black 
discoloration of the lining of the large intestine. This condition is sometimes called 
pseudomelanosis coli because the pigment deposits consist of a pigment known as 
lipofuscin and do not contain
 melanin as implied by the term "melanosis." 
Lipofuscin is a cellular pigment that forms when cells are destroyed, often 
called "wear and tear" pigment that can be found throughout the body. The dark color of the intestinal lining may be uniform 
or patterned, and the discoloration may be slight or very pronounced. The 
intensity and pattern of the discoloration may even vary among different sites 
in the colon of a single person. The condition may also be reversed upon 
discontinuation of laxative use. In some cases, the wall of the colon appears 
normal to the eye, but microscopic evaluation of biopsies by a pathologist reveals areas of pigment in 
the colon's lining. The pigment in melanosis coli does not accumulate in polyps 
or tumors of the large intestine. 
SYMPTOMS:  Melanosis coli does not cause 
symptoms.
 
CAUSES:  Melanosis coli usually results from chronic use 
of laxatives of the anthranoid group. Some examples of anthranoid laxatives are
 senna (sennosides; Senocot,
 Senokot EXTRA and others) and rhubarb derivatives. Many of these laxatives have been in use for 
hundreds of years. In 1997, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) banned 
the use of the popular anthranoid laxative
phenolphthalein due to fears that it 
might be carcinogenic (
 cancer -causing). Animal studies had shown that extremely 
high doses of phenolphthalein led to tumors in animals, but it has never been 
shown to cause cancers in humans. The anthranoid laxatives pass through the gastrointestinal tract unabsorbed 
until they reach the large intestine, where they are changed into their active 
forms. The resulting active compounds cause damage to the cells in the lining of 
the intestine and leads to apoptosis (a form of 
cell death). The damaged (apoptotic) cells appear as darkly pigmented bodies that may be taken up by 
scavenger cells known as macrophages. When enough cells have been damaged, the 
characteristic pigmentation of the bowel wall develops. The condition can 
develop after just a few months of laxative use.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Melanosis coli can be observed during endoscopic procedures that examine the large intestine, such as
 colonoscopy and sigmoidoscopy. Sometimes the diagnosis is made upon microscopic examination of biopsies taken during endoscopic procedures. What is the prognosis (outcome) of melanosis coli? If a person stops using anthranoid laxatives, the changes associated with melanosis coli lessen over 
time and may disappear. Early studies suggested that anthranoid laxatives might 
have carcinogenic or
 tumor -promoting activities in humans and that the presence 
of melanosis coli might signal an increased risk for the development of
 colorectal cancer . However, more recent follow-up studies have failed to show an 
association between
 colon cancer and anthranoid laxative use or between colon
 cancer and the 
finding of melanosis coli.
</first>
</file1>