<file1>
<first>Mental Illness Basics
What Causes Mental Illness? Although the exact cause of most mental illnesses is not known, it is 
becoming clear through research that many of these conditions are caused by a 
combination of genetic, biological, psychological, and environmental factors -- 
not personal
 weakness or a character defect -- and recovery from a mental 
illness is not simply a matter of will and self-discipline. Heredity (genetics) : Many mental illnesses run in families, 
 suggesting they may be passed on from parents to children through genes. 
 Genes contain instructions for the function of each cell in the body and are 
 responsible for how we look, act, think, etc. However, just because your 
 mother or father may have or had a mental illness doesn't mean you will have 
 one. Hereditary just means that you are more likely to get the condition 
 than if you didn't have an affected family member. Experts believe that many 
 mental conditions are linked to problems in multiple genes -- not just one, 
 as with many diseases -- which is why a person inherits a susceptibility to 
 a mental disorder but doesn't always develop the condition. The disorder 
 itself occurs from the interaction of these genes and other factors -- such 
 as psychological
 trauma and environmental stressors -- which can influence, 
 or trigger, the illness in a person who has inherited a susceptibility to 
 it. Biology : Some mental illnesses have been linked to an abnormal 
 balance of brain chemicals called neurotransmitters. Neurotransmitters help 
 nerve cells in the brain communicate with each other. If these chemicals are 
 out of balance or are not working properly, messages may not make it through 
 the brain correctly, leading to symptoms of mental illness. In addition, 
 defects in or injury to certain areas of the brain also have been linked to 
 some mental conditions. Psychological trauma : Some mental illnesses may be triggered by 
 psychological trauma suffered as a child, such as severe emotional, 
 physical, or sexual abuse; a significant early loss, such as the loss of a 
 parent; and neglect. Environmental stressors : Certain stressors -- such as a death or 
 divorce, a dysfunctional family life, changing jobs or schools, and
 substance abuse -- can trigger a disorder in a person who may be at risk for 
 developing a mental illness.
 Can Mental Illness Be Prevented? Unfortunately, most mental illnesses are caused by a combination of factors
and cannot be prevented. How Common Is Mental Illness? Mental illnesses are very common. In fact, they are more common than
 cancer ,
 diabetes , or
 heart disease . According to the National Institute of Mental 
Health, about 25% of American adults (those ages 18 and older) and about 13% of 
American children (those ages 8 to 15) are diagnosed with a mental disorder 
during a given year. Major depression ,
 bipolar disorder , and
 schizophrenia are among the U.S.'s 
top 10 leading causes of disability. Mental illness does not discriminate. It can affect people of any age, income 
or educational level, and cultural background. Although mental illness affects 
both males and females, certain conditions -- such as
 eating disorders -- tend 
to occur more often in females, and other disorders -- such as attention deficit
 hyperactivity disorder (
 ADHD ) -- more commonly occur in children. How Is Mental Illness Treated? A mental illness, like many chronic illnesses, requires ongoing treatment. 
Fortunately, much progress has been made in the last two decades in treating 
mental illnesses. As a result, many mental conditions can be effectively treated 
with one or a combination of the following therapies: Medication. Psychotherapy . Group therapy. Day treatment or partial hospital treatment. Specific therapies, such as cognitive-
 behavior therapy and behavior 
 modification. Other treatments available include: Alternative therapies, such as water therapy,
 massage , and biofeedback. Creative therapies, such as art therapy, music therapy, or play therapy. Hypnotherapy. Electroconvulsive therapy (
 ECT ). Vagus nerve stimulation (
 VNS ). Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) is a newer therapy.
 What Is the Outlook for People with Mental Illness? When diagnosed early and treated properly, many people fully recover from their mental illness or are able to successfully control their symptoms. Although some people become disabled because of a chronic or severe mental illness, many others are able to live full and productive lives. In fact, as many as 8 in 10 people suffering from a mental illness can effectively return to their normal activities if they receive appropriate treatment. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>