<file1>
<first>Microcephaly
Microcephaly facts* *
ABOUT: medical author:
 Charles Patrick Davis, MD, PhD Microcephaly is a condition where the head (circumference) is smaller than normal. Microcephaly may be caused by genetic abnormalities or by
 drugs ,
 alcohol , certain
 viruses , and toxins that are exposed to the fetus during
 pregnancy and damage the developing brain tissue. Unfortunately, a 2015-2016 outbreak of
 Zika virus in Brazil has been associated with a large number of infants born with microcephaly. Epidemiological and some viral isolations suggest that pregnant women who get Zika virus have a high chance of fetal infection that may lead to microcephaly, although 
 a definitive link between Zika virus infection and microcephaly is not yet proven. Signs and symptoms of microcephaly may include a smaller than normal head circumference that usually remains smaller than normal as the child grows,
 dwarfism or
 short stature , delayed motor and speech functions, mental retardation,
 seizures , facial distortions,
 hyperactivity , balance and coordination problems, and other brain-related or neurological problems; although some with the disorder may develop normal intelligence. There is no treatment to change the head size; programs are available to help these individuals reach their maximum potential and
 genetic counseling may help explain the risk for microcephaly in future pregnancies. Women who are interested in becoming pregnant are being advised by the CDC and other agencies to avoid traveling to areas where Zika virus is found to reduce the chance of becoming infected while pregnant. Research on microcephaly is ongoing; for example, researchers found that amino acid therapy may reduce
 seizure activity in some patients. There is no vaccine available for Zika virus; researchers predict a vaccine will take three to five years to develop. What is microcephaly? Microcephaly is a medical condition in which the circumference of the head is smaller than normal because the brain has not developed properly or has stopped growing. Microcephaly can be present at birth or it may develop in the first few years of life.
 
CAUSES:  It is most often caused by genetic abnormalities that interfere with the growth of the cerebral cortex during the early months of
 fetal development . It is associated with Down&amp;#39;s syndrome, chromosomal syndromes, and neurometabolic syndromes.
 Babies may also be born with microcephaly if, during pregnancy, their mother abused drugs or alcohol, became infected with a
 cytomegalovirus ,
 rubella (
 German measles ), or
 varicella (
 chicken pox ) virus, was exposed to certain toxic chemicals, or had untreated
 phenylketonuria (PKU). Babies born with microcephaly will have a smaller than normal head that will fail to grow as they progress through infancy. 
SYMPTOMS:  Depending on the severity of the accompanying syndrome, children with microcephaly may have impaired cognitive development, delayed motor functions and speech, facial distortions, dwarfism or short stature, hyperactivity, seizures , difficulties with coordination and balance, and other brain or neurological abnormalities. Some children with microcephaly will have normal intelligence and a head that will grow bigger, but they will track below the normal growth curves for head circumference.
 Is there any treatment for microcephaly? There is no treatment for microcephaly that can return a child&amp;#39;s head to a normal size or shape. Treatment focuses on ways to decrease the impact of the associated deformities and neurological disabilities. Children with microcephaly and developmental delays are usually evaluated by a pediatric neurologist and followed by a medical management team. Early childhood intervention programs that involve physical, speech, and occupational therapists help to maximize abilities and minimize dysfunction. Medications are often used to control seizures, hyperactivity, and neuromuscular symptoms. Genetic counseling may help families understand the risk for microcephaly in subsequent pregnancies. What is the
prognosisfor microcephaly? Some children will only have mild disability. Others, especially if they are otherwise growing and developing normally, will have normal intelligence and continue to develop and meet regular age-appropriate milestones. What research is being done on microcephaly? The National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS) conducts research relating to microcephaly in its laboratories at the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and supports additional research through grants to major medical institutions across the country. A small group of researchers studying a rare neurometabolic syndrome (3-PGDH), which causes microcephaly, have successfully used amino acid replacement therapy to reduce and prevent seizures.
 For more information The Arc of the United States
 1825 K Street, NW
 Suite 1200
 Washington, DC 20006
 [email protected] http://www.thearc.org Tel: 202-534-3700 800-433-5255
 Fax: 202-534-3731 Birth Defect Research for Children, Inc.
 976 Lake Baldwin Lane
 Suite 104
 Orlando, FL 32814
 [email protected] http://www.birthdefects.org Tel: 407-895-0802 March of Dimes Foundation
 1275 Mamaroneck Avenue
 White Plains, NY 10605
 [email protected] http://www.marchofdimes.com Tel: 914-997-4488 888-MODIMES (663-4637)
 Fax: 914-428-8203 National Dissemination Center for Children with Disabilities
 U.S. Dept. of Education, Office of Special Education Programs
 1825 Connecticut Avenue NW, Suite 700
 Washington, DC 20009
 [email protected] http://www.nichcy.org Tel: 800-695-0285 202-884-8200
 Fax: 202-884-8441
</first>
</file1>