<file1>
<first>Dental Health Mouth Guards
Who Needs a Mouth Guard? Mouth guards should be used by
 anyone -- both children and
 adults -- who play
contact sports such as football, boxing, soccer, ice hockey, basketball,
lacrosse, and field hockey. However, even those participating in noncontact
sports (for example, gymnastics) and any recreational activity (for example,
skateboarding, mountain biking) that might pose a risk of injury to the mouth
would benefit from wearing a protective mouth guard. Adults and children who grind their teeth at night should have a nocturnal
bite plate or bite splint made to prevent tooth damage.
 Why Use a Mouth Guard When Playing Sports? Because accidents can happen during any physical activity, the advantage of using a mouth guard is that it can help limit the risk of mouth-related injuries to your lips, tongue, and soft tissues of your mouth. Mouth guards also help you avoid chipped or broken teeth, nerve damage to a tooth or even tooth loss. Can I Wear a Mouth Guard if I Wear Braces? Yes. Since an injury to the face could damage orthodontic brackets or other
fixed appliances, a properly fitted mouth guard may be particularly important
for people who wear
 braces or have fixed
 bridge work. Your dentist or
orthodontist can determine the mouth guard that will provide the best
protection for your unique mouth work. An important reminder: do not wear any
 retainers or other removable appliance during any contact sports or during any
recreational activities that put your mouth at risk for injury.
 How Do I Care for My Mouth Guard? To care for your mouth guard: Rinse your mouth guard with
 cold water or with a mouth rinse before and
after each use and/or clean it with
 toothpaste and a
 toothbrush . Occasionally clean the mouthguard in cool, soapy water and rinse it
thoroughly. Place the mouth guard in a firm, perforated container to store or transport
it. This permits air circulation and helps to prevent damage. Protect the mouth guard from high
 temperatures -- such as hot water, hot
surfaces, or direct
 sunlight -- to minimize distorting its shape. Occasionally check the mouth guard for general wear. If you find holes or
tears in it or if it becomes loose or causes discomfort, replace it. Bring the mouth guard to each regularly scheduled dental visit to have your
dentist exam it. Reviewed by the doctors at
 The Cleveland
Clinic Department of Dentistry .
 Reviewed by Harold Burstein, PhD, MD, on May 1, 2005
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson Mathis, MD, on May 1, 2005
 Portions of this page © The Cleveland Clinic 
2000-2005
</first>
</file1>