<file1>
<first>Nicotine (Tobacco Addiction and Abuse)
What Is Tobacco Addiction? When people are addicted, they have a compulsive 
need to seek out and use a substance, even when they understand the harm it can 
cause.
 Tobacco products -- cigarettes, cigars, pipes, and
 smokeless tobacco -- can all 
be addictive. Everyone knows that
 smoking is bad for you, and most people that 
do it want to quit. In fact, nearly 35 million people make a serious attempt to 
quit each year. Unfortunately, most who try to quit on their own relapse -- often 
within a week. Is Nicotine Addictive? Yes. It is actually the nicotine in tobacco that is 
addictive. Each
 cigarette contains about 10 milligrams of nicotine. Because the 
smoker inhales only some of the smoke from a cigarette, and not all of each puff 
is absorbed in the
 lungs , a smoker gets about 1 to 2 milligrams of the drug from 
each cigarette. Although that may not seem like much, it is enough to make 
someone addicted. Is Nicotine the Only Harmful Part of Tobacco? No. Nicotine is only one of 
more than 4,000 chemicals, many of which are poisonous, found in the smoke from 
tobacco products. Smokeless tobacco products also contain many toxins, as well 
as high levels of nicotine. Many of these other ingredients are things we would 
never consider putting in our bodies, like tar, carbon monoxide, acetaldehyde, 
and nitrosamines. Tar causes
 lung cancer ,
 emphysema , and bronchial diseases. 
Carbon monoxide causes heart problems, which is one reason why smokers are at 
high risk for
 heart disease .
 How Is Tobacco Used? Tobacco can be smoked in cigarettes, cigars, or pipes. 
It can be chewed or, if powdered, sniffed. "Bidis" are an alternative cigarette. 
They originally came from India and were hand-rolled. In the United States, bidis were popular with
 teens because they come in colorful packages with flavor 
choices. Some teens think that bidis are less harmful than regular cigarettes, 
but in fact they have more nicotine, which may make people smoke more, giving 
bidis the potential to be even more harmful than cigarettes. Hookah -- or water 
pipe
 smoking -- practiced for centuries in other countries, has recently become 
popular among teens in the United States as well. Hookah tobacco comes in many 
flavors, and the pipe is typically passed around in groups. Although many hookah 
smokers think it is less harmful than
 smoking cigarettes, water pipe smoking 
still delivers the addictive drug nicotine and is at least as toxic as cigarette 
smoking. What Are the Common Street Names? You might hear cigarettes referred to as 
"smokes," "cigs," or "butts." Smokeless tobacco is often called "chew," "dip," 
"spit tobacco," "snus," or "
 snuff ." People may refer to hookah smoking as "narghile," 
"argileh," "shisha," "hubble-bubble," or "goza." How Many Teens Use It? The good news is that smoking is at historically low 
levels among 8th, 10th, and 12th graders, according to NIDA's Monitoring the 
Future study. In 2011, rates for smoking in the past month were reported as 18.7 
percent for 12th graders, 11.8 percent for 10th graders, and 6.1 percent for 8th 
graders. Use of smokeless tobacco had been showing a decline over the past 
decade -- until 2009, when use began to rise. According to the study, in 2011 
current use of smokeless tobacco among 8th graders was 3.5 percent and 6.6 
percent among 10th graders. Among 12th graders, 8.3 percent reported using 
smokeless tobacco in the last month, a number not seen since the late 1990s.
 How Does Tobacco Deliver Its Effects? With each puff of a cigarette, a smoker pulls nicotine and other harmful 
substances into the lungs, where it is absorbed into the blood. It takes just 8 
seconds for nicotine to hit the brain. Nicotine happens to be shaped like the 
natural brain chemical acetylcholine. Acetylcholine is one of many chemicals 
called neurotransmitters that carry messages between brain cells. Neurons (brain 
cells) have specialized proteins called receptors, into which specific 
neurotransmitters can fit, like a key fitting into a lock. Nicotine locks into 
acetylcholine receptors, rapidly causing changes in the brain and body. For 
instance, nicotine increases
 blood pressure , heart rate, and
 respiration (
 breathing ). Nicotine also attaches to acetylcholine receptors on neurons that release a 
neurotransmitter called dopamine. Dopamine is released normally when you 
experience something pleasurable like good food, your favorite activity, or the 
company of people you love. But smoking cigarettes causes neurons to release 
excess dopamine, which is responsible for the feelings of pleasure. However, 
this effect wears off rapidly, causing people who smoke to get the urge to light 
up again for another dose of the drug. Nicotine may be the primary addictive component in tobacco but it's not the 
only ingredient that is biologically important. Using advanced neuroimaging 
technology, scientists have found that people who smoke have a significant 
reduction in the levels of an enzyme called monoamine oxidase (MAO) in the brain 
and throughout the body. This enzyme is responsible for the breakdown of 
dopamine, other neurotransmitters involved in mood regulation, and in a variety 
of bodily functions. Having lower amounts of MAO in the brain may lead to higher 
dopamine levels and be another reason that people who smoke continue to do so -- to 
sustain the pleasurable feelings that high dopamine levels create. Also, researchers have recently shown in animals that acetaldehyde, another 
chemical constituent of tobacco smoke, dramatically increases the rewarding 
properties of nicotine -- particularly in adolescent animals -- which may be one 
reason why teens are more vulnerable to becoming addicted to tobacco than 
adults.
 What Happens When Someone Uses Tobacco for Long Periods of Time? Long-term use of nicotine frequently leads to
 addiction . Research is just 
beginning to document all of the changes in the brain that accompany nicotine 
addiction. The behavioral consequences of these changes are well documented, 
however. The way that nicotine is absorbed and metabolized by the body enhances its 
addictive potential. Each
 inhalation brings a rapid distribution of nicotine to 
the brain -- peaking within 10 seconds and then disappearing quickly, along with 
the associated pleasurable feelings. Over the course of the day, tolerance 
develops -- meaning that higher (or more frequent) doses are required to produce 
the same initial effects. Some of this tolerance is lost overnight, and people 
who smoke often report that the first cigarette of the day is the strongest or 
the "best." When a person quits smoking, they usually experience withdrawal symptoms, 
which often drive them back to tobacco use. Nicotine withdrawal symptoms include 
irritability, cognitive and attentional deficits,
 sleep disturbances, 
increased 
appetite, and craving. Craving -- an intense urge for nicotine that can persist for 
6 months or longer -- is an important but poorly understood component of the 
nicotine withdrawal syndrome. Some people describe it as a major stumbling block 
to quitting. Withdrawal symptoms usually peak within the first few days and may subside 
within a few weeks. The withdrawal syndrome is related to the pharmacological 
effects of nicotine, but many behavioral factors also affect the severity and 
persistence of withdrawal symptoms. For example, the cues associated with 
smoking -- the end of a meal, the sight or smell of a cigarette, the ritual of 
obtaining, handling, lighting, and smoking the cigarette, the people you hung 
out with when you smoked, and alcohol use -- all can be powerful triggers of 
craving that can last or re-emerge months or even years after smoking has 
ceased. While nicotine gum and patches may stop the pharmacological aspects of 
withdrawal, cravings often persist.
 What Are Other Adverse Health Effects? Tobacco abuse harms every organ in the body. It has been conclusively linked 
to
 leukemia ,
 cataracts , and
 pneumonia , and accounts for about one-third of all
 cancer deaths. The overall rates of death from
 cancer are twice as high among 
people who smoke as those who don't, with people who smoke heavily having rates 
that are four times greater than those of people who don't smoke. And, you 
guessed it -- foremost among the cancers caused by tobacco use is
 lung cancer . In 
fact, cigarette smoking has been linked to about 90 percent of all lung
 cancer cases, the number-one cancer killer of both men and women. Tobacco abuse is also 
associated with cancers of the mouth, pharynx, larynx,
 esophagus , stomach, 
pancreas, cervix, kidney, ureter, and bladder. People who smoke also lose some of their sense of smell and taste, don't have 
the same stamina for
 exercise and sports they once did, and may smell of smoke. 
After smoking for a long time, people find that their skin ages faster and their
 teeth discolor or turn brown. Smoking doesn't just affect the person who smokes. People who do not smoke 
are exposed to "
 secondhand smoke ," which comes from both the exhaled smoke and 
from the smoke floating from the end of a cigarette,
 cigar , or pipe. Inhaling
 secondhand smoke increases a person's risk of developing
 heart disease by 25 to 
30 percent and lung cancer by 20 to 30 percent. In fact, secondhand smoke is 
estimated to contribute to as many as 40,000 deaths related to
 heart disease and 
about 3,000 lung cancer deaths per year among people who do not smoke. 
Secondhand smoke also causes respiratory problems in people who do not smoke, 
like
 coughing , phlegm, and reduced lung function. Children exposed to secondhand smoke are at an increased risk for 
sudden 
infant death syndrome, acute respiratory infections, ear problems, and more 
severe
 asthma . And, believe it or not, dropped cigarettes are the leading cause 
of residential fire fatalities, leading to more than 700 such deaths each year. Each year, almost half a million Americans die from tobacco use. One of every 
five deaths, or about 440,000 deaths, in the United States is a result of 
tobacco use, making tobacco more lethal than all other addictive
 drugs combined.
 Smoking and Pregnancy: What Are the Risks? In the United States between 2009 and 2010, 22.7 percent of teens age 15 to 
17 smoked cigarettes during their pregnancies. Carbon monoxide and nicotine from 
tobacco smoke may interfere with fetal oxygen supply -- and because nicotine readily 
crosses the placenta, it can reach concentrations in the fetus that are much 
higher than maternal levels. Nicotine concentrates in fetal blood, amniotic 
fluid, and breast milk, exposing both fetuses and infants to toxic effects. 
These factors can have severe consequences for the fetuses and infants of 
mothers who smoke, including increased risk for stillbirth, infant mortality,
 sudden infant death syndrome , preterm birth, and respiratory problems. In 
addition, smoking more than a pack a day during
 pregnancy nearly doubles the 
risk that the affected child will become addicted to tobacco if that child 
starts smoking. How Is Tobacco Addiction Treated? The good news is that treatments for tobacco addiction do work. Although some 
people who smoke can quit without help, many people need help. Behavioral 
treatment programs help people learn about and change their behaviors using 
self-help materials, counselor-staffed telephone "quitlines," and individual 
therapy. Over-the-counter medications, such as the
 nicotine patch , gum, 
inhalers, and lozenges, replace nicotine and relieve the symptoms of withdrawal. 
It is important to know that nicotine replacement medicines can be safely used 
as a medication when taken properly. They have lower overall nicotine levels 
than tobacco and they have little abuse potential since they do not produce the 
pleasurable effects of tobacco products. They also don't contain the carcinogens 
and gases found in tobacco smoke, making them a good treatment approach for 
quitting. There are also prescription medications now available for
 smoking cessation , 
such as
 bupropion (
 Zyban ) and
 varenicline tartrate (
 Chantix ), that have been 
shown to help people quit. But research shows that the most effective way to 
quit smoking is to use both medications and behavioral treatment programs. The bottom line: People who quit smoking can have immediate health benefits. 
Believe it or not, within 24 hours of quitting, a person's blood pressure 
decreases and they have less of a chance of having a
 heart attack . Over the long 
haul, quitting means less chance of
 stroke , lung and other cancers, and coronary 
heart disease, and more chance for a long and healthy life.
 What If a Person Wants To Quit? If someone you know is smoking or using tobacco in another way, encourage him 
or her to talk to a parent, school guidance counselor, or other trusted adult. A 
national toll-free number, 1-800-QUIT-NOW (1-800-784-8669), can help people get 
the information they need to quit smoking. Callers to the number are routed to 
their state's smoking cessation quitline or, in states that have not established 
quitlines, to one maintained by the National Cancer Institute. In addition, a 
Web site --
 www.smokefree.gov -- from the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services 
offers online advice and downloadable information to make stopping easier.
</first>
</file1>