<file1>
<first>Oral Surgery
Impacted Teeth Wisdom teeth , otherwise known as third molars, are the last set of
 teeth to
develop. Sometimes these teeth emerge from the gum line and the jaw is large
enough to allow room for them, but most of the time, this is not the case. More
often, one or more of these third molars fails to emerge in proper alignment or
fails to fully emerge through the gum line and becomes entrapped or
"impacted" between the jawbone and the gum tissue. Impacted wisdom
teeth can result in swelling,
 pain , and infection of the gum tissue surrounding
the
 wisdom teeth . In addition, impacted wisdom teeth can cause permanent damage
to nearby teeth, gums, and bone and can sometimes lead to the formation of
 cysts or tumors that can destroy sections of the jaw. Therefore, dentists
recommend people with impacted wisdom teeth have them surgically removed. It's not just wisdom teeth that sometimes become impacted and need to be
removed. Other teeth, such as the cuspids and the bicuspids can become impacted
and can cause the same types of problems described with impacted wisdom
teeth. Tooth Loss Dental implants are an option for tooth loss due to an accident or
infection or as an alternative to
 dentures . The implants are tooth root substitutes that are surgically
anchored in place in the jawbone and act to stabilize the artificial teeth to
which they are attached. Suitable candidates for dental implants need to have
an adequate bone level and density, must not be prone to infection, and must be
willing to maintain good oral hygiene practices.
 Jaw-Related Problems Unequal jaw growth. In some individuals, the upper and lower jaw
fail to grow properly. This can cause difficulty in speaking, eating,
swallowing, and
 breathing . While some of these
 problems -- like improper teeth
 alignment -- can be corrected with
 braces and other orthodontic appliances, more
serious problems require oral surgery to move all or part of the upper jaw,
lower jaw, or both into a new position that is more balanced, functional, and
healthy. Improve fit of dentures. For first-time
 denture wearers, oral
surgery can be done to correct any irregularities of the jaws prior to creating
the
 dentures to ensure a better fit. Oral surgery can also help long-term
denture wearers. Supporting bone often deteriorates over time resulting in
dentures that no longer fit properly. In severe cases, an
 oral surgeon can add
a bone graft to areas where little bone remains. Temporomandibular joint (TMJ) disorders. Dysfunction of the
 TMJ , the small joint in front of the ear where the skull and lower jaw
meet, is a common source of
 headache and facial
 pain . Most patients with TMJ
disorders can be successfully treated with a combination of oral medications,
physical therapy, and splints. However, joint surgery is an option for advanced
cases and when the diagnosis indicates a specific problem in the joint. Other Conditions Treated by Oral Surgery Facial injury repair. Oral surgery is often used to fix fractured
jaws and broken facial bones. Lesion removal and biopsy. Oral surgeons can take a small sample of
abnormal growth or tissue and then send it for laboratory testing for
identification. Some lesions can be managed medically or can be removed by the
oral surgeon. Cleft lip and cleft palate repair. Cleft lip and
 cleft palate result when all or portions of the mouth and nasal cavity do
not grow together properly during
 fetal development . The result is a gap in the
lip and/or a split in the opening in the roof of the mouth. Oral surgeons work
as part of a team of healthcare specialists to correct these problems through a
series of treatments and surgical procedures over many years. Facial infections. Pain and swelling in the face, neck or jaws may
indicate an infection. Infections in this area of the body can sometimes
develop into life-threatening emergencies if not treated promptly and
effectively. An oral surgeon can assist in diagnosing and treating this
problem. Surgical treatment, if needed, may include cutting into and draining
the infected area as well as extracting any teeth that might be involved. Snoring/sleep apnea. When conservative methods fail to alleviate
this problem, surgery can be tried. Surgical procedures involve removing the
soft tissues of the oropharynx (an area in the back portion of the mouth) or
the lower jaw. Laser surgery is a newer treatment option. Depending on the
surgical technique used, the laser is used to either slowly scar the palate,
which tightens it, or to remove palate tissue. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry. Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson, MD, 
on May 1, 2005.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005
</first>
</file1>