<file1>
<first>Ovarian Cysts Causes, Signs, Symptoms, Types, and Treatment
What should I know about ovarian cysts? Ovarian
 cysts are closed, sac-like structures within the ovary that are filled with a liquid or semisolid substance. Ovarian cysts may not cause signs or symptoms. Larger cysts are more likely to cause signs and
 symptoms such as:
 Pain in the abdomen, pelvis, sometimes radiating to the low back, is the most common symptom Feeling of
 bloating or
 indigestion Increased abdominal girth Feeling an urge to have a bowel movement or having difficult, painful bowel movements Pain during sexual intercourse (dyspareunia) Pain in the lower right or left quadrant of the abdomen on one side Nausea and
 vomiting There are many causes and types of ovarian cysts, for example, follicular cysts, "
 chocolate cysts," dermoid cysts, and cysts due to
 polycystic ovary syndrome (
 PCOS ). Most ovarian cysts are not cancerous. Most ovarian cysts are diagnosed with
 ultrasound or physical examination. Transvaginal ultrasound is a common way to examine ovarian cysts. The treatment of an
 ovarian cyst depends upon the cause of the
 cyst and varies from observation and monitoring to surgical treatment. Rupture of an ovarian cyst is a complication that sometimes produces severe pain and
 internal bleeding . A ruptured (burst) ovarian cyst usually causes pain on one side that comes on suddenly. What 
are the ovaries 
and how big are they? The ovary is one of a pair of reproductive glands in women that are located in the pelvis, one on each side of the uterus. Each ovary is about the size and shape of a walnut. The ovaries produce eggs (ova) and the female hormones estrogen and
 progesterone . The ovaries are the main source of female hormones, which control the development of female body characteristics such as the breasts, body shape, and body hair. They also regulate the
 menstrual cycle and
 pregnancy . What are ovarian cysts? Ovarian cysts are closed, sac-like structures within an ovary that contain a liquid, or semisolid substance. "Cyst" is merely a general term for a fluid-filled structure, which may or may not represent a
 tumor or neoplasm (new growth). If it is a tumor, it may be benign or
 malignant . The ovary is also referred to as the female gonad. 
SYMPTOMS:  Most ovarian cysts are never noticed and resolve without women ever realizing that they are there. When a cyst causes symptoms, pain in the abdomen or pelvis is the most common one. The pain can be caused from: rupture of the cyst, rapid growth and stretching, bleeding into the cyst, or twisting of the cyst around its blood supply (known as torsion). If the cyst has reached a large size, other symptoms may arise as a result of pressure or distortion of adjacent anatomical structures. These other symptoms can include abdominal fullness, expansion of the abdomen, or bloating, low back pain , indigestion , feeling full after eating only a small amount (early satiety), urinary urgency , difficulty with emptying the bladder completely, feeling an urge to defecate having difficult bowel movements, or pain with sexual intercourse. 
SYMPTOMS:  A ruptured (burst) ovarian cyst will not always cause symptoms, particularly if the cyst is small. However, sometimes a ruptured ovarian cyst can lead to severe pain and internal bleeding. The pain with a ruptured ovarian cyst typically comes on suddenly and occurs on one side only. The pain may begin during physical activity such as vigorous
 exercise or may begin during sexual intercourse. A ruptured ovarian cyst usually does not cause
 fever or gastrointestinal symptoms. 
CAUSES:  What are the types of ovarian cysts? There are many causes of ovarian cysts, and most ovarian cysts are not cancerous. Follicular cysts: The most common type is a follicular cyst, which results from the growth of a follicle. A follicle is the normal fluid-filled sac that contains an egg.
 Follicular cysts form when the follicle grows larger than normal during the menstrual cycle and does not open to release the egg. Usually, follicular cysts resolve on their own over the course of days to months. Follicular cysts can contain blood (hemorrhagic cysts) from leakage of blood into the egg sac. Corpus luteum cysts: A Corpus luteum cyst is related to the menstrual cycle. The corpus luteum is an area of tissue within the ovary that occurs after an egg has been released from a follicle. If a pregnancy doesn&amp;#39;t occur, the corpus luteum usually breaks down and disappears. It may, however, fill with fluid or blood and persist as a cyst on the ovary. Usually, this cyst is found on only one side, produces no symptoms and resolves spontaneously. "Chocolate cysts:" Endometriosis is a condition in which cells that normally grow inside as a lining of the uterus (womb), instead grow outside of the uterus in other locations. The ovary is a common site for
 endometriosis . When
 endometriosis involves the ovary, the area of endometrial tissue may grow and bleed over time, forming a blood-filled cyst with red- or brown-colored contents called an endometrioma, sometimes referred to as a
 "chocolate cyst ." Polycystic ovarian syndrome: The condition known as
 polycystic ovarian syndrome (PCOS) is characterized by the presence of multiple small cysts within both ovaries. PCOS is associated with a number of hormonal problems and is the most common cause of
 infertility in women. Dermoid cysts (benign cystic teratomas): Both benign and malignant tumors of the ovary may also be cystic. Occasionally, the tissues of the ovary develop abnormally to form other body tissues such as hair or
 teeth . Cysts with these abnormal tissues are really tumors called benign cystic teratomas or
 dermoid cysts . Tubo-ovarian abscesses: Infections of the pelvic organs can involve the ovaries and Fallopian tubes. In severe cases, pus-filled cystic spaces may be present on, in, or around the ovary or tubes. These are known as tubo-ovarian abscesses. Can ovarian cysts cause cancer? Most ovarian cysts are not due to
 cancer , and having an ovarian cyst does not cause
 ovarian cancer . However, some ovarian
 cancers develop cystic areas inside the tumor.
 Ovarian cancer is much less common than benign ovarian cysts. What about ovarian cysts during pregnancy? Ovarian cysts are sometimes discovered during pregnancy. In most cases, they are an incidental finding at the time of routine
 prenatal ultrasound screening. The majority of ovarian cysts found during pregnancy are benign conditions that do not require surgical intervention. However, surgery may be indicated if there is a suspicion of
 malignancy , if an acute complication such as rupture or torsion (twisting of the cyst, disrupting the blood supply) develops, or if the size of the cyst is likely to present problems with the pregnancy. Can a woman get ovarian cysts during menopase or postmenopause? Ovarian cysts may develop during pregnancy or at any point in a woman&amp;#39;s life. Some kinds of ovarian cysts are related to the menstrual cycle and occur before a woman has reached
 menopause (the time point at which a women has not had a
 menstrual period for 12 consecutive months). However,
 postmenopausal women may still develop other types of ovarian cysts. Which specialties of doctors treat ovarian cysts? Gynecologists-obstetricians are the medical specialists most likely to treat ovarian cysts. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Sometimes ovarian cysts may be noticed by a doctor during a bimanual examination of the pelvis. If a cyst is suspected based upon symptoms or physical examination, imaging techniques are used. Most cysts are diagnosed by ultrasound, which is the best imaging technique for detecting them. Ultrasound uses sound waves to produce an image of structures within the body. Ultrasound imaging is painless and harmless. Transvaginal ultrasound is a diagnostic tool to better visualize the ovaries using a thin ultrasound probe inside the vagina. Cysts can also be detected with other imaging methods, such as
 CT scan or
 MRI scan (
 magnetic resonance imaging ). Functional ovarian cysts: If a woman is in her 40&amp;#39;s, or younger, and has regular menstrual periods, most ovarian masses are
 "functional ovarian cysts," which are not really abnormal. Examples include follicular cysts and corpus luteum cysts. These are related to the process of
 ovulation that happens with the menstrual cycle. They usually disappear on their own during a future menstrual cycle. Therefore, especially in women in their 20&amp;#39;s and 30&amp;#39;s, these cysts are watched for a few menstrual cycles to verify that they disappear. Because
 oral contraceptives work by preventing ovulation, physicians will not generally expect women who are taking oral contraceptives to have common "functional ovarian cysts." These women do not have functional ovarian cysts. They may receive further evaluation with pelvic ultrasound or possibly surgical intervention. Functional ovarian cysts do not occur in women after they have reached
 menopause . Small cystic arrested follicles may persist in the ovary after
 menopause . Other factors are helpful in evaluating ovarian cysts (besides the woman&amp;#39;s age, or whether she is taking oral contraceptives). A cyst that contains a simple sac of fluid on ultrasound is more likely to be a benign neoplasm than a cyst with solid tissue in it. So the ultrasound appearance also plays a role in determining the level of suspicion regarding an ovarian tumor. Cancer risks: Ovarian cancer is rare in women younger than age 40. After age 40, an ovarian cyst has a higher chance of being cancerous than before age 40, although most ovarian cysts are still benign even after age 40. CA-125 blood testing can be used as a marker of
 ovarian cancer , but it does not always represent
 cancer , even when it is abnormal, and it may be normal in the presence of malignancy. CA-125 is a protein that is elevated in the bloodstream of many women with advanced ovarian
 cancer . First, many benign conditions in women of childbearing age can cause the CA-125 level to be elevated, so CA-125 is not a specific test, especially in younger women. Pelvic infections,
 uterine fibroids , pregnancy, benign (hemorrhagic) ovarian cysts, endometriosis, and
 liver disease are some of the conditions that may elevate blood CA-125 levels in the absence of ovarian cancer. Second, even if the woman has an ovarian cancer, not all ovarian cancers will cause the CA-125 level to be elevated. Furthermore, CA-125 levels can be abnormally high in women with breast, lung, and
 pancreatic cancer . 
TREATMENT:  Most ovarian cysts in women of childbearing age are follicular or corpus luteum cysts (functional cysts) that disappear naturally in one to three months, although they can rupture and cause pain. They are benign and have no long-term medical consequences. They may be diagnosed coincidentally during a pelvic examination in women who do not have any related symptoms. All women have follicular cysts at some point that generally go unnoticed. Ultrasound is useful to determine if the cyst is simple (just fluid with no solid tissue, suggesting a benign condition) or compound (with solid components that often requires surgical resection). In summary, the ideal treatment of ovarian cysts depends on the likely cause of the cysts and whether or not it is producing symptoms. The woman&amp;#39;s age, the size (and any change in size) of the cyst, and the cyst&amp;#39;s appearance on ultrasound help determine the treatment. Cysts that are functional are usually observed (watchful waiting) with frequent monitoring unless they rupture and cause significant bleeding, in which case, surgical treatment is required. Benign and malignant tumors require operation. Treatment can consist of simple observation, or it can involve evaluating blood tests such as a CA-125 to help determine the potential for cancer (keeping in mind the many limitations of CA-125 testing described above). There are no natural or home remedies to treat ovarian cysts, other than taking non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
 drugs for
 pain management . What about surgery for ovarian cysts? Any type of ovarian mass, including a cyst, can be surgically removed either with
 laparoscopy , or if needed, an open abdominal incision (laparotomy) if it is causing severe pain, not resolving, or if it is suspicious in any way. Once the cyst is removed, the growth is sent to a pathologist who examines the tissue under a microscope to make the final diagnosis as to the type of cyst present. What is the prognosis for a woman with ovarian cysts? Most functional (related to the menstrual cycle) ovarian cysts resolve on their own and do not cause long-term problems. Benign cysts or benign tumors can be surgically removed. The vast majority of ovarian cysts do not cause any long-term problems. Rarely, cysts may be present within an ovarian cancer. In this case, the prognosis depends upon the extent of spread and exact type of cancer that is present. 
PREVENTION:  There is no known way to prevent the development of ovarian cysts.</first>
</file1>