<file1>
<first>Abdominal Migraine in Children

ABOUT: Abdominal
 migraine is believed to be a 
variant of
 migraine that is common in children but rare in adults. Abdominal migraine is characterized by
 pain in the center of the abdomen that may be severe. Symptoms can last for one hour or up to 
a several days. Nausea and
 vomiting may be associated 
with the
 pain . Sleep typically brings relief from 
abdominal migraine. Medications used to treat classic migraine can also be 
effective, although there is no single treatment that is known to be effective 
in all patients. Most children with abdominal migraine 
have a family history of migraine, and most go on to develop migraine as adults. The exact cause of abdominal migraine 
is poorly understood. It may be related to both neurologic and endocrinologic 
 (hormone) 
factors. The diagnosis of abdominal migraine can 
be difficult, and depends upon ruling out other potential causes for the
 abdominal pain and symptoms. There is no one diagnostic test that confirms the 
diagnosis. What is abdominal migraine? Like adults, children can develop migraines. This can be the same type of 
condition seen in adults, which is typically occurs with a
 headache , and is 
sometimes preceded by an aura.
 Nausea ,
 vomiting , and
 photophobia (decreased 
tolerance to light) can occur. Children also develop some unusual and atypical 
variations of migraine, not associated with
 headaches in particular, that are 
not usually observed in adults. Abdominal migraine is one of these variants. Abdominal migraine is a condition thought to be related to migraine that is 
characterized by pain in the abdomen. It is often precipitated by the usual 
triggers of classic migraine. The pain can be severe, and nausea and vomiting 
can occur. Abdominal migraine is rare in adults, but it has been estimated that up to 2% 
of all children may develop abdominal migraines. Children who have the condition 
usually go on to develop migraine
 headaches as adults. Girls are affected more 
frequently than boys. Abdominal migraine typically occurs for the first time 
between the ages of 2 and 10.
 
CAUSES:  The cause of abdominal migraine is poorly understood. Abdominal migraine is 
thought by some researchers to be related to neurologic or endocrinologic 
changes and may be caused by alterations in the levels of
 serotonin and 
histamine in the body. Genetic factors may also be involved as the condition is 
more common in children who have a family history of migraine. About 60% of 
children with the condition have a positive family history for migraine. Triggers for abdominal migraine have been described, similar to triggers for 
classic migraine. These include
 chocolate or nitrite-containing foods,
 stress , 
and
 anxiety . 
SYMPTOMS:  As mentioned, abdominal migraine causes pain in the abdomen that can be 
severe and debilitating. It is typically located in the middle portion of the 
belly, often around the umbilicus. Cramping, nausea, and vomiting can accompany 
the pain. Pallor (paleness) of the skin is often observed. There may not be associated
 headache . The symptoms are usually relieved by
 sleep and can last anywhere from 
one hour to several days. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Because of the frequent absence of
 headache , the condition can be difficult 
to diagnose, especially during the first episode. There is no specific test that 
can establish the diagnosis of abdominal migraine, so the diagnosis is based on 
exclusion of other conditions. Laboratory tests and imaging studies are usually 
directed to rule out other conditions that could be responsible for the 
symptoms. Electroencephalography (
 EEG ) is sometimes done to rule out a
 seizure disorder as the cause of the symptoms.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of abdominal migraine has two components - to reduce symptoms 
of an acute attack and to prevent or lessen the severity of future episodes. 
Research to date has not provided sufficient data to firmly establish the role 
of any particular medication in either treating symptoms or preventing future 
episodes of abdominal migraine. Still, many patients respond to anti-migraine 
medications and other medications. Medications to treat abdominal migraine Types of medications that may be used to manage abdominal migraine include: Analgesic
 drugs , such as nonsteroidal 
anti-inflammatory medications (
 NSAIDs ) or
 acetaminophen Sumatriptan (
 Imitrex ,
 Alsuma ), a member of the triptan 
class of drugs used to treat migraine in adults, has been used to treat some 
older children with abdominal migraine Tricyclic antidepressants and drugs 
that block the effects of serotonin have been used in some patients to decrease 
frequency of attacks. Valproic acid (
 Depakote ), an 
antiseizure medication, has been used to treat abdominal migraine. Ergotamine medications, also used for 
adults with migraine, are used to treat some childhood variants of migraine. Low dose
 aspirin and 
 low dose 
beta-blocker medications have been used over the long term in some patients in 
an attempt to diminish the frequency of future attacks. The antihistamine
 cyproheptadine has 
been shown to be effective in some children with migraine variants. Other aspects of treatment may include the administration of intravenous 
fluids if vomiting is severe, and the use of sedatives or antiemetic drugs. Treatment may also include advice to recognize and avoid triggers, if these 
are known. For example, if food triggers have been identified, these should be 
avoided, although not all those who experience abdominal migraine have 
identifiable food triggers.
 Stress management and relaxation programs may be of 
benefit to some.
 What is the prognosis for abdominal migraine? The prognosis for abdominal migraine is good; most children eventually stop 
having the attacks of
 abdominal pain . However, most children (about 70% in one 
study of 54 children) who have abdominal migraine go on to develop migraines in 
adulthood.
</first>
</file1>