<file1>
<first>Pacemaker
Pacemaker definition and facts* A pacemaker is a small device that&amp;#39;s placed in the chest or abdomen to help control
 abnormal heart rhythms . This device uses low-energy electrical pulses to prompt the heart to beat at a normal rate. Pacemakers are used to treat arrhythmias. Arrhythmias are problems with the rate or rhythm of the heartbeat. During an
 arrhythmia , the heart can beat too fast, too slow, or with an irregular rhythm. Pacemakers can relieve some arrhythmia symptoms, such as
 fatigue (
 tiredness ) and
 fainting . A pacemaker also can help a person who has abnormal heart rhythms resume a more active lifestyle. Doctors also treat arrhythmias with implantable
 cardioverter defibrillators (ICDs). ICDs are similar to pacemakers. However, besides using low-energy electrical pulses to control abnormal heart rhythms, ICDs also can use high-energy electrical pulses to treat certain dangerous arrhythmias. Doctors recommend pacemakers for a number of reasons. The most common reasons are bradycardia and
 heart block . Bradycardia is a slower than normal heartbeat. Heart block is a problem that occurs with the heart&amp;#39;s electrical system. The disorder occurs when an electrical signal is slowed or disrupted as it moves through the heart. Before recommending a pacemaker, your doctor will consider any arrhythmia symptoms you have, such as
 dizziness , unexplained
 fainting , or
 shortness of breath . He or she also will consider whether you have a history of
 heart disease , what medicines you&amp;#39;re currently taking, and the results of heart tests. A pacemaker consists of a battery, a computerized generator, and wires with sensors called electrodes on one end. The electrodes detect your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity and send data through the wires to the computer in the generator. If your heart rhythm is abnormal, the computer will direct the generator to send electrical pulses to your heart. The pulses then travel through the wires to reach your heart. Newer pacemakers also can monitor your blood temperature,
 breathing , and other factors and adjust your heart rate to changes in your activity. Placing a pacemaker requires minor surgery. The surgery usually is done in a hospital or special heart treatment laboratory. You&amp;#39;ll be given medicine just before the surgery that will help you relax and may make you sleepy. The surgery takes just a few hours, but you&amp;#39;ll stay in the hospital overnight so your health care team can check your heartbeat and make sure your pacemaker is working properly. Complications from pacemaker surgery are rare. Most people can return to their normal activities within a few days. Your doctor may ask you to avoid vigorous
 exercise or heavy lifting for about a month after your surgery. After you have fully recovered from surgery, discuss with your doctor how much and what kinds of physical activity are safe for you. Once you have a pacemaker, you have to avoid close or prolonged contact with electrical devices or devices that have strong magnetic fields. You also need to avoid certain medical procedures that can disrupt your pacemaker. Let all of your doctors, dentists, and medical technicians know that you have a pacemaker. Your doctor can give you a card that states what kind of pacemaker you have. Carry this card in your wallet. You may want to consider wearing a medical ID bracelet or necklace that explains that you have a pacemaker. Your doctor will want to check your pacemaker regularly. Some pacemaker functions can be checked remotely through a telephone call or a computer connection to the Internet. Your doctor may ask you to come to his or her office to check your pacemaker. Pacemaker batteries last between 5 and 15 years (average 6 to 7 years), depending on how active your pacemaker is. The wires of your pacemaker also may need to be replaced eventually. Your doctor can tell you whether your pacemaker or its wires need to be replaced.
 What is a pacemaker? A pacemaker is a small device that&amp;#39;s placed in the chest or abdomen to help control abnormal heart rhythms. This device uses electrical pulses to prompt the heart to beat at a normal rate. Pacemakers are used to treat arrhythmias (ah-RITH-me-ahs). Arrhythmias are problems with the rate or rhythm of the heartbeat. During an arrhythmia, the heart can beat too fast, too slow, or with an irregular rhythm. A heartbeat that&amp;#39;s too fast is called tachycardia (TAK-ih-KAR-de-ah). A heartbeat that&amp;#39;s too slow is called bradycardia (bray-de-KAR-de-ah). During an arrhythmia, the heart may not be able to pump enough blood to the body. This can cause symptoms such as
 fatigue (tiredness), shortness of breath, or fainting. Severe arrhythmias can damage the body&amp;#39;s vital organs and may even cause
 loss of consciousness or death. A pacemaker can relieve some arrhythmia symptoms, such as
 fatigue and fainting. A pacemaker also can help a person who has abnormal heart rhythms resume a more active lifestyle. How do pacemakers regulate arrhythmias? Faulty electrical signaling in the heart causes arrhythmias. Pacemakers use low-energy electrical pulses to overcome this faulty electrical signaling. Pacemakers can: Speed up a slow heart rhythm. Help control an abnormal or fast heart rhythm. Make sure the ventricles contract normally if the atria are quivering instead of beating with a normal rhythm (a condition called
 atrial fibrillation ). Coordinate electrical signaling between the upper and lower chambers of the heart. Coordinate electrical signaling between the ventricles. Pacemakers that do this are called cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) devices. CRT devices are used to treat
 heart failure . Prevent dangerous arrhythmias caused by a disorder called long QT syndrome. Pacemakers also can monitor and record your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity and heart rhythm. Newer pacemakers can monitor your blood temperature, breathing rate, and other factors. They also can adjust your heart rate to changes in your activity. Pacemakers can be temporary or permanent. Temporary pacemakers are used to treat short-term heart problems, such as a slow heartbeat that&amp;#39;s caused by a
 heart attack , heart surgery, or an overdose of medicine. Temporary pacemakers also are used during emergencies. They might be used until your doctor can implant a permanent pacemaker or until a temporary condition goes away. If you have a temporary pacemaker, you&amp;#39;ll stay in a hospital as long as the device is in place. Permanent pacemakers are used to control long-term heart rhythm problems. This article mainly discusses permanent pacemakers, unless stated otherwise. Doctors also treat arrhythmias with another device called an implantable cardioverter
 defibrillator (ICD). An ICD is similar to a pacemaker. However, besides using low-energy electrical pulses, an ICD also can use high-energy pulses to treat life-threatening arrhythmias. Your heart has its own internal electrical system that controls the rate and rhythm of your heartbeat. With each heartbeat, an electrical signal spreads from the top of your heart to the bottom. As the signal travels, it causes the heart to contract and pump blood. Each electrical signal normally begins in a group of cells called the sinus node or sinoatrial (SA) node. As the signal spreads from the top of the heart to the bottom, it coordinates the timing of heart cell activity. First, the heart&amp;#39;s two upper chambers, the atria (AY-tree-uh), contract. This contraction pumps blood into the heart&amp;#39;s two lower chambers, the ventricles (VEN-trih-kuls). The ventricles then contract and pump blood to the rest of the body. The combined contraction of the atria and ventricles is a heartbeat.
 Who needs a pacemaker? Doctors recommend pacemakers for many reasons. The most common reasons are bradycardia and heart block. Bradycardia is a heartbeat that is slower than normal. Heart block is a disorder that occurs if an electrical signal is slowed or disrupted as it moves through the heart. Heart block can happen as a result of
 aging , damage to the heart from a heart attack, or other conditions that disrupt the heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity. Some nerve and muscle disorders also can cause heart block, including muscular dystrophy. Your doctor also may recommend a pacemaker if: Aging or
 heart disease damages your sinus node&amp;#39;s ability to set the correct pace for your heartbeat. Such damage can cause slower than normal heartbeats or long pauses between heartbeats. The damage also can cause your heart to switch between slow and fast rhythms. This condition is called sick sinus syndrome. You&amp;#39;ve had a medical procedure to treat an arrhythmia called
 atrial fibrillation . A pacemaker can help regulate your heartbeat after the procedure. You need to take certain heart medicines, such as
 beta blockers . These medicines can slow your heartbeat too much. You faint or have other symptoms of a slow heartbeat. For example, this may happen if the main artery in your neck that supplies your brain with blood is sensitive to pressure. Just quickly turning your neck can cause your heart to beat slower than normal. As a result, your brain might not get enough blood flow, causing you to feel faint or collapse. You have heart muscle problems that cause electrical signals to travel too slowly through your heart muscle. Your pacemaker may provide cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) for this problem. CRT devices coordinate electrical signaling between the heart&amp;#39;s lower chambers. You have long QT syndrome, which puts you at risk for dangerous arrhythmias. Doctors also may recommend pacemakers for people who have certain types of congenital
 heart disease or for people who have had heart transplants. Children,
 teens , and adults can use pacemakers. Before recommending a pacemaker, your doctor will consider any arrhythmia symptoms you have, such as
 dizziness , unexplained fainting, or shortness of breath. He or she also will consider whether you have a history of heart disease, what medicines you&amp;#39;re currently taking, and the results of heart tests.
 How are abnormal heart rhythms (arrhythmias) diagnosed? Many tests are used to detect arrhythmias. You may have one or more of the following tests. An
 EKG is a simple, painless test that detects and records the heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity. The test shows how fast your heart is beating and its rhythm (steady or irregular). An EKG also records the strength and timing of electrical signals as they pass through your heart. The test can help diagnose bradycardia and heart block (the most common reasons for needing a pacemaker). A standard EKG only records the heartbeat for a few seconds. It won&amp;#39;t detect arrhythmias that don&amp;#39;t happen during the test. To diagnose heart rhythm problems that come and go, your doctor may have you wear a portable EKG monitor. The two most common types of portable EKGs are Holter and event monitors. A Holter monitor records the heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity for a full 24- or 48-hour period. You wear one while you do your normal daily activities. This allows the monitor to record your heart for a longer time than a standard EKG. An event monitor is similar to a Holter monitor. You wear an event monitor while doing your normal activities. However, an event monitor only records your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity at certain times while you&amp;#39;re wearing it. For many event monitors, you push a button to start the monitor when you feel symptoms. Other event monitors start automatically when they sense abnormal heart rhythms. You can wear an event monitor for weeks or until symptoms occur. Echocardiography (echo) uses sound waves to create a moving picture of your heart. The test shows the size and shape of your heart and how well your heart chambers and valves are working. Echo also can show areas of poor blood flow to the heart, areas of heart muscle that aren&amp;#39;t contracting normally, and injury to the heart muscle caused by poor blood flow. For this test, a thin, flexible wire is passed through a vein in your groin (upper thigh) or arm to your heart. The wire records the heart&amp;#39;s electrical signals. Your doctor uses the wire to electrically stimulate your heart. This allows him or her to see how your heart&amp;#39;s electrical system responds. This test helps pinpoint where the heart&amp;#39;s electrical system is damaged. Some heart problems are easier to diagnose when your heart is working hard and beating fast. During stress testing, you
 exercise to make your heart work hard and beat fast while heart tests, such as an EKG or echo, are done. If you can&amp;#39;t exercise, you may be given medicine to raise your heart rate.
 How does a pacemaker work? A pacemaker consists of a battery, a computerized generator, and wires with sensors at their tips. (The sensors are called electrodes.) The battery powers the generator, and both are surrounded by a thin metal box. The wires connect the generator to the heart. A pacemaker helps monitor and control your heartbeat. The electrodes detect your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity and send data through the wires to the computer in the generator. If your heart rhythm is abnormal, the computer will direct the generator to send electrical pulses to your heart. The pulses travel through the wires to reach your heart. Newer pacemakers can monitor your blood temperature, breathing, and other factors. They also can adjust your heart rate to changes in your activity. The pacemaker&amp;#39;s computer also records your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity and heart rhythm. Your doctor will use these recordings to adjust your pacemaker so it works better for you. Your doctor can program the pacemaker&amp;#39;s computer with an external device. He or she doesn&amp;#39;t have to use needles or have direct contact with the pacemaker. Pacemakers have one to three wires that are each placed in different chambers of the heart. The wires in a single-chamber pacemaker usually carry pulses from the generator to the
 right ventricle (the lower right chamber of your heart). The wires in a dual-chamber pacemaker carry pulses from the generator to the
 right atrium (the upper right chamber of your heart) and the right ventricle. The pulses help coordinate the timing of these two chambers&amp;#39; contractions. The wires in a
 biventricular pacemaker carry pulses from the generator to an
 atrium and both ventricles. The pulses help coordinate electrical signaling between the two ventricles. This type of pacemaker also is called a cardiac resynchronization therapy (CRT) device. Types of Pacemaker Programming The two main types of programming for pacemakers are demand pacing and rate-responsive pacing. A demand pacemaker monitors your heart rhythm. It only sends electrical pulses to your heart if your heart is beating too slow or if it misses a beat. A rate-responsive pacemaker will speed up or slow down your heart rate depending on how active you are. To do this, the device monitors your sinus node rate, breathing, blood temperature, and other factors to determine your activity level. Your doctor will work with you to decide which type of pacemaker is best for you.
 What should I expect during pacemaker surgery? Placing a pacemaker requires minor surgery. The surgery usually is done in a hospital or special heart treatment laboratory. Before the surgery, an intravenous (IV) line will be inserted into one of your veins. You will receive medicine through the IV line to help you relax. The medicine also might make you sleepy. Your doctor will numb the area where he or she will put the pacemaker so you don&amp;#39;t feel any
 pain . Your doctor also may give you antibiotics to prevent infection. First, your doctor will insert a needle into a large vein, usually near the shoulder opposite your dominant hand. Your doctor will then use the needle to thread the pacemaker wires into the vein and to correctly place them in your heart. An x-ray "movie" of the wires as they pass through your vein and into your heart will help your doctor place them. Once the wires are in place, your doctor will make a small cut into the skin of your chest or abdomen. He or she will slip the pacemaker&amp;#39;s small metal box through the cut, place it just under your skin, and connect it to the wires that lead to your heart. The box contains the pacemaker&amp;#39;s battery and generator. Once the pacemaker is in place, your doctor will test it to make sure it works properly. He or she will then sew up the cut. The entire surgery takes a few hours. What should I expect after pacemaker surgery? Expect to stay in the hospital overnight so your health care team can check your heartbeat and make sure your pacemaker is working well. You&amp;#39;ll likely have to arrange for a ride to and from the hospital because your doctor may not want you to drive yourself. For a few days to weeks after surgery, you may have
 pain , swelling, or tenderness in the area where your pacemaker was placed. The pain usually is mild; over-the-counter medicines often can relieve it. Talk to your doctor before taking any pain medicines. Your doctor may ask you to avoid vigorous activities and heavy lifting for about a month after pacemaker surgery. Most people return to their normal activities within a few days of having the surgery.
 
RISKS:  Pacemaker surgery generally is safe. If problems do occur, they may include: Swelling, bleeding,
 bruising , or infection in the area where the pacemaker was placed Blood vessel or nerve damage A collapsed lung A bad reaction to the medicine used during the procedure Talk with your doctor about the benefits and risks of pacemaker surgery. How will a pacemaker affect my lifestyle? Once you have a pacemaker, you have to avoid close or prolonged contact with electrical devices or devices that have strong magnetic fields. Devices that can interfere with a pacemaker include: Cell phones and MP3 players (for example, iPods) Household appliances, such as microwave ovens High-tension wires Metal detectors Industrial welders Electrical generators These devices can disrupt the electrical signaling of your pacemaker and stop it from working properly. You may not be able to tell whether your pacemaker has been affected. How likely a device is to disrupt your pacemaker depends on how long you&amp;#39;re exposed to it and how close it is to your pacemaker. To be safe, some experts recommend not putting your cell phone or MP3 player in a shirt pocket over your pacemaker (if the devices are turned on). You may want to hold your cell phone up to the ear that&amp;#39;s opposite the site where your pacemaker is implanted. If you strap your MP3 player to your arm while listening to it, put it on the arm that&amp;#39;s farther from your pacemaker. You can still use household appliances, but avoid close and prolonged exposure, as it may interfere with your pacemaker. You can walk through security system metal detectors at your normal pace. Security staff can check you with a metal detector wand as long as it isn&amp;#39;t held for too long over your pacemaker site. You should avoid sitting or standing close to a security system metal detector. Notify security staff if you have a pacemaker. Also, stay at least 2 feet away from industrial welders and electrical generators. Some medical procedures can disrupt your pacemaker. These procedures include: Magnetic resonance imaging , or
 MRI Shock-wave
 lithotripsy to get rid of
 kidney stones Electrocauterization to stop bleeding during surgery Let all of your doctors, dentists, and medical technicians know that you have a pacemaker. Your doctor can give you a card that states what kind of pacemaker you have. Carry this card in your wallet. You may want to wear a medical ID bracelet or necklace that states that you have a pacemaker.
 How often do pacemakers need to be checked? Your doctor will want to check your pacemaker regularly (about every 3 months). Over time, a pacemaker can stop working properly because: Its wires get dislodged or broken Its battery gets weak or fails Your heart disease progresses Other devices have disrupted its electrical signaling To check your pacemaker, your doctor may ask you to come in for an office visit several times a year. Some pacemaker functions can be checked remotely using a phone or the Internet. Your doctor also may ask you to have an EKG (
 electrocardiogram ) to check for changes in your heart&amp;#39;s electrical activity. How long do pacemaker batteries last? Pacemaker batteries last between 5 and 15 years (average 6 to 7 years), depending on how active the pacemaker is. Your doctor will replace the generator along with the battery before the battery starts to run down. Replacing the generator and battery is less-involved surgery than the original surgery to implant the pacemaker. Your pacemaker wires also may need to be replaced eventually. Your doctor can tell you whether your pacemaker or its wires need to be replaced when you see him or her for followup visits.
</first>
</file1>