<file1>
<first>Phobias

ABOUT: The definition of a
 phobia is the persistent fear of a situation, activity, or thing that causes one to want to avoid it. The three types of phobias are social phobia (fear of public speaking, meeting new people or other social situations),
 agoraphobia (fear of being outside), and specific phobias (fear of other items or situations). Although phobias often go underreported, the statistics for people who have phobias are thought to be more than 6 million people in the United States. The average age that phobias begin is about 10 years of age. Women tend to be twice as likely to develop a phobia compared to men. While there are almost as many phobias as there are situations, the most common kinds of phobias include social phobia, agoraphobia, claustrophobia, coulrophobia, aerophobia, zoophobia, arachnophobia, dentophobia, aichmophobia, ophidiophobia, acrophobia, mysophobia, and hemophobia. Agoraphobia often co-occurs with
 panic disorder . If not treated, a phobia may worsen to the point where the person&amp;#39;s life is seriously impacted by the phobia and by attempts to avoid or hide it, resulting in problems with physical health, friends and family, failure in school, and/or lost jobs while struggling to cope. Phobias tend to run in families, can be influenced by culture and
 parenting style, and can be triggered by life events. People with phobias seem to be more likely to deal with
 stress by avoiding the trigger for the stress and have trouble minimizing the severity of the fearful situation. Symptoms of phobias often involve
 panic attacks . The evaluation of phobias often includes questions by a health-care professional that explore the symptoms that are occurring, a medical interview, and a physical examination. The treatment of phobias often includes the use of desensitization, cognitive behavioral therapy, and/or medications. The groups of medications doctors tend to choose from when treating a phobia include selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, beta-blockers, and occasionally,
 benzodiazepines . Phobia sufferers sometimes cope with their fears by talking about it, refraining from avoiding situations they find stressful, visualization, and making positive self-statements.
 What is a phobia? What are the different kinds of phobias? A phobia is defined as the persistent fear of a situation, activity, or thing that causes the sufferer to want to avoid it. The three types of phobias are social phobia (fear of public speaking, meeting new people, or other social situations), agoraphobia (fear of being outside), and specific phobias (fear of particular items or situations). Phobias are largely underreported, probably because many people with phobias find ways to avoid the situations that they fear. Therefore, statistics for how many people have phobias vary widely. Phobias are fairly common. Women are thought to be twice as likely to develop a phobia than men. Some of the most common phobias include fears of public speaking or other social situations (social phobia or
 social anxiety disorder ), open spaces (agoraphobia), closed-in spaces (claustrophobia), the dark, clowns (coulrophobia), flying (aerophobia), blood, birds (ornithophobia) or all animals (zoophobia), commitment (gamophobia), driving (vehophobia), snow (chionophobia), spiders (arachnophobia) and bugs, needles (aichmophobia), snakes (ophidiophobia), death, math, heights (acrophobia or altophobia), bridges or tunnels, germs (mysophobia), and having dental work done (dentophobia). Fears of midgets, haunted houses, long words, helmets, pickles,
 feet , and phobias of holes are just a few unusual fears/phobias and may be considered weird or strange by some but can be just as debilitating as those phobias that are more common. Agoraphobia often coexists with panic disorder.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  If not treated, a phobia can worsen to the point in which the person&amp;#39;s quality of life is seriously impaired, both by the phobia itself and/or by attempts to avoid or hide it. For example, a fear of flying can result in the sufferer being unable to travel. Some people have problems with their relationships, have failed in school, and/or been unable to maintain employment as the result of a severe phobia. While there may be periods of spontaneous improvement, a phobia does not usually go away unless the individual gets treatments that are specifically designed to address this condition. Alcoholics can be up to 10 times more likely to develop a phobia than nonalcoholics, and phobic individuals may be twice as likely to suffer from
 alcoholism or another
 addiction than those who have never been phobic. It has even been found that phobic
 anxiety can be life-threatening for some people, increasing the risk of suffering from
 heart disease in both men and women. 
CAUSES:  While there is no single known cause for phobias, they are thought to run in families, be influenced by culture and how one is parented and can be triggered by different life events. Immediate family members of phobia sufferers are about three times more likely to also have a phobia than those who do not have such a family history. People whose parents either were overly protective or were distant in raising them may be at more risk of developing phobias. Phobia sufferers tend to be more likely to manage stress by avoiding the stressful situation and have trouble decreasing the intensity of the fearful situation. Another possible contributor to the development of phobias is classical conditioning. In classical conditioning, an individual responds to something that scares them by generalizing the fear of that specific thing or situation to more generalized things or situations. For example, a person may respond to a real threat by one dog to developing a phobia of all
 dogs .
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of phobias often involve having a
 panic attack -- in that they include feelings of intense fear, dread, or terror, despite understanding that those feelings are out of proportion to any real threat -- in addition to physical symptoms like
 tremors ,
 sweating , "mind going blank,"
 nausea , rapid heartbeat, trouble
 breathing , and an overwhelming desire to withdraw from the situation that is causing the phobic reaction. Also, extreme measures are sometimes taken to prevent or leave the situation. How do health-care professionals diagnose phobias? Many health-care providers may assess for the diagnosis of phobias, including licensed mental-health therapists, family doctors, or other primary-care medical providers, specialists whom you see for a medical condition, psychiatrists, psychologists, and social workers. If one of these practitioners suspects that you may have a phobia, you will likely be asked a number of questions to explore all the symptoms you may be having and you may need to have a medical interview and physical examination. A phobia may co-occur with a number of other mental-health problems, including
 schizophrenia ,
 depression ,
 obsessive-compulsive disorder (
 OCD ), and substance-abuse disorders. Phobias are particularly associated with other
 anxiety disorders. In addition to panic disorder, examples of other anxiety disorders include
 generalized anxiety disorder (
 GAD ) and
 posttraumatic stress disorder (
 PTSD ). In children, school phobia or a fear of being alone may occur with or without
 separation anxiety disorder. As anxiety disorders in general may co-occur with a number of medical conditions or can be a reaction to various medications, routine laboratory tests are often done during the initial evaluation to rule out other possible causes of the symptoms.
 
TREATMENT:  Helping phobia sufferers is thought to be most effective when
 psychotherapy and medications that are specific to the treatment of phobia are both used. One type of mental-health therapy involves the supportive and gradual exposure of the person with phobias to situations that are increasingly similar to the one they are phobic about (desensitization). These circumstances can either include actual or computer-generated anxiety-provoking stimuli. Cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) has been found to often quite effectively decrease phobic symptoms by helping the person with the illness change his or her way of thinking. CBT uses three techniques to accomplish this goal: Didactic component: This part of treatment involves educating the person about phobias and treatment and helps to establish positive expectations for therapy and promote the cooperation of the individual with a phobia. Cognitive component: It helps to recognize the ideas and assumptions that influence the behavior of the phobia sufferer, especially those that may predispose him or her to developing the disorder. Behavioral component: This uses behavior-modifying techniques to teach the person with a phobia more effective strategies for coping with problems. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) medications are often used to treat phobias, especially when desensitization and CBT are inadequately effective. These medications enhance levels of serotonin in the brain. Examples of these medications include
 fluoxetine (
 Prozac ),
 sertraline (
 Zoloft ),
 paroxetine (
 Paxil ),
 fluvoxamine (
 Luvox ),
 citalopram (
 Celexa ),
 escitalopram (
 Lexapro ),
 vortioxetine (
 Brintellix ), and vilazodone (Viibryd). The possible side effects of these medications can vary greatly from person to person and somewhat depend on which medication is being used. Common side effects of this group of medications include
 dry mouth , sexual dysfunction,
 nausea ,
 tremors , trouble sleeping,
 blurred vision ,
 constipation or soft stools, and
 dizziness . Some people gradually gain weight over time. In rare cases, people have been thought to become more acutely more anxious or
 depressed on the medication, even trying to or completing
 suicide or homicide. Children and
 teens are thought to be more vulnerable to this rare side effect compared to adults. Phobias are also sometimes treated using beta-blocker medications, which decrease the physical symptoms associated with panic by blocking the effects that adrenaline (epinephrine) has on the body. One example of a beta-blocker is
 propranolol . These disorders are also sometimes treated with
 drugs in a medication class called benzodiazepines or minor tranquilizers. This class of medications causes relaxation but is used with caution these days to treat anxiety due to the possibility of addiction and the risk of overdose, especially if taken when alcohol is also being consumed. Examples of medications from that group include
 diazepam (
 Valium ),
 alprazolam (
 Xanax ),
 lorazepam (
 Ativan ), and
 clonazepam (
 Klonopin ).
 What is the prognosis for phobias? Cognitive therapy and exposure therapy alone, in combination, or with relaxation training have been found to be effective in treating phobias. Relaxation training alone has also been found to be effective in treating phobias. While some interventions, like sedating people who are phobic about getting dental work, may be useful in the short term, they may undermine truly overcoming the condition. 
PREVENTION:  Phobia prevention that involves educating people with this illness, their loved ones, and other involved individuals like children&amp;#39;s teachers have been found to be effective in preventing phobias from ever occurring. How can people cope with phobias? Ways that individuals with a phobia can work toward overcoming their fears include talking about their phobia, refraining from avoiding situations they find stressful, imagining themselves facing their fears (visualization), and making positive statements to themselves like, "I will be OK." In fact, when self-help methods are combined with brief psychotherapy, phobia sufferers may achieve significant improvement in symptoms. Where can people get information and help for phobias? American Academy of Child and Adolescent Psychiatry
 http://www.aacap.org American Counseling Association
 http://www.counseling.org American Psychiatric Association
 http://www.psych.org American Psychological Association
 http://helping.apa.org Anxiety and Depression Association of America
 http://www.adaa.org/ Freedom From Fear
 http://www.freedomfromfear.org National Association of Social Workers
 http://www.naswdc.org National Mental Health Association
 http://www.nmha.org National Panic/Anxiety Disorder News, Inc.
 http://www.npadnews.com What research is being done on phobias? Research studies are focused upon how well phobias respond to various treatments over the long term, as well as how age-related changes in thinking ability (cognition) may interact with anxiety. The use of herbal and other
 dietary supplements in the treatment of phobias is being explored, as well.
</first>
</file1>