<file1>
<first>Acne (Pimples)
What is acne? Acne (
 acne vulgaris , common
 acne ) is a disease of the hair follicles of the face, chest, and back that affects almost all teenagers during
 puberty -- the only exception being members of a few primitive Neolithic tribes living in isolation. It is not caused by bacteria, although bacteria play a role in its development. It is not unusual for some women to develop
 acne in their mid- to late-20s. Acne appears on the skin as occluded pores ("
 comedones "), also known as blackheads or whiteheads, tender red
 bumps also known as
 pimples or zits, pustules (bumps containing pus), and occasionally as cysts (the deep pimples and
 boils of
 cystic acne ). One can do a lot to treat acne using products available at a drugstore or cosmetic counter that do not require a prescription. However, for tougher cases of acne, one should consult a physician for treatment options. 
CAUSES:  No one factor causes acne. Acne occurs when sebaceous (oil) glands attached to the hair follicles are stimulated at the time of puberty or due to other hormonal changes. Sebum (oil) is a natural substance that lubricates and protects the skin. Associated with increased oil production is a change in the manner in which the skin cells mature, predisposing them to plug the follicular pore. The plug can appear as a
 whitehead if it is covered by a thin layer of skin, or if exposed to the air, the darker exposed portion of the plug is called a "
 blackhead ." The plugged
 hair follicle gradually enlarges, producing a bump. As the follicle enlarges, the wall may rupture, allowing irritating substances and normal skin bacteria access into the deeper layers of the skin, ultimately producing inflammation. Inflammation near the skin&amp;#39;s surface produces a
 pustule ; deeper inflammation results in a papule (
 pimple ); if the inflammation is deeper still, it forms a
 cyst . Here are some factors that don&amp;#39;t usually play a role in acne: Food : Parents often tell
 teens to avoid pizza, greasy and fried foods, and junk food. While these foods may not be good for overall health, they don&amp;#39;t play an important causal role in acne. Although some recent studies have implicated a high-carbohydrate
 diet , milk, and pure
 chocolate in aggravating acne, these findings are far from established. Dirt : Blackheads are oxidized oil, not dirt. Sweat does not cause acne and is produced by entirely separate glands in the skin. On the other hand, excessive washing can dry and irritate the skin. Stress : Some people get so upset by their pimples that they pick at them and make them last longer.
 Stress , however, does not play much of a
 direct role in causing acne. In occasional patients, the following may be contributing factors: Heredity : If one of your parents had severe acne, it is likely that your acne will be more difficult to control. Pressure : In some patients, pressure from helmets, chin straps, collars, suspenders, and the like can aggravate acne. Drugs : Some medications may cause or worsen acne, such as those containing iodides, bromides, or oral or injected steroids (either the medically prescribed
 prednisone [
 Deltasone , Orasone, Prednicen-M,
 Liquid Pred ] or the steroids that bodybuilders or athletes sometimes take). Other
 drugs that can cause or aggravate acne are anticonvulsant medications and
 lithium (Eskalith,
 Lithobid ). Most cases of acne, however, are not drug related. Occupations : In some jobs, exposure to industrial products like cutting oils may produce acne. Cosmetics : Some
 cosmetics and skin care products are pore clogging ("comedogenic"). Of the many available brands of skin care products, it is important to read the list of ingredients and choose those which have water listed first or second if one is concerned about acne. These "water-based" products are usually best for those with acne. 
SYMPTOMS:  Rosacea : This condition is characterized by pimples but not comedones and occurs in the middle third of the face, along with redness, flushing, and superficial blood vessels. It generally affects people in their 30s and 40s and older. Pseudofolliculitis: This is sometimes called "
 razor bumps " or "razor
 rash ." When cut too close to the skin, growing hairs twist into the skin and produce tender bumps. This is a mechanical problem, and treatment involves shaving less (growing a beard, laser
 hair removal ). Pseudofolliculitis can, of course, occur in patients who have acne, too. Folliculitis : Pimples can occur on other parts of the body, such as the abdomen, buttocks, or legs. These represent not acne but inflamed follicles. If these don&amp;#39;t go away on their own, doctors can prescribe oral or external antibiotics, generally not the same ones used for acne. Gram-negative
 folliculitis : Some patients who have been treated with oral antibiotics for long periods of time develop pustules filled with bacteria that are resistant to the antibiotics that were previously used. Bacterial culture tests can identify these germs, leading the doctor to prescribe different antibiotics or other forms of treatment. When should someone start acne treatment? Since everyone gets acne at some time, the right time to treat it is when it becomes bothersome or when the potential for scarring develops. This can be when severe acne flares suddenly, for mild acne that just won&amp;#39;t go away, or even when a single pimple decides to show up the week before one&amp;#39;s prom or wedding. What can people do to get rid of their acne? Moderation and regularity are good things, but not everyone can
 sleep eight hours, eat three healthy meals per day, and drink plenty of water a day. Probably the most useful lifestyle changes one can make is to
 never to pick or squeeze pimples. Playing with or popping pimples, no matter how careful and clean one is, nearly always makes bumps stay redder and bumpier longer. People often refer to redness as "scarring," but fortunately, it usually isn&amp;#39;t permanent. It&amp;#39;s just a mark that takes months to fade if left entirely alone. Occasional visits to an esthetician who is an expert at safely removing blackheads during a facial can be beneficial. Despite what one might read in popular style and fashion magazines, there is no magic product or regimen that is right for every person and situation. Mild cleansers : Washing once or twice a day with a mild cleansing bar or liquid (for example, Dove, Neutrogena, Basis, Purpose, and Cetaphil are all inexpensive and popular) will keep the skin clean and minimize sensitivity and irritation. Exfoliating cleansers and masks : A variety of mild scrubs, exfoliants, and masks can be used. These products may contain salicylic acid in a concentration that makes it a very mild peeling agent. These products remove the outer layer of the skin and thus open pores. Products containing glycolic or alpha hydroxy acids are also gentle skin exfoliants. Retinol : Not to be confused with the prescription medication Retin-A, this derivative of
 vitamin A can help promote skin peeling. Antibacterial cleansers : The most popular ingredient in
 over-the-counter antibacterial cleansers is
 benzoyl peroxide . Topical (external) applications : Antibacterial cleansers come in the form of gels, creams, and lotions that are applied to the affected area. The active ingredients that kill surface bacteria include benzoyl peroxide, sulfur, and resorcinol. Some brands promoted on the Internet and cable TV (such as ProActiv) are much more costly than identical and sometimes more potent products one can buy in the drugstore. Benzoyl peroxide causes red and scaly skin irritation in a small number of people, which goes away as soon as one stops using the product. Keep in mind that benzoyl peroxide is a bleach, so do not let products containing benzoyl peroxide come into contact with fabrics, leaving unsightly white spots on colored clothes, shirts, towels, and carpets. One cannot stop oil glands from producing oil. Even
 isotretinoin (Accutane, see below) only slows down oil glands for a while; they resume normal activity later. It is possible to get rid of oil on the surface of the skin and reduce the appearance of shine. Use a gentle astringent/toner to wipe away oil. (There are many brands available in pharmacies, as well as from manufacturers of cosmetic lines.) Products containing glycolic acid or one of the other alpha hydroxy acids are also helpful in clearing the skin by causing the superficial layer of the skin to peel (
 exfoliate ). Masks containing sulfur and other ingredients draw out facial oil. Antibacterial pads containing benzoyl peroxide have the additional benefit of helping to wipe away oil. What are other things you can do for acne? Are there any home remedies for acne? Cosmetics : Don&amp;#39;t be afraid to hide blemishes with flesh-tinted cover-ups or even foundation, as long as it is water-based (which makes it noncomedogenic). There are many quality products available. Facials : While not absolutely essential, steaming and "deep-cleaning" pores is useful, both alone and in addition to medical treatment, especially for people with "whiteheads" or "blackheads."
 Having these pores unclogged by a professional also reduces the temptation to do it oneself . Pore strips : Pharmacies now carry, under a variety of brand names, strips which one applies to the nose, forehead, chin, etc., to "pull out" oil from pores. These are, in effect, a do-it-yourself facial. They are inexpensive, safe, and work reasonably well if used properly. Toothpaste : One popular home remedy is to put
 toothpaste on zits. There is no medical basis for this. The same applies to vinegar. How does a doctor
treatacne? Is it possible to remove acne scars? It&amp;#39;s best to consult a primary care physician or dermatologist if an individual is unable to adequately control his or her acne. The goal of treatment should be the prevention of scarring (not a flawless complexion) so that after the condition spontaneously resolves there is no lasting sign of the affliction. Here are some of the options available: Topical (externally applied) antibiotics and antibacterials : These include
 erythromycin (E-Mycin,
 Eryc ,
 Ery-Tab ,
 PCE , Pediazole, Ilosone),
 clindamycin (
 BenzaClin ,
 Duac ), sulfacetamide (
 Klaron ), azelaic acid (
 Azelex or
 Finacea ), and
 dapsone (Aczone). Retinoids : Retin-A (
 tretinoin ) has been in use for years, and preparations have become milder and gentler while still maintaining its effectiveness. Newer retinoids include
 adapalene (
 Differin ) and
 tazarotene (
 Tazorac ). These medications are especially helpful for unclogging pores. Side effects may include irritation and a mild increase in sensitivity to the sun. Adapalene 0.1% is now available without a prescription. With proper
 sun protection , however, they can be used even during sunny periods. The combination medication known as Epiduo gel -- which contains the retinoid, adapalene, along with the antibacterial, benzoyl peroxide -- is applied once a day. Oral antibiotics : Doctors may start treatment with
 tetracycline (Sumycin) or one of the related "cyclines," such as
 doxycycline (
 Vibramycin ,
 Oracea ,
 Adoxa ,
 Atridox , and others) and
 minocycline (
 Dynacin ,
 Minocin ). Other oral antibiotics that are useful for treating acne are
 cefadroxil (Duricef),
 amoxicillin (
 Amoxil , DisperMox,
 Trimox ), and the sulfa drugs.
 Problems with these drugs can include
 allergic reactions (especially sulfa), gastrointestinal upset, and increased sun sensitivity. Doxycycline, in particular, is generally safe but can sometime cause
 esophagitis (irritation of the
 esophagus , producing discomfort when swallowing) and an increased tendency to
 sunburn . Despite the concern that the long-term use of tetracycline antibiotics for acne might "weaken the immune system" or induce bacterial resistance, these concerns seem to be unwarranted. Oral contraceptives :
 Oral contraceptives (
 birth control pills ), which are low in estrogen to promote safety, have little effect on acne one way or the other. Some
 contraceptive pills have been shown to have modest effectiveness in treating acne. Those that have been U.S. FDA approved for treating acne are Estrostep, Ortho Tri-Cyclen, and Yaz. Most dermatologists work together with primary care physicians or gynecologists when recommending these medications. Spironolactone (Aldactone) : This drug blocks
 androgen (hormone) receptors. It can cause breast tenderness, menstrual irregularities, and increased potassium levels in the bloodstream. It can help some women with resistant acne, however, and is generally well-tolerated in the young women who need it. Cortisone injections : To make large pimples and cysts flatten out fast, doctors inject them with a form of cortisone. Isotretinoin : Accutane was the original brand name; there are now several generic versions in common use, including Sotret,
 Claravis , and
 Amnesteem . Isotretinoin is an excellent treatment for severe, scarring, persistent acne and has been used on millions of patients since it was introduced in Europe in 1971 and in the U.S. in 1982. It should be used for people with severe acne, chiefly of the cystic variety, that has been unresponsive to conventional therapies like those listed above. If taken in sufficient dosage, it should eliminate the need to continue the use of prescription drugs in most patients. The drug has many potential serious side effects and requires a number of unique controls before it is prescribed. This means that isotretinoin is not a good choice for people whose acne is not that severe but who are frustrated and want "something that will knock acne out once and for all." In order to use the drug, the prescribing physician, the patient, and the supplying pharmacy must be enrolled in the online "iPLEDGE PROGRAM." Used properly, isotretinoin is safe and produces few side effects beyond dry lips and occasional muscle aches. This drug is prescribed for five to six months at a dosage that has a high likelihood of preventing the return of acne. Fasting blood tests are monitored monthly to check
 liver function and the level of
 triglycerides , substances related to
 cholesterol , which often rise a bit during treatment but rarely to the point at which treatment has to be modified or stopped. Even though isotretinoin does not remain in the body after therapy is stopped, improvement is often long-lasting. It is safe to take two or three courses of the drug if unresponsive acne makes a comeback. It is, however, best to wait at least several months and to try other methods before using isotretinoin again. Isotretinoin has a high risk of inducing
 birth defects if taken by
 pregnant women. Women of childbearing age who take isotretinoin need two negative
 pregnancy tests (blood or urine) before starting the drug, monthly tests while they take it, and another after they are done. Those who are sexually active must use two forms of
 contraception , one of which is usually the oral contraceptive pill. Isotretinoin leaves the body completely when treatment is done; women must be sure to avoid
 pregnancy for one month after therapy is stopped. There is, however, no risk to childbearing after that time. Other concerns include
 inflammatory bowel disease and the risk of
 depression and
 suicide in patients taking isotretinoin. Recent evidence seems to indicate that these problems are exceedingly rare. Government oversight has resulted in a highly publicized and very burdensome national registration system for those taking the drug. This has reinforced concerns in many patients and their families have that isotretinoin is dangerous. In fact, large-scale studies so far have shown no convincing evidence of increased risk for those taking isotretinoin compared with the general population. It is important for those taking this drug to report changes in mood or bowel habits (or any other symptoms) to their doctors. Even patients who are being treated for
 depression are not barred from taking isotretinoin, whose striking success often improves the mood and outlook of patients with severe disease. Light treatments : Recent years have brought reports of success in treating acne using special lights and similar devices, alone or in conjunction with photosensitizing dyes. It appears that these treatments are safe and can be effective, but it is not clear that their success is lasting. At this point, laser treatment of acne is best thought of as an adjunct to conventional therapy, rather than as a substitute. Chemical peels : Whether the superficial peels (like glycolic acid) performed by estheticians or deeper ones performed in the doctor&amp;#39;s office, chemical peels are of modest, supportive benefit only, and in general, they do not substitute for regular therapy. Treatment of acne scars : For those patients whose acne has gone away but left them with permanent scarring, several options are available. These include surgical procedures to elevate deep,
 depressed acne
 scars and
 laser resurfacing to smooth out shallow acne scars. Newer forms of laser resurfacing ("fractional resurfacing") are less invasive and heal faster than older methods, although results are less complete and the procedures may need to be repeated three or more times. These treatments can help, but they are never completely successful at eliminating acne scars. What is a good basic skin regimen? These are all good basic skin regimens that may help with the acne battle: How would you summarize current-day acne treatment? Treating acne requires patience and perseverance. Any of the treatments listed above may take two or three months to start working (even isotretinoin). Unless there are side effects such as excessive dryness or
 allergy , it is important to give each regimen or drug enough time to work before giving up on it and moving on to other methods. Using modern methods, doctors can help clear up the skin of just about everyone. Just hang in there. And don&amp;#39;t pick. Please.</first>
</file1>