<file1>
<first>Plastic Surgery (Cosmetic Surgery and Procedures)
Introduction Fighting the effects of aging on the outside; your guide to the risks of cosmetic surgical and non-surgical procedures Trying to fight the effects of
 aging ? Below is a basic guide to the risks involved in both surgical and
 non-surgical cosmetic procedures . For more information on each procedure, click on the highlighted links of the procedure. Cosmetic Procedures: Surgical Breast Augmentation: Breasts are enlarged by placing an implant behind each breast. implants can rupture, leak, and deflate infection hardening of
 scar tissue around implant, causing breast firmness,
 pain , distorted shape, or implant movement bleeding pain nipples may get more or less sensitive numbness near incision blood collection around implant/incision calcium deposits around implant harder to find
 breast lumps and to see breast changes on a
 mammogram in rare instances, implants can cause anaplastic large cell
 lymphoma (ALCL) - a rare
 cancer of the immune system Breast Lift - Extra skin is removed from the breast to raise and reshape breast. scarring skin loss infection loss of feeling in nipples or breast nipples put in the wrong place breasts not symmetrical Breast Reduction - Fat, tissue, and skin is removed from breast. Eyelid Surgery: Extra fat, skin, and muscle in the upper and/or lower
 eyelid is removed to correct "droopy" eyelids. blurred or
 double vision infection bleeding under the skin swelling dry eyes whiteheads can't close eye completely pulling of lower lids blindness Facelift: Extra fat is removed, muscles are tightened, and skin is rewrapped around the face and neck to improve sagging facial skin, jowls, and loose neck skin. infection bleeding under skin scarring irregular earlobes nerve damage causing numbness or inability to move your face hair loss skin damage Facial Implant: infection feeling of tightness or scarring around implant shifting of implant infection feeling of tightness or scarring around implant shifting of implant Forehead Lift: Extra skin and muscles that cause
 wrinkles are removed, eyebrows are lifted, and forehead skin is tightened. infection scarring bleeding under skin eye dryness or irritation impaired eyelid function loss of feeling in eyelid skin injury to facial nerve causing loss of motion or muscle
 weakness Lip Augmentation: Material is injected or implanted into the lips to create fuller lips and reduce
 wrinkles around the mouth. infection bleeding lip asymmetry lumping scarring Liposuction: Excess fat from a targeted area is removed with a vacuum to shape the body. baggy skin skin may change color and fall off fluid retention toxic
 shock infection that requires antibiotics or additional surgery burning fat clots in the
 lungs pain damage to organs if punctured numbness at the surgery site heart problems kidney problems disability death Nose Surgery: Nose is reshaped by resculpting the bone and cartilage in the nose. infection bursting blood vessels red spots bleeding under the skin scarring Tummy Tuck: Extra fat and skin in the abdomen is removed, and muscles are tightened to flatten tummy. blood clots infection bleeding scarring fluid accumulation under the skin
 Cosmetic Procedures: Non-Surgical Botox Injection: Botox is injected into a facial muscle to paralyze it, so lines don't form when a person frowns or squints. face pain muscle weakness flu -like symptoms headaches loss of facial expression droopy eyelids asymmetric smile drooling Collagen/fat Injection: Collagen from a cow or fat from your thigh or abdomen is injected into facial
 wrinkles , pits, or
 scars . trigger an autoimmune disease contour problems hives rash swelling flu-like symptoms Dermabrasion: A small, spinning wheel or brush with a roughened surface removes the upper layers of facial skin. A new layer of skin appears during healing, giving the face a smoother appearance. Used to treat facial scars, heavy wrinkles, and problems like
 rosacea . abnormal color changes whiteheads infection allergic reaction fever blisters cold sores thickened skin Hyaluronic acid injection: This gel is injected into your 
face to smooth lines, wrinkles, and scars on the skin. swelling infection redness tenderness acne lumps tissue hardening risks unknown if used in combination with collagen Laser hair removal: Laser light is passed over the skin to remove hair. hair regrowth scarring change in skin color Laser skin resurfacing: Laser light is used to remove wrinkles, lines,
 age spots , scars,
 moles , tattoos, and
 warts from the surface of the skin. burns scarring change in skin color infection herpes flare-up (
 fever , facial pain, and flu-like symptoms) Sclerotherapy : A solution is injected into spider and varicose leg veins (small purple and red blood vessels) to remove the veins. blood clots color changes in the skin vein removal may not be permanent scarring Chemical Peel: A solution is put onto the face (or parts of the face) that causes the skin to blister and peel off. It is replaced with new skin. whiteheads Infection raised scarring allergic reaction cold sores color changes or blotchiness heart problems Tooth Whiteners (peroxide agents): Depending on the product, either you or the dentist applies peroxide using strips; a mouth guard with gel; or a tray inside your mouth around your
 teeth If not customized for you by a dentist or dental hygienist, there may be unknown ingredients and unknown results
</first>
</file1>