<file1>
<first>Menstrual Cramps and Premenstrual Syndrome (PMS) Medication Guide

ABOUT: Menstrual cramps that occur in the absence of a known abnormality or cause are medically referred to as primary
 dysmenorrhea . Non-drug treatments for
 menstrual cramps include adequate rest and
 sleep , regular
 exercise (especially
 walking ), and
 smoking cessation . Menstrual cramps are not the same as the symptoms experienced due to
 premenstrual syndrome (
 PMS ), although the symptoms of both disorders can sometimes be experienced together. Premenstrual syndrome (
 PMS ) is a combination of emotional, physical, psychological, and mood disturbances that occur after a woman's
 ovulation ; and usually end with the onset of her menstrual flow. For moderate menstrual cramps, the 
nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
 drugs (
 NSAIDs , such as
 ibuprofen [
 Advil ,
 Motrin ,
 Nuprin , etc.] or
 naproxen [
 Aleve ,
 Anaprox ,
 Naprosyn ,
 Naprelan ]) are often helpful. The NSAIDs are more effective than
 aspirin in inhibiting the production and action of the prostaglandins that cause menstrual cramps.
 What are menstrual cramps? Menstrual cramps are abdominal and pelvic pains experienced by a woman around the time of her
 menstrual period . Menstrual cramps usually start shortly before the menstrual period, peak within 24 hours after their onset, and subside after a day or two. Menstrual cramps can range from mild to severe. Mild menstrual cramps may be barely noticeable, short-lived, and are sometimes felt only as a sense of mild pressure in the abdomen and pelvis. Severe menstrual cramps can be so painful that they interfere with a woman&amp;#39;s regular activities for several days. The discomfort can extend to the lower back or legs. Menstrual cramps are not the same as the symptoms experienced due to
 premenstrual syndrome (PMS), although the symptoms of both disorders can sometimes be experienced together. Many women suffer from both PMS and menstrual cramps. Medical research of menstrual cramps has shown that they are often worse in women who began menstruating early and who have long menstrual periods associated with heavy menstrual flow.
 Smoking and a family history of severe menstrual cramps are also associated with severe dysmenorrhea.
 What is the treatment for common menstrual cramps (primary dysmenorrhea)? Treatment options vary and each woman needs to find the treatment that works best for her. Non-drug measures that may help include adequate rest and
 sleep , regular
 exercise (especially walking), and
 smoking cessation. Some women find that abdominal
 massage ,
 yoga , or orgasmic sexual activity can help. A heating pad applied to the abdominal area may also relieve the
 pain . For mild menstrual cramps, over-the-counter (OTC) aspirin and
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ), or acetaminophen plus a diuretic (such as Diurex MPR, Midol, Pamprin, Premesyn) may help. However, aspirin has a limited effect in curbing the production of prostaglandin and is only useful for mild cramps. For moderate menstrual cramps, the nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) can be helpful. The NSAIDs are more effective than aspirin in inhibiting the production and action of the prostaglandins. NSAIDs that are available OTC are: ibuprofen (Advil, Midol IB, Motrin, Nuprin, and others); naproxen sodium (Aleve, Anaprox); and ketoprofen (Actron, Orudis KT). For optimal control of menstrual cramps, a woman should start taking a NSAID before the onset of her
 pain becomes difficult to control. This might mean starting medication 1 to 2 days before the onset of her period and continuing the medication for the first 1 to 2 days of her period. The best results are obtained by taking one of the NSAIDs on a regular schedule rather than on an as needed basis. Therefore, ibuprofen should be taken every 4-6 hours, ketoprofen every 4-8 hours, and naproxen every 8-12 hours for the first few days of the menstrual flow. Prescription NSAIDs available for the treatment of menstrual cramps include
 mefenamic acid (
 Ponstel ).
 What is premenstrual syndrome (PMS)? Premenstrual syndrome (PMS) is a combination of emotional, physical, psychological, and mood disturbances that occur after a woman&amp;#39;s ovulation and normally end with the onset of her menstrual flow. PMS remains a puzzle because of the wide-ranging symptoms and the difficulty in making a firm diagnosis. Several theories have been advanced to explain the cause of PMS. None of these theories has been proven and specific treatments for PMS largely lack a solid scientific basis. Most evidence suggests that PMS results from alterations in or interactions among the levels of sex hormones and brain chemical messengers known as neurotransmitters. 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of PMS can sometimes be as challenging as diagnosing the condition. Some measures lack a solid scientific basis but seem to help some women. Other treatments with a sound scientific basis may not help all patients. General measures include: Exercise: Aerobic exercise for 30 minutes 3-5 times a week improves general health and helps relieve nervous tension and
 anxiety . Exercise also improves
 cardiovascular fitness and muscle tone, decreases weight and fluid retention, and improves self-esteem. Emotional support from family and friends. Stress reduction and stress management : Learning relaxation techniques, and developing coping mechanisms to reduce 
 stress . Dietary changes: Reduce salt and refined
 sugar intake (too much salt and refined
 sugar  exacerbates fluid retention). Avoid caffeine , as this may increase irritability Decrease the intake of animal fats . Avoid cigarettes and alcohol. Research studies have linked a deficiency of calcium and magnesium to PMS; therefore, it may be beneficial for woman to try
 supplements of these nutrients at recommended dosages. Some women have reported relief of symptoms with these
 supplements . It is always important to follow recommended guidelines when taking vitamin supplements, since taking excess doses of some supplements may be harmful.
 
TREATMENT:  Medications used to treat the different
 symptoms of PMS include taking: Diuretics, which are medications that increase urine production, thereby eliminating excess fluid and relieving
 weight gain ,
 bloating , and swelling. Ammonium chloride,
 caffeine , and pamabrom are mild diuretics that are ingredients in nonprescription OTC products such as Diurex PMS, Lurline PMS, Midol PMS, Pamprin Multisymptom, and Premesyn PMS.
 Spironolactone (
 Aldactone ) is a prescription diuretic that has been used to treat premenstrual swelling of the hands,
 feet , and/or face. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications (NSAIDs) that are commonly used for menstrual cramps,
 headaches , and pelvic discomfort. NSAIDs are available as both prescription and non-prescription products. Examples of NSAIDs include ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin), naproxen (Aleve, Anaprox), ketoprofen (Orudis), and mefenamic acid (Ponstel). Oral
 contraceptive pills (OCPs) that are sometimes prescribed by doctors to decrease fluctuations in ovarian hormone levels. While older studies failed to provide evidence that OCPs can consistently provide relief for symptoms of PMS, the newer low-dose 
 birth control pills , with their improved hormonal formulations, seem to be more beneficial. Ovarian suppressors such as
 danazol (
 Danocrine ) have been prescribed by doctors to suppress ovarian hormone production. Danocrine cannot be used over long periods because of side effects. Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogs, which cause the complete suppression of ovarian function, and have been found to be helpful in treating some women with PMS. These GnRH analogs are not prescribed long term (more than 6 months) because of their adverse effects on
 bone density and an increased risk of bone thinning (
 osteoporosis ). Antidepressants  which are prescribed by doctors to treat the mood disturbances related to PMS. Antidepressants appear to work by increasing brain chemical (
 serotonin and others) levels that are affected by the ovarian hormones. Fluoxetine (
 Prozac ) and
 paroxetine (
 Paxil ). These are examples of
 antidepressant medications that have been found to be effective in treating the mood changes associated with PMS.
 What are some guidelines for the safe use of OTC products for menstrual cramps and PMS?</first>
</file1>