<file1>
<first>Porphyria
Porphyria facts* *
ABOUT: medically edited by William C. Shiel Jr., MD, FACP, FACR Porphyria is a group of diseases that are due to the deficiency of one of the enzymes needed to make an important substance in the body called heme. Porphyrias are often classified as acute or cutaneous. Acute types of porphyria affect the nervous system, whereas cutaneous types mainly affect the skin. Most porphyrias are inherited disorders. People with cutaneous forms of porphyria develop
 blisters ,
 itching , and swelling of their skin when it is exposed to sunlight. Those with acute forms of porphyria develop numbness, tingling,
 paralysis , cramping,
 vomiting ,
 constipation , personality changes or mental disorders, and/or
 pain in the abdomen, chest, limbs, or back. Doctors diagnose porphyria using blood, urine, and stool tests. Treatment may involve avoiding triggers, receiving heme through a vein, taking medicines to relieve symptoms, or having blood drawn to reduce iron in the body. People who have severe attacks may need to be hospitalized. What is porphyria? Porphyria is a term that refers to a group of disorders -- the porphyrias -- that affect the nervous system or skin, or both. Each type of porphyria is due to the deficiency of one of the enzymes needed to make a substance in the body called heme. Enzymes are proteins that help chemical reactions happen in the body. Making heme involves a series of eight different enzymes, each acting in turn. Heme is a red pigment composed of iron linked to a chemical called protoporphyrin. Heme has important functions in the body. The largest amounts of heme are in the blood and bone marrow in the form of
 hemoglobin within
 red blood cells . Hemoglobin gives blood its red color and carries oxygen from the
 lungs to all parts of the body. In the
 liver , heme is a component of proteins that have many functions, including breaking down hormones,
 drugs , and other chemicals and generating high-energy compounds that keep liver cells alive and functioning normally. The body makes heme mainly in the bone marrow and the liver. The process of making heme is called the heme biosynthetic pathway. Each step of the process is controlled by one of eight enzymes. If any one of the enzymes is deficient, the process is disrupted. As a result, porphyrin or its precursors - chemicals formed at earlier steps of the process -- may build up in body tissues and cause illness.
 What are the types of porphyria? The table below lists each type of porphyria and the deficient enzyme responsible for the disorder. Porphyrias are often classified as acute or cutaneous. Acute types of porphyria affect the nervous system, whereas cutaneous types mainly affect the skin. Two forms of porphyria - hereditary coproporphyria and variegate porphyria -- may be either acute or cutaneous, or both. The most common type of porphyria overall is porphyria cutanea tarda. In the United States, acute intermittent porphyria is the most common acute porphyria. 
CAUSES:  Most porphyrias are inherited disorders, meaning they are caused by abnormalities in genes passed from parents to children. Scientists have identified the genes for all eight enzymes in the heme pathway. Some forms of porphyria result from inheriting an abnormal gene from one parent. Other forms are due to inheriting two abnormal genes - one from each parent. The risk that members of an affected family will have the disease or transmit it to their children depends on the type of porphyria. One type of porphyria -- porphyria cutanea tarda -- is most often an acquired disorder. It occurs when factors other than genes cause an enzyme deficiency in the liver. Porphyria can be triggered by: Drugs such as
 barbiturates , tranquilizers,
 birth control pills , and sedatives Chemicals Fasting Smoking Drinking alcohol, especially heavy drinking Infections Excess iron in the body Emotional and physical
 stress Menstrual hormones Exposure to the sun
 
SYMPTOMS:  People with cutaneous forms of porphyria develop
 blisters ,
 itching , and swelling of their skin when it is exposed to sunlight. Symptoms of acute forms of porphyria include
 pain in the abdomen, chest, limbs, or back; numbness, tingling, paralysis, or cramping;
 vomiting ;
 constipation ; and personality changes or mental disorders. Acute attacks of porphyria can develop over hours or days and last for days or weeks. Symptoms can vary widely in severity. Some people with gene mutations that can cause porphyria have no signs or symptoms of the disorder. These people are said to have latent porphyria. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Doctors diagnose porphyria using blood, urine, and stool tests. Interpreting test results can be complex, and initial tests may be followed by further testing to confirm the diagnosis. Diagnosis may be delayed because the symptoms of porphyria are similar to symptoms of other disorders. How is porphyria treated? Each type of porphyria is treated differently. Treatment may involve avoiding triggers, receiving heme through a vein, taking medicines to relieve symptoms, or having blood drawn to reduce iron in the body. People who have severe attacks may need to be hospitalized.
</first>
</file1>