<file1>
<first>Toothache
What is a toothache? A
 toothache is
 pain that occurs in or around a tooth. The
 pain originates from within a tooth or the surrounding gum and bone structures. One usually feels toothache pain as a constant or intermittent ache that does not go away. Temperature changes, such as exposure to cold
 drinks or pressure on the tooth while chewing, can stimulate a toothache. In other instances,
 tooth pain can arise spontaneously without any stimulation.
 Odontalgia is another name for a toothache. It&amp;#39;s hard to ignore an aching tooth while eating or going about one&amp;#39;s day. Persistent pain urges us to find out how to get rid of a toothache. While bothersome, it is a way for the painful tooth or area to signal that one should seek some attention and care from a dentist before things get worse. 
CAUSES:  Injury or
 trauma to the tooth or area usually cause toothaches. Injury is commonly a result of
 tooth decay (or cavity). People usually feel
 cavities when they get larger and deeper into the layers of tooth structure. Enamel is the hard, outer layer of tooth, and dentin is the softer layer beneath the enamel. Dentin is the tooth&amp;#39;s sensitive layer with tiny microscopic tubes that originate from the very center of the tooth. The pulp chamber (the center of the tooth) contains the pulp. The pulp is comprised of blood vessels and nerves. If decay gets past enamel into the dentin, the cavity can sometimes cause discomfort. A deeper cavity that approaches the center of the tooth will likely cause pain since there is more damage to the tooth and there is less tooth structure to insulate and protect the pulp. Localized infection between the gum and tooth (periodontal
 abscess ) can cause toothache. A traumatic physical blow to a tooth can induce a sore tooth, as well. Other causes of toothache include the following: 
SYMPTOMS:  Signs and symptoms that can might indicate a tooth problem are pain with biting or chewing, teeth hypersensitivity to changes in temperature, cheek or gums swelling near tooth, discharge or
 bleeding of gums , constant throbbing within a tooth. A toothache can present as a dull or sharp pain that may arise spontaneously on its own or by stimulation. Additional symptoms may include headache , neck pain , earache , fever , bad taste or odor in the mouth . 
DIAGNOSIS:  The dentist performs a series of diagnostic tests along with
 dental X-rays to determine the origin of a toothache. These tests try to mimic what may be causing the pain, such as cold stimuli, biting or chewing pressure, and finger pressure on the gums. The response to a cold stimuli test can help in determining whether a tooth is vital (nerve is intact within tooth) or suffering from pulpitis (inflammation of the pulp). Determining duration and acuity of pain from cold stimuli can help diagnose and determine treatment. Sometimes, the cause of a toothache may come from somewhere different from where pain is actually felt (called "referred pain"). For these situations, diagnostic tests performed by the dentist are particularly important in accurately detecting the problem.
 
TREATMENT:  Toothache treatment depends on the cause of the pain and how much damage is present. In general, the best way to stop a toothache is for the dentist to remove any present infection or decay and repair the damage to protect exposed, sensitive areas. For a shallow cavity on a tooth, a dentist removes the decay and seals the tooth with a filling. If the cavity is very deep and gets into the pulp, the dentist performs "
 root canal treatment" because the pulp has been exposed and infected with bacteria. This procedure essentially removes all the vital contents of the tooth (nerves and blood vessels) and seals the inner aspects of the tooth (root canal system) with an inert filling material. An
 abscessed tooth that has very localized infection usually needs root canal treatment with antibiotic therapy. If the infection has become widespread, one may need antibiotic therapy and additional steps to properly drain the infection. Dentists often prescribe pain medications to manage the pain. Sometimes extraction of the tooth may be the only option for treatment if the tooth or surrounding gum and bone are too damaged. For a periodontal abscess, a dentist performs a simple drainage procedure under local anesthesia. Additionally, a dentist thoroughly cleans the affected gum pocket to remove any tartar buildup and debris. Once cleaned, the pocket is irrigated with an antimicrobial rinse containing chlorhexidine. Sometimes, antibiotics are locally administered into the pocket to further aid in healing. Depending on the extent of the abscess, a dentist may prescribe oral antibiotics. Additionally, for the short-term, a dentist may prescribe chlorhexidine oral rinse as a mouthwash to aid in healing. The area should be kept clean with gentle tooth brushing and warm water rinses. A follow-up visit is recommended to make sure the infection has completely resolved and develop a plan to properly maintain the area. For tooth fractures or cracked tooth syndrome situations,
 dental crown placement is the usual treatment. A crown will replace missing tooth structure and/or it will help protect the weakened tooth from further breakdown and sensitivity.
 Are
home remedieseffective for a toothache? Generally, home remedies are only effective as a temporary measure to calm severe tooth pain and are not intended to cure the problem. How does one try to get instant relief without the aid of a dental professional? Oral pain medication will be a key step.
 Over-the-counter pain medicines such as
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ) or
 naproxen (
 Aleve ) are nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
 drugs and are best taken on a schedule to provide pain relief.
 Acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ) is an alternative painkiller. In some cases, alternating doses of ibuprofen and acetaminophen is effective. The essential oil, clove oil, is a toothache remedy that is actually an ingredient in some sedative dental filling materials. It is a natural home remedy that has a numbing effect and can provide instant relief. Clove oil (eugenol) can be found at the pharmacy. Small amounts of clove oil should be used to the affected area. Dilute a few drops in a teaspoon of olive oil to avoid burning the mouth tissue. Before application of the diluted clove oil, rinse the mouth thoroughly with warm salt water or warm water to clear any debris from the affected area. Then, place a small cotton ball soaked with a few drops of the diluted clove oil on the tooth or gum area. Allow a few minutes after application for the numbing effect to take place. Other products that contain benzocaine (including Orajel or Anbesol) can temporarily numb the affected tooth or gums and provide pain relief as well. If clove oil is not available, plain olive oil can also provide some relief by coating a painful area. To help a toothache until treatment can be found, one should avoid chewing on the affected tooth/area and minimize extreme temperatures of hot and cold. Keeping the area clean and free of food debris may help as well. Warm salt water or plain warm water rinses can help soothe the affected area and keep the mouth clean. If swelling of the surrounding gums or tissues is present, immediate treatment with a dentist or physician is advised to avoid the spread of infection. Home remedies may temporarily alleviate pain but do not to treat infection. Above all, proper diagnosis and timely treatment by a dentist is strongly advised to effectively treat a toothache.
 How is a toothache treated during pregnancy? Dentists can safely perform treatment during
 pregnancy as long as a few guidelines are followed. Generally, if dental work is required to treat a toothache, the recommended time for treatment is during the
 second trimester of pregnancy. However, if there is a risk of infection or severe pain, dental treatment may need to be performed at any point during a pregnancy. The obstetrician is consulted on what would be the safest option to avoid any possible complications during dental treatment. If a dental X-ray is needed, a lead apron is always used for every patient. For a
 pregnant patient, this is particularly important in protecting the unborn child. Careful consideration should be made to ensure that any medications that are used are safe during pregnancy. This applies to local anesthetics administered during dental treatment and antibiotics (such as
 amoxicillin [
 Amoxil ,
 Trimox ,
 Moxatag ,
 Larotid ]) taken before or after treatment. Over-the-counter drugs such as
 aspirin , ibuprofen, or naproxen are avoided as these are not considered safe during pregnancy. Acetaminophen is considered safe for
 pain management .
 What is the prognosis for a toothache? For the most part, the prognosis is good for a toothache. In this era of modern dental care, dentists can quickly identify the problem and treat it effectively. The outcome is best when toothache is treated as early as possible to avoid further damage or risk of spreading infection. 
PREVENTION:  Conscientious efforts to practice good oral hygiene go a long way in preventing dental problems. Toothbrushing with fluoride
 toothpaste and use of dental floss are essential to good dental care at home. Furthermore, regular maintenance visits with a dentist can serve to keep things in check. Small cavities can be found before turning into larger cavities or an abscessed tooth. Gum problems, including periodontal abscess, can be addressed before advancing to a more diseased state. To keep teeth strong, avoid the habit of chewing on ice or very hard foods that can cause tooth fractures. Using our teeth as a tool to open a bag of potato chips or cracking open a nutshell increase the chances of a tooth fracture as well. Minimize high
 sugar content foods or
 beverages to decrease the risk of dental decay. Be mindful of acidity in beverages as this can be a source of sensitivity and cavities for teeth.
</first>
</file1>