<file1>
<first>Postherpetic Neuralgia (PHN)
Postherpetic neuralgia (PHN) facts PHN is a painful complication that 
occurs after a
 shingles infection. PHN is caused by viral damage to nerve cells. PHN is diagnosed by the patient's history and physical exam. Treatment often 
requires more than one agent to reduce
 pain . PHN may last one to two months, but some 
patients have PHN for longer than a year. Older people and people with 
relatives who get
 shingles are at a higher risk for PHN. Complications of PHN 
may include severe
 pain , pain-medicine
 addiction , diminished lifestyle, and in a 
few patients,
 paralysis of the affected area. The prognosis of PHN ranges from 
good to poor, depending on the length of time the disease lingers and on the 
development of complications. PHN can be prevented in many people by a vaccine 
designed to prevent
 shingles (
 Zostavax ). What is postherpetic neuralgia (PHN)? Postherpetic neuralgia (also termed PHN) is a condition of recurring or persistent pain in an area of the body that has undergone an outbreak of
 herpes zoster virus (HZ), also known as the
 varicella zoster virus , commonly termed
 shingles . It usually begins after shingles lesions (
 blisters ) begin to crust over and heal but may occur in some patients who do not produce lesions. Some investigators suggest the pain has to be present for three months to be termed PHN. 
CAUSES:  Postherpetic neuralgia is thought to be 
caused by the damage or alteration of nerves that register pain, pressure, and 
other sensory nerves (for example, touch) that occur when the reactivated HZ
 viruses travel down nerves to the skin. This process first begins when the virus 
causes
 chickenpox in an individual; the viruses can infect various dorsal root 
ganglia (nerve cells) as the
 chickenpox subsides. These viruses then can be 
reactivated, usually decades later, and produce shingles lesions. The 
reactivation of HZ is thought to be due to a
 stress on the body from either another 
infection or a immunocompromised state (for example, some patients undergoing 
treatments for
 leukemia ) that allows the HZ to escape the dorsal root cells. PHN 
does not occur in everyone who gets shingles; about 9%-14% have symptoms after 
one 
month post-shingles and about 5% have PHN three months post-shingles.
 
SYMPTOMS:  The main symptom is pain. The pain can be severe (allodynia - pain due to a stimulus that does not usually provoke pain); patients describe the pain as burning, sharp, jabbing, deep, and aching. Often, the patient feels increased pain when any pressure, even clothing, touches the area. Some patients describe itchy skin and
 weakness or paralysis of the area. 
RISKS:  Age is a high risk factor for PHN; the older a person when he or she develops 
shingles, the more likely it is that the person will develop PHN. People over 60 
years of age have about a 60% 
chance while people 70 or older have about a 75% chance of developing PHN after 
getting shingles. Another risk factor is family; those people who have close 
relatives who developed PHN are at a higher risk than people with no family 
history of PHN. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The majority of patients who are diagnosed with PHN are done by follow-up of 
a shingles infection or by the patient's history of a recent shingles infection. 
The pain is located in the same nerve distribution (dermatome) area, usually 
on only one side of the person's body where the shingles lesions occurred.
 
TREATMENT:  Treatment is individualized for each patient; there is no treatment that is effective for all PHN patients, so clinicians often use two or more of the drug categories with examples listed below: Lidocaine skin patches ([
 Lidoderm ] small, bandage-like patches applied to painful areas) Capsaicin skin patches ([
 Capsagel ,
 Salonpas ] applied in a doctor&amp;#39;s office by trained staff) Opioids (
 tramadol [
 Ultram ],
 oxycodone [
 OxyContin ], morphine) Anticonvulsants (
 pregabalin [
 Lyrica ],
 gabapentin [
 Neurontin ]) have been shown to lessen the pain of PHN probably by stabilizing abnormal electrical activity in your nervous system. Antidepressants (
 venlafaxine [
 Effexor ],
 duloxetine [
 Cymbalta ]) are often prescribed in lower doses than for
 depression . Because some
 drugs (opioids) can be addictive and because some patients may need long-term treatments (over one year), consultation with a pain-management specialist may be advised. Some individuals claim tamanu oil rubbed into the affected may reduce the symptoms of PHN. One small study and a few case reports indicate that
 acupuncture can be helpful in relieving the pain of PHN. Infrequently, other methods are used. TENS (
 transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation ) devices are designed to interrupt the body&amp;#39;s pain sensations while
 nerve blocks (short-term chemical nerve sensation blockade) and nerve ablation (surgically cutting a nerve) are also used. Results vary but the methods often do not give lasting pain relief.
 How long does postherpetic neuralgia last? Only approximately 9%-15% of patients who get shingles develop PHN. For those few patients who develop PHN, the length of time that PHN lasts is variable; the majority of PHN patients have discomfort lasting one to two months. About one-third of PHN patients have symptoms that last about three months, and about one-fifth last a year or longer. 
COMPLCATIONS:  PHN itself is a complication of shingles. A serious complication of PHN is addiction to pain medications. Some patients may have an inability to live a normal lifestyle (unable to
 exercise ) because of constant pain, while others have
 sleep and activities limited or even prohibited by touching the affected area, including just having contact with their own clothing. Patients taking opioids may become very constipated. In a few cases of PHN, muscle weakness can be an additional complication. What is the prognosis for postherpetic neuralgia? For the majority of patients who develop PHN, the prognosis is good although they may have to take pain medications for about one to three months. For others, the prognosis is fair to poor if the pain is severe, lasts longer than three months, or markedly reduces their quality of life. PHN occasionally results in permanent nerve damage; however, the disease is not fatal. 
PREVENTION:  If shingles can be prevented, then PHN can be prevented. Fortunately, the vaccine Zostavax is about 70% effective in preventing shingles. The CDC recommends that everyone older than 60 years of age get the vaccine; in 2011, the FDA approved the vaccine for people aged 50 and above. The CDC states, "Zostavax should not be given to
 pregnant women, persons with a primary or acquired
 immunodeficiency , or to persons with a history of anaphylactic reaction to gelatin,
 neomycin , or any other component of the vaccine.
 Herpes zoster vaccine can be administered simultaneously with other indicated vaccines."
</first>
</file1>