<file1>
<first>Vaginal Pain Symptoms, Location, During Pregnancy

ABOUT: Vulvodynia (
 vaginal pain ) refers to
 pain in the area of the vulva and vaginal opening for which no cause can be identified. Vulvodynia is not related to sexually-transmitted diseases (
 STDs ). The exact cause of vulvodynia is not known. Symptoms include a burning, throbbing, or aching
 pain that can be localized to one area of the vulva or more widespread. Vaginal itching may be associated with vulvodynia. Vulvodynia can be treated with medications and/or self-care (home remedy) measures. No one treatment is effective for all women. Local anesthetics, local estrogen creams,
 antidepressants , and anticonvulsive
 drugs are examples of medical treatments for vulvodynia. Biofeedback, exercises, and
 nerve blocks may benefit other women. Vulvodynia is not associated with
 cancer or serious medical conditions, but it can be a source of long-term physical and emotional discomfort. What is vaginal pain (vulvodynia)? Vulvodynia refers to pain in the area of the vulva and vaginal opening. Vulvodynia is considered pain for which there is no known cause. It is different from pain that is located deep in the pelvis or internally in the vagina.
 This article focuses on pain in the vulvar region and at the opening (introitus) of the vagina. Deeper vaginal pain can also occur due to infections, tumors, and conditions that cause more generalized pain in the pelvic organs. Vaginal pain can be chronic and can last for years in some women. The degree of severity varies among women. It often occurs in the absence of physical signs or visible abnormalities. It can be severe and can interfere with sexual activity and cause
 painful intercourse (dyspareunia). However, there are a number of other causes of vaginal pain during or after sex.
 
SYMPTOMS:  The pain of vulvodynia can be debilitating and interfere with daily activities and sexual intercourse. It can make women feel a loss of control their bodies, causing profound emotional and physical discomfort. Symptoms of vulvodynia and vaginal pain may include: Burning or stinging pain in the vulva or vaginal opening Sharp, aching, or throbbing pain in the vagina or vulva Vaginal
 itching , sometimes with pain Pain that is constant or comes and goes Pain that occurs during sex or
 exercise Some women report pain that is localized to one side or one area of the vulva, while others have more generalized and wide-spread pain. Usually, no physical signs or changes occur in and around the vagina with vulvodynia; however, sometimes the skin may be inflamed. What if you have vaginal pain and are pregnant? Vaginal pain may occur during the
 third trimester of
 pregnancy due to an increase in pressure on the cervix. Women who experienced vulvodynia before
 becoming pregnant may continue to experience this symptom during pregnancy.
 
CAUSES:  It is unclear why some women develop vulvodynia. It is not thought to be related to sexually-transmitted diseases (
 STDs ), although some women with vulvodynia have had multiple STDs. Some theories suggest that vulvodynia may be related to damage or irritation of nerves, abnormal responses to irritation or inflammation, allergic reactions, muscle spasms , a history of sexual abuse, or frequent use of antibiotics. Familial or genetic factors also have been suggested to play a role in vulvodynia. Unfortunately, the exact cause has not been determined and most women have no known contributing factors. 
RISKS:  Who gets it? Since the cause is poorly understood, it is difficult to predict who is at risk for vulvodynia. It can affect women of all ages and races. It can begin as early as adolescence and can occur both before and after
 menopause . It may occur during the
 menstrual period or independent of the menstrual period.
 
CAUSES:  No specific tests confirm vulvodynia. Usually, vaginal pain and vulvodynia are diagnosed based upon the characteristic symptoms of the condition. However, since vulvar and vaginal infections, (for example, yeast infections,
 bacterial vaginosis , and
 vaginitis ) are associated with vaginal burning and
 itching , cultures or other diagnostic tests may be ordered to rule out vaginal infections. 
TREATMENT:  Can the condition be cured? Vulvodynia is a chronic condition (it may last for months to years) in some women; in others it may come and go. Vulvodynia and vaginal pain can be managed using medical treatments and self-care (home remedies). Not all treatments will be effective for every woman, and a woman may have to try different treatments to find the most effective option for her. Vulvodynia is not associated with
 cancer or with any serious medical diseases, but it may be a source of
 chronic pain and emotional discomfort for some women. What
medicationsand home therapies can relieve vaginal pain? Some of the medications that have been useful include: Topical estrogen creams Topical or local anesthetics Tricyclic antidepressants Anticonvulsants (anti-
 seizure medications are sometimes useful in managing
 chronic pain ) Other medical therapies for women with severe vulvodynia include: Injections of
 interferon or nerve blocks, in which medications are injected to reduce signaling from nerves in the affected areas Biofeedback training and pelvic floor exercises have been helpful for some women. Surgical removal of affected tissue can be of benefit in women with vulvodynia due to vulvar vestibulitis syndrome, a particular type of vulvodynia that is located at the area of the hymenal ring.
 
TREATMENT:  Home remedies and self-care measures for vulvodynia can bring relief for many women. Some self-care measures to relieve the pain of vulvodynia include:</first>
</file1>