<file1>
<first>16 Natural Remedies for Pregnancy Changes and Body Discomforts
Natural remedies for pregnancy changes and body discomforts facts* *
ABOUT: medically edited by:
 Melissa Conrad Stöppler, MD A number of body changes can occur during a healthy, normal
 pregnancy that may be surprising or at times uncomfortable. Colostrum is the first milk produced by the body. Some women notice colostrum in late pregnancy as a discharge from the nipples that begins in the
 third trimester . Backache and
 sciatica are common pregnancy complaints that occur due to pressure from the expanding uterus. Fatigue and
 sleep disturbances are a source of discomfort for many
 pregnant women . Other physical discomforts sometimes experienced by pregnant women include
 hemorrhoids , itching , constipation , heartburn , "
 morning sickness ," swelling, and urinary leakage. Fortunately, there are a number of self-care tips that can help alleviate these common sources of discomfort during pregnancy. Introduction to natural remedies for pregnancy changes and body discomforts Everyone expects pregnancy to bring an expanding waistline. But many women are surprised by the other body changes that pop up. Get the low-down on
 stretch marks ,
 weight gain ,
 heartburn and other "joys" of pregnancy. Find out what you can do to feel better. Body aches As your uterus expands, you may feel aches and pains in the back, abdomen, groin area, and thighs. Many women also have backaches and aching near the pelvic bone due the pressure of the baby&amp;#39;s head, increased weight, and loosening joints. Some pregnant women complain of pain that runs from the lower back, down the back of one leg, to the knee or foot. This is called sciatica (SYE-AT-ick-uh). It is thought to occur when the uterus puts pressure on the
 sciatic nerve . What might help: Lie down Rest Apply heat Call the doctor if the pain does not get better. Breast changes A woman&amp;#39;s breasts increase in size and fullness during pregnancy. As the due date approaches, hormone changes will cause your breasts to get even bigger to prepare for
 breastfeeding . Your breasts may feel full, heavy, or tender. In the
 third trimester , some pregnant women begin to leak colostrum (coh-LOSS-truhm) from their breasts. Colostrum is the first milk that your breasts produce for the baby. It is a thick, yellowish fluid containing antibodies that protect newborns from infection. What might help: Wear a maternity bra with good support. Put pads in your bra to absorb leakage. Tell your doctor if you feel a lump or have
 nipple changes or discharge (that is not colostrum) or skin changes. Constipation Many pregnant women complain of
 constipation . Signs of
 constipation include having hard, dry stools; fewer than three bowel movements per week; and painful bowel movements. Higher levels of hormones due to pregnancy slow down
 digestion and relax muscles in the bowels leaving many women constipated. Plus, the pressure of the expanding uterus on the bowels can contribute to
 constipation . What might help: Drink eight to 10 glasses of water daily. Don&amp;#39;t drink
 caffeine . Eat
 fiber -rich foods such as fresh or dried fruit, raw vegetables, and whole-grain cereals and breads. Try mild physical activity. Tell your doctor if constipation does not go away. Fatigue, sleep problems During your pregnancy, you might feel tired even after you&amp;#39;ve had a lot of
 sleep . Many women find they&amp;#39;re exhausted in the
 first trimester . Don&amp;#39;t worry, this is normal! This is your body&amp;#39;s way of telling you that you need more rest. In the
 second trimester ,
 tiredness is usually replaced with a feeling of well being and energy. But in the third trimester, exhaustion often sets in again. As you get larger, sleeping may become more difficult. The baby&amp;#39;s movements, bathroom runs, and an increase in the body&amp;#39;s metabolism might interrupt or disturb your
 sleep . Leg cramping can also interfere with a good night&amp;#39;s sleep. What might help: Lie on your left side. Use pillows for support such as behind your back, tucked between your knees, and under your tummy. Practice good sleep habits such as going to bed and getting up at the same time each day and using your bed only for sleep and sex. Go to bed a little earlier. Nap if you are not able to get enough sleep at night. Drink needed fluids earlier in the day so you can drink less in the hours before bed.
 Heartburn and indigestion Hormones and the pressure of the growing uterus cause
 indigestion and heartburn. Pregnancy hormones slow down the muscles of the digestive tract. So food tends to move more slowly and digestion is sluggish. This causes many pregnant women to feel bloated. Hormones also relax the valve that separates the
 esophagus from the stomach. This allows food and acids to come back up from the stomach to the esophagus. The food and acid causes the burning feeling of heartburn. As your baby gets bigger, the uterus pushes on the stomach making heartburn more common in later pregnancy. What might help: Eat several small meals instead of three large meals - eat slowly. Drink fluids between meals - not with meals. Don&amp;#39;t eat greasy and fried foods. Avoid citrus fruits or juices and spicy foods. Do not eat or drink within a few hours of bedtime. Do not lie down right after meals. Call the doctor if symptoms don&amp;#39;t improve after trying these suggestions. Ask your doctor about using an antacid. Hemorrhoids Hemorrhoids (HEM-roidz) are swollen and bulging veins in the rectum. They can cause
 itching , pain, and bleeding. Up to 50 percent of pregnant women get
 hemorrhoids .
 Hemorrhoids are common during pregnancy for many reasons. During pregnancy blood volume increases greatly, which can cause veins to enlarge. The expanding uterus also puts pressure on the veins in the rectum. Plus, constipation can worsen hemorrhoids. Hemorrhoids usually improve after delivery. What might help: Drink lots of fluids. Eat fiber-rich foods like whole grains, raw or cooked leafy green vegetables, and fruits. Try not to strain with bowel movements. Talk to your doctor about using products such as
 witch hazel to soothe hemorrhoids. Leg cramps At different times during your pregnancy, you might have sudden
 muscle spasms in your legs or feet. They usually occur at night. This is due to a change in the way your body processes calcium. What might help: Gently stretch muscles. Get mild
 exercise . For sudden cramps, flex your foot forward. Eat calcium-rich foods. Ask your doctor about
 calcium supplements . Morning Sickness In the first trimester hormone changes can cause
 nausea and
 vomiting . This is called "
 morning sickness ," although it can occur at any time of day. Morning sickness usually tapers off by the second trimester. What might help: Eat several small meals instead of three large meals to keep your stomach from being empty. Don&amp;#39;t lie down after meals. Eat dry toast, saltines, or dry cereals before getting out of bed in the morning. Eat bland foods that are low in fat and easy to digest, such as cereal, rice, and bananas. Sip on water, weak tea, or clear
 soft drinks . Or eat ice chips. Avoid smells that upset your stomach. Contact your doctor if you have
 flu -like symptoms, which may signal a more serious condition. You have severe, constant
 nausea and/or
 vomiting several times every day. Swelling Many women develop mild swelling in the face, hands, or ankles at some point in their pregnancies. As the due date approaches, swelling often becomes more noticeable. What might help: Drink eight to 10 glasses of fluids daily. Don&amp;#39;t drink
 caffeine or eat salty foods. Rest and elevate your feet. Ask your doctor about support hose. Call your doctor if your hands or feet swell suddenly or you rapidly gain weight — it may be
 preeclampsia . Urinary frequency and leaking Temporary bladder control problems are common in pregnancy. Your unborn baby pushes down on the bladder, urethra, and pelvic floor muscles. This pressure can lead to more frequent need to urinate, as well as leaking of urine when
 sneezing ,
 coughing , or laughing. What might help: Take frequent bathroom breaks. Drink plenty of fluids to avoid
 dehydration . Do Kegel exercises to tone pelvic muscles. Call your doctor if you experience burning along with frequency of urination - it may be an infection. Varicose veins During pregnancy blood volume increases greatly. This can cause veins to enlarge. Plus, pressure on the large veins behind the uterus causes the blood to slow in its return to the heart. For these reasons,
 varicose veins in the legs and anus (hemorrhoids) are more common in pregnancy. Varicose veins look like swollen veins raised above the surface of the skin. They can be twisted or bulging and are dark purple or blue in color. They are found most often on the backs of the calves or on the inside of the leg. Avoid tight knee-highs. Sit with your legs and feet raised.
 Stretch marks, skin changes Stretch marks are red, pink, or brown streaks on the skin. Most often they appear on the thighs, buttocks, abdomen, and breasts. These
 scars are caused by the stretching of the skin, and usually appear in the second half of pregnancy. Some women notice other skin changes during pregnancy. For many women, the nipples become darker and browner during pregnancy. Many pregnant women also develop a dark line (called the linea nigra) on the skin that runs from the belly button down to the pubic hairline. Patches of darker skin usually over the cheeks, forehead, nose, or upper lip also are common. Patches often match on both sides of the face. These spots are called
 melasma or chloasma and are more common in darker-skinned women. What might help: Be patient - stretch marks and other changes usually fade after delivery. Nasal Problems Nosebleeds and nasal stuffiness are common during pregnancy. They are caused by the increased amount of blood in your body and hormones acting on the tissues of your nose. What might help: Blow your nose gently. Drink fluids and use a cool mist humidifier. To stop a nosebleed, squeeze your nose between your thumb and forefinger for a few minutes. Call your doctor if your
 nosebleeds are frequent and do not stop after a few minutes. Numb or tingling hands Feelings of swelling, tingling, and numbness in fingers and hands, called
 carpal tunnel syndrome , can occur during pregnancy. These symptoms are due to
 swelling of tissues in the narrow passages in your wrists, and they should disappear after delivery. What might help Take frequent breaks to rest hands. Ask your doctor about fitting you for a splint to keep wrists straight. Dizziness Many pregnant women complain of
 dizziness and
 lightheadedness throughout their
 pregnancies .
 Fainting is rare but does happen even in some healthy pregnant women. There are many reasons for these symptoms. The growth of more blood vessels in early pregnancy, the pressure of the expanding uterus on blood vessels, and the body&amp;#39;s increased need for food all can make a pregnant woman feel lightheaded and dizzy. What might help: Stand up slowly. Avoid standing for too long. Don&amp;#39;t skip meals. Lie on your left side. Wear loose clothing. Call the doctor if you feel faint and have
 vaginal bleeding or
 abdominal pain . Itching About 20 percent of pregnant women feel
 itchy during pregnancy. Usually women feel
 itchy in the abdomen. But red, itchy palms and soles of the
 feet are also common complaints. Pregnancy hormones and stretching skin are probably to blame for most of your discomfort. Usually the itchy feeling goes away after delivery. What might help: Use gentle soaps and moisturizing creams. Avoid hot showers and baths. Avoid itchy fabrics. Contact your doctor if symptoms don&amp;#39;t improve after a week of self-care.
</first>
</file1>