<file1>
<first>Healthy Pregnancy Diet Menu Plans

ABOUT: A healthy diet during
 pregnancy ensures optimal health for both the mother and fetus. Women need only 300 extra calories per day during pregnancy. A healthy pregnancy
 diet should focus on unprocessed foods that come mostly from plant-sources. A healthy pregnancy diet 
 also can include some animal products. The diet during pregnancy should include extra calcium, iron, folate, zinc, iodine, and
 vitamin D . During pregnancy, avoid these foods
 unpasteurized cheese and meat, alcohol, caffeine , high-mercury fish, and artificial sweeteners . During pregnancy, an ideal dinner plate should be
 ½ veggies, ¼ protein like beans, ¼ whole grain carbs like quinoa, and topped with about 2 tablespoons of
 healthy fats like olive oil. Is there a pre-pregnancy diet plan? Women who are planning in advance to become
 pregnant have a great opportunity to focus on a healthy diet and get into optimum health before conceiving. 
Many women are encouraged to consider the 3 months before
 conception as a 
"pre-mester" or a trimester of pregnancy before conception. Not only does following healthy pregnancy diet 
plan guideline help a woman get into optimal health, it may help her conceive more easily. The father-to-be 
also is encouraged to follow a pre-pregnancy diet because it may help the 
mother-to-be stick to a healthy pregnancy eating plan. What is a healthy pregnancy diet plan? Myths of pregnancy such as &amp;#39;
 you need to eat twice as much because you&amp;#39;re eating for two &amp;#39; or that indulging your cravings will give your baby
 birthmarks are outdated and inaccurate. From a scientific perspective, 
there are increased nutrient demands during pregnancy, but the wisdom of the body also tells us pregnancy is a time to focus on nourishment. It is a time for the mother-to-be to focus on being as healthy as she can because that care will translate to her baby in utero. 
Also, establishing healthy habits now will set a positive example that will benefit the child over 
his or her lifetime. The increased caloric needs during pregnancy are minimal; about 300 extra calories are needed each day. This is equivalent to three-quarters of a blueberry muffin or 2 apples or 2 ounces of 
 chocolate milk. There also are a number of micronutrients or
 vitamins that are needed in increased amounts. The increased requirements are not 
 solely due to the growth of the fetus. The changes in 
the mother&amp;#39;s
 metabolism also contribute to the increased nutritional needs. The goal of healthy eating during pregnancy is to maximize micronutrient density. In other worlds, make sure you are getting maximum 
 nutrition out of every bite, and that you avoid "empty" calories. It&amp;#39;s also important to know what foods,
 drinks , medications, and 
 other toxins to avoid, for example, foods that have a higher risk of food-borne illness and foods that are toxic to a developing fetus such as alcohol, mercury-containing fish, and trans
 fats 1.   For many women, taking a
 prenatal multivitamin can be "insurance" against 
 days when they aren&amp;#39;t able to eat much (for example, to make up for lack of
 nutrition due to
 morning sickness , or not sticking to a healthy
 diet one 
 day); however, it is important to remember that
 supplements supplement the
 diet ; they aren&amp;#39;t replacements for healthy eating. What foods are part of a pregnancy diet menu plan? A well-balanced, micronutrient dense diet is the key to a healthy pregnancy. Ideally, women should start eating this way before conception, but making healthier choices at any time will always help. A well-balanced diet should contain: carbohydrates from whole grain sources and fruits and vegetables; protein from beans, nuts, seeds and hormone-free animal products like meat and dairy; and healthy fats such as olive oil, avocados, and the fats that occur in nuts, seeds, and fish. Pregnant women need more iron, folic acid, calcium, zinc, iodine, and vitamin D, and higher amounts of most other nutrients, than nonpregnant women.
 The US Recommended Daily Allowance 2 sets the level of nutrient intake that is estimated to meet the nutritional needs of 97.5% of pregnant women. Malnutrition increases the risk of having a low birth weight baby or going into preterm labor. Pregnant women need the following daily: 600mcg of folic acid 27 mg of iron 1000mg of calcium 11mg of zinc 220 mcg of iodine 600 IU vitamin D In general, women will get high levels of these nutrients by choosing a diverse, colorful diet that focuses primarily (but not entirely) on plant-based foods.
 How much weight is OK to gain during pregnancy? Pregnant women only need about 300 extra calories per day. While every woman is going to be different, research shows that for a normal weight woman (
 BMI 18.5 – 25), the optimal pregnancy total
 weight gain is about 25-35 pounds
 7 . Larger women will gain less and smaller women gain more. All women should decrease their focus on weight and focus on the quality of their diet, ensuring good nutrition. BMI &lt;18.5 kg/m2 (underweight) - typically gain 28 to 40 lbs. BMI 18.5 to 24.9 kg/m2 (optimal weight) - typically gain 25 to 35 lbs. BMI 25.0 to 29.9 kg/m2 (
 overweight ) - typically gain 15 to 25 lbs. BMI &amp;ge;30.0 kg/m2 (obese) - typically gain 11 to 20 lbs. During the first and second trimesters, weight gain manifests as an increase in maternal fat stores, plus a 60% increase in blood volume. Later in pregnancy, more of the weight gain is due to the fetal growth,
 amniotic fluid , breast development, and placenta. Overweight women sometimes even experience
 weight loss during the
 first trimester and slowly gain a small amount over the second and third trimesters. There is no 
minimum amount of weight an overweight woman needs to gain as long as she is eating micronutrient dense foods and fetal growth is on track. Is it OK to diet during pregnancy? Regardless of the weight of the woman when she becomes pregnant, it isn&amp;#39;t a good idea to diet during pregnancy. Research from famines during 
World War II in Europe have taught us about the epigenetic implications of restriction during pregnancy.
 Epigenetics describes the impact of the prenatal environment on the genetic programming of the child that stays with them for life. In fact, the prenatal environment has an impact on the developing ovaries and eggs in the female fetus, having an impact on the next generation too! A mother&amp;#39;s nutritional choices during pregnancy can affect her grandchildren! During the famines in World War II, pregnant Dutch women lived on less than 900 calories a day for a winter and their
 metabolism became very efficient at storing energy. When the war ended and food supplies 
returned to normal, and the
 babies were born, the women and their babies had normal 
calorie intake. However, those babies were far more likely to go on to become obese or develop
 diabetes because their genes were influenced 
during the time of scarcity. In the same way,
 dieting during pregnancy can have unintentionally metabolic consequences on the genetic programming of the infant that will stay with them for life. While
 dieting (restricting calories) during pregnancy is discouraged, eating a healthier diet by removing extra
 sugar and processed foods is an excellent idea. This is the type of "diet" I put all my patients on. The focus should be on high quality nutrition, optimizing micronutrient intake, and minimizing empty calories. Low carb diet menu plans during pregnancy Low carbohydrate diets can be healthy during pregnancy, as they are for any life phase, but the devil is in the details, as they say. More precise 
than simply a low carb diet, glycemic load diet is beneficial during pregnancy (and throughout life). Glycemic load is a term that measures how quickly a carbohydrate is digested and turned into
 blood sugar . Carbohydrates with lots of
 fiber , or combined with fat or protein have lower glycemic loads and raise blood sugar slowly, providing steady energy and preventing a spike in blood sugar and the subsequent
 low blood sugar drop. How do you follow a low glycemic load diet? Choose carbohydrates in their unrefined (less processed) form: Fruits Vegetables Brown rice Quinoa Beans Lentils An easy way to do this is to stay away from "white" foods: White sugar White flour White rice White bread White potato, etc. White foods are also low in micronutrients. Stay away from processed carbs such as: Flour Cookies Cake Chips Candy Juice or fruit cocktail beverages Sugar Breads Pastas Soda Pastries Dr. Brewer Pregnancy Diet Dr. Brewer Pregnancy Diet is a diet plan that was popular in the 1980s. While it is a little 
 outdated, the basics are still relevant and credible. Dr. Brewer calls for 
 frequent snacks and pays close attention to salt, calories, and protein. The 
 recommendations include getting daily servings from major groups of healthy 
 foods, like calcium or iron containing foods.
 Holistic diet menu plan during pregnancy Healthy breakfast options may include: Fresh fruit and unsweetened Greek yogurt (higher in protein and lower in fat that regular yogurt) with herbal tea or oatmeal (steel-cut or low-
 sugar ) with walnuts and 
 berries An omelet made with 2 hormone-free eggs, spinach, and tomato. Healthy lunch options may include: Salads with added protein like garbanzo beans smoked salmon, diced 
 chicken) or vegetable-based soups Bean and veggie tortilla wraps (as long as they don&amp;#39;t have too much 
 cheese) Vegetable based soups Dinners should have half the plate filled with Vegetables A quarter with protein (beans, lentils, lean meat or fish) A quarter with unrefined carbohydrates (brown rice, quinoa, sweet 
 potato) Add about 1 tablespoon of added healthy fats such as olive oil, chopped 
 nuts or seeds, or hormone free butter to the dish. Healthy snacks may include: Fruit Nuts Vegetable juices Protein shakes Celery Peanut butter Hummus and carrots Whole grain crackers with hormone-free pasteurized cheese Other important micronutrients during pregnancy are
 omega-3 fatty acids , DHA specifically, and
 probiotics . DHA is necessary for healthy development of brain and nervous system and may have beneficial effects on the cognitive development of the child. Probiotics , when taken by the mother during pregnancy 
reduce
 allergy and atopic disease in children, 
according to some research studies.
 3 Pregnancy superfoods may be included in a holistic pregnancy diet to ensure that optimal amounts of nutrients are enjoyed from food. Vegetarian and vegan diet menu plans during pregnancy Pregnant women can absolutely follow
 vegan or vegetarian diets during pregnancy. In fact, doing so may help them avoid some of the added hormones that are common in non-organic animal products. However, there are some nutrients that are commonly deficient in vegetarian diets. Pregnant women who are vegan or vegetarian should be extra careful to ensure they are getting enough calcium, iron, and B-12. Protein intake needs to be monitored too. Vegetarian protein sources include: Beans Lentils Nuts and nut butters Seeds Quinoa Peas Hemp milk/almond milk/
 soy milk Hormone-free unsweetened yogurt Hormone-free cheese Hormone-free eggs These last three are not part of a vegan 
pregnancy diet, but are appropriate for a lacto-ovo-vegetarian diet. B-12 is needed for proper DNA expression in the growing embryo and fetus. Deficiencies cause
 anemia and are associated with low birth weight, pre-term delivery,
 preeclampsia , and
 neural tube defects 8 . Pregnant women need 30mcg a day 
according to the Recommended Daily Allowance, and the sources are all animal-based. 
Vegan women may want to ensure they get enough by taking a methylcobalamin supplement. Other B vitamins, specifically folate and B6, are important in pregnancy. A good-quality prenatal multi or B complex will provide these nutrients. Protein needs during pregnancy Protein requirements in pregnancy are increased by 50%. On average, a pregnant woman needs about 70 grams of protein per day. Protein will not only ensure good growth of the baby, it will help keep the mother&amp;#39;s blood sugar stable and may help reduce
 morning sickness . Research studies have shown better birth outcomes (fewer underweight or early babies) when a mother&amp;#39;s daily diet is at least 25% protein. Most people think of meat when they think about protein, but there are many excellent vegetarian sources. A vegan or vegetarian pregnancy diet can easily get enough protein from bean, nut, and grain sources.  Additionally, relying only meat sources can increase your intake of saturated fat and other components of meat that are wise to limit in the diet. Here are some examples of good sources of healthy proteins. 1 egg, 6g 1 c Greek yogurt, 14g 11 c edamame, 29g 2T hummus, 9g 2T almond butter, 8g 1c cooked spinach, 5g 3.5oz chicken breast, 30g 3.5 oz. fish, 22g 1 scoop protein powder, 14g 1 c beans, 18g 1 oz. nuts, 6g 1 c cooked quinoa, 8g Iron needs during pregnancy Iron is a common deficiency during pregnancy. Iron is an essential mineral needed to transport oxygen to tissues. It is also necessary for DNA repair and mitochondrial energy production. Insufficient iron can cause
 anemia and symptoms of: fatigue , pallor, hair loss , poor
 exercise tolerance, restless legs, and poor cognitive development in children. Anemia has been linked to pre-term births, low birth weight, and even
 autism and increased maternal mortality
 10 . Thus, it&amp;#39;s really important to get enough iron during pregnancy. The RDA for iron is 27mg during pregnancy; your obstetrician 
or midwife may recommend 40mg per day to correct a deficiency. Cooking in cast-iron skillets can also increase iron intake – you can add 5mg of additional iron for each per saucy,
 vitamin C -rich dish you cook in cast iron. These are some good food sources of iron: 3 oz. canned clams, 24mg 1 packet instant oatmeal, 11mg 1 oz. Floradix or other liquid herbal iron, 10mg 1 oz. pumpkin seeds, 4.5mg ½ c lentils, 3.5mg 1 cup spinach, 6mg ½ c chickpeas/garbanzos, 2.5mg 3 oz. duck, lamb, turkey or other DARK meat, 2.5mg 1 Tbsp. blackstrap molasses, 3.5mg
 Folate needs during pregnancy Folate occurs naturally in vegetables and whole grains but it is lost in the processing of refined grains.  Folate deficiency increases the risk of congenital anomalies, most notably neural tube defects such as
 spina bifida . For this reason, it&amp;#39;s one of the most serious nutritional deficiencies in pregnancy. Unfortunately, the critical time for neural tube development occurs in the first few weeks of pregnancy, often before a woman knows she&amp;#39;s pregnant and thus when she is less likely to be taking a prenatal vitamin with folic acid or getting enough in the diet. Because of this, fortification of grain products (adding back in what was lost in processing) was mandated in 1998, and the prevalence of neural tube defects has dropped dramatically. Unfortunately, these foods are fortified with synthetic folic acid, not folate, and a very common genetic variant of the MTHFR gene (that codes for an enzyme important in processing of amino acids), makes it difficult for people to convert folic acid to useable folate and pregnant women with this variant are at particular risk. Researchers have suggested it would be much better to supplement pregnant women, and enrich food, with the active form methyltetrahydrofolate, rather than folic acid
 11 . Fortunately, pregnant women can get the necessary 600mcg of active, natural form folate from these dietary sources: 1 cup of black-eyed peas, 356mcg 1 cup lentils, 358mcg 1 cup asparagus, 268mcg 1 cup cubed avocado, 122mcg 3 oz. romaine lettuce, 116mcg 1 c broccoli, 55mcg 1c beets, 135mcg 1c
 papaya , 116mcg Calcium needs during pregnancy Calcium is critical for developing bones. It also reduces the risk of pre-eclampsia and hypertension. Women who get enough calcium during pregnancy have a 35% lower risk of
 high blood pressure and a 55% lower risk of preeclampsia. If the mother isn&amp;#39;t getting enough additional calcium in the diet, the fetus will still get enough, but it will come from the reserves in 
the mother&amp;#39;s bones. The mother&amp;#39;s ability to absorb calcium is greatly increased during pregnancy. This is why the RDA for calcium doesn&amp;#39;t increase during pregnancy. However, most adult women don&amp;#39;t get enough calcium in the first place. When 
we think about calcium, most people think about milk, but there are numerous non-dairy sources of calcium. Women who are lactose intolerant can choose non-dairy sources. Pregnant women need 1000mg of calcium per day
 9 . This can be reached with a few servings per day from the food list below. The
 minerals in vegetables sources, like spinach, can be 
made more available by cooking them with an acid such as vinegar or lemon juice. Try sautéing kale with apple cider vinegar and walnuts. 8 oz. skim milk, 300mg 8 oz. soy milk, 368mg 8 oz. Greek yogurt, 452mg 8 oz. regular yogurt, 415mg 1 cup collards, 356mg 1 cup spinach, 230mg 1 cup kale, 122mg 8 oz. juice with calcium, 300mg 1 packet oatmeal, ~110mg ½ c edamame (soy), 130mg ½ c white beans, 113mg 3 oz. canned sardines, 325mg 3oz. canned salmon, 181mg Iodine needs during pregnancy Iodine needs increase by almost 50% during pregnancy. Iodine is used for
 thyroid hormone function and for the developing nervous system of the fetus. Women who have iodine deficiency, or are hypothyroid for other reasons, are at risk of slowing the brain development of their baby. Pregnant women need 220mcg of iodine and the American Thyroid Association suggests pregnant women supplement with 150mcg of iodine daily
 12. Seaweed and seafood are the major source of iodine, but because of the need to limit mercury exposure in pregnancy, relying on seafood may not be wise. ¼ c kelp, 415mcg 2 oz. cranberries, 200mcg 1 c low-fat yogurt, 87mcg 1 baked potato with peel, 80mcg 3 oz. shrimp, 35mcg 1 whole egg, 24mcg Zinc 
needs during pregnancy Research suggests that 82% of pregnant women are deficient in zinc, which makes it one of the most important nutrients to pay attention to during pregnancy
 12 . In addition to the negative outcomes of low birth weight, early delivery, and preeclampsia that result from deficiency, zinc is important for the immune system of the mother and baby. Iron competes with zinc for absorption, so women who are supplementing with extra iron also need to make sure they are getting extra zinc. Some food sources are: 4 oz. mushrooms, 11mg 4 oz. beef or lamb, 6mg ¼ c sesame or pumpkin seeds, 3mg 1 cup green peas, 2 mg 3 oz. 
 shellfish (mussels, clams, oysters), 75 mg
 Vitamin D needs and pregnancy Pregnant women need 600 IU of
 vitamin D according to the USDA RDA guidelines; however, many experts believe this estimate is far too low. Humans synthesize vitamin D from sun exposure and there are very few food sources. Additionally, factors such as skin pigmentation,
 obesity , and
 sunscreen usage impact the ability to make vitamin D from sunlight. In clinical practice, I measure patients&amp;#39; blood levels of vitamin D and find that many are deficient even if they are taking a 2000mcg vitamin D3 supplement every day. Pregnant women who are concerned about vitamin D can consult a midwife, naturopathic midwife, or obstetrician who is willing to test their vitamin D levels so they know how much they need. Here are a few food sources: 4 oz. salmon, 411 IU 3 oz. canned sardines, 231 IU 8 oz. fortified soy milk, 100 IU 8 oz. fortified cow milk, 98 IU 1 egg, 23 IU 1 cup mushrooms, 114 IU Are supplements, herbs, and over-the-counter (OTC) medications safe to take 
during pregnancy? Pregnant women should take a good quality prenatal multivitamin that includes 
natural folate/methylfolate and iron. Most pregnant women may need supplemental vitamin D based on blood tests. Supplements should remain supplemental to a healthy diet and if the diet includes fruits and vegetables at every meal, most nutritional needs should be met. Some supplements and herbs can also be useful to manage some of the
 symptoms of pregnancy , such as morning sickness.
 Ginger and vitamin B6 both have been studied and found helpful for
 nausea in some women
 14 ,15 . While commonly used, some over the counter medications that have been recommended for
 nausea , like
 antihistamines , actually make it worse for some people
 16 . Magnesium is helpful for
 constipation , and may reduce the risks of developing pre-eclampsia and other poor birth outcomes
 17 . Herbals teas such as raspberry leaf,
 lemon balm , and chamomile have been traditionally used during pregnancy and are safe to consume, although mint can exacerbate
 heartburn , so use with care. Women should discuss all of the medications, supplements, and herbs with their midwife or obstetrician. 
SYMPTOMS:  While bland carbohydrates are commonly recommended for morning sickness and heartburn, studies have actually shown that protein helps more. Eat a low glycemic-load, healthy pregnancy diet to minimize the risks of feeling poorly. Eat regularly to keep blood sugars stable to minimize nausea. Make sure to consume enough water to stay hydrated and to keep bowels moving regularly. Exercise should be regular and not more vigorous that what the woman was used to before pregnancy. Long walks, prenatal yoga classes, and stretching are all excellent options for exercise while pregnant. Research has shown that all types of physical activity are safe in pregnancy except scuba diving, and extra care should be taken to avoid falling. Other healthy habits to help troublesome pregnancy symptoms include getting outside for fresh air, and ensuring good sleep also make a difference for both the pregnant woman and her baby.
 What about a post pregnancy diet? After delivery, the best diet is one that meets the nutritional needs of breastfeeding and helps the mother gradually return to her pre-pregnancy weight. Breastfeeding requires about 500 calories per day, so many women lose excess weight quickly. The nutritional needs of breast feeding require extra calcium and protein. Women also should be prepared for irregular meal patterns as they may be sleeping and awake at odd hours over the first few months as the baby&amp;#39;s needs for nursing and sleeping evolve. New mothers shouldn&amp;#39;t be focused on weight loss through calorie restriction while breastfeeding. Instead, they should continue the nutrient-dense diet recommended during pregnancy, and focus on increasing physical activity to accelerate a return to pre-pregnancy weight. What foods, drinks, or medicatons should be avoided during pregnancy? Pregnant women should stay away from several categories of unsafe foods: ones that have a higher likelihood of being contaminated with bacteria, ones that are toxic to the fetus, and ones that simply 
 add calories without adding
 nutrition . Common bacteria pose a greater risk to pregnant women and their fetus, so extra precautions should be followed. Listeria ,
 salmonella and
 toxoplasmosis are examples of
 bacterial infections that should be prevented in pregnancy. These infections can increase the risk of
 miscarriage , damage to fetal brain development and other organs. 
Infections also put the mother at risk with symptoms like
 diarrhea ,
 dehydration , and
 fever . To minimize risk, make sure meats are fully cooked and stay away from raw or undercooked meat and seafood. No sushi during pregnancy! Deli meats, meat spreads, and smoked lox are also questionable and should be heated to steaming hot in order to kill any bacteria. Dairy products can also be a source of bacterial contamination. This is why pregnant women are encouraged to stay away from soft unpasteurized cheeses. The important part to remember is that 
pasteurizing (flash heating) foods kills bacteria; for example, pasteurized Brie would be fine. Vegetables and fruit aren&amp;#39;t immune to bacterial contamination that occurs during the harvesting or preparation process. Toxoplasma is present in the soil and can contaminate vegetables. Always wash fruits and vegetables before eating them. 
Washing them with a water and white vinegar mixture can be more effective then a 
pure water wash. Alcohol, in any amount, should be avoided. There is no known safe amount of intake, and drinking alcohol puts the fetus at risk for fetal alcohol spectrum disorder and associated developmental problems. Caffeine , whether from coffee, soda, or tea, has been associated with decreased birth weight
 4 . Some fish, such as tuna, are high in mercury 
and should be avoided. Mercury is neurotoxic and can impede fetal brain development. Pregnant women should avoid fish that are potentially high in mercury. Some fish are known to be low in mercury (for example, salmon and sardines). In general long lived fish, high on the food chain will contain higher mercury levels. A guide to selecting safe fish can be found at Natural Resources Defense Council&amp;#39;s
 Sustainable Seafood Guide .
 5 Some of the man-made food additives are known to cause problems and should be avoided. For example, trans fats cross the maternal/fetal barrier, and are absorbed by fetus and may cause adverse effects on cellular membrane structure.
 6 Although limited research is available to quantify the risks of
 artificial sweeteners in pregnancy, they are able to cross the placenta into the fetal circulation and are typically found in nutrient-poor, processed foods that should be limited regardless. Illicit drugs, some over-the-counter (OTC), and 
many prescription drugs should also be avoided. If you are having trouble stopping taking illicit drugs or alcohol during pregnancy, talk to your midwife or obstetrician to get help specifically for pregnant women right away. There is help. Medications, either OTC or prescription, can be harmful to the fetus; double check with your health-care 
professional or look up the "Pregnancy Class" of the medication before taking it. Uncooked/undercooked animal products (like sushi and rare meat), including eggs Unpasteurized dairy products (like soft cheeses) Tuna, lake fish, and other high mercury fish Alcohol Caffeine (in coffee, tea, or soda) Trans fats (anything labeled hydrogenated or partially hydrogenated) Artificial sweeteners Certain drugs
</first>
</file1>