<file1>
<first>Early Pregnancy Signs and Symptoms

ABOUT: Not all moms-to-be experience the same symptoms when
 pregnant , and symptoms vary in severity. A woman will not necessarily experience the same symptoms in the same way in subsequent
 pregnancies as with her first
 pregnancy . Certain early signs, like absence of
 menstruation and
 weight gain , are common to all pregnancies. Other possible early symptoms and signs of pregnancy include:
 Mood changes Increased urination Headaches Low backache and/or
 pain Sore breasts Darkened areolas Tiredness Nausea , often referred to as "
 morning sickness " Implantation bleeding Late
 pregnancy symptoms can include:
 Leg swelling Backache Heartburn Leakage of urine Shortness of breath Braxton-Hicks contractions are non-
 labor contractions of the uterus that occur in late pregnancy. Unlike
 true labor , these contractions do not increase in intensity and are irregular. Many medications are safe for pregnant women. Home remedies and self-care strategies can bring relief for many pregnancy symptoms. Sometimes,
 symptoms of PMS , including pre-period mood changes,
 fatigue , and breast tenderness, may be mistaken for
 early pregnancy symptoms . How soon do early pregnancy symptoms start? Some women may experience early signs and symptoms within the first weeks of pregnancy in the
 first trimester , while others may develop symptoms later on in the pregnancy. First signs and symptoms of early pregnancy can also be similar to symptoms experienced prior to the
 menstrual period , so a woman may not recognize the symptoms as related to pregnancy. Are pregnancy symptoms the same for every woman? Symptoms of pregnancy can vary among different women. They may vary in quality or severity, and even the same woman may not experience the same symptoms in every pregnancy. The first signs and symptoms of pregnancy may also be noticed or begin at different points in the pregnancy. A
 pregnancy test is based on levels of human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) in the urine or blood, and is the characteristic diagnostic test for pregnancy. hCG is a hormone produced after the fertilized egg has implanted in the wall of the uterus. Modern home
 pregnancy tests may sometimes be positive before a
 missed menstrual period . Blood tests can detect pregnancy earlier than urine pregnancy tests. This article describes the most common symptoms of pregnancy in its early and later stages.
 16 early pregnancy signs and symptoms A number of symptoms begin in the early
 stages of pregnancy : 
SYMPTOMS:  Many of the early symptoms of pregnancy can persist during the second and third
 trimesters , for example: Mood changes Headaches Increased urination Backache Food cravings Fatigue Certain symptoms, like tender breasts and nausea, often improve as pregnancy advances. Additional symptoms of later pregnancy are related to the size of the growing uterus and weight gain in the second timester until giving birth. As with symptoms of early pregnancy, not all women experience all these symptoms, and women do not experience them to the same degree. 
SYMPTOMS:  There are a number of home remedies and self-care strategies that can help relieve some of the unpleasant symptoms of pregnancy. Many medications, including some kinds of antibiotics, are also safe to take during pregnancy. Talk to your doctor about considering taking, or taking any
 over-the-counter , prescription medicine, or any
 supplements or
 vitamins . The following are some self-care measures can help alleviate some of the symptoms that may be troubling: Proper
 diet and
 exercise can help lessen symptoms by keeping weight gain under control and strengthening and toning your abdominal muscles. After the first trimester, avoid exercises that involve lying on the back for a prolonged time. A pregnancy girdle or sling can help support your abdomen. Wear comfortable shoes that are not too tight, particularly if you have swelling of the legs. Exercise caution when lifting your other children or heavy objects. Be sure to bend the knees when lifting and try to keep the back straight. Sleep on a firm mattress. Lying on your side with a pillow between your legs may be a comfortable position that provides some relief. Wear a bra that provides good support if breasts are tender or sore. Eat lots of
 fiber to keep the bowels moving and avoid
 constipation . This means fresh fruits and vegetables, and whole grains. Taking fiber or
 stool softeners may help. Eat small, frequent meals to combat nausea, and avoid foods that trigger nausea. Avoid fatty foods and drink plenty of fluids. Small, frequent meals can also help prevent heartburn. Pregnancy symptoms vs. PMS (premenstrual syndrome) Many of the symptoms of early pregnancy, like breast tenderness,
 fatigue , mood swings, mild cramping,
 back pain , and others, are also symptoms that women may experience with
 premenstrual syndrome (
 PMS ) or after
 ovulation in the days prior to their menstrual period. Until the menstrual period begins or a pregnancy test is positive, there is no way to tell whether these symptoms are related to
 PMS or pregnancy.
</first>
</file1>