<file1>
<first>Pregnancy: H1N1 Influenza (Swine Flu) and the H1N1 Vaccine
Pregnancy and H1N1 influenza (swine flu) introduction These questions and answers have been updated to include new information on 
2009
 H1N1 flu in
 pregnant women. Both seasonal and 2009 H1N1 flu
 viruses will 
circulate during the 2009-2010 flu season. A pregnant woman who thinks she has 
the flu should call her doctor right away to see if treatment with an antiviral 
medicine is needed. The medicine is most helpful if it is started soon after the 
pregnant woman becomes sick. The latest advice for getting seasonal and 2009 
H1N1 vaccines during pregnancy is also included. What if I am pregnant and I get 2009 H1N1? Call your doctor right away if you have
 flu symptoms or if you have close 
contact with someone who has the flu. Pregnant women who get sick with 2009 H1N1 
can have serious health problems. They can get sicker than other people who get 
2009 H1N1 flu. Some pregnant women sick with 
2009 H1N1 have had 
early labor and 
severe
 pneumonia . Some have died. If you are pregnant and have symptoms of the 
flu, take it very seriously. Call your doctor right away for advice. What can I do to protect myself, my baby and my family? Getting a
 flu shot is the single best way to protect against the flu. Talk 
with your doctor about getting a seasonal flu shot and the 2009 H1N1 flu shot. 
You will need both flu shots this year to be fully protected against flu. You 
should get both shots as soon as they are available to protect you and your 
baby. The seasonal flu shot has been shown to protect both the mother and her 
baby (up to 6 months old) from flu-like illness. Talk with your doctor right away if you have close contact with someone who 
has 2009 H1N1 flu. You might need to take medicine to reduce your chances of 
getting the flu. Your doctor may prescribe
 Tamiflu ® or
 Relenza ® to help prevent 
2009 H1N1 flu. To prevent flu, you would take a lower dose of the antiviral 
medicine for 10 days.
 Is it safe for pregnant women to get a flu shot? The seasonal flu shot has been given to millions of pregnant women over many 
years. Flu shots have not been shown to cause harm to pregnant women or their
 babies . The 2009 H1N1 flu shot is made in the same way and in the same places as 
the seasonal flu shot. It is very important for pregnant women to get both the 
seasonal flu shot and the 2009 H1N1 flu shot. Who else should get a flu shot? Anybody who will be taking care of babies younger than 6 months of age should 
get a seasonal flu shot and a 2009 H1N1 flu shot to protect against the flu. 
This includes you and any family members or other people who will be caring for 
your baby for the first 6 months of his or her life. What else can I do? Take these everyday steps to help prevent the spread of germs and protect 
your health and the health of your family: Cover your nose and mouth with a tissue when you
 cough or sneeze, or sneeze 
into your sleeve. Throw the tissue in the trash after you use it.
 Wash your hands often with soap and warm water, especially after you
 cough or 
sneeze. If soap and water are not available, an alcohol-based hand rub can be 
used.
 Avoid touching your eyes, nose or mouth. Germs spread this way.
 Try to avoid close contact with sick people.
 If there is 2009 H1N1 flu in your community, pay extra attention to your body 
and how you are feeling. If you think you have the flu, call your doctor or 
clinic right away.
 If you are pregnant and you live with or have close contact with someone who 
has 2009 H1N1 flu, talk with your doctor about medicines to prevent flu.
 Have a plan for someone else to take care of a sick family member.
 Stock up on household, health, and emergency supplies, such as
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ®), water, and non-perishable foods.
 What are the symptoms of seasonal and 2009 H1N1 flu? You may have the flu if you have some or all of these symptoms: Fever *
 Cough
 Sore throat Runny or stuffy nose
 Body
 aches Headaches Chills Fatigue Sometimes,
 diarrhea and
 vomiting *It's important to note that some people with flu will not have a
 fever . What should I do if I get sick? If you get sick with flu-like symptoms, stay home, stay away from others , and 
call your doctor right away. If needed, he or she will prescribe an antiviral 
medicine that treats the flu. Have someone check in with you often if you are 
feeling ill. This is always a good idea. How is 2009 H1N1 flu treated? 2009 H1N1 flu is treated with antiviral
 drugs such as Tamiflu® (
 oseltamivir ) 
or Relenza® (
 zanamivir ). Antiviral drugs are prescription pills, liquids or an 
inhaled powder that fight against the flu by keeping the germs from growing in 
your body. These medicines work best if they are taken as soon as you have 
symptoms of the flu. For that reason, it is important that you call your doctor 
as soon as you notice flu-like symptoms.
 If your doctor prescribes an antiviral to treat your flu, you will need to 
take it for 5 days. The medicine can make you get better faster and make your 
symptoms milder.
 At this time, there have been no reports to show harm to the pregnant woman 
or her unborn baby. Flu can cause serious illness and even death in pregnant 
women. Taking antiviral medicine can help prevent these severe outcomes.
 Antiviral medicines can be taken at any stage during pregnancy.
 Treat any fever right away. Acetaminophen (Tylenol®) is best for a pregnant 
woman to use to reduce a fever.
 Drink plenty of fluids to replace those you lose when you are sick.
 If you have had close contact with someone who is sick with the flu, your 
doctor may prescribe Tamiflu® or Relenza® to help prevent 2009 H1N1 flu. To 
prevent flu, you would take a lower dose of the medicine for 10 days.
 Antiviral medicines can be taken at any stage during pregnancy.
 When should I get emergency medical care? If you have any of these signs, call 911 right away: Difficulty
 breathing or
 shortness of breath Pain or pressure in the chest or abdomen
 Sudden
 dizziness Confusion Severe or persistent
 vomiting A high fever that is not responding to Tylenol®
 Decreased or no movement of your baby How should I feed my baby if I am sick? If you can, breastfeed. Breast milk is the perfect food for your baby. There 
are many ways that
 breastfeeding and breast milk protect your baby's health. 
Babies who are breastfed get sick from infections like the flu less often and 
less severely than babies who are not breastfed. Flu can be very serious in young babies. You do not have to stop 
breastfeeding if you have the flu, but you have to be careful to protect your 
baby from getting sick. Please see http://www.cdc.gov/h1n1flu/infantfeeding.htm 
to learn more about how to feed your baby if you are sick. Why does CDC advise pregnant women to receive the 2009 H1N1 influenza (flu) vaccine (shot)? Getting the flu shot is the single best way to protect against the flu. It is 
important for a pregnant woman to receive both the 2009 H1N1 flu shot and the 
seasonal flu shot. A pregnant woman who gets any type of flu has a greater 
chance for serious health problems. Compared with people in general who get 2009 
H1N1 flu (formerly called "
 swine flu "), pregnant women with 2009 H1N1 flu are 
more likely to be admitted to hospitals. Pregnant women are also more likely to 
have serious illness and death from 2009 H1N1 flu. When a pregnant woman gets a 
flu shot, it can protect both her and her baby. Research has found that pregnant 
women who had a flu shot get sick less often with the flu than do pregnant women 
who did not get a flu shot. Babies born to mothers who had a flu shot in 
pregnancy also get sick with flu less often than do babies whose mothers did not 
get a flu shot.
 Will the seasonal flu shot also protect against the 2009 H1N1 flu? Seasonal flu and 2009 H1N1 flu are caused by different viruses. The 
seasonal
 flu vaccine will not protect against the 2009 H1N1 flu. Also, the 2009 H1N1 flu 
vaccine will not protect against seasonal flu. Are there flu vaccines that pregnant women should not get? The seasonal and 2009 H1N1 flu vaccines can be given by shot or by nasal 
spray. Pregnant women should get the "flu shot" - a vaccine made with killed flu 
virus. This one is given with a needle, usually in the arm. The other type of 
flu vaccine - a nasal spray - is not approved for pregnant women. This vaccine is 
made with live, weakened flu virus. Nasal spray flu vaccine should be used only 
in healthy people 2-49 years of age who are not pregnant. The nasal spray 
vaccine is safe for women after they have delivered, even if they are
 nursing . Can the seasonal flu shot and the 2009 H1N1 flu shot be given at the same 
time? Seasonal and 2009 H1N1 flu shots can be given on the same day but should be 
given at different sites (e.g., one shot in the left arm and the other shot in 
the right arm). If a woman is getting her vaccines after delivery, she can get 
the nasal spray flu vaccine. However, she should not get the seasonal and 2009 
H1N1 nasal spays on the same day; they should be given 4 weeks apart. Is the 2009 H1N1 flu shot safe for pregnant women? The seasonal flu shot has been given to millions of pregnant women over many 
years. Flu shots have not been shown to cause harm to pregnant women or their 
babies. The 2009 H1N1 flu vaccine is being made in the same way and at the same 
places where the seasonal flu vaccine is made. What studies have been done on the 2009 H1N1 flu shots and have any been done 
in pregnant women? Studies to test the 2009 H1N1 flu shots in healthy children and adults and 
pregnant women are being done now. Results are available from some of the 
studies done in non-pregnant adults and children. These results show that the 
immune system responded well to the 2009 H1N1 vaccine, and the safety results 
were very similar to those seen in studies of seasonal flu vaccine. These 
studies are being conducted by the National Institute of
 Allergy and Infectious 
Diseases (NIAID) and the vaccine manufacturers. Does the 2009 H1N1 flu shot have mercury in it? There is no evidence that thimerosal (a mercury preservative in vaccine that 
comes in multi-dose vials) is harmful to a pregnant woman or a fetus. However, 
because some women are concerned about thimerosal during pregnancy, vaccine 
companies are making preservative-free seasonal flu vaccine and 2009 H1N1 flu 
vaccine in single-dose syringes for pregnant women and small children. CDC 
advises pregnant women to get flu shots either with or without thimerosal. Does the 2009 H1N1 flu shot have an adjuvant or squalene in it? Adjuvants are agents that are sometimes added to a vaccine to make it more 
effective. There are no adjuvants (such as squalene) in either the 2009 H1N1 or 
seasonal flu shot used in the United States. Can the 2009 H1N1 flu shot be given at any time during pregnancy? Both seasonal flu shots and 2009 H1N1 flu shots are recommended for pregnant 
women at any time during pregnancy. How many 2009 H1N1 flu shots will a pregnant woman need to get? The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved the use of one shot 
for full protection for persons 10 years and older. Therefore, a pregnant woman 
is recommended to get one dose of the 2009 H1N1 vaccine. Should the 2009 H1N1 flu shot be given to a pregnant woman who had flu 
between April 2009 and now? Do I need a test to know if I need the shot or not? A pregnant woman who had a flu-like illness at any time in the past should 
still get the 2009 H1N1 shot because she cannot assume that the illness she had 
was caused by the 2009 H1N1 virus. Pregnant women who had flu symptoms in the 
past do not need to be tested now, but should get the vaccine.
 What are the possible side effects of the 2009 H1N1 flu shots? The side effects from 2009 H1N1 flu shots are expected to be like those from 
seasonal flu shots. The most common side effects after flu shots are mild, such 
as being sore and tender and/or red and swollen where the shot was given. Some 
people might have
 headache , muscle aches, fever, and
 nausea or feel tired. If 
these problems happen, they usually begin soon after the shot and may last as 
long as 1-2 days. Some people may faint after getting any shot. Sometimes, flu 
shots can cause serious problems like severe
 allergic reactions. But, 
life-threatening allergic reactions to vaccines are very rare. A person who has 
a severe (life-threatening)
 allergy to eggs or to anything else in the vaccine 
should not get the shot, even if she is pregnant. Pregnant women should tell the 
person giving the shots if they have any severe
 allergies or if they have ever 
had a
 severe allergic reaction following a flu shot. Is the 2009 H1N1 flu shot expected to be associated with Guillain-Barre 
Syndrome (GBS)? In 1976, an earlier type of swine flu vaccine was associated with cases of a 
severe paralytic illness called
 Guillain-Barre Syndrome (GBS) at a rate of 
approximately 1 case of GBS per 100,000 persons vaccinated. Some studies done 
since 1976 have shown a small risk of GBS in persons who received the seasonal
 influenza vaccine. This risk is estimated to be no more than 1 case of GBS per 1 
million persons vaccinated. Other studies have shown no increase in risk of GBS. 
Pregnant women should tell the person giving the shots if they have ever had 
GBS.
 What about the H1N1 nasal spray vaccine? Can family members or other close contacts of a pregnant woman receive the 
nasal spray vaccine? Pregnant women should not receive nasal spray for the seasonal or 2009 H1N1 
flu vaccine, but it is okay for a pregnant woman to be around a family member or 
another close contact who has received nasal spray flu vaccine. The nasal spray 
vaccine can be used in healthy people 2-49 years of age who are not pregnant and 
in women after they deliver, even if they are nursing. Can a pregnant healthcare provider give the live nasal spray flu vaccine? Yes. No special precautions are needed. Nurses and doctors should wash their 
hands or use an alcohol-based hand rub before and after giving the vaccine. What if a pregnant woman gets the live nasal spray flu vaccine instead of the 
flu shot? The nasal spray flu vaccine has not been approved for pregnant women. It 
differs from the flu shot because it is made with live, weakened virus. However, 
sometimes a pregnant woman might get the nasal spray flu vaccine—for example, 
before she knew she was pregnant. If this happened, she would not be expected to 
have any additional problems. The weakened, live flu virus has never been shown 
to be passed to the unborn baby. However, if a woman does get the nasal spray 
vaccine while she is pregnant, she should talk to her healthcare provider. If a pregnant woman delivers her baby before receiving her seasonal flu shot 
or her 2009 H1N1 flu shot, should she still receive them? Yes. Besides protecting her from infection, the shot may also help protect 
her infant. Flu shots are only given to infants 6 months of age and older. 
Everyone who lives with or gives care to an infant less than 6 months of age 
should get both the seasonal flu and 2009 H1N1 vaccines. A woman can get either 
the shots or the nasal spray after she delivers.
 What about breastfeeding and the H1N1 influenza and vaccination safety? Can a breastfeeding mother receive the flu shot or the nasal spray? Yes. Both seasonal and 2009 H1N1 flu vaccines should be given to 
breastfeeding mothers and breastfeeding women can receive either the shot or the 
nasal spray form of the vaccine. Breastfeeding is fully compatible with flu 
vaccination, and preventing the flu in mothers can reduce the chance that the 
infant will get the flu. Also, by breastfeeding, mothers can pass on to the 
infant the antibodies that their bodies make in response to the flu shots, which 
can reduce the infant's chances of getting sick with the flu. This is especially 
important for infants less than 6 months old, who have no other way of receiving 
vaccine antibodies, since they are too young to be vaccinated. What can I do to protect my baby? Take everyday precautions such as washing your hands with plain soap and 
water before feeding your baby. If soap and water are not available, use an 
alcohol-based hand rub to clean your hands before feeding your baby. In addition, try not to 
cough or sneeze in the baby's face while feeding your baby, or any other time 
you and your baby are close. If possible, only family members who are not sick 
should care for infants. If you are sick and there is no one else to care for 
your baby, wear a facemask, if available and tolerable, and cover your mouth and 
nose with a tissue when
 coughing or
 sneezing . Is it OK to for me to feed my baby if I am sick? Infants are thought to be at higher risk for severe illness from 2009 H1N1 
infection and very little is known about
 prevention of 2009 H1N1 flu infection 
in infants. If you are breastfeeding or giving your baby
 infant formula , a 
cautious approach would be to protect your baby from exposure to the flu virus 
in the following ways: Ask for help from someone who is not sick to feed and care for your baby, if 
possible.
 If there is no one else who can take care of your baby while you are 
 sick, try to wear a face mask at all times when you are feeding or caring 
 for your baby. You should also be very careful about washing your hands and 
 taking everyday precautions to prevent your baby from getting flu. 
Using a cloth blanket between you and your baby during feedings might also help.
 If you are breastfeeding, someone who is not sick can give your baby your 
expressed milk. Ideally babies less than about 6 months of age should get their 
feedings from breast milk. It is OK to take medicines to treat the flu while you 
are breastfeeding. Does breastfeeding protect babies from this new flu virus? There are many ways that breastfeeding and breast milk protect babies' 
health. Flu can be very serious in young babies. Babies who are not breastfed 
get sick from infections like the flu more often and more severely than babies 
who are breastfed. Since this is a new virus, we don't know yet about specific protection 
against it. Mothers pass on protective antibodies to their baby during 
breastfeeding. Antibodies are a type of protein made by the immune system in the 
body. Antibodies help fight off infection. If you are sick with flu and are breastfeeding, someone who is not sick can 
give your baby your expressed milk. Should I stop breastfeeding my baby if I think I have come in contact with 
the flu? No. Because mothers make antibodies to fight diseases they come in contact 
with, their milk is custom-made to fight the diseases their babies are exposed 
to as well. This is really important in young babies when their immune system is 
still developing. It is OK to take medicines to prevent the flu while you are 
breastfeeding. You should make sure you wash your hands often and take everyday 
precautions. However, if you develop 
symptoms of the flu such as fever, cough, or
 sore throat , you should ask someone 
who is not sick to care for your baby. If you become sick, someone who is not 
sick can give your baby your expressed milk. Is it okay to take medicine to treat or prevent 2009 H1N1 flu while 
breastfeeding? Yes. Mothers who are breastfeeding and taking medicine to treat flu because 
they are sick should express their breast milk for bottle feedings, which can be 
given to your baby by someone who is not sick. Mothers who are breastfeeding and 
are taking medicines to prevent the flu because they have been exposed to the 
virus should continue to feed their baby at the breast as long as they do not 
have symptoms of the flu such as fever, cough, or
 sore throat . If my baby is sick, is it okay to breastfeed? Yes. One of the best things you can do for your sick baby is keep 
breastfeeding. Do not stop breastfeeding if your baby is sick. Give your baby many chances 
to breastfeed throughout the illness. Babies who are sick need more fluids than 
when they are well. The fluid babies get from breast milk is better than 
anything else, even better than water, juice, or
 Pedialyte ® because it also 
helps protect your baby's immune system.
 If your baby is too sick to breastfeed, he or she can drink your milk from a 
cup, bottle, syringe, or eye-dropper.
</first>
</file1>