<file1>
<first>Pregnancy: Prenatal Care and Tests

ABOUT: *
 
ABOUT: Medically Edited by: Melissa Conrad Stöppler, MD The definition of prenatal care is the health care of women throughout the course of
 pregnancy . Good prenatal care helps ensure the health of both the mother and the baby. Regular checkups and prenatal testing are important parts of prenatal care. Prenatal care practitioners include obstetricians, family practice doctors, certified nurse-midwives (CNM), certified professional midwives (CPM), and doulas. A woman can give birth in a hospital, birth center, or at home. The presence of certain health problems or pregnancy complications may prohibit a home birth. Typically, a woman's age, family history, medical history, and pregnancy risk factors are assessed during the initial prenatal doctor visit. A breast exam,
 Pap test ,
 pelvic exam , and cervical exam may also be performed. Part of prenatal care is screening also will be assessed for conditions like
 anemia , Rh factor incompatibility, toxoplasmosis , hepatitis B , syphilis , Chlamydia , and HIV . Blood type and immunity to
 rubella (
 German measles ) and
 chickenpox will also be assessed. Prenatal tests are performed to monitor the health and development of the baby. Prenatal tests include
 amniocentesis , ultrasound , quad screen, chorionic villus sampling , group B strep screening, and a urine test. Certain factors, such as
 gestational diabetes ,
 preeclampsia , and being over the age of 35 increase the risk of having a high-risk pregnancy. Women who have a high-risk pregnancy may need more frequent doctor visits and special care. Prenatal care costs can be expensive. Programs and services are available to help women get the care they need. Prenatal care and tests introduction Medical checkups and screening tests help keep you and your baby healthy during pregnancy. This is called prenatal care. It also involves education and counseling about how to handle different aspects of your pregnancy. During your visits, your doctor may discuss many issues, such as healthy eating and physical activity, screening tests you might need, and what to expect during
 labor and delivery .
 Choosing a prenatal care provider You will see your prenatal care provider many times before you have your baby. So you want to be sure that the person you choose has a good reputation, and listens to and respects you. You will want to find out if the doctor or midwife can deliver your baby in the place you want to give birth, such as a specific hospital or birthing center. Your provider also should be willing and able to give you the information and support you need to make an informed choice about whether to breastfeed or bottle-feed. Health care providers that care for women during pregnancy include: Obstetricians (OB) are medical doctors who specialize in the care of
 pregnant women and in delivering
 babies . OBs also have special training in surgery so they are also able to do acesarean delivery. Women who have health problems or are at risk for pregnancy complications should see an obstetrician. Women with the highest risk pregnancies might need special care from a
 maternal-fetal medicine specialist . Family practice doctors are medical doctors who provide care for the whole family through all stages of life. This includes care during pregnancy and delivery, and following birth. Most family practice doctors cannot perform cesarean deliveries. A
 certified nurse-midwife (CNM) and
 certified professional midwife (CPM) are trained to provide pregnancy and postpartum care. Midwives can be a good option for healthy women at low risk for problems during pregnancy, labor, or delivery. A CNM is educated in both
 nursing and midwifery. Most CNMs practice in hospitals and birth centers. A CPM is required to have experience delivering babies in home settings because most CPMs practice in homes and birthing centers. All midwives should have a back-up plan with an obstetrician in case of a problem or emergency. A doula (DOO-luh) is a professional labor coach, who gives physical and emotional support to women during labor and delivery. They offer advice on
 breathing , relaxation, movement, and positioning. Doulas also give emotional support and comfort to women and their partners during labor and birth. Doulas and midwives often work together during a woman's labor. A recent study showed that continuous doula support during labor was linked to shorter labors and much lower use of:
 Pain medicines Oxytocin (ok-see-TOHS-uhn) (medicine to help labor progress) Cesarean delivery Check with your health insurance company to find out if they will cover the cost of a doula. When choosing a doula, find out if she is certified by Doulas of North America (DONA) or another professional group. Ask your primary care doctor, friends, and family members for provider recommendations. When making your choice, think about: Reputation Personality and bedside manner The provider's gender and age Office location and hours Whether you always will be seen by the same provider during office checkups and delivery Who covers for the provider when she or he is not available Where you want to deliver How the provider handles phone consultations and after-hour calls
 Places to deliver your baby Many women have strong views about where and how they'd like to deliver their babies. In general, women can choose to deliver at a hospital, birth center, or at home. You will need to contact your health insurance provider to find out what options are available. Also, find out if the doctor or midwife you are considering can deliver your baby in the place you want to give birth. Hospitals are a good choice for women with health problems, pregnancy complications, or those who are at risk for problems during labor and delivery. Hospitals offer the most advanced medical equipment and highly trained doctors for pregnant women and their babies. In a hospital, doctors can do a cesarean delivery if you or your baby is in danger during labor. Women can get epidurals or many other
 pain relief options. Also, more and more hospitals now offer on-site birth centers, which aim to offer a style of care similar to standalone birth centers. Questions to ask when choosing a hospital: Is it close to your home? Is a doctor who can give pain relief, such as an epidural, at the hospital 24-hours a day? Do you like the feel of the labor and delivery rooms? Are private rooms available? How many support people can you invite into the room with you? Does it have a
 neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) in case of serious problems with the baby? Can the baby stay in the room with you? Does the hospital have the staff and set-up to support successful
 breastfeeding ? Does it have an on-site birth center? Birth or birthing centers give women a "homey" environment in which to labor and give birth. They try to make labor and delivery a natural and personal process by doing away with most high-tech equipment and routine procedures. So, you will not automatically be hooked up to an IV. Likewise, you won't have an electronic fetal monitor around your belly the whole time. Instead, the midwife or nurse will check in on your baby from time to time with a handheld machine. Once the baby is born, all exams and care will occur in your room. Usually certified nurse-midwives, not obstetricians, deliver babies at birth centers. Healthy women who are at low risk for problems during pregnancy, labor, and delivery may choose to deliver at a birth center. Women cannot receive epidurals at a birth center, although some pain medicines may be available. If a cesarean delivery becomes necessary, women must be moved to a hospital for the procedure. After delivery, babies with problems can receive basic emergency care while being moved to a hospital. Many birthing centers have showers or tubs in their rooms for laboring women. They also tend to have comforts of home like large beds and rocking chairs. In general, birth centers allow more people in the delivery room than do hospitals. Birth centers can be inside of hospitals, a part of a hospital or completely separate facilities. If you want to deliver at a birth center, make sure it meets the standards of the Accreditation Association for Ambulatory Health Care, The Joint Commission, or the American Association of Birth Centers. Accredited birth centers must have doctors who can work at a nearby hospital in case of problems with the mom or baby. Also, make sure the birth center has the staff and set-up to support. Homebirth is an option for healthy pregnant women with no risk factors for complications during pregnancy, labor or delivery. It is also important women have a strong after-care support system at home. Some certified nurse midwives and doctors will deliver babies at home. Many health insurance companies do not cover the cost of care for homebirths. So check with your plan if you'd like to deliver at home. Homebirths are common in many countries in Europe. However, in the United States, planned homebirths are not supported by the American Congress of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG). ACOG states that hospitals are the safest place to deliver a baby. In case of an emergency, says ACOG, a hospital's equipment and highly trained doctors can provide the best care for a woman and her baby. If you are thinking about a homebirth, you need to weigh the pros and cons. The main advantage is that you will be able to experience labor and delivery in the privacy and comfort of your own home. Since there will be no routine medical procedures, you will have control of your experience. The main disadvantage of a homebirth is that in case of a problem, you and the baby will not have immediate hospital/medical care. It will have to wait until you are transferred to the hospital. Plus, women who deliver at home have no options for pain relief. To ensure your safety and that of your baby, you must have a highly trained and experienced midwife along with a fail-safe back-up plan. You will need fast, reliable transportation to a hospital. If you live far away from a hospital, homebirth may not be the best choice. Your midwife must be experienced and have the necessary skills and supplies to start emergency care for you and your baby if need be. Your midwife should also have access to a doctor 24 hours a day.
 Prenatal checkups During pregnancy, regular checkups are very important. This consistent care can help keep you and your baby healthy, spot problems if they occur, and prevent problems during delivery. Typically, routine checkups occur: Once each month for weeks four through 28 Twice a month for weeks 28 through 36 Weekly for weeks 36 to birth Women with high-risk pregnancies need to see their doctors more often. At your first visit your doctor will perform a full physical exam, take your blood for lab tests, and calculate your due date. Your doctor might also do a breast exam, a pelvic exam to check your uterus (womb), and a cervical exam, including a Pap test. During this first visit, your doctor will ask you lots of questions about your lifestyle, relationships, and health habits. It's important to be honest with your doctor. After the first visit, most prenatal visits will include: Checking your
 blood pressure and weight Checking the baby's heart rate Measuring your abdomen to check your baby's growth You also will have some routine tests throughout your pregnancy, such as tests to look foranemia, tests to measure risk of gestational
 diabetes , and tests to look for harmful infections. Become a partner with your doctor to manage your care. Keep all of your appointments — every one is important! Ask questions and read to educate yourself about this exciting time. Monitor your baby's activity After 28 weeks, keep track of your baby's movement. This will help you to notice if your baby is moving less than normal, which could be a sign that your baby is in distress and needs a doctor's care. An easy way to do this is the "count-to-10" approach. Count your baby's movements in the evening — the time of day when the fetus tends to be most active. Lie down if you have trouble feeling your baby move. Most women count 10 movements within about 
one hour. It is rare for a woman to count less than 10 movements within two hours at times when the baby is active. Count your baby's movements every day so you know what is normal for you. Call your doctor if you count less than 10 movements within two hours or if you notice your baby is moving less than normal. If your baby is not moving at all, call your doctor right away.
 Prenatal tests Tests are used during pregnancy to check your and your baby's health. At your fist prenatal visit, your doctor will use tests to check for a number of things, such as: Your blood type and Rh factor Anemia Infections, such as toxoplasmosis and sexually transmitted infections (STIs), including
 hepatitis B , syphilis, chlamydia, and
 HIV Signs that you are immune to
 rubella (German
 measles ) and
 chicken pox Throughout your pregnancy, your doctor or midwife may suggest a number of other tests, too. Some tests are suggested for all women, such as screenings for gestational
 diabetes ,
 Down syndrome , and
 HIV . Other tests might be offered based on your: Age Personal or family health history Ethnic background Results of routine tests Some tests are screening tests. They detect risks for or signs of
 possible health problems in you or your baby. Based on screening test results, your doctor might suggest diagnostic tests. Diagnostic tests confirm or rule out health problems in you or your baby. The following chart describes some of the most common prenatal tests: If your doctor suggests certain prenatal tests, don't be afraid to ask lots of questions. Learning about the test, why your doctor is suggesting it for you, and what the test results could mean can help you cope with any worries or fears you might have. Keep in mind that screening tests do not diagnose problems. They evaluate risk. So if a screening test comes back abnormal, this doesn't mean there is a problem with your baby. More information is needed. Your doctor can explain what test results mean and possible next steps.
 High-risk pregnancy Pregnancies with a greater chance of complications are called "high-risk." But this doesn't mean there will be problems. The following factors may increase the risk of problems during pregnancy: Very young age or older than 35 Overweight or underweight Problems in previous pregnancy Health conditions you have before you become pregnant, such as
 high blood pressure , diabetes, autoimmune disorders,
 cancer , and HIV Pregnancy with twins or other multiples Health problems also may develop during a pregnancy that make it high-risk, such as gestational diabetes or preeclampsia. Women with high-risk pregnancies need prenatal care more often and sometimes from a specially trained doctor. A maternal-fetal medicine specialist is a medical doctor that cares for high-risk pregnancies. If your pregnancy is considered high risk, you might worry about your unborn baby's health and have trouble enjoying your pregnancy. Share your concerns with your doctor. Your doctor can explain your risks and the chances of a real problem. Also, be sure to follow your doctor's advice. For example, if your doctor tells you to take it easy, then ask your partner, family members, and friends to help you out in the months ahead. You will feel better knowing that you are doing all you can to care for your unborn baby.
 Paying for prenatal care Pregnancy can be stressful if you are worried about affording health care for you and your unborn baby. For many women, the extra expenses of prenatal care and preparing for the new baby are overwhelming. The good news is that women in every state can get help to pay for medical care during their pregnancies. Every state in the United States has a program to help. Programs give medical care, information, advice, and other services important for a healthy pregnancy. To find out about the program in your state: Call 800-311-BABY (800-311-2229) – This toll-free telephone number will connect you to the Health Department in your area code. Call 800-504-7081 for information in Spanish. Call or contact your local Health Department. You may also find help through these places: Local hospital or social service agencies – Ask to speak with a social worker on staff. She or he will be able to tell you where to go for help. Community clinics – Some areas have free clinics or clinics that provide free care to women in need. Women, Infants and Children (WIC) Program – This government program is available in every state. It provides help with food, nutritional counseling, and access to health services for women, infants, and children. Places of worship</first>
</file1>