<file1>
<first>Heart Attack Prevention
(How to Prevent a Heart Attack)

ABOUT: Heart disease is the leading cause of death in the U.S. About 735,000 
Americans suffer from a
 heart attack each year – that&amp;#39;s about one heart attack 
every 43 seconds! 525,000 of those heart attacks are the first for the person affected, 
 while 210,000 of them happen in people who have previously had a heart 
 attack. Symptoms of a heart attack in men and women include
 chest discomfort and discomfort in one or both arms, neck jaw, back, 
  or stomach, shortness of breath , sweating , and palpitations . Women experience the same symptoms of a heart attack as listed above; 
 however in addition women may have
 pain in the upper abdomen, extreme
 fatigue , dizziness , lightheadedness or
 fainting . Leading a heart-healthy lifestyle such as eating a heart healthy
 diet ,
 exercise ,
 stress reduction , and
 disease prevention or management is the best way to prevent heart 
disease and heart attack. What is a heart attack? A heart attack happens when the flow of blood that brings oxygen to the heart 
muscle is significantly reduced or cut off completely. This is often a result of 
atherosclerosis, a process whereby the arteries narrow due to a buildup of 
plaque (fat,
 cholesterol , and other substances). Sometimes these plaques can 
break off, and
 blood clots can form around them. The clots in the coronary 
arteries then block blood flow to the heart, starving it of oxygen and nutrients 
(ischemia), causing damage or death to heart muscle. This damage to the heart 
muscle is a heart attack. Heart attack is medically termed myocardial 
infarction (MI).
 
SYMPTOMS:  Chest discomfort or pain that may feel like pressure or tightness Squeezing, or fullness discomfort in one or both arms Back, neck, jaw or
 stomach pain Shortness of breath, which may or may not be accompanied by chest discomfort Nausea Palpitations Lightheadedness Sweating Sometimes people having a heart attack experience no symptoms at all. The medical term for this is silent ischemia, commonly referred to as a "silent" heart attack. If you think you are experiencing signs of a heart attack, call 911 immediately! Are signs and symptoms of a heart attack different in women? Women also experience
 chest pain and discomfort as a symptom of a heart 
attack. But women are more likely than men to experience other symptoms 
including shortness of breath, nausea and
 vomiting , and back or
 jaw pain . 
Sometimes the symptoms of a heart attack in women are more subtle, such as pain in the upper abdomen dizziness lightheadedness or
 fainting extreme
 fatigue If you think you are experiencing signs of a heart attack, call 911 
immediately! What are the signs and
symptoms of heart disease(cardiovascular disease)? Chest pain (
 angina ) Extreme
 fatigue Shortness of breath Heart
 palpitations Pain in the neck, jaw, throat, back, or upper abdomen Indigestion or
 heartburn Nausea or
 vomiting Swelling in
 feet , ankles, legs, and abdomen
 
PREVENTION:  Leading a heart-healthy lifestyle with a nutritious low-fat
 diet and
 exercise is the best way to prevent heart disease and heart attack. A heart-healthy diet includes nutrient-rich foods such as fruits and vegetables and whole grains. Fat and
 sugar should be limited. Regular exercise can also help keep you at a healthy weight and prevent heart disease and heart attacks. Other tips for lifestyle changes that can help prevent heart disease or a heart attack include not
 smoking , limiting alcohol, reducing
 stress , and managing 
 diabetes and high blood pressure. 
PREVENTION:  A heart-healthy diet is full of: Fruits and veggies Whole grains Legumes Low-fat dairy Lean poultry Fish Nuts Limit: Sugar Red meat Sugary sodas There is evidence that natural plant-based,
 vegetarian or vegan diets may be helpful in preventing and even reversing heart disease. The DASH (Dietary Approaches to Stop
 Hypertension ) is an eating plan that helps manage
 high blood pressure and is effective in reducing the risk of heart attack. 
PREVENTION:  Leading a heart-healthy lifestyle is the best way to prevent heart disease and heart attack. Follow these tips to reduce your risk factors for heart attack. Eat a heart-healthy diet. Maintain a healthy weight. Don&amp;#39;t smoke. Limit alcohol intake. Manage
 diabetes and
 blood pressure . Exercise regularly. Reduce stress (take
 stress management classes or
 yoga ) Take prescribed medications as directed.
 
RISKS:  Regular exercise can help prevent heart attacks. Just 40 minutes of moderate-to-vigorous-intensity physical activity, 3-4 times per week can lower blood pressure, lower cholesterol, help you
 lose weight and maintain a healthy weight. It also helps manage stress. Exercise tips: Start slowly and work your way up to more time and intensity. Even just 10 minutes of light
 walking will benefit your health. A tip is to find activities you enjoy such as Yoga Swimming Tai Chi Walk for 20 minutes and spend time with nature 
RISKS:  The following increases your risk of heart attack: Diabetes High blood pressure (hypertension) High cholesterol (
 hyperlipidemia ) Obesity Smoking Aging Family history of heart disease Alcoholism If you have a heart attack and are home alone when it occurs here are some tips help improve your outcome. Know the symptoms of a heart attack. Keep your cell phone available at all times. If you suspect you are experiencing symptoms of a heart attack, call 911 immediately. Minutes count! Do this FIRST, before anything else. If the 911 operator suggests it, take an
 aspirin if you are not
 allergic . Be prepared  talk to your doctor and find out if you should be on aspirin therapy to prevent a heart attack before it occurs. The Internet has spread the idea of "
 cough CPR," however, the American Heart Association does not endorse this as a way to prevent heart attacks. If you are having a sudden abnormal heart rhythm (
 arrhythmia ) and are conscious you may be able to
 cough forcefully enough to maintain enough blood flow to the brain to stay conscious a few seconds more until the arrhythmia breaks. Coughing probably won&amp;#39;t hurt, but always call 911 first.
</first>
</file1>