<file1>
<first>IBS (Irritable Bowel Syndrome) Triggers and Prevention

ABOUT: Irritable bowel syndrome (
 IBS ) is a recurrent disease of the bowel. Treatment and management of symptoms include psychological support, dietary measures, management of food intake, and management of medications and/or psychological conditions. Foods and
 drinks that dehydrate the body can
 trigger
 constipation in people with
 irritable bowel syndrome . Fatty foods can
 trigger
 diarrhea in people with the condition, but specific food triggers of
 diarrhea and other symptoms may vary between individuals. Stress and
 anxiety can stimulate symptoms in many people with
 IBS . Drugs like antibiotics,
 antidepressants and/or medicines that contain
 sorbitol may trigger symptoms. In many women with
 IBS , menses and/or menstrual pain is related to the onset of symptoms. Other triggers for symptoms may include
 a chronic lack of
 exercise , frequently eating while under
 stress , and eating foods that are very hot or very
 cold . There are several ways to reduce or stop many of the causes that trigger
 symptoms ; for example, eat a balanced
 diet , avoid food and drinks that dehydrate the body or may cause
 diarrhea , keep a journal to identify personal triggers, reduce stressors or causes of
 anxiety , and discuss medications you are taking that may be triggering your symptoms with your doctor. Consequently, for each individual, it is important to determine what foods, medications and/or conditions trigger symptoms. This short article is designed to be an introduction to treatment and management and provides common triggers of the condition. These are general descriptions of items that can trigger IBS. IBS is not
 contagious from person to person and researchers are actively trying to determine the cause of this disease. What is IBS (irritable bowel syndrome)? Irritable bowel syndrome (IBS) is a chronic relapsing gastrointestinal (mainly the
 large intestine or colon) disorder with signs and symptoms that may include: Abdominal cramping or pain Bloating Mucus in the
 stool Gassiness Altered bowel habits (alternating periods of diarrhea and
 constipation ) IBS is a chronic condition that can be triggered in individuals by certain items in their
 diet , medications and/or by other conditions such as stress. Some health care professional categorize and term IBS into one of four categories: Not all health care professionals recognize these four categories. Are stress and anxiety triggers for IBS? Stress and anxiety may be triggers for IBS and the development of recurrent symptoms. Chronic stress experienced early in life (less than age 18) may increase the chances of developing the condition. Moreover, people diagnosed with IBS can have stress or anxiety trigger symptoms, such as: Diarrhea Constipation Abdominal bloating Mucus defecation Feelings of incomplete bowel movements Are menstrual pain and IBS related? Some studies show that many women with IBS have worse symptoms during their menstrual periods. Although the mechanism is not clear, some gastrointestinal cells have receptors for estrogen and
 progesterone so that changes in the hormone levels during the
 menstrual cycle may trigger increasing IBS symptoms. Women are twice as likely to develop IBS as men. What foods in the diet trigger constipation in IBS? Any food or fluids that tend to dehydrate a person is likely to trigger constipation in people with irritable bowel syndrome. Foods that may promote constipation and should be avoided in an IBS diet include: Chocolate Dairy products such as milk and cheese (particularly those that contain lactose) Red meat Unripe bananas Items that contain
 caffeine if you are slightly dehydrated. Coffee, carbonated drinks and alcohol may lead to
 dehydration and constipation in IBS patients (and other people, too). Foods that help prevent constipation and should be included in an IBS diet include: Prunes Various types of beans Whole grain breads like rye bread Pears and fruits like kiwi Vegetables that will help boost
 fiber intake What foods in the diet trigger diarrhea in IBS? Several foods may play a role in developing diarrhea in people with IBS. Major categories of foods that are thought to contribute are those that contain
 fats (fatty meats, fatty dairy products, for example). Each individual is slightly different and may respond differently to food types. Consequently, dietitians and health care professionals who treat people with IBS often suggest that they keep a journal or diary to track those foods that cause diarrhea. Some foods that trigger diarrhea do so because they are ingested in large quantities; for example, a bite of a banana may not cause diarrhea, but eating a whole banana in some people with IBS may trigger diarrhea. Other foods that contain high levels of fructose,
 artificial sweeteners , high FODMAP foods, and fried foods may also trigger diarrhea. Broccoli, onions, cabbage and large helpings of beans may produce
 gas and increase the discomfort of diarrhea. Probiotics may help reduce the symptoms of diarrhea and gas in some individuals. What prescription or OTC drugs trigger IBS? Some drugs can trigger IBS symptoms resulting in colonic spasms, constipation and/or diarrhea. Such drugs include antibiotics (especially those administered over a long period of time),
 tricyclic antidepressants , for example,
 amitriptyline (
 Elavil ,
 Endep ),
 nortriptyline (
 Pamelor ), and
 doxepin , and medicines containing sorbitol (for example, some cough syrup preparations and common pain medicines like
 Advil gel capsules). Consequently, patients with the condition should check the ingredients, both active and inactive, for the presence of sorbitol as sorbitol is often listed as an "inactive" ingredient. What are the other IBS triggers? Other triggers of IBS are variable and differ from person to person. However, some other common triggers include: Lack of
 exercise Eating foods too quickly Eating while under some other stress such as driving or working Eating foods that are very hot or cold Chewing gum Keep a journal and record the symptoms and the activities you are doing when symptoms develop. This can help you determine your personal triggers for any symptoms. Researchers also suggest that changes in hormone levels and/or other acute illnesses such as infectious diarrhea may also trigger symptoms. Although a patient&amp;#39;s primary care physician may care for IBS patients, specialists in gastroenterology, immunology, psychiatry and dietary professionals may be consulted to help patients manage the condition. 
PREVENTION:  There are many different ways to help prevent you from triggering IBS symptoms such as: Eat a balanced diet with a moderate amount of fiber. Avoid extremes of food temperatures (very hot or cold foods). Do not eat while experiencing anxiety or under stressful conditions (for example, while working or driving). Avoid foods and drinks that may cause
 dehydration or diarrhea. Keep a journal to help identify those foods that are do or do not trigger symptoms. Try biofeedback, exercise, meditation, or
 yoga to reduce anxiety. Discuss medications you are taking that may be triggering symptoms with your doctor. Avoid those foods and drinks that are likely to increase or trigger symptoms. Avoid foods that increase
 intestinal gas (some legumes and vegetables like broccoli, cauliflower, cabbage, and Brussels sprouts). Talk to your doctor or health care professional about taking
 probiotics .</first>
</file1>