<file1>
<first>Problems With Dental Fillings
Introduction Tooth sensitivity following placement of a filling is fairly common. A tooth may be sensitive to pressure, air, sweet foods, or temperature. Usually, the sensitivity resolves on its own within a few weeks. During this time, avoid those things that are causing the sensitivity.
 Pain relievers are generally not required. Contact your dentist if the sensitivity does not subside within 2 to 4 weeks or if your tooth is extremely sensitive. He or she may recommend you use a desensitizing
 toothpaste , may apply a desensitizing agent to the tooth, or possibly suggest a
 root canal procedure. Pain Around Fillings There are several explanations for
 pain around
 fillings , each resulting from a different cause. Allergic Reactions to Amalgam (Silver) Fillings Allergic reactions to silver fillings are rare. Fewer than 100 cases have ever been reported, according to the ADA. In these rare circumstances, mercury or one of the metals used in an amalgam restoration is thought to trigger the allergic response. Symptoms of amalgam
 allergy are similar to those experienced in a typical skin
 allergy and include skin rashes and
 itching . Patients who suffer amalgam
 allergies typically have a medical or family history of
 allergies to metals. Once an
 allergy is confirmed, another restorative material can be used. Deteriorating Fillings Constant pressure from chewing, grinding or clenching can cause dental fillings to wear away, chip or crack. Although you may not be able to tell that your filling is wearing down, your dentist can identify weaknesses in your restorations during a regular check-up. If the seal between the tooth enamel and the filling breaks down, food particles and decay-causing bacteria can work their way under the filling. You then run the risk of developing additional decay in that tooth. Decay that is left untreated can progress to infect the dental pulp and may cause an
 abscessed tooth . If the filling is large or the recurrent decay is extensive, there may not be enough tooth structure remaining to support a replacement filling. In these cases, your dentist may need to replace the filling with a crown. New fillings that fall out are probably the result of improper cavity preparation, contamination of the preparation prior to placement of the restoration or a fracture of the restoration from bite or chewing
 trauma . Older restorations will generally be lost due to decay or fracturing of the remaining tooth. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry. Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson, MD, February 1, 2003.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2003
</first>
</file1>