<file1>
<first>Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis (PSC)
Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) definition Primary sclerosing cholangitis describes a disease process in which the bile 
ducts in the
 liver become inflamed, narrow and prevent bile from flowing 
properly. The liver produces bile to help digest food in the intestine. Bile from liver 
cells is transported through the bile ducts in the biliary tree, where it then 
enters the gallbladder. When food enters the small intestine, bile helps break 
down fat into fatty acids so that they can be absorbed and used by the body. 
This also helps in the absorption of fat soluble
 vitamins (A,D,E &amp; K). As the bile ducts become inflamed and narrow, bile cannot easily flow and 
begins to back up. This increases the pressure within the liver causing liver 
cells to become inflamed. Over time, this inflammation decreases blood flow 
within the liver, increasing the pressure in the portal vein. This eventually 
causes
 portal hypertension , a back up in the portal system causing veins that 
line the
 esophagus , stomach, and intestine to swell (varices) and the 
spleen to 
swell (
 splenomegaly ). As the disease progress, liver cells die and are replace by
 scar tissue . This 
is called
 cirrhosis and is associated with liver failure.
 
CAUSES:  The cause of PSC is unknown but it has an association with inflammatory bowel 
disease, especially
 ulcerative colitis . It is thought that there may be an 
autoimmune component to the disease, where the body's immune system attacks the 
bile ducts in the liver and causes them to become, inflamed and narrowed. 
RISKS:  The cause of PSC is unknown but it may be an autoimmune disease. PSC is more often seen in men in the 20-30 age range. There is an association 
with inflammatory bowel, disease, most often with
 ulcerative colitis and less 
commonly with
 Crohn's Disease . People with PSC who do not have
 inflammatory bowel disease , are more likely 
to be female and older.
 
SYMPTOMS:  In its early stages, PSC is asymptomatic (there are no symptoms). It is only when the person develops cholestasis because of the inability of bile to drain from the liver, do symptoms occur. These early symptoms include
 itching and
 fatigue . As the bilirubin levels in the blood become elevated,
 jaundice or a yellowish tinge to the skin, may occur. Since there may be liver inflammation, the person may complain of
 pain beneath the ribs in the right upper quadrant of the abdomen. The inability of the bile ducts to adequately drain reduces the flow of bile and there can be sludge formation in the bile ducts leading to the risk of infection. This may cause
 fever and increased
 pain . Because PSC is a progressive disease, symptoms may come and go over several months and years after the diagnosis is made. As the disease progresses, cirrhosis may occur leading to decreased
 liver function and its associated signs and symptoms. These include bleeding from the esophagus and stomach due to varices,
 ascites (fluid collection in the abdomen) because of poor protein production by the liver, easy bruising because of decreased platelets in the blood as because they are trapped in the
 enlarged spleen , and
 confusion due to hepatic
 encephalopathy because the liver cannot clear waste products of
 metabolism .
 
DIAGNOSIS:  PSC may remain silent for several years before symptoms arise. In patients with
 inflammatory bowel disease , the health care professional should have a high suspicion of the diagnosis because of the relationship between PSC and
 ulcerative colitis . Depending upon how far the disease has progressed and the effect on liver function, physical examination may reveal an
 enlarged liver , tenderness in the right upper quadrant beneath the ribs, and an enlarged spleen. The skin may be jaundiced or yellow and there can be evidence of scratching due to intense skin
 itching . In cirrhosis with end stage
 liver disease , there may be bruising of the skin, a swollen abdomen due to ascites or fluid caused by decreased protein production and decreased blood flow through the scarred liver, gastrointestinal bleeding, and mental confusion because of elevated ammonia levels in the bloodstream. Blood tests are helpful in assessing the liver and potential blockages within the bile ducts. These may include a
 complete blood count , INR/PTT (that measures blood clotting and the ability of the liver to produce clotting factors), liver function studies including AST, and ALT to assess liver inflammation, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin which measure the degree of bile blockage. Imaging tests may include
 ultrasound to look at the liver structure and magnetic resonance cholangiogram, an
 MRI of the abdomen that can assess the bile duct structure of the liver. If the diagnosis based on laboratory tests and imaging is still in doubt, a biopsy may be performed. A gastroenterologist or interventional radiologist will place a long, fine needle through the skin into the liver to obtain a piece of tissue. This is analyzed under a microscope by a pathologist to make the diagnosis.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of PSC is supportive, monitoring the progression of the disease and treating symptoms and complications as they arise. The only "cure" is liver transplantation, which may be an option when the disease progresses to cirrhosis and the liver function is affected. When some of the larger bile ducts become blocked, there is potential to open them with ERCP (endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography) and balloon dilatation and/or stent placement. A gastroenterologist passes a thin video endoscope into the mouth and threads it through the stomach into the duodenum and using a catheter, enters the bile ducts. Should a narrow duct or stricture be found, a balloon can be used to dilate the narrowing and a stent can be placed to keep the duct open. This is similar to how a cardiologist opens a blocked blood vessel in the heart In some cases, surgery may be an option to remove some scarred and blocked bile ducts and having more normal bile ducts reconnected bypassing scarred areas of the bile ducts.
 Medications There is no medication that is approved to treat primary sclerosing 
cholangitis, but medications may be used to control symptoms.
 Ursodiol (Actigal), 
also known as ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA), may improve liver function tests but 
has not been shown to increase survival and may be associated with complications 
like bleeding. While it is thought that PSC may be an autoimmune disease, 
immunosuppressive medications have not been shown to work. Itching is often treated with
 antihistamines including
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ),
 hydroxyzine (Atarax) and
 cyproheptadine (Periactin).
 Cholestyramine (
 Questran ,
 Questran Light ), 
a medication that helps bind bile salts may also be helpful. Should infection occur, treatment may require antibiotics. As the disease progresses, the damaged liver may not be able to help with the 
absorption of
 vitamins and nutrients from the intestine. Vitamins and other 
dietary and calorie
 supplements may be required to treat malnutrition.
 Liver transplant Liver transplant is the only "cure" for primary sclerosing cholangitis, but it is only recommended for patients whose disease has progressed to liver failure. The three-year U.S. survival rate for all transplants is 81%. The five-year survival rate is about 75%, according to the data from the Scientific Registry of Transplant Recipients. The goal of liver transplantation is to restore liver function. Though unlikely, it is possible for PSC to recur in the new liver. 
COMPLCATIONS:  PSC is a progressive disease, damaging the bile ducts and reducing the bile flow, ultimately leading to portal
 hypertension , cirrhosis, and liver failure. Some cancers are associated with primary sclerosing cholangitis including
 gallbladder cancer , hepatocellular
 cancer (
 cancer of the liver cells) and cholangiocarcinoma (
 cancer of the bile ducts). 
PREVENTION:  The specific cause of PSC is still unknown and therefore it seems not to be 
preventable. It is appropriate for patients with inflammatory bowel disease 
(especially ulcerative
 colitis ) and their health care professional to be aware of 
the relationship with primary sclerosing cholangitis, in case symptoms 
suggestive of the disease arise. However, PSC is seen in only 3% of patients 
with inflammatory bowel disease. What is the prognosis and life expectancy for a person with primary sclerosing cholangitis? Aside from liver transplantation, there are no effective treatments for PSC. In the US, studies suggest that life expectancy ranges from 9 to 18 years if the patient does not undergo liver transplantation. Using different population study models, researchers in the Netherlands concluded that life expectancy may be longer than 21 years from the time when the diagnosis is made. The prognosis and life expectance is poorer in older patients, those who have an enlarged liver and spleen, and in patients who are persistently jaundiced with elevated bilirubin levels in their bloodstream.
</first>
</file1>