<file1>
<first>Pulmonary Hypertension (Symptoms, Treatment Medications, and Life Expectancy)

ABOUT: Pulmonary
 hypertension is abnormally elevated pressure in the pulmonary circulation. The classification of primary and secondary pulmonary
 hypertension has been reclassified, and now is based on the main underlying disease or condition, symptoms, and treatment options for pulmonary
 hypertension . There are five classes or groups in this new classification system. Pulmonary hypertension can have no identifiable cause and is then referred to as idiopathic pulmonary hypertension (formerly called primary pulmonary hypertension). Pulmonary hypertension can be caused by certain
 drugs , diseases (
 scleroderma ,
 dermatomyositis , systemic
 lupus ), infections (
 HIV ,
 schistosomiasis ),
 liver disease ,
 valvular heart disease , congenital
 heart disease ,
 chronic obstructive lung disease (
 COPD ),
 blood clots in the
 lungs , and persistent pulmonary hypertension of the
 newborn (PPHN). Risk factors for pulmonary hypertension are
 liver failure, chronic lung disease, blood clotting disorders, and underlying diseases, such as scleroderma,
 dermatomyositis , and
 systemic lupus erythematosus . Signs and symptoms of pulmonary hypertension include
 shortness of breath , difficulty
 breathing with exertion, dizziness , rapid breathing, and rapid heart rate. Pulmonary hypertension is diagnosed by measuring the pulmonary pressures by either
 ultrasound of the heart (
 echocardiogram ) or right heart catheterization. The treatment for pulmonary hypertension can include oxygen, diuretics, blood thinners, medications that open the pulmonary arteries, and treatments for any underlying disease. The prognosis and life expectancy for a person with pulmonary hypertension is improving as newer treatment options become available; however, prognosis may depend on the underlying disease or condition that is causing pulmonary hypertension. What is pulmonary hypertension? Pulmonary hypertension occurs when the pressure in the pulmonary arteries increases abnormally. To help explain this condition further, here is how the pulmonary arteries work. The human body has two major sets of blood vessels that distribute blood from the heart to the body. One set pumps blood from the right heart to the lungs, and the other from the left heart to the rest of the body (systemic circulation). When a doctor or a nurse measures the blood pressure on a person&amp;#39;s arm, he/she is measuring the pressures in the systemic circulation. When these pressures are abnormally high, the person is diagnosed as having high blood pressure (systemic hypertension). The portion of the circulation that distributes the blood from the right side of the heart to the lungs and back to the left side of the heart is referred to as the pulmonary (lung) circulation. The
 right ventricle pumps blood returning from the body into the pulmonary arteries to the lungs to receive oxygen. The pressures in the lung arteries (pulmonary arteries) are normally significantly lower than the pressures in the systemic circulation. When pressure in the pulmonary circulation becomes abnormally elevated, it is referred to as pulmonary hypertension. This most commonly occurs when the pulmonary venous pressure is elevated, so called pulmonary venous hypertension (PVH). This pressure is transmitted back to the right side of the heart and the pulmonary arteries. The result is elevated pulmonary pressure throughout the pulmonary circulation. Some of this is a direct pressure transmission from the venous system backward and some can result from a reactive constriction of the pulmonary arteries. Less commonly, pulmonary hypertension results from constriction, or stiffening, of the pulmonary arteries that supply blood to the lungs, so called pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH). Whether it is pulmonary venous or pulmonary arterial hypertension, it becomes more difficult for the heart to pump blood forward through the lungs. This
 stress on the heart leads to enlargement of the right heart and eventually fluid can build up in the liver and other tissues, such as the in the legs. When the heart pumps blood it is referred to as systole, and when the heart fills with blood it is referred to as diastole. Normal pulmonary artery pressures range from an upper pressure (systolic) of 15-30 mmHg and a lower pressure (diastolic) of 4-12 mmHg. These values can be obtained approximately by and ultrasound of the heart (echocardiogram), and more accurately using a catheter to measure the pressures in the pulmonary circulation (right heart catheterization).
 Signs and
symptomsof pulmonary hypertension Many people with pulmonary hypertension may have no symptoms at all, especially if the disease is mild or in the early stages. Pulmonary hypertension symptoms may include: Signs of pulmonary hypertension may include: Which diseases are common in people with the condition? There are no clear statistical data on the prevalence of pulmonary hypertension. Since pulmonary hypertension is seen in multiple different conditions, it is perhaps better to look at the prevalence in each condition. It is fairly common in patients with heart failure,
 COPD , and
 sleep apnea . It occurs in 7% to 12% of patients with
 collagen vascular disease , and in less than 5% of
 HIV patients. Classification of primary and secondary pulmonary hypertension The conventional classification, primary (idiopathic) and secondary pulmonary hypertension, which also is called pulmonary arterial hypertension, has been reclassified and is now is based on the main underlying cause, characteristics, and treatments of pulmonary hypertension. These terms were updated in 2013.This system classifies the condition based on five classes. Pulmonary arterial hypertension including idiopathic previously referred to as primary pulmonary arterial hypertension),
 inherited pulmonary arterial hypertension, drug-induced pulmonary arterial hypertension Pulmonary arterial hypertension associated with the following: Connective tissue diseases like
 systemic lupus erythematosus , or scleroderma HIV Liver disease (elevated pressures in the liver,
 portal hypertension ); Congenital
 heart disease Schistosomiasis (a parasite infection that can clog the pulmonary arteries) Pulmonary Veno-occlusive disease (very rare) Persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn Pulmonary hypertension due to left
 heart disease ; an elevation of pulmonary arterial pressure because of increased pulmonary venous pressure, backing up into the lungs. This includes heart failure, valvular heart disease, and some congenital heart disease. Pulmonary hypertension due to lung diseases and/or hypoxia (low oxygen levels). This includes: Chronic obstructive lung disease (
 COPD ) Interstitial lung diseases Sleep apnea Chronic exposure to high altitudes Congenital lung disease Chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension (chronic blood clots to the lungs that don&amp;#39;t dissolve). Pulmonary hypertension with unclear multifactorial mechanisms, for example: Blood disorders (including hemolytic anemias) Systemic disorders(such as sarcoid) Metabolic disorders where cellular chemistry is abnormal (such as glycogen storage diseases) Tumors obstructing flow through the lungs
 
CAUSES:  There are many causes of pulmonary hypertension. Often more than one mechanism is involved in a specific disease process. This can also change as the disease progresses. Primary pulmonary hypertension has no identifiable underlying cause. This term is mainly a historical name and no longer used. The current term used to describe this condition is idiopathic pulmonary hypertension. Idiopathic pulmonary hypertension is more common in young people and more common in females than males. Idiopathic pulmonary hypertension unusually is an aggressive and often fatal form of pulmonary hypertension. Whereas it is known that the arterial obstruction is caused by a building up of the smooth muscle cells that line the arteries, the underlying cause of the disease has long been a mystery. A genetic cause of the familial form of idiopathic pulmonary hypertension, now referred to as Heritable PAH, has been discovered. It is caused by mutations in a gene called BMPR2. BMPR2 encodes a receptor (a transforming growth factor beta type II receptor) that sits on the surface of cells and binds molecules of the TGF-beta superfamily. Binding triggers conformational changes that are shunted down into the cell&amp;#39;s interior where a series of biochemical reactions occur, ultimately affecting the cell&amp;#39;s behavior. The mutations block this process. This discovery may provide a means of genetic diagnosis and a potential target for the therapy of people with familial (and possibly also sporadic) primary pulmonary hypertension.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  The first step in diagnosis of pulmonary hypertension is to clinically suspect it. This may be done as part of an evaluation of another disease that can lead to pulmonary hypertension (such as scleroderma or
 chronic obstructive pulmonary disease ), or based on patients and signs and symptoms as described above. Many tests, such as echocardiogram, may be performed that may give clues to the possibility of pulmonary hypertension. It is important that a Doppler study be performed with the echocardiogram, which enables the doctor to approximate the pulmonary artery pressures. These values are calculated based on the sound quality of the wave approaching and leaving the echocardiogram machine sensor/probe. This is based on the principle that explains why the sound of an approaching and then passing train varies. But the gold standard (the best test available) is right
 heart catheterization . This test entails inserting a catheter through the groin into the femoral vein, a large vein in the lower body (or under the collar bone or in the upper arm or neck into a large vein in the upper body) and advancing it to the right side of the heart. The catheter is connected to a device that can monitor and measure blood pressure in the right side of the heart and pulmonary arteries.
 During right heart catheterization, oxygen levels are measured during various positions of the catheter in the pulmonary circulation. This can help determine if a congenital or acquired hole has formed in the heart contributing to the elevated pulmonary pressures. Certain medications or activities can be administered or performed during the procedure to help with the assessment. Nitric oxide can be inhaled and in certain forms of PAH a dramatic improvement in pressures can occur suggesting specific treatment options such as the use of
 calcium channel blocker medication. Some patients have an exaggerated pulmonary pressure response to
 exercise and this too can be measured by utilizing arm
 exercise during the procedure. Titration of medications for pulmonary hypertension while the he catheter is in place can help monitor the response to treatment and assist in optimizing therapy. This can assist in providing individualized therapy for patients with this complex disease. Pulmonary hypertension is defined as the mean pulmonary artery blood pressure greater than 25 millimeter of mercury (mmHg) measured by right heart catheterization. The pressures can be much higher than 25 mmHg in some people. Therefore, the pulmonary hypertension can be labeled as mild, moderate, or severe based on the pressures. Mean arterial pressure calculated by multiplying the diagnostic pressure two times, and adding the systolic pressure to that number, and then divide by three (systolic is the upper number and diastolic is the lower number in measuring blood pressure). Normally, the pulmonary blood pressure is much lower pressure system than the systemic blood pressure (which is usually measured with a blood pressure cuff). Other tests available for diagnosing pulmonary hypertension include
 electrocardiogram (
 ECG ,
 EKG ),
 chest X-ray , and echocardiogram. An ECG may show some abnormalities that may be suggestive of right heart failure. Chest x-ray may also show enlargement of the chambers of the right heart. And echocardiogram (ultrasound of the heart) shows ultrasound images of the heart and can detect evidence of right heart failure and with the use of Doppler (as described previously) can estimate pressures in the pulmonary artery. These tests, in the right clinical setting, are very useful in diagnosing and managing pulmonary hypertension. Other tests may be useful in evaluating the conditions leading to secondary pulmonary hypertension. For example, a ventilation-perfusion scan (V/Q scan) can suggest blood clots in the pulmonary arteries or sometimes a
 CT scan of the chest can be used. The chest CT scan can detect pulmonary arterial clots, but also can show abnormalities of the lung tissue and surrounding structures that can contribute to pulmonary hypertension. Pulmonary function testing can be useful in diagnosing
 chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), and other lung diseases, and monitor disease progression. This test can be used to detect many aspects of lung function including airflow and evidence of obstruction, lung volumes, and the capacity for the lung to extract oxygen from the air. Sleep studies can confirm the diagnosis of
 sleep apnea and its severity and management options such as
 CPAP therapy.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment for pulmonary hypertension depends on the underlying cause. If left sided heart failure is the primary problem, then adequate treatment of the left heart failure by a cardiologist is the mainstay of treatment. In cases where hypoxia (low oxygen levels) due to any chronic lung disease, such as COPD, is the cause, then providing oxygen and appropriately treating the underlying lung disease by a lung doctor (pulmonologist) is the first step in treatment. In some patients, the elevated pressure may be related to obstructive sleep apnea syndrome (OSAS), and can be reduced with the use of a CPAP, (a device that delivers positive
 airway pressure during sleep). In conditions, such as scleroderma, which often can cause pulmonary hypertension, a
 rheumatologist is involved in the treatment program. Anticoagulation (thinning the blood) may be a treatment option if the main underlying cause is thought to be recurrent
 blood clot (chronic thromboembolic pulmonary hypertension). As indicated in previous section, referral to a specialty center may be warranted for a possible surgical removal of
 blood clot (thromboendarterectomy). For patients with primary pulmonary hypertension (those with no underlying cause), more advanced therapy may be attempted. These drugs have complex mechanisms, but in general they work by dilating (opening up) the pulmonary arteries and, therefore, by reducing the pressure in these blood vessels and some help prevent the excessive overgrowth of tissue in the blood vessels (that decrease remodeling of the vessels, as described previously). Besides constriction, PAH can result in an actual structural change of the pulmonary arteries, whether it is due to chronically elevated pressures or the disease itself, or a combination of the two is not completely clear. These drugs also can delay and in some cases reduce the degree of remodeling of the pulmonary arteries. Medications There are three major classes of drugs used to treat idiopathic pulmonary hypertension and pulmonary hypertension associated with collagen vascular diseases: 1) prostaglandins; 2) phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitor; and 3) endothelium-receptor antagonists. A unique drug, riociguat (Adempas), that is indicated for pulmonary hypertension due to chronic thromboembolic disease (CTEPH). The mechanism of action is different then the drugs above. It works by increasing the effect of nitric oxide causing increased pulmonary vasodilation. In rare cases,
 calcium channel blockers (
 CCBS ) may be of benefit. Currently, research is investigating the best ways to combine these medications for the optimal clinical outcomes. It should be noted that these medications are extremely expensive, costing of dollars per year. The companies that manufacture these medications often have programs to assist in funding. These more advanced therapies have also been used for other forms of pulmonary hypertension, however, no clinical studies have yet confirmed benefits in these situations. Is there a cure? Despite advances in various treatments, there is no cure for pulmonary hypertension. What is the
life expectancy? Generally, the prognosis of pulmonary varies depending on the underlying condition that is causing it. For idiopathic or familial pulmonary hypertension, the overall prognosis depends on the severity and whether treatment was instituted. The statistics show a survival of about 3 years in idiopathic pulmonary hypertension without any therapy. Some of the other factors may indicate even poorer prognosis which include severe symptoms, age of onset greater than 45 years, evidence of right sided heart failure, and failure to respond to treatment. For patients with idiopathic pulmonary hypertension who get started on treatment and respond to it, the prognosis is better. Studies are underway to determine optimal treatment regimens. Which types of doctors treat pulmonary hypertension? Generally, pulmonary physicians (pulmonologists) and cardiologists treat pulmonary hypertension. Depending on the cause, other physicians also may be involved such as sleep medicine doctors, rheumatologists, and perhaps even infectious disease specialists. Today, more health-care professionals in the community are becoming adept at managing pulmonary hypertension. However, it is reasonable to get a second opinion regarding management at a tertiary, university setting because the field of management of pulmonary artery hypertension is evolving rapidly.
</first>
</file1>