<file1>
<first>Pulmonary Fibrosis

ABOUT: Pulmonary fibrosis refers to scarring 
of the lung tissue (fibrosis of the lungs). Symptoms of pulmonary fibrosis include:
 Cough Shortness of breath or difficulty
 breathing Decreased
 exercise tolerance The most common type of pulmonary 
fibrosis is called idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis; its cause is not understood. A number of different medical 
conditions can also cause pulmonary fibrosis. Causes of pulmonary fibrosis can 
include:
 Environmental toxins Medications, chronic inflammation Infections Treatment options for pulmonary 
fibrosis are limited as the disease is progressive (worsening over time). The prognosis (outlook) is poor for 
pulmonary fibrosis. The survival (life expectancy) for most patients is less 
than 5 years. What is pulmonary fibrosis? "Fibrosis" is a term used to refer to scarring, so pulmonary fibrosis means scarring throughout the lungs. What is idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis? The definition of "idiopathic" is "of unknown cause;" thus idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is fibrosis (scarring) of the lungs without a known cause. IPF mostly affects middle-aged and older adults, and there is no cure. The progress of the disease varies from person to person, but often people diagnosed with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis live about three to five years following their diagnosis. While the cause of IPF is unknown, it is thought that genetics may be a factor. When more than one member of a family has IPF, the disease is referred to as familial idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. 
CAUSES:  Pulmonary fibrosis can be caused by many conditions including: Chronic inflammatory processes (
 sarcoidosis ,
 Wegener's granulomatosis ) Infections Environmental agents (
 asbestos , 
 silica, exposure to certain gases) Exposure to ionizing radiation (such as
 radiation therapy to treat tumors of the chest) Chronic conditions (
 lupus ,
 rheumatoid arthritis ) Certain medications In a condition known as
 hypersensitivity pneumonitis , fibrosis of the lung can develop following a heightened immune reaction to inhaled organic dusts or occupational chemicals. This condition most often results from inhaling dust contaminated with bacterial, fungal, or animal products. In some people, chronic pulmonary inflammation and fibrosis develop without an identifiable cause. Most of these people have a condition called idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) that does not respond to medical therapy, while some of the other types of fibrosis, such as nonspecific
 interstitial pneumonitis (NSIP), may respond to immune suppressive therapy. Synonyms (other names) for various types of pulmonary fibrosis that have been used in the past include
 chronic interstitial pneumonitis , Hamman-Rich syndrome, and diffuse fibrosing alveolitis.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Signs and symptoms of pulmonary fibrosis include: Shortness of breath (dyspnea), 
including shortness of breath with everyday activities Coughing (chronic, dry, hacking cough) Diminished
 exercise tolerance Fast, shallow breathing Fatigue /
 tiredness Weakness Chest discomfort Muscle and joint aches Loss of appetite Unexplained/unintended
 weight loss "
 Clubbing " of the tips of the fingers 
and toes (thickening of flesh under the nails, causing a widening and rounding 
appearance Symptoms vary depending on the cause of the pulmonary fibrosis. The severity of symptoms and the progression (worsening) of symptoms over time can vary. 
SYMPTOMS:  The most common form,
 idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis , has a slow and relentless progression. Early on in the disease, patients often complain of a dry, unexplained
 cough. Often, slow and insidious onset of shortness of breath can set in. With time, shortness of breath (dyspnea) worsens. Dyspnea initially occurs only with activity and is often attributed to
 aging .  
Over time, the dyspnea occurs with little or no activity. Eventually, the 
shortness of breath becomes disabling, limiting all activity and even occurring 
while sitting still. In rarer cases, the fibrosis can be rapidly progressive, 
with shortness of breath (dyspnea and disability occurring in weeks to months from the onset of the disease.  This form of pulmonary fibrosis has been referred to as Hamman-Rich syndrome. What are the stages of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis? Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis has been loosely staged and categorized as 
 mild, moderate, or severe, or early versus advanced. The staging is usually 
 based on pulmonary function tests, although these stages are considered 
 arbitrary. There are some newer proposed staging systems: Mortality risk scoring system: This is 
based on four predictors
 age, recent respiratory hospitalization, baseline 
forced vital capacity (FVC, a measure of lung function), and 24-week change in 
FVC. Taking these factors into account gives a score, which helps predict the 
expected 1-year probability of death. The GAP index: This staging system is 
based on four baseline variables
 gender (G), age (A) and  two lung physiology 
variables (P) (FVC plus the diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon monoxide, 
or D
 LCO ,). The GAP index uses these variables to categorize patients in three 
different stages, which estimate the individual risk for patients. Which specialties of doctors treat pulmonary fibrosis? If you have not been diagnosed with pulmonary fibrosis, but have any symptoms of the disease such as shortness of breath, chronic dry cough, diminished exercise tolerance, shallow breathing, chest discomfort, weakness, or other symptoms, see a doctor. If you have already been diagnosed with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis or probable idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis you should be monitored regularly, and you should referred for evaluation for lung transplantation, even if one is not needed at the immediate time. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Pulmonary fibrosis is suggested by a history of progressive (worsening over time) shortness of breath with exertion. Sometimes, during examination of the lungs with a stethoscope, the doctor can hear crackling sounds in the chest.  These crackles have a very characteristic sound and are very similar to the sound heard when Velcro is pulled apart.  These are often referred to as "
 Velcro crackles (or rales)". The
 chest X-ray may or may not be abnormal. However, a special X-ray test called a high resolution
 CT scan will frequently demonstrate abnormalities. This type of X-ray provides a cross-sectional picture of the lungs in very detailed resolution. The classic findings in idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis show diffuse peripheral scarring of the lungs with small bubbles (known as bullae) adjacent to the outer lining of the surface of the lung, often at the bases of the lungs. Lung function testing is distinctly abnormal. The volumes of the lungs may be reduced, as may the airflow, but the characteristic finding is a reduction in the diffusing capacity.  The diffusing capacity is a measure of the ability of the lungs to exchange gases (oxygen and carbon dioxide) into and out of the blood stream. The diagnosis 
of pulmonary fibrosis can be confirmed by lung biopsy. An open surgical biopsy, meaning that the chest wall must be surgically opened under general anesthesia to remove a portion of lung tissue, may be necessary to obtain enough tissue to make an accurate diagnosis.  The most common type of biopsy in this situation is by a
 video assisted thoracoscope .  
This involves placing a small tube into the chest cavity through which biopsy samples can be obtained.  Often, if the clinical situation is very classical in presentation, a biopsy may be unnecessary.  The biopsy specimen is examined microscopically by a pathologist to confirm the presence of fibrosis.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment options for idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis are very limited. There is no evidence that any medications can help this condition, since scarring is permanent once it has developed. Lung transplantation is the only therapeutic option available. At times, this diagnosis can be difficult to make even with tissue biopsy reviewed by pathologists with specific experience in this field.
 Research trials using different
 drugs that may reduce fibrous scarring are ongoing. Two drugs, nintedanib (Ofev) and
 pirfenidone (
 Esbriet , 
pirfenex, Pirespa) have offered some new hope. The results from two large studies show some slowing of progression of fibrosis, as well as some minor changes to tests of lung function. 
Unfortunately, the side effects from both of these drugs have resulted in some patients being unable to take 
this medication. Since some types of lung fibrosis can respond to
 corticosteroids (such as
 prednisone ) or other medications that suppress the body's immune system; these types of drugs sometimes 
are prescribed in an attempt to decrease the processes that lead to fibrosis. These drugs do not help idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. 
However, other causes of lung fibrosis may be responsive to immune suppression. The immune system is felt to play a central role in the development of many forms of pulmonary fibrosis. The goal of treatment with immune suppressive agents such as corticosteroids is to decrease lung inflammation and subsequent scarring. Responses to treatment are variable. Once scarring has developed, it is permanent. 
Conditions that improve with immune suppressive treatment probably are not idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. The toxicity and side effects of treatments can be serious. Therefore, patients with pulmonary fibrosis should be followed by a lung specialist experienced in this condition. The lung specialist will determine the need 
and duration of treatment, and will monitor the response to therapy along with any side effects. Only a minority of patients respond to corticosteroids alone, so other immune-suppressing medications are used in addition to corticosteroids especially if a different cause for
 interstitial lung disease is suspected. These include: cyclophosphamide (
 Cytoxan ) azathioprine (Imuran, Azasan) methotrexate (
 Rheumatrex ,
 Trexall ) penicillamine (
 Cuprimine ,
 Depen ) cyclosporine The anti-inflammatory medication
 colchicine has also been used with limited success. Other trials using drugs such as gamma
 interferon and
 mycophenolate mofetil (
 Cellcept ) have not met with much success in the treatment of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Pulmonary fibrosis causes decreased oxygen levels in the blood. A decrease in blood oxygen level (
 hypoxia ) can lead to elevated pressure in the pulmonary artery (the vessel that carries blood from the heart to the lungs to receive oxygen), a condition known as
 pulmonary hypertension , which can in turn lead to failure of the
 right ventricle of the heart. Therefore, patients with pulmonary fibrosis are frequently treated with supplemental oxygen 
therapy to prevent pulmonary
 hypertension . A consensus statement was issued revising the 2011 clinical practice guidelines for the treatment of 
idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. This statement was issued by 
one the largest respiratory physician groups in the world, including members from the United States, Europe, Japan, and Latin America. These recommendations are partially based on a recent study involving the use of prednisone, azathioprine, and 
N-acetylcysteine, so called triple therapy.  In this study, drug recipients had a 10 fold increase in the
 death rate than the placebo group.   These new guidelines therefore strongly discourage the use of triple therapy in 
idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. These guidelines also suggest that anticoagulation and anti
 GERD (gastroesophageal reflux disease) not be administered for 
idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis alone.  These medications should not be used without other medical indications in patients with 
idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis. Lastly, patients with idiopathic pulmonary 
fibrosis often have pulmonary
 hypertension as their disease progresses. There is currently no indication to use pulmonary hypertensive medication in these patients except oxygen in those with low oxygen levels.
 What about pulmonary rehabilitation for pulmonary fibrosis? Pulmonary rehabilitation along with medical care helps improve the quality of 
life of people who have chronic breathing problems such as pulmonary fibrosis. 
It involves: Exercise conditioning Nutrition counseling Patient education on managing the 
disease Breathing strategies Techniques to help conserve energy Counseling and/or support groups Patients diagnosed with idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis who are current smokers 
are encouraged to quit. It is also recommended that patients with IPF receive 
vaccination against
 influenza and pneumococcal infection. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis tends to be relentless in its progression. The complications that occur are a reflection of the failure of the pulmonary system.  
Shortness of breath, decreased activity, and signs of heart 
failure can occur.  As the lungs fail, the
 blood pressure in the lungs rises.  This results in increased work for and ultimately failure of the right side of the heart which pumps the blood through the lungs.  This failure can result in
 fatigue ,
 leg swelling , and overall fluid accumulation in the body.  The immobility and sluggish blood flow can increase the risks for
 blood clots .
 Depression is frequently seen in this devastating disease. 
PREVENTION:  Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis has an increased frequency in 
cigarette smokers. The cause of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis is unknown, and therefore prevention is difficult.  There is a rare form of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis 
is hereditary (runs in families). Work is being done at National Jewish Hospital in Denver, CO trying to identify markers for this disease. Unfortunately, since this is a fatal disease without effective therapy, there are many charlatans trying to take advantage of these stricken individuals and their families. There is no evidence that
 special diets or
 supplements or bowel preparations will help this disease in any way. What is the
prognosis and life expectancy for a person withpulmonary fibrosis? The prognosis of this disease is poor.  The survival of patients with 
pulmonary fibrosis 
is less than 5 years.  It is best to become involved with an academic center in the area where research on interstitial lung diseases is studied in order to receive the latest treatments.  These centers often are linked with a lung transplant program. Clinical trials are the best way of treating this disease at this time. Where can I get information to improve the quality of life for those with pulmonary fibrosis? For information quality of life and living with pulmonary fibrosis please visit
 Pulmonaryfibrosis.org .
</first>
</file1>