<file1>
<first>Pancreatitis (Acute, Chronic) Symptoms, Causes, Diet, and Treatment
What should I know about pancreatitis? What is the medical definition of pancreatitis? Pancreatitis is an inflammation of the pancreas. Of the many causes of pancreatitis, the most common are alcohol consumption and
 gallstones . About 210,000 cases of acute pancreatitis occur in the US every year. How do I know if I have pancreatitis? nausea and
 vomiting abdominal pain that may radiate to the back pain that worsens after eating chills and
 fever tenderness of the abdomen to touch lethargy and
 weakness How do I know if I have pancreatitis? Diagnosis of pancreatitis is generally with blood and imaging tests. How to treat pancreatitis Most cases of acute pancreatitis require hospitalization; however, treatment of chronic pancreatitis may be managed in an outpatient setting. 
COMPLCATIONS:  diabetes pancreatic cancer malnutrition infection pseudocyst formation What is the pancreatitis prognosis? Pancreatitis can range from a mild, self-limited disease to a condition with life-threatening complications.
 What is pancreatitis? Pancreatitis is a condition characterized by inflammation of the pancreas. The pancreas is an abdominal gland situated behind the stomach in the upper abdomen. The main function of the pancreas is to secrete hormones and enzymes that help with
 digestion and regulate blood
 sugar (glucose) metabolism. The
 digestive enzymes are released via the pancreatic duct into the small intestine where they are activated to help break down
 fats and proteins. The digestive hormones (
 insulin and glucagon) produced by the pancreas are released into the blood stream where they help regulate blood
 sugar levels. Pancreatitis is categorized as being either acute or chronic. Acute pancreatitis generally develops suddenly, and it is usually a short-term (a few days to weeks) illness that typically resolves with appropriate medical management. Chronic pancreatitis , which typically develops after multiple episodes of acute pancreatitis, is a long-term condition that can last for months or even several years. Pancreatitis is a condition that may be mild and self-limiting, though it can also lead to severe complications that can be life-threatening. The acute form of pancreatitis, in its most severe form, can have deleterious effects on many other body organs, including the
 lungs and kidneys.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Pancreatitis causes upper
 abdominal pain which can range from mild to severe. The
 pain may come on suddenly or it may develop gradually. Often, the pain will start or worsen after eating, which can also occur with gallbladder or ulcer pain.
 Abdominal pain tends to be the hallmark of acute pancreatitis. People with acute pancreatitis usually feel very ill. Signs and symptoms of acute pancreatitis may include: Abdominal pain that may radiate to the back Nausea and
 vomiting Worsening pain after eating Tenderness to touch of the abdomen Fever and chills Weakness and lethargy In chronic pancreatitis, abdominal pain also can be present, but it is often not as severe, and some people may not have any pain at all. Signs and symptoms of chronic pancreatitis may include: Abdominal pain Unintentional
 weight loss Foul smelling, oily
 stool 
CAUSES:  Normally, digestive enzymes released by the pancreas are not activated to break down fats and proteins until they reach the small intestine. However, when these digestive enzymes are activated while still in the pancreas, inflammation and local damage to the pancreas occurs leading to pancreatitis. The causes of pancreatitis include: Alcohol consumption Gallstones High
 triglyceride levels Abdominal injury or surgery Certain medications Exposure to certain chemicals Smoking Family history of pancreatitis Cystic fibrosis Pancreatic cancer Alcohol consumption and gallstones account for over 80% of all cases of pancreatitis in the US.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  There are a number of tests that alone, or in combination, will help establish the diagnosis of pancreatitis. Amylase and/or lipase levels are typically elevated in cases of acute pancreatitis. These blood tests may not be elevated in cases of chronic pancreatitis. These are usually the first tests performed to establish the diagnosis of pancreatitis, as these results are generally readily and quickly available. Other blood tests may be ordered, for example: liver and kidney function tests tests for infection, and tests for
 anemia . A CT (computed tomography) scan of the abdomen may be ordered to visualize the pancreas and to evaluate the extent of inflammation, as well as any of the potential complications that can arise from pancreatitis, such as bleeding or pseudocyst (a collection of fluid) formation. The
 CT scan may also detect gallstones (a major cause of pancreatitis) and other abnormalities of the biliary system. Ultrasound imaging can be used to look for gallstones and abnormalities of the biliary system. Because ultrasound imaging does not emit
 radiation , this modality is frequently the initial imaging test obtained in cases of pancreatitis. Depending on the underlying cause of pancreatitis and the severity of illness, additional testing may be ordered.
 
TREATMENT:  In most cases of acute pancreatitis, admission to the hospital is needed, whereas some cases of chronic pancreatitis can be managed in an outpatient setting. Depending on the underlying cause of pancreatitis, management may vary to address the specific cause. In general, however, the following treatment regimen will always be initiated for the treatment of pancreatitis. First-line treatment will involve: Fasting to help the pancreas to rest and recover. IV fluids to prevent
 dehydration while fasting Pancreatitis can be very painful, thus intravenous pain medication is often necessary. If pancreatitis is due to an obstructing gallstone, surgical intervention may be required to remove the gallstone and/or remove the gallbladder. Intervention may also be required to treat a pseudocyst or to remove part of the affected pancreas. If alcohol consumption is the cause of pancreatitis, abstinence from alcohol and an alcohol rehabilitation program will be recommended. If a medication or chemical exposure is found to be the cause of pancreatitis, then removal of the medication or offending exposure is recommended. If high
 triglycerides are the cause of pancreatitis, then your health-care professional may prescribe medication to decrease the patient&amp;#39;s
 triglyceride levels .
 Medications for pancreatitis In general, the above treatment regimen is the mainstay of pancreatitis management. Pain medication and medication to control nausea may also be prescribed. In cases of chronic pancreatitis, your health-care professional also may prescribe pancreatic enzyme
 supplements in order to help the body digest certain nutrients. Is there a diet for pancreatitis? For people with pancreatitis, low-fat meals that are high in nutrients is the recommended
 diet . Adequate fluid intake is also recommended to prevent
 dehydration .
 
COMPLCATIONS:  Pancreatitis can be a life-threatening illness with severe complications. Complications may include: Diabetes : Damage to the pancreas can lead to
 diabetes due to the disruption in the secretion of insulin. Pseudocyst formation: During acute pancreatitis, fluid and debris can collect in and around the pancreas. If rupture of this fluid-containing sac occurs, severe pain, infection and
 internal bleeding can result. Malnutrition: Damage to the pancreas can lead to a decrease or absence of digestive enzymes produced, which can affect the absorption of various nutrients. This may lead to malnutrition and unintentional
 weight loss . Pancreatic cancer : Chronic pancreatitis is a risk factor for the development of
 pancreatic cancer . Infection: Individuals with pancreatitis are at risk for the development of infection, which can lead to multi-organ failure,
 sepsis and ultimately death.
 
PREVENTION:  What is the prognosis for pancreatitis? The prognosis for pancreatitis depends on many different factors, such as the underlying condition causing pancreatitis, the severity of the pancreatitis, and the patient&amp;#39;s age and underlying medical problems. Patients with pancreatitis can experience everything from a brief self-limited illness with a full recovery to severe course of illness that can lead to life-threatening complications and death. If an individual has repeated episodes of acute pancreatitis, they may develop chronic pancreatitis, a lifelong condition that can lead to a decreased quality of life.
</first>
</file1>