<file1>
<first>Parkinson's Disease Symptoms, Causes, Stages, Treatment, and Life Expectancy
Parkinson's definition and disease facts Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is a neurodegenerative disorder, which leads to progressive deterioration of motor function due to loss of
 dopamine -producing brain cells. The cause of Parkinson’s Disease is unknown but researchers speculate that both genetic and environmental factors are involved; some genes have been linked to the disease. Primary symptoms include: Tremor Stiffness Slowness Impaired balance Shuffling gait later in the disease Some secondary symptoms include:
 Anxiety Depression Dementia Most people with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are diagnosed when they are 60 years old or older, but early-onset Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease also occurs. Several staging systems for Parkinson’s disease exist.The Parkinson&amp;#39;s Disease Foundation supports 5 stages, which include:
 Stage 1. Symptoms are mild and do not interfere with the person’s quality of life. Stage 2. Symptoms worsen and daily activities become more difficult and take more time to complete. Stage 3 is considered mid-stage Parkinson’s disease. The individual loses balance, moves more slowly, and falls are common. Symptoms impair daily activities, for example, dressing, eating, and brushing
 teeth . Stage 4. Symptoms become severe and the individual needs assistance walking and performing daily activities. Stage 5 is the most advanced stage of Parkinson’s disease. The individual is unable to walk and will need full time assistance with living. With proper treatment, most individuals with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease can lead long, productive lives. The life expectancy is about the same as people without the disease.
 What is Parkinson's disease? Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is the second most common neurodegenerative disorder and the most common movement disorder. Characteristics of Parkinson’s disease are progressive loss of muscle control, which leads to trembling of the limbs and head while at rest, stiffness, slowness, and impaired balance. As symptoms worsen, it may become difficult to walk, talk, and complete simple tasks. The progression of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease and the degree of impairment vary from person to person. Many people with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease live long productive lives, whereas others become disabled much more quickly. Complications of Parkinson’s such as falling-related injuries or
 pneumonia . However, studies of patent populations with and without Parkinson’s Disease suggest the life expectancy for people with the disease is about the same as the general population. Most people who develop Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are 60 years of age or older. Since overall life expectancy is rising, the number of individuals with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease will increase in the future. Adult-onset Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is most common, but early-onset Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease (onset between 21-40 years), and juvenile-onset Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease (onset before age 21) can occur. Descriptions of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease date back as far as 5000 BC. Around that time, an ancient Indian civilization called the disorder Kampavata and treated it with the seeds of a plant containing therapeutic levels of what is today known as levodopa. Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease was named after the British doctor James Parkinson, who in 1817 first described the disorder in detail as "shaking palsy."
 What are the early
signs and symptomsof Parkinson's disease? The primary symptoms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are all related to voluntary and involuntary motor function and usually start on one side of the body. Symptoms are mild at first and will progress over time. Some people are more affected than others are. Studies have shown that by the time that primary symptoms appear, individuals with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease will have lost 60% to 80% or more of the dopamine-producing cells in the brain. Characteristic motor symptoms include: Tremors: Trembling in fingers, hands, arms,
 feet , legs, jaw, or head. Usually
 tremors occur while resting, but not while involved in a task.
 Tremors may worsen when a person is excited, tired, or stressed. Rigidity: Stiffness of the limbs and trunk, which may increase during movement. Rigidity may produce muscle aches and
 pain . Loss of fine hand movements can lead to cramped handwriting (micrographia) and may make eating difficult. Bradykinesia: Slowness of voluntary movement. Over time, it may become difficult to initiate movement and to complete movement. Bradykinesia together with stiffness can also affect the facial muscles and result in an expressionless, "mask-like" appearance. Postural instability: Impaired or lost reflexes can make it difficult to adjust posture to maintain balance. Postural instability may lead to falls. Parkinsonian gait: Individuals with more progressive Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease develop a distinctive shuffling walk with a stooped position and a diminished or absent arm swing. It may become difficult to start walking and to make turns. Individuals may freeze in mid-stride and appear to fall forward while walking.
 What are the later secondary
signs and symptomsof Parkinson's disease? While the main symptoms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are movement-related, progressive loss of muscle control and continued damage to the brain can lead to secondary symptoms. These secondary symptoms vary in severity, and not everyone with Parkinson&amp;#39;s will experience all of them, and may include: Anxiety , insecurity, and
 stress Confusion Memory loss Dementia (more common in the elderly) Constipation Depression Difficulty swallowing and excessive salivation Diminished sense of smell Increased
 sweating Erectile dysfunction (
 ED ) Skin problems Slowed, quieter speech, and monotone voice Urinary frequency/urgency
 What
causesParkinson's disease? A substance called dopamine acts as a messenger between two brain areas - the substantia nigra and the corpus striatum - to produce smooth, controlled movements. Most of the movement-related symptoms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are caused by a lack of dopamine due to the loss of dopamine-producing cells in the substantia nigra. When the amount of dopamine is too low, communication between the substantia nigra and corpus striatum becomes ineffective, and movement becomes impaired; the greater the loss of dopamine, the worse the movement-related symptoms. Other cells in the brain also degenerate to some degree and may contribute to non-movement related symptoms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Although it is well known that lack of dopamine causes the motor symptoms of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, it is not clear why the dopamine-producing brain cells deteriorate. Genetic and pathological studies have revealed that various dysfunctional cellular processes, inflammation, and
 stress can all contribute to cell damage. In addition, abnormal clumps called Lewy bodies, which contain the protein alpha-synuclein, are found in many brain cells of individuals with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. The function of these clumps in regards to Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is not understood. In general, scientists suspect that dopamine loss is due to a combination of genetic and environmental factors. What are the 5 stages of Parkinson's disease? Researchers may disagree on the number of stages of Parkinson’s disease (range from 3-5 stages). However, they all agree the disease is a progressive disease with symptoms that usually occur in one stage may overlap or occur in another stage. The stage increase in number value for all stage naming systems reflect the increasing severity of the disease. The five stages used by the Parkinson’s Foundation are: Stage 1: mild symptoms (tremors and/or movement symptoms like swinging arm while walking) do not interfere with daily activities and occur on one side of the body. Stage 2: Symptoms worsen with walking problems and both sides of the body affected. Stage 3: Main symptoms worsen with loss of balance and slowness of movement. Stage 4: Severity of symptoms require help; usually person cannot live alone. Stage 5: Caregiver needed for all activities; patient may not be able to stand or walk and may be bedridden and may also experience
 hallucinations and
 delusions .
 Is Parkinson's disease inherited (genetic)? In most people with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is idiopathic, which means that it arises sporadically with no known cause. However, some of people diagnosed with Parkinson&amp;#39;s also have family members with the disease. By studying families with hereditary Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, scientists have identified several genes that are associated with the disorder. Studying these genes helps understand the cause of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease and may lead to new therapies. So far, five genes have been identified that are definitively associated with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Several other chromosome regions and the genes GBA (glucosidase beta acid), SNCAIP (synuclein alpha interacting protein), and UCHL1 (ubiquitin carboxyl-terminal esterase L1) may also be linked to Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Who gets Parkinson's disease? Age is the largest risk factor for the development and progression of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Most people who develop Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease are older than 60 years of age. Men are affected about 1.5 to 2 times more often than women. A small number of individuals are at increased risk because of a family history of the disorder. Head
 trauma , illness, or exposure to environmental toxins such as pesticides and herbicides may be a risk factor.
 What tests diagnose Parkinson's disease? An early and accurate diagnosis of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is important in developing good treatment strategies to maintain a high quality of life for as long as possible. However, there is no test to diagnose Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease with certainty (except after the individual has passed away). A diagnosis of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease - especially in the early phase - can be challenging due to similarities to related movement disorders and other conditions with Parkinson-like symptoms. Individuals may sometimes be misdiagnosed as having another disorder, and sometimes individuals with Parkinson-like symptoms may be inaccurately diagnosed as having Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. It is therefore important to re-evaluate individuals in the early phase on a regular basis to rule out other conditions that may be responsible for the symptoms. A neurologist who specializes in movement disorders will be able to make the most accurate diagnosis. An initial assessment is made based on medical history, a neurological exam, and the symptoms present. For the medical history, it is important to know whether other family members have Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, what types of medication have been or are being taken, and whether there was exposure to toxins or repeated head trauma previously. A neurological exam may include an evaluation of coordination, walking, and fine motor tasks involving the hands. Several guidelines have been published to assist in the diagnosis of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. These include the Hoehn and Yahr scale and the Unified Parkinson&amp;#39;s Disease Rating Scale. Tests are used to measure mental capacity, behavior, mood, daily living activities, and motor function. They can be very helpful in the initial diagnosis, to rule out other disorders, as well as in monitoring the progression of the disease to make therapeutic adjustments. Brain scans and other laboratory tests are also sometimes carried out, mostly to detect other disorders resembling Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. The diagnosis of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is more likely if: What is the treatment for Parkinson's disease? There is currently no treatment to cure Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Several therapies are available to delay the onset of motor symptoms and to ameliorate motor symptoms. All of these therapies are designed to increase the amount of dopamine in the brain either by replacing dopamine, mimicking dopamine, or prolonging the effect of dopamine by inhibiting its breakdown. Studies have shown that early therapy in the non-motor stage can delay the onset of motor symptoms, thereby extending quality of life. The most effective therapy for Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is levodopa (
 Sinemet ), which is converted to dopamine in the brain. However, because long-term treatment with levodopa can lead to unpleasant side effects (a shortened response to each dose, painful cramps, and involuntary movements), its use is often delayed until motor impairment is more severe. Levodopa is frequently prescribed together with
 carbidopa (Sinemet), which prevents levodopa from being broken down before it reaches the brain. Co-treatment with carbidopa allows for a lower levodopa dose, thereby reducing side effects. In earlier stages of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, substances that mimic the action of dopamine (dopamine agonists), and substances that reduce the breakdown of dopamine (monoamine oxidase type B (MAO-B) inhibitors) can be very efficacious in relieving motor symptoms. Unpleasant side effects of these preparations are quite common, including swelling caused by fluid accumulation in body tissues, drowsiness,
 constipation ,
 dizziness , hallucinations, and
 nausea . For some individuals with advanced, virtually unmanageable motor symptoms, surgery may be an option. In
 deep brain stimulation (DBS), the surgeon implants electrodes to stimulate areas of the brain involved in movement. In another type of surgery, specific areas in the brain that cause Parkinson&amp;#39;s symptoms are destroyed. An alternative approach that has been explored is the use of dopamine-producing cells derived from
 stem cells . While stem cell therapy has great potential, more research is required before such cells can become of therapeutic value in the treatment of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. In addition to medication and surgery, general lifestyle changes (rest and
 exercise ), physical therapy, occupational therapy, and speech therapy may be beneficial.
 What is the prognosis and life expectancy for Parkinson's disease? The severity of Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease symptoms and signs vary greatly from person to peson, and it is not possible to predict how quickly the disease will progress. Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease itself is not a fatal disease, and the average life expectancy is similar to that of people without the disease. Secondary complications, such as
 pneumonia , falling-related injuries, and choking can lead to death. Many treatment options can reduce some of the symptoms and prolong the quality of life. Can Parkinson's disease be prevented? Scientists currently believe that Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is triggered through a complex combination of genetic susceptibility and exposure to environmental factors such as toxins, illness, and trauma. Since the exact causes are not known, Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease is at present not preventable. What other conditions resemble Parkinson's disease? In its early stages, Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease can resemble a number of other conditions with Parkinson-like symptoms known as Parkinsonism. These conditions include: Multiple system atrophy P
 rogressive supranuclear palsy C
 orticobasal degeneration , Lewy body dementia S
 troke E
 ncephalitis (inflammation of the brain) Head trauma Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease and primary lateral sclerosis can also be mistaken for Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease. Other similar conditions include essential
 tremor , dystonic tremor, vascular Parkinsonism, and drug-induced Parkinsonism. How can people learn to cope with Parkinson's disease? Although Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease progresses slowly, it will eventually affect every aspect of life - from social engagements, work, to basic routines. Accepting the gradual loss of independence can be difficult. Being well informed about the disease can reduce anxiety about what lies ahead. Many support groups offer valuable information for individuals with Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease and their families on how to cope with the disorder. Local groups can provide emotional support as well as advice on where to find experienced doctors, therapists, and related information. It is also very important to stay in close contact with health care professionals to monitor the progression of the disease and to adjust therapies to maintain the highest quality of living.
</first>
</file1>