<file1>
<first>Mumps
Mumps (parotitis) facts What is mumps? Mumps is a vaccine-preventable viral infection transmitted by and affecting only humans. While the salivary glands (especially the parotid gland at the sides of the cheeks) are well known to be involved during a mumps infection, many other organ systems may also experience effects of the virus infection. There is no cure for mumps, but the illness is of short duration (seven to 10 days) and resolves spontaneously. Prior to the introduction of mumps immunization, the highest incidence of new cases of mumps was reported in the late winter to early spring. What is the history of mumps? Medical historians believe that documentation of a clinical illness consistent with mumps dates back to Greco-Roman times. The first effective vaccine against mumps was introduced in 1948 and used from 1950-1978. Unfortunately, this vaccine strain had limited long-term immune memory effectiveness. The current strain used in the United States and worldwide provides 88% long-term immunity. The current childhood mumps immunization schedule recommends vaccination at 12-15 months old and a booster at 4-6 years of age. The mumps vaccine is commonly administered as part of a combination vaccine (MMR) also providing protection against
 measles and
 rubella (
 German measles ). Prior to the routine administration of the MMR vaccine, approximately 186,000 cases per year were documented in the United States. With immunization, that number has fallen to 2,015 cases in 2015. Recently, there have been outbreaks of mumps in Washington state. 
CAUSES:  Is mumps
contagious? How is mumps
transmitted? Mumps virus is a single strand of RNA housed inside a two-layered envelope that provides the virus its characteristic immune signature. Only one type of mumps virus has been demonstrated to exist (in contrast to the many virus types that can cause the
 common cold ). Mumps is highly contagious on the order of magnitude of both
 influenza and rubella (German measles). It is, however, less contagious than measles and
 varicella (
 chickenpox ). It is transmitted only from human to human. Mumps has a rapid spread among members living in close quarters. The virus most commonly is spread directly from one person to another via respiratory droplets expelled during
 sneezing or
 coughing . Less frequently, the respiratory droplets may land on fomites (sheets, pillows, clothing) and then be transmitted via hand-to-mouth contact after touching such items. Animals cannot contract or spread mumps. What is the incubation period for mumps? There is a 14-18-day period between contracting the mumps virus and onset of symptoms and signs. Viral shedding is short lived and a patient should be isolated from other susceptible individuals for the first five days following the onset of swelling of the salivary (parotid) glands. What is the contagious period for mumps? The highest likelihood of spreading mumps covers the period of two days before the onset of symptoms and the first five days of parotid gland swelling and tenderness. How long does mumps last? Routine cases of mumps last approximately seven to 10 days. 
RISKS:  What does mumps look like? The unique physical exam findings seen in those with mumps is swelling and tenderness of one or both parotid glands on the sides of the face. The parotid glands are imbedded into the cheeks in front of the ear where a large set of sideburns would be. Less commonly affected are the salivary glands located under the lower jaw (mandible) or under the tongue (sublingual salivary glands). 
SYMPTOMS:  Nonspecific symptoms of low-grade
 fever ,
 headache , muscle aches (
 myalgia ), reduced appetite, and malaise occur during the first 48 hours of mumps infection. Parotid gland swelling characteristically is present on day three of illness. (The parotid gland is a salivary gland located anterior to the ear and above the angle of the jaw -- imagine a large set of sideburns.) The parotid gland is swollen and tender to touch, and referred
 pain to the ear may also occur. Parotid gland swelling may last up to 10 days, and adults generally experience worse symptoms than children. Approximately 95% of individuals who develop symptoms of mumps will experience tender inflammation of their parotid glands. Interestingly about 15%-20% of mumps cases have no clinical evidence of infection, and 50% of patients will have only nonspecific respiratory symptoms and not the characteristic description above. Adults are more likely to experience such a subclinical or respiratory-only constellation of symptoms while children between 2-9 years of age are more likely to experience the classic presentation of mumps with parotid gland swelling. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of mumps is primarily one of clinical acumen. Laboratory studies are generally done to support the clinical impression. The purpose of these laboratory studies is to exclude other
 viruses that may give a similar clinical presentation as well as to exclude very infrequent similarly presenting parotid gland enlargement (for examples,
 salivary gland cancer ,
 Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome , IgG-4 related disease,
 sarcoidosis , side effects of
 thiazide diuretics , etc.). 
TREATMENT:  The mainstay of treatment (regardless of age range) is to provide comfort for this self-limited disease. Taking analgesics (acetaminophen, ibuprofen) and applying warm or cold packs to the swollen and inflamed salivary gland region may be helpful. 
TREATMENT:  Most cases of mumps are not complicated and thus may be managed by health care professionals such as pediatricians, internists, or family practice doctors. An infectious-disease specialist may need to be consulted for unusual health circumstances or medically complicated patients.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  There are four serious health complications of mumps:
 meningitis (infection of the spinal fluid which surrounds the brain and spinal cord), encephalitis (infection of the brain substance), deafness, and orchitis (infection of the testicle/testicles). All four complications may occur without the patient experiencing the classic involvement of the parotid gland. Less frequent health complications of mumps infection include
 arthritis , infection of the pancreas, infection of the
 myocardium (heart muscle), and neurological conditions (for example, facial palsy,
 Guillain-Barré syndrome , etc.).
 
PREVENTION:  Is there a vaccine for mumps? Prior to the start of mumps vaccination in 1948, outbreaks during the winter/spring would commonly affect young schoolchildren with secondary spread to other family members not yet immune. Until an effective vaccine program was introduced, isolation of the infected individual was the only public health control option. The current MMR strain used in the United States and other developed countries was licensed in 1967. Another strain is more commonly used in developing countries. Both strains provide approximately 88% immunity following the two-vaccination schedule detailed below. A single dose of mumps vaccine provides immunity to only 78% of recipients. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) recommends a combination vaccine (MMR) to children at 12 to 15 months of age with a booster dose at 4 to 6 years of age. During periods of possible mumps outbreaks, the booster dose may be administered after a minimum of 28 days following the initial immunization. The MMR immunization is designed to prevent measles, mumps, and rubella (German measles). Adults born after 1956 should receive at least one MMR vaccination. Those born prior to 1956 are generally found to have acquired natural immunity and no vaccination is necessary. More common side effects of the MMR vaccine include stinging/burning at the injection site, mild fever, and mild skin
 rash . The fever and skin
 rash most commonly develop five to 12 days postvaccination and occur more commonly after the first vaccination. Some recipients of the vaccine will note mild enlargement and tenderness of local (for example, neck)
 lymph nodes . It should be noted that these relatively common side effects are considerably less severe than acquiring any of the three illnesses the MMR vaccine is designed to prevent. In extremely rare situations, more severe reactions affecting the nervous system, gastrointestinal system, and digestive organs, the skin, and others may occur. Who should not get vaccinated with the MMR? A very small population should not receive the MMR vaccine. These include individuals with a compromised immune system (
 HIV/AIDS ,
 cancer , those receiving more than two continuous weeks of oral steroids) or who are
 allergic to any component of the vaccine, including gelatin or
 neomycin . MMR
 vaccines are very unlikely to produce a severe reaction to those who are egg white allergic. Daily use of inhaled steroids (such as those used to control certain pulmonary diseases such as
 asthma ,
 COPD , etc.) is not a contraindication to the MMR vaccine. Patients with a mild illness (for example, the
 common cold ) may safely receive the MMR vaccine.
 Conception should be avoided until at least 28 days following vaccination. Multiple international studies have not demonstrated any causative relationship between administration of the MMR vaccine and the development of
 autism , disproving previous erroneous theories. What is the prognosis of a mumps infection? Mumps is generally a benign self-limited disease that produces lifelong immunity. Severe medical side effects are extremely rare; more common complications (though still relatively rare) are listed above. Non-immune women who contract mumps during the
 first trimester of their
 pregnancy have an increased rate of
 miscarriage , but infants carried to term have no higher risk for
 congenital malformations . Where can people find more information on mumps? The CDC web site (
 http://www.cdc.gov ) provides an excellent resource for the disease and vaccination program for mumps and many other common infectious diseases. In addition, the American Academy of Pediatrics (
 http://www.aap.org ) also provides valuable information for the medically trained and nonmedically trained individual. Can people get mumps twice? Since there is only a single mumps virus in existence, lifelong immunity is generally acquired after a mumps infection. Ways to document mumps immunity include Mumps immunity after complete vaccination is approximately 88%. A boost in immunity occurs when exposed to an individual with an active case of mumps.
</first>
</file1>