<file1>
<first>Pelvic Exam
What is a pelvic exam? A pelvic exam is an examination of a woman's genital system. A pelvic exam 
examines organs including the vulva, vagina, uterus, ovaries, and Fallopian 
tubes; the bladder and rectum are also usually included in the exam. A pelvic 
exam involves visual examination of the external genitalia and an internal 
visual exam of the vaginal walls and cervix using a speculum to open the vaginal 
canal. It also involves palpation, or examination by feeling the size and shape 
of the pelvic organs. Whyis a pelvic exam performed? A pelvic exam may be performed as part of a regular checkup (or wellness visit) or can be done to investigate symptoms such as abnormal bleeding, unusual vaginal discharge, or
 pain . Pelvic exams are also done during
 pregnancy check-ups. Pelvic exams are necessary for
 cervical cancer screenings, in which a sample of cells from the uterine opening (cervix) are taken for microscopic examination (known as the
 Pap smear or
 Pap test ). What
conditionscan be evaluated with a pelvic exam? A pelvic exam can be useful in the evaluation and diagnosis of multiple 
conditions. Some examples include: sexually-transmitted infections, such 
as
 gonorrhea ,
 syphilis ,
 Trichomonas ,
 human papillomavirus , and
 Chlamydia bacterial vaginosis yeast infections urinary tract infections abnormal uterine bleeding fibroid tumors ovarian cysts infertility polycystic ovary syndrome rectal bleeding endometriosis tumors of the genital organs genital warts pregnancy ectopic pregnancy How is a pelvic exam performed? There is no special preparation needed for a pelvic exam. A pelvic exam is 
performed in the doctor's office and takes only a few minutes. The woman 
undergoing the exam lies on an examination table, covered with a sheet. The 
doctor and/or nurse will help the woman get in position for the speculum 
examination, which involves bending the knees and placing the
 feet in metal 
supports on the side of the exam table. The speculum is a metal or
 plastic device that is inserted into the vagina to allow the vaginal walls and cervix to 
be seen. A small sample of the cells of the cervix is taken by a brush or a 
small spatula for the Pap test. While there may be some discomfort, a pelvic 
exam should not be painful. A bimanual exam is another component of the pelvic exam. This involves 
placement of two fingers inside the vaginal canal and pressing on the lower 
abdomen with the other hand to palpate (feel) the pelvic organs. A rectal exam 
is also often performed at this time. The bimanual exam may reveal enlarged 
organs or tissue masses.
</first>
</file1>