<file1>
<first>Pendred Syndrome
What is Pendred syndrome? Pendred syndrome is a
 genetic disorder that causes early
 hearing loss in children. It also can affect the
 thyroid gland and sometimes may affect a 
person's balance. The syndrome is named after Vaughan Pendred, the physician who 
first described individuals with the disorder. Children who are born with Pendred syndrome may begin to 
lose their
 hearing at birth or by the time they are three years old. The hearing 
loss is progressive, which means that a child will have less hearing over time. Some 
individuals may become totally deaf. The loss of hearing often happens suddenly and in 
stages. Sometimes, after a sudden decrease in hearing, a person's hearing will 
nearly return to its previous level. Almost all people with Pendred syndrome 
have bilateral
 hearing loss , or hearing loss in both ears. The hearing loss 
often is greater in one ear 
than in the other. How does Pendred syndrome affect other parts of the body? Pendred syndrome can affect the
 thyroid by causing it to 
grow too large. An enlarged thyroid gland also is called a goiter. The thyroid is 
a small, butterfly-shaped gland in the front of your neck, just above your collarbones. The thyroid plays a major 
role in how your body uses energy from food. In children, the thyroid is 
important for normal growth and development. Children with Pendred syndrome, 
however, rarely have problems growing and developing properly even if their 
thyroid is affected. Roughly 60 percent of individuals with Pendred syndrome will develop a goiter 
in their lifetime. Most people with Pendred syndrome are in their
 teens or 
twenties before they develop a goiter. If a goiter becomes large, a person may 
have problems
 breathing and swallowing. A health professional is needed to check 
a person's goiter over time and decide what treatment is necessary. Pendred syndrome also may affect the
 vestibular system , 
which controls balance. About 40 percent of individuals with Pendred syndrome 
will show some
 vestibular weakness when their balance system is tested. However, 
the brain is 
very good at making up for a weak vestibular system, and most children and 
adults with Pendred syndrome do not have a problem with their balance or have 
difficulty doing routine tasks. Some
 babies with Pendred syndrome may start
 walking later than other babies. It is not known why some individuals with Pendred syndrome develop a goiter 
or have balance problems and others do not.
 
CAUSES:  Pendred syndrome can be caused by changes, or 
mutations, to a gene known as SLC26A4 (also referred to as the PDS gene) on 
 chromosome 7. Because it is a recessive trait, a child needs to inherit two 
mutated SLC26A4 genes—one from each parent—to have Pendred syndrome. The child's 
parents do not need to have Pendred syndrome to be a carrier of a mutation in 
the SLC26A4 gene. Couples who are concerned that they might be able to pass Pendred syndrome on 
to their children may seek genetic testing. A possible sign that a person may be 
a carrier of a mutated SLC26A4 gene is a family history of early hearing loss. 
Another sign is a family member who has both a goiter and hearing loss. A 
mutation in the SLC26A4 gene can be determined by genetic testing that uses a 
blood sample. The decision to have a genetic test is complex. Most people receive 
assistance from a genetic counselor trained to help them weigh the medical, 
emotional, and ethical considerations. A genetic counselor is a health 
professional who provides information and support to individuals and families 
who have a
 genetic disease or who are at risk for such a disease.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  A physician called an otolaryngologist or a 
clinical geneticist will consider a person's hearing, inner ear structures, and 
sometimes the thyroid in diagnosing Pendred syndrome. The specialist will 
evaluate the timing, amount, and pattern of hearing loss. He or she will ask 
questions such as: "When did the hearing loss start?,"
 "Has it worsened over 
time?," and
 "Did it happen suddenly or in stages?." Early hearing loss is one of 
the most common characteristics of Pendred syndrome; however, this symptom alone 
does not mean a child has the condition. The specialist uses inner ear imaging techniques known 
as
 magnetic resonance imaging (
 MRI ) or computed tomography (CT or CAT) to look for two key 
characteristics of Pendred syndrome. One characteristic might be a cochlea with 
too few turns. The cochlea is the spiral-shaped part of the inner ear that 
converts sound into electrical signals that are sent to the brain. A healthy 
cochlea has two-and-a-half turns, but the cochlea of a person with Pendred 
syndrome may have only one-and-a-half turns. A second characteristic of Pendred syndrome is enlarged 
vestibular aqueducts (see figure). The vestibular aqueduct is a bony canal that 
runs from the vestibule (a part of the inner ear between the cochlea and the 
semicircular canals) to the inside of the skull. Inside the vestibular aqueduct 
is a fluid-filled tube called the endolymphatic duct, which ends at a balloon-shaped 
endolymphatic sac. When the vestibular aqueduct is enlarged, the endolymphatic 
duct and sac grow large with excess fluid in comparison to their normal sizes. 
The function of the vestibular aqueduct is not well understood. Picture of the Inner Ear When screening for Pendred syndrome, it is not recommended to test the blood 
for
 thyroid hormone because the amount usually is the same whether someone has 
Pendred syndrome or not. Some people may receive a "perchlorate washout test," a 
test that determines whether the thyroid is functioning properly. Although this 
test is probably the best test for determining thyroid function in Pendred 
syndrome, it is not used often and may be replaced by genetic testing. 
Individuals who have a goiter may be referred to an endocrinologist, a doctor 
who specializes in glandular disorders, to determine whether the goiter is due 
to Pendred syndrome or to another cause. Goiter is a common feature of Pendred 
syndrome, but many individuals who develop a goiter do not have Pendred 
syndrome. Conversely, many people who have Pendred syndrome never develop a 
goiter.
 How common is Pendred syndrome? Scientists estimate that about two to three 
children out of every 1,000 have early hearing loss, and about half of these 
cases are inherited. The SLC26A4 gene, which causes Pendred syndrome, accounts 
for about five to ten percent of hereditary hearing loss. As researchers gain 
more insight about the syndrome and its features, they hope to improve doctors' 
ability to detect and diagnose the disorder in people. Can Pendred syndrome be treated? Treatment options are available for individuals with 
Pendred syndrome. Because the syndrome is inherited and can involve thyroid and 
balance problems, many specialists may be involved in treatment. The treatment 
team may include a primary care physician, an 
 audiologist, an endocrinologist, a clinical geneticist, a genetic counselor, an 
otolaryngologist, and a speech-language pathologist. To reduce the likelihood of progression of hearing loss, 
individuals with Pendred syndrome should: avoid contact sports that might lead to
 head injury ;
 wear head protection when engaged in activities that might lead to head injury 
(such as bicycle riding or skiing); and
 avoid situations that can lead to
 barotrauma (extreme, 
rapid changes in pressure), such as scuba diving or hyperbaric oxygen treatment. Pendred syndrome cannot be cured. However, the medical team can help parents 
and individuals make informed choices about treatment options. They also can 
help them prepare for increased hearing loss and other possible long-term 
consequences of the syndrome. Children with Pendred syndrome should start early treatment to learn skills 
that will help them communicate, such as learning sign language or cued speech 
or how to use a hearing aid. Most 
individuals with Pendred syndrome will have hearing loss significant enough to 
be considered eligible for a cochlear implant. A cochlear implant is an 
electronic device that is surgically inserted into the cochlea. A cochlear 
implant does not restore or create normal hearing. Instead, a cochlear implant 
helps a person develop a new way of understanding speech. Children over 12 
months of age as well 
as adults are eligible to receive an implant. Individuals with Pendred syndrome who develop a goiter need to have it 
checked regularly. The goiter in Pendred syndrome is unusual because the thyroid 
is making the right amount of thyroid hormone but it is growing in size. Such a 
goiter often is called a euthyroid 
goiter.
 What research is being conducted? NIDCD has been working to understand 
hearing loss caused by inherited syndromes such as Pendred syndrome as well as 
from other causes. Researchers also are looking carefully at the characteristics 
of the disorder and how the syndrome might cause problems in such different 
parts of the body as the thyroid and inner ear. Scientists continue to study the genetic basis of 
Pendred syndrome. The protein that the SLC26A4 gene encodes, called pendrin, is found in the inner 
ear, kidney, and thyroid gland. Researchers have identified more than 90 
deafness-causing mutations or alterations of this gene. Scientists have altered the gene in mice so that the 
mice have an abnormal SLC26A4 gene. The study of these mice is providing 
information on how the abnormal gene affects the form and function of different 
parts of the body. For example, by studying the inner ears of mice with SLC26A4 
mutations, scientists now realize that the enlarged vestibular aqueduct 
associated with Pendred syndrome is not caused by a sudden stop in the normal 
development of the ear. Studies such as this are important because they help 
scientists rule out some 
causes of a disorder while helping to identify areas needing more research. 
Eventually, researchers are hopeful that these studies will lead to therapies 
that can target the basic causes of the condition. SOURCE: National Institute on Deafness and 
Other Communication Disorders, National Institutes of Health
</first>
</file1>