<file1>
<first>Percutaneous Ethanol (Alcohol) Injection of Liver
How is percutaneous alcohol injection done and how does it work? In this technique, sterile, 100% alcohol is injected into cancerous growths, or tumors, in the
 liver  to kill
 cancer cells. This has worked best against growths comprised of hepatocellular carcinoma or primary liver cancer, but has been tried as well against liver metastases from other types of cancer arising elsewhere (secondary cancers). The alcohol is injected through the skin (percutaneously) into the
 tumor using a very thin needle with the help of
 ultrasound or CT visual guidance. Alcohol causes tumor destruction by drawing water out of tumor cells (dehydrating them) and thereby altering (denaturing) the structure of cellular proteins. It may take up to five or six sessions of injections to completely destroy the
 cancer . Which patients are treated with percutaneous alcohol injection? The ideal patient for alcohol injection has fewer than three Hepatocellular
 Carcinoma (HCC) tumors, each of which is: well defined (distinct margins) less than 3cm in diameter surrounded by a shell consisting of
 scar tissue (fibrous encapsulation) not near the surface of the liver Additionally, patients with HCC undergoing alcohol injection should have no signs of chronic liver failure, such as free fluid build-up around the liver or in the abdominal cavity (
 ascites ) or
 jaundice . (Patients with severe liver damage and little remaining normal
 liver function are said to be in liver failure, and would not be able to tolerate the alcohol injections.) What are the side effects of percutaneous alcohol injection? The most common side effect of alcohol injection is leakage of alcohol onto the surface of the liver and into the abdominal cavity, thereby causing
 pain and
 fever . It is important that the location of the tumor relative to the adjacent blood vessels and bile ducts is clearly identified. The reason for needing to locate these structures is to avoid injuring them during the procedure and causing bleeding, bile duct inflammation, or bile leakage.
</first>
</file1>