<file1>
<first>Rapid Strep Test Procedure Kit Accuracy, and False Positive
What is a rapid strep test? The rapid
 strep test is a quick and accurate diagnostic tool used to 
determine whether or not strep bacteria are present in the patient's throat. The 
same test may be used to evaluate for the presence of
 Streptococci in other 
infected areas (for example, perianal infection in either gender, or vulvar 
infection in pre-pubertal girls). 
ABOUT: The incidence of sore throats (
 pharyngitis ) varies with season, age of the patient, and geographic area. Sore throats can be caused by infection from either
 viruses or bacteria. Less than one-third of all sore throats is bacterial, the most common bacteria being Group A
 streptococcus (
 GAS ). Children 5 years to 15 years of age are the most common age group 
infected by
 group A strep . Infection is most common during the winter/early spring season.  This is likely due in part to the seasonal variation of 
strep bacteria
 concentration in the community as well as the higher likelihood of close proximity 
of individuals due to either weather conditions and/or school attendance during winter months. The pediatric population may have different
 strep throat (GAS) symptoms : The majority of sore throats (70% to 85%) are caused by viruses. Representative examples are: EBV (
 Epstein-Barr virus or
 mononucleosis ) and
 CMV (cytomegalic inclusion virus) infections may produce a 
 mononucleosis symptom 
complex (
 sore throat , fever, disproportionate
 fatigue , tender and swollen neck 
 lymph nodes, and commonly 
 enlargement of the spleen and
 liver ); adenovirus (which may be associated with
 conjunctivitis ("pink 
eye"); influenza ; and miscellaneous others -
 herpes , rhinovirus (cause of the common 
 "
 cold "), etc. Unfortunately, no single characteristic element of 
either the patient's history or physical examination discriminates between strep 
thraot (GAS) and 
non-strep
 sore throat . As a result, it is imperative to have laboratory evaluation since 
strep 
throat should be 
treated with antibiotics, while relief of symptoms remains the mainstay of 
treatment for viral sore throats.
 Why is identification of
streptococcalinfection important? Patients benefit both immediately and potentially in the long-term by rapid 
confirmation of
 streptococcal cause of their sore throat. Antibiotic treatment 
provides a quicker reduction of symptoms, shortens the duration of illness and 
quickly, and efficiently eliminates the possibility of spread of infection to 
others. Although rare, serious consequences of
 streptococcal infections do 
occur.
 Rheumatic fever is associated with
 heart, 
 joint and nervous 
system damage and is preventable by rapid treatment of strep disease. Serious
 kidney disease that may result in
 kidney failure may also be a consequence of
 streptococcal infection. A throat infection due to strep needs antibiotic 
therapy initiated as 
rapidly as possible. The rapid strep test facilitates this goal. What is the traditional test for strep throat? The traditional test for a
 strep throat has been a throat culture. The major 
drawback of a throat culture is that the results take two to three days due to 
the time necessary to allow enough GAS bacteria to grow to enable accurate 
identification. Why is the rapid test
better? By comparison with culture methods, a rapid strep test is much quicker and 
can produce results within minutes.
 How is a rapid strep test done? Obtaining a specimen is the same whether your doctor will do a throat culture 
or rapid test for strep. A cotton swab (similar to a Q-tip) is quickly rubbed 
over both
 tonsils as well as the back wall of the mouth (the posterior pharynx). 
It is important to avoid contact with other structures inside the mouth such as 
the tongue or cheeks. The 
swab is then placed in a specialized container and the rapid test performed. 
Many people find that obtaining the swab produces a gagging sensation. However, since the entire swabbing process lasts less than 
five seconds this inconvenience is minimal. What are the
limitationsof the rapid strep test? There are several manufactures of rapid strep tests. Each manufacturer has designed 
their test to 
respond only to the presence of the particular
 streptococcal bacteria (Group A) 
responsible for
 strep throat . Other bacteria which are less much less likely to 
cause sore throats are not identified by the rapid strep test. The test will not 
detect viral causes of sore throat. A positive test response occurs when a 
reaction occurs between a protein on the surface of strep bacteria and chemicals in the 
test materials. Either living or dead strep bacteria will produce a 
positive reaction. Most rapid strep tests have a
 sensitivity of 95%, meaning that 
the test will be positive in 95 of 100 patients who are documented to have strep 
throat via throat culture obtained at the same time. Since 5 of 100 patients 
with strep throat will be missed using a rapid strep test, all negative swab 
specimens should be sent for culture to confirm the absence of strep bacteria. A 
positive culture requires antibiotics. The rapid strep test has a 98%
 specificity. This 
means that 98 of 100 positive tests correctly indicate the 
presence specifically of Group A
 streptococcus bacteria; 2 of 100 positive 
results are "false positives" - indicative of similarities between various surface
 proteins found on strep bacteria and other non-strep bacteria found in the 
mouth.
</first>
</file1>