<file1>
<first>Rash

ABOUT: What are the causes, symptoms, and signs of common
typesof noninfectious rashes? Some common, noninfectious rashes are listed on the following pages. If you have a new rash and you have a
 fever or some other generalized illness associated with it, it would be best to see your doctor.
 Atopic dermatitis Atopic dermatitis , often called
 eczema , is a common disorder of childhood that produces red
 itchy , weeping rashes on the inner aspects of the elbows and in back of the knees as well as the cheeks, neck, wrists, and ankles. It is commonly found in patients who also have
 asthma and/or
 hay fever . Seborrheic dermatitis Seborrheic dermatitis is the single most common rash affecting adults. It produces a red scaling often
 itchy eruption that characteristically affects the
 scalp , forehead, brows, cheeks, and external ears. In infants, it may involve and scalp (
 cradle cap ) and
 diaper area.
 Contact dermatitis Contact dermatitis is a rash that is brought on either by contact with a specific chemical to which the patient is uniquely
 allergic or with a substance that directly irritates the skin. Some chemicals are both irritants and allergens. This rash tends to be weepy and oozy and affects the parts of the skin which have come in direct contact with the offending substance. Common examples of
 allergic contact dermatitis are
 poison ivy ,
 poison sumac ,
 poison oak (same chemical, different plant) and reactions to costume jewelry containing nickel. Diaper rash This is a common type of
 irritant contact dermatitis that occurs in most infants and some adults who wear diapers when feces and urine are in contact with skin for too long. Stasis dermatitis This is a weepy, oozy
 dermatitis that occurs on the lower legs of individuals who have chronic swelling because of poor circulation in veins.
 Psoriasis This bumpy scaling eruption which does not weep or ooze.
 Psoriasis tends to occur on the scalp, elbows, and knees. The skin condition produces silvery flakes of skin that scale and fall off. Hives These red itchy
 bumps come on in a sudden fashion and then resolve in about eight hours. They tend to recur frequently. If hives are caused by a drug, that drug should be avoided in the future.
 Nummular eczema This is a weepy, oozy dermatitis that tends to occur as coin-shaped plaques in the wintertime and is associated with very
 dry skin . Drug eruptions Certain
 drugs (like antibiotics) can produce a skin rash as an unwanted side effect. The common appearance is similar to rashes produced by certain common viral infections. On the other hand, drugs may produce a wide variety of other types of rashes.
 Heat rash(miliaria) This skin eruption is caused by the occlusion of sweat ducts during hot, humid weather. It can occur at any age but is most common in infants who are kept too warm.
 Heat rash looks like a red cluster of
 acne or small
 blisters . It is more likely to occur on the neck and upper chest, in the groin, under the breasts, and in elbow creases. Treatment involves moving the individual to a cooler environment. Rashes not caused by infectious organisms, can be treated with
 over-the-counter 1% hydrocortisone cream for a week or so prior to seeking medical attention. Over-the-counter oral
 antihistamines like
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) or
 hydroxyzine (
 Vistaril , Atarax) can be helpful in controlling the
 itching sensation.
 
TREATMENT:  Dermatologists, pediatricians, infectious diseases specialists, and many internists are capable of identifying most rashes. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The term
 rash has no precise meaning but often is used to refer to a wide variety of red skin eruptions. A rash is any inflammatory condition of the skin. Dermatologists have developed various terms to describe skin rashes. The first requirement is to identify a primary, most frequent feature. The configuration of the rash is then described using adjectives such as "circular," "ring-shaped," "linear," and "snake-like." Other characteristics of the rash that are noted include density, color, size, consistency, tenderness, shape, and even temperature. Finally, the distribution of the rash on the body can be very useful in diagnosis since many skin diseases have a predilection to appear in certain body areas. Although certain findings may be a very dramatic component of the skin disorder, they may be of limited value in producing an accurate diagnosis. These include findings such as ulcers, scaling, and scabbing. Using this framework, it is often possible to develop a list, called a differential diagnosis, of the possible diseases to be considered. An accurate diagnosis of a skin rash often requires a doctor or other health care professional. On the basis of the differential diagnosis, specific laboratory tests and procedures can be conducted to identify the cause of a particular rash.
 Rashes produced by fungal infections Fungal infections are fairly common. Yeasts are botanically related to fungi and can cause skin rashes. These tend to affect folds of skin (like the skin under the breasts or the groin). They look fiery red and have pustules (
 blisters ) around the edges. Fungus and yeast infections have little to do with hygiene -- clean people get them, as well. Fungal rashes are not commonly acquired from
 dogs or other animals. They seem to be most easily acquired in gyms, showers, pools, or locker rooms, or from other family members. Many effective antifungal creams can be bought at the drugstore without a prescription, including 1%
 clotrimazole (Lotrimin, Mycelex) and 1%
 terbinafine (
 Lamisil ). With extensive infection, or when toenails are involved, a prescription drug may be useful, such as oral terbinafine. If a fungus has been repeatedly treated without success, it is worthwhile considering the possibility that it was never really a fungus to start with but rather a form of
 eczema .
 Eczema is treated entirely differently. A fungal infection can be independently confirmed by performing a variety of simple tests. Rashes produced by bacterial infections The most common
 bacterial infections of the skin are
 folliculitis and
 impetigo .
 Staph or
 strep germs may cause
 folliculitis and/or
 impetigo , two conditions that are much more common in children than adults. Eruptions caused by bacteria are often pustular (the bumps are topped by pus) or may be plaque-like and quite painful (such as with
 cellulitis ). Rarely, streptococcal
 sore throat can produce
 scarlet fever , a rash affecting large areas of skin. Rashes produced by certain classes of bacteria,
 Rickettsia or spirochetes,
 Rocky Mountain spotted fever , and secondary
 syphilis respectively, are often able to be suspected clinically.
 Rash due to parasites One of the most common rashes from a parasite infection is
 scabies .
 Scabies is produced by a small
 mite (related to a spider). This mite is usually contracted by prolonged contact with another infected individual. The mite lives in the superficial layers of human skin. It does not produce symptoms until the host becomes allergic to it, which occurs about three weeks after the initial infection. It can resemble eczema.
 Bedbugs cause a series of eruptions where they pierce the skin. Viral exanthems Rashes that characteristically occur as part of certain viral infections are called exanthems. Many rashes from
 viruses are more often symmetrical and affect the skin surface all over the body, including
 roseola and
 measles . Sometimes certain viral rashes are localized to the cheeks, such as parvovirus infections (
 fifth disease ). Other viral infections, including
 herpes or
 shingles , are mostly localized to one part of the body. Patients with such rashes may or may not have other symptoms like
 coughing ,
 sneezing , localized burning, or stomach upset (
 nausea ). Viral rashes usually last a few days to two weeks and resolve on their own.
 
TREATMENT:  Most rashes are not dangerous. Many rashes last a while and get better on their own. It is therefore not unreasonable to treat symptoms like itchy and/or
 dry skin for a few days to see whether the condition gets milder and goes away. Nonprescription (over-the-counter) remedies include the following: Anti-
 itch creams containing 1% hydrocortisone cream can be effective Oral antihistamines like diphenhydramine and hydroxyzine can be helpful in controlling the
 itching . Moisturizing lotions Fungal infections are best treated with topical antifungal medications that contain clotrimazole (Lotrimin),
 miconazole (
 Micatin ), or terbinafine (Lamisil). If these measures do not help, or if the rash persists or becomes more widespread, a consultation with a general physician or dermatologist is advisable. There are many, many other types of rashes that we have not covered in this article. So, it is especially important, if you have any questions about the cause or medical treatment of a rash, to contact your doctor. This article, as the title indicates, is just an introduction to common skin rashes. People with
 atopic dermatitis or eczema should not be vaccinated against
 smallpox , whether or not the condition is active. Patients with
 atopic dermatitis are more susceptible to having the virus spread on their skin, which can lead to a serious, even life-threatening condition called
 eczema vaccinatum . In the case of other rashes, the risk of medical complications is much less. Consult your doctor about the
 smallpox vaccine . What is the prognosis for a rash? The prognosis depends on the cause of the rash. An accurate identification is, therefore, of great importance in predicting its resolution. 
PREVENTION:  If the cause of a particular rash is known it can be avoided. For example: a
 measles vaccination would be of great benefit in preventing the rash of measles, as well more serious consequences of measles infections.
</first>
</file1>