<file1>
<first>Radiofrequency Ablation (RFA) of the Liver
What is radiofrequency ablation (RFA) of the liver? Radiofrequency ablation (RFA) is a technique that uses high frequency 
electrical energy that creates heat, delivered through a thin instrument known 
as a probe, to destroy tissue. It is used in the
 liver to destroy tumors 
(either primary
 liver cancers or cancers that have metastasized or spread to the 
liver) that cannot be removed by traditional surgery. Radiofrequency ablation also is  used in many 
other medical conditions. Examples of other uses of radiofrequency ablation include: The management 
of
 lumbar or low back
 arthritis pain by ablating nerve tissue to reduce
 pain signals Destruction of areas of the heart that cause
 abnormal heart rhythms (arrhythmias) Treatment of
 varicose veins Destruction of tumors in other 
sites of the body, including the
 esophagus , kidney, lung, and prostate. What are uses of radiofrequency ablation (RFA) of the liver? Radiofrequency ablation is used to treat hepatocellular carcinomas (HCC) of the liver, primary 
cancers that arise in the liver cells, when these tumors are small and the 
patient is not an appropriate candidate for surgical removal of the
 tumor or 
liver transplantation. Radiofrequency ablation also can be used on liver tumors that have originated 
elsewhere in the body and have spread (metastasized) to the liver.
 What size tumor is treated by radiofrequency ablation (RFA)? The maximum size for a liver tumor to be treated by ablation has not been 
established. However, radiofrequency ablation is best suited for tumors less than 5 cm. Larger 
tumors may require more than one session. How do I prepare for radiofrequency ablation (RFA)? Your doctor will give you specific instructions on how to prepare for the 
procedure. You may be advised to stop taking blood-thinner medications before 
the procedure and not to drink or eat anything for some hours beforehand. 
Depending on the type of radiofrequency ablation that is done, and whether or not anesthesia is 
required, you may be able to return home after the procedure, or you may remain 
overnight in the hospital. What kind of equipment is used for radiofrequency ablation (RFA)? Imaging procedures like
 CT (computed tomography) 
scan,
 ultrasound , or magnetic 
resonance imaging (
 MRI ) are used to help guide the probe into the area of the 
tumor. The probe is designed like a long needle electrode through which a 
high-frequency electrical current is passed. How does the radiofrequency ablation (RFA) procedure work? Radiofrequency ablation can be performed in different ways. It may be 
administered during open surgery, laparoscopic surgery, or percutaneously 
(through the skin) using imaging studies to guide the placement of the probe. 
Interventional radiologists are the doctors who most commonly perform RFA 
through the skin, while surgeons may perform RFA during laparoscopic or open 
surgeries. In all cases of radiofrequency ablation, a probe is inserted into the center of the tumor and the 
non-insulated electrodes, which are shaped like prongs, are projected out from 
the central probe into the tumor. The local heat that is generated melts the 
tissue (in a process known as coagulative necrosis) that is adjacent to the 
probe. The probe is left in place for about 10 to 15 minutes. For larger tumors 
it might be necessary to re-position the probe in different areas of the tumor. 
Imaging studies are done anywhere from a few hours to weeks after the procedure 
to ensure that the entire tumor tissue has been cauterized.
 What can expect during radiofrequency ablation (RFA)? Radiofrequency ablation may be done using local anesthesia or general anesthesia (typically if 
RFA is performed during surgery). Radiofrequency ablation performed by inserting the needle probe 
through the skin can be done under local anesthesia in which the skin insertion 
site is numbed. Typically, an intravenous line is placed for delivery of fluid 
and medications. Monitoring devices to measure heart rate and
 blood pressure are 
attached to the body. How long does the procedure last? Each radiofrequency ablation typically takes 10-30 minutes. Ablating more than 
one area requires more time. The entire procedure is usually finished in 1-3 
hours. After the procedure, the patient remains in a recovery room 
until fully awake. What are the risks and side effects of radiofrequency ablation (RFA) therapy? Radiofrequency ablation is generally well-tolerated, and does not typically cause any serious pain 
after the treatment. There is a very low risk of bleeding or infection after the 
treatment as well as a low risk of injury to the gallbladder or bile ducts. 
Sometimes, a low-grade
 fever and
 flu -like symptoms may be present after the 
procedure for a few days.  Other possible side effects of radiofrequency ablation include post-procedure 
pain, inflammation of the gallbladder, and injury to the bowel. What is the success rate of radiofrequency ablation (RFA) therapy? In most studies, radiofrequency ablation is over 85% successful at destroying small liver tumors. 
Studies also show that over half of the tumors removed by radiofrequency 
ablation do not recur (come 
back). Because the treatment typically does not cause serious health risks,
 chemotherapy can be resumed (if needed) soon after the procedure. 
Radiofrequency 
ablation usually 
has few complications, and can be repeated if necessary for the same or 
additional tumors.
</first>
</file1>