<file1>
<first>Rhabdomyolysis

ABOUT: Rhabdomyolysis is the rapid destruction of skeletal muscle resulting in 
leakage into the urine of the muscle protein myoglobin. Rhabdomyolysis has many causes. Medications can cause muscle injury and rhabdomyolysis. Rhabdomyolysis can cause
 muscle pain and
 weakness . Blood levels of muscle enzymes, including CPK, SGOT, SGPT, and LDH, as well 
as blood and urine myoglobin are used to diagnose and monitor rhabdomyolysis. Hospitalization is sometimes required to treat rhabdomyolysis. What is rhabdomyolysis? Rhabdomyolysis (RAB-DOE-MY-O-LIE-SIS) is the rapid destruction of skeletal muscle resulting in 
leakage into the urine of the muscle 
protein myoglobin. There are three different types of muscle in the
 human body ; The 
skeletal muscle is the muscle of movement of the body (moving the skeleton at the joints). Skeletal muscle is affected by 
rhabdomyolysis. Myoglobin is a protein component of the muscle cells that is released into 
the blood when the skeletal muscle is destroyed in rhabdomyolysis. 
Creatine 
kinase is an enzyme (a protein that facilitates chemical reactions in the body) 
also in the muscle cells. The level of each of these proteins can be 
measured in blood to monitor the degree of muscle injury from rhabdomyolysis. Myoglobin can 
also be measured in samples of urine.
 
CAUSES:  Rhabdomyolysis has many causes. Some of the common ones include: Muscle
 trauma or crush injury Severe
 burns Physical torture or
 child abuse Prolonged lying down on the ground (people who fall or are unconscious and are unable to get up for several hours) Prolonged
 coma Severe muscle contractions from prolonged
 seizures Cocaine use with related hyperthermia (increased body temperature) Extreme physical activity (
 running a marathon, extreme workouts) Drug and alcohol intoxication Low circulating phosphate, potassium, or magnesium levels in the blood (
 electrolytes ) Genetic muscle diseases (familial paroxysmal rhabdomyolysis) Prolonged
 drowning or
 hypothermia (low core body temperature) Medications: most notably
 statins used to treat
 high cholesterol (
 simvastatin [
 Zocor ],
 atorvastatin [
 Lipitor ],
 pravastatin [Pravachol], or
 lovastatin [
 Mevacor ]) and other medications such as Parkinson&amp;#39;s medication, psychiatric medications, anesthesia medications,
 HIV medications,
 colchicine Variety of
 viruses and some bacteria Severe
 hypothyroidism (low
 thyroid level), especially if the person is also taking statin
 drugs for
 cholesterol Lack of blood perfusion to a limb Some inflammatory disorders of the muscle, called myopathies, (
 myositis ,
 dermatomyositis ,
 polymyositis ) Venom from certain snake bites (mainly in Africa, Asia, and South America)
 
SYMPTOMS:  Rhabdomyolysis may not cause any symptoms at all. Muscle
 aches and
 pain (
 myalgia ), stiffness, and muscle weakness can occur with rhabdomyolysis, and is especially common with severe muscle damage. Rhabdomyolysis may cause a darkening of the urine color. Myoglobin is released from the muscles when they break down and is excreted into the urine. This can cause a red or cola color of the urine. What should I do if I think I have rhabdomyolysis? If you have signs and symptoms suggestive of rhabdomyolysis, your doctor 
needs to be notified promptly. It is important to realize that these symptoms 
are not specific for rhabdomyolysis as they may be caused by other conditions. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Rhabdomyolysis is suggested by the history of recent and past events and the physical examination. It is confirmed by blood and urine testing. An important part of diagnosing rhabdomyolysis is a comprehensive medical history and physical examination. The medical history may include questions about any medication use, drug and alcohol use, other medical conditions, any trauma or accident, etc. Blood tests include a
 complete blood count (
 CBC ), a metabolic panel, muscle enzymes, and
 urinalysis . The diagnosis of rhabdomyolysis is confirmed by detecting elevated muscle enzymes in blood, which include creatine phosphokinase (CPK), SGOT, SGPT, and LDH . The levels of these enzymes rise as the muscle is destroyed in rhabdomyolysis. While the SGOT, SGPT, and LDH enzymes are found in muscles, they are more frequently associated with the
 liver . Therefore, elevations of SGOT and SGPT, without elevated CPK, are more typically indications of liver damage. Of note, CPK is also in heart muscle (
 cardiac muscle ) and brain. The laboratory is usually able to distinguish between the different components of this enzyme. For example, the fraction coming from skeletal muscle is referred to as CK-MM and the one from heart muscle is designated as CK-MB. There are small amounts of the CK-MB component in the skeletal muscle as well. 
COMPLCATIONS:  One of the dreaded complications of rhabdomyolysis is
 kidney failure . This can occur for a variety of reasons. Direct injury to the kidney and plugging of the filtering tubes of the kidneys by the muscle proteins are among the causes of kidney function impairment in the setting of rhabdomyolysis. Another serious complication of rhabdomyolysis is called the
 compartment syndrome  where muscle injury leads to swelling and increased pressure in a confined space (a compartment). This leads to compromised circulation which can endanger the affected tissue. The
 compartment syndrome is most common after injury in the lower leg, arms, or the muscles of the abdominal wall and can require emergency surgery. Rhabdomyolysis can also cause abnormality of electrolytes in the blood. Because of muscle injury, the contents of the muscle cells can be released into the blood causing high levels of potassium (
 hyperkalemia ) and phosphorus (hyperphosphatemia). How is rhabdomyolysis treated? The treatment of rhabdomyolysis depends on its cause and severity. If a cause for rhabdomyolysis is identified, it is addressed; for example: discontinuing a toxic medication, replacing electrolytes, or treating an 
underlying muscle disease. In cases of mild rhabdomyolysis without any evidence of complications, 
management can take place at home by simply recognizing the cause and correcting 
it, such as discontinuing a medication and rehydration. In more 
severe cases, or if home therapy is not possible, hospitalization may be required. Prompt initiation 
of hydration with intravenous fluids, in 
addition to the removal the provoking factor(s), is an essential part of the 
treatment of rhabdomyolysis. Monitoring and managing kidney dysfunction, correcting any disturbance in the electrolytes, 
and monitoring the muscle enzyme levels (CPK, SGOT, SGPT, LDH) are most 
effectively done in the hospital when rhabdomyolysis is severe.
 What is the prognosis for rhabdomyolysis? The overall prognosis of rhabdomyolysis is favorable as long 
as it is recognized and treated promptly. Most causes of rhabdomyolysis 
reversible. Severe cases of rhabdomyolysis may be associated with kidney damage 
and electrolyte imbalance and hospitalization and even
 dialysis can be required.
</first>
</file1>