<file1>
<first>Rheumatic Fever (Acute Rheumatic Fever or ARF)
Rheumatic fever (acute rheumatic fever or ARF) facts Rheumatic fever is an autoimmune disease that may develop after a
 strep throat infection, especially in children ages 5-15, although older
 teens and adults may develop the disease. The revised Jones criteria help physicians make the clinical diagnosis of rheumatic fever. Rheumatic fever does not affect all individuals who have had a
 strep throat infection. Rheumatic fever affects the joints, heart, skin, and nervous system. Antibiotics treat a
 strep throat infection and may prevent development of rheumatic fever. Antibiotics will not help cure acute rheumatic fever. Rheumatic fever may cause long-term damage to the heart and its valves. What is rheumatic fever? Rheumatic fever (acute rheumatic fever or ARF) is an autoimmune disease that may occur after a group A
 streptococcal throat infection . Such a reaction to a
 strep throat causes inflammatory lesions in connective tissue, the heart, joints and blood vessels of various organs and subcutaneous tissue. The disease has been around since the 1500s, but the association between a throat infection and rheumatic fever symptom development was not described until the 1880s. The
 sore throat was later associated with fever and
 rash (caused by streptococcal exotoxins) in the 1900s. Prior to the broad availability of
 penicillin , rheumatic fever was a leading cause of death in children and one of the leading causes of acquired
 heart disease in adults. The disease has many symptoms and can affect different parts of the body, including the heart, joints, skin, and brain. There is no single diagnostic test for rheumatic fever, so the American Heart Association&amp;#39;s modified Jones criteria (first published in 1944 and modified in 1992) guide the physician in making the proper diagnosis.
 What are the revised Jones criteria for acute rheumatic fever? The revised Jones criteria are guidelines decided on by the American Heart Association to help doctors diagnose rheumatic fever. Two major criteria or one major and two minor criteria plus laboratory evidence of a preceding group A streptococcal (GAS) infection are required to make the diagnosis of rheumatic fever. The major criteria for diagnosis include migratory
 arthritis of several joints (polyarthritis), heart inflammation (
 carditis :
 pericarditis or
 heart valve disease ), nodules under the skin (subcutaneous nodules or Aschoff bodies), rapid, jerky movements (Sydenham&amp;#39;s chorea, also known as St. Vitus&amp;#39; dance), and a characteristic skin
 rash (erythema marginatum). The minor criteria for diagnosis include fever, elevated ESR (erythrocyte
 sedimentation rate or CRP [
 C-reactive protein ], nonspecific laboratory signs of inflammation), joint pain (
 arthralgia ), EKG (
 electrocardiogram ) changes, and history of previous acute rheumatic fever of rheumatic
 heart disease . Evidence of preceding streptococcal infection includes the following: Positive throat culture for GAS infection Positive rapid direct GAS throat swab Recent
 scarlet fever Supporting blood studies for recent GAS infection. These could include rising ASO titers, anti-DNase titers, or antihyaluronidase titers. Measurement of rising ASO titers is the preferred study.
 
CAUSES:  There is a direct and well-described connection between certain
 streptococcal infections and rheumatic fever. Most commonly, rheumatic fever is preceded by a throat infection caused by group A beta-hemolytic
 Streptococcus bacteria (
 strep throat, GABHS, or GAS). The bacterium causes an autoimmune (antibodies that attack the host&amp;#39;s own cells) inflammatory response in some people which leads to the myriad of signs and symptoms described by the revised Jones criteria. Streptococcal throat infections are
 contagious , but rheumatic fever is not. The symptoms of rheumatic fever generally develop within two to three weeks following an infection with streptococcal bacteria, and usually the first symptoms are
 painful joints or arthritis. 
SYMPTOMS:  As mentioned above, there are quite a few symptoms associated with rheumatic fever. Major Jones criteria include the following: Minor Jones criteria include the following: 
DIAGNOSIS:  The person must have a history of an infection with group A streptococcal bacteria, either by laboratory documentation (for example, a positive
 rapid strep test ) or positive strep culture, and must have two major or one major and two minor revised Jones criteria findings. 
TREATMENT:  The first step in treating rheumatic fever is to eradicate the bacteria (usually with penicillin) that initially caused the immunologic response. For penicillin-
 allergic patients, there are other options such as
 erythromycin azithromycin or a member of the cephalosporin family. It is important to make sure that patients receive treatment for the acute infection, but such treatment won&amp;#39;t necessarily change the course of rheumatic fever once the immunologic response has begun. Your doctor will decide on the best treatment option for you.
 Aspirin or aspirin-related medications treat the
 joint pains . It may be necessary to use very high doses to decrease the symptoms. (Caution: Do not routinely use aspirin in pediatric patients because of its association with
 Reye&amp;#39;s syndrome .) Consult a pediatric specialist for treatment protocols. High-dose steroids treat carditis, but it may be necessary to use other cardiac medications to control the inflammation of the heart. Health care professionals initially manage this serious condition in a hospital. The most challenging and unpredictable symptom to treat is the chorea (involuntary movements). It often responds to antipsychotic medications such as
 haloperidol (
 Haldol ) but may continue for a protracted period. For patients who develop Sydenham&amp;#39;s chorea, it can be the most difficult of the symptoms, since it involves involuntary movements and can interfere with daily activities. These individuals must remain on chronic long-term antibiotics to prevent recurrence of the strep infection, as a recurrent strep infection may cause chorea to recur.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  The most concerning of the complications of ARF are cardiac in nature. Patients with rheumatic fever who develop carditis may develop long-lasting heart dysfunction. Often the
 mitral valve or the
 aortic valve is affected. For patients not responsive to medications, surgical valve replacement may become necessary.
 Atrial fibrillation (irregular fast heart rate) and
 heart failure can occur. Sydenham&amp;#39;s chorea can be the most difficult complication to treat, and the individuals with this complication may get recurrence of the movement disorder. A few people remain very susceptible to reinfection with GABHS and may require lifetime antibiotic treatment. 
PREVENTION:  Prevention of rheumatic fever requires the recognition and diagnosis of group A strep throat infections and appropriate antibiotic therapy. In children 5-15 years of age, strep throat infections are very common and appear as a sudden onset of throat
 pain , fever,
 headache , and
 abdominal pain . Generally, patients with strep throat do not have symptoms such as
 runny nose ,
 nasal congestion ,
 cough , or other symptoms more commonly seen with a routine upper
 respiratory infection (URI, or the
 common cold ). Most providers either test for a GAS infection with a rapid strep test or throat culture. Most causes of
 sore throat are not bacterial but are viral, do not carry the risk of rheumatic fever, and cannot be treated with antibiotics. In addition, once an individual develops rheumatic fever after a strep throat infection, that individual remains at risk for subsequent episodes of rheumatic fever during subsequent strep throat infections. These individuals may need to receive chronic long-term prophylaxis (preventive treatment) with antibiotics. Researchers continue to attempt development of a
 vaccine against group A beta-hemolytic streptococcal infection, but currently no vaccine is available. Infectious disease specialists emphasize the importance of preventing recurrent episodes of ARF. There are several options varying from a once a month long-acting injection of penicillin to daily oral antibiotics. The guidelines currently recommend a prophylactic (preventative) antibiotic regimen for patients without carditis for five years or to 21 years of age (whichever is longer). For those with carditis but no residual heart disease, prevention should be for 10 years or well into adulthood (whichever is longer). Those who have residual heart disease because of carditis are advised to utilize antibiotic prophylaxis until 40 years of age and some specialists recommend lifelong therapy.
 How common is rheumatic fever? In the United States and other developed nations, rheumatic fever is exceedingly rare today, though there have been sporadic outbreaks. This is due to the availability of antibiotics and preventive services. In other parts of the world, it remains a common disease and is the leading cause of cardiovascular death in individuals under the age of 50.
</first>
</file1>