<file1>
<first>Rheumatoid Factor (RF)
Rheumatoid factor (RF) facts Rheumatoid factor is an antibody that is detectable in the blood of approximately 80% of adults with
 rheumatoid arthritis . Rheumatoid factor test is used by health care professionals to help in diagnosing
 rheumatoid arthritis . Sometimes rheumatoid factor can be detected in the blood of normal individuals and of those with other autoimmune diseases that are not
 rheumatoid arthritis . In people with
 rheumatoid arthritis , high levels of rheumatoid factor can indicate a tendency toward more aggressive disease and/or a tendency to develop rheumatoid nodules and/or rheumatoid lung disease. What is rheumatoid factor? Rheumatoid factor is an antibody that is measurable in the blood with a routine blood test. Rheumatoid factor is actually an antibody that can bind to other antibodies. Antibodies are normal proteins in our blood that are important parts of our immune system. Rheumatoid factor is an antibody that is not usually present in the normal individual. Because rheumatoid factor antibody binds to normal antibodies, it can be generally referred to as an autoantibody. Health care professionals use the rheumatoid factor test to assist in the diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatoid factor is sometimes abbreviated as "RF." What is the
normal rangefor rheumatoid factor? The "normal" range (or negative test result) for rheumatoid factor is less than 14 IU/ml. Any result with values 14 IU/ml or above is considered abnormally high, elevated, or positive. For what is the rheumatoid factor
testused? Most commonly, rheumatoid factor is used as a blood test for the diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatoid factor is present in about 80% of adults (but a much lower proportion of children) with rheumatoid arthritis.
 Can rheumatoid factor be present in a patient without rheumatoid arthritis? Yes. Rheumatoid factor is also present in patients with other conditions, including other connective tissue diseases (such as
 systemic lupus erythematosus and
 Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome ), some infectious diseases (such as infectious
 hepatitis ,
 syphilis ,
 infectious mononucleosis , parasites, and
 tuberculosis ),
 liver disease , and
 sarcoidosis . Rheumatoid factor can also sometimes be present in normal individuals without diseases. This occurs more frequently in people with family members who have rheumatoid arthritis. So precise interpretation of rheumatoid factors requires a complete knowledge of the patient&amp;#39;s history and medical status. What significance do high
levelsof rheumatoid factor hold for patients with rheumatoid arthritis? High levels of rheumatoid factor (rheumatoid factor "positive") are associated with a tendency toward more severe
 rheumatoid disease . This factor is also associated with a higher tendency to develop non-joint manifestations of rheumatoid disease, such as rheumatoid nodules and rheumatoid lung disease.
</first>
</file1>