<file1>
<first>Rhinoplasty, Septorhinoplasty &amp; Repair Of Nasal Fractures

ABOUT: These procedures are done to change, correct, or repair the nose. A thorough discussion of the patient&amp;#39;s goals, anticipated results, and possible surgical limitations is an essential part of pre-surgical planning. Surgery is usually done in an outpatient surgicenter facility under anesthesia. Assistance is required for the first day after surgery. Several office visits for nose care and optimal results will be necessary following surgery. What is rhinoplasty? Rhinoplasty 
is a facial cosmetic procedure, usually performed to enhance the appearance or 
reconstruct 
the nose. During rhinoplasty, the nasal cartilages and bones are modified, or 
tissue is added, to improve the 
visual appeal of the nose. Rhinoplasty is also frequently performed 
to repair nasal fractures. When rhinoplasty is used to repair nasal 
fractures, the goal is to restore pre-injury appearance of the nose. 
 Septorhinoplasty is a related 
procedure performed for patients who also have nasal obstruction. 
Septorhinoplasty not only improves the appearance of the nose, but it removes 
any internal obstructions and stabilizes structures that may be blocking nasal
 breathing . Initial evaluation for rhinoplasty Cosmetic 
concerns and expectations should be fully discussed prior to surgery. The 
surgeon's recommendations and any particular limitations set forth by the 
structure of your nose, face, and skin 
are important to understand and have explained. Photographs (without make-up) are 
usually obtained before surgery to help with preoperative planning 
and after surgery to document postoperative results.
 What happens before rhinoplasty surgery? In most situations, the surgery is performed as an outpatient at either the hospital or the surgicenter. In both facilities, quality care can be provided without the expense and inconvenience of an overnight stay. An anesthesiologist is present for monitoring vital functions throughout the procedure. Usually, the anesthesiologist will call the night before surgery to review the medical history. Preoperative laboratory studies will need to be done several days in advance. Transportation after the procedure will need to be arranged and someone should stay with the patient during the first night. Aspirin , or any product containing aspirin, should not be taken within 10 days of the date of surgery. Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medications (such as
 Advil ,
 Motrin ,
 Naprosyn ) should not be taken within 7 days of the date of surgery. Many
 over-the-counter products contain aspirin or Advil type
 drugs so it is important to check all medications carefully. If there is any question, please call the office or consult a pharmacist.
 Tylenol is an acceptable
 pain reliever . Prescriptions for
 pain medications are usually written prior to the date of surgery and should be filled in advance.  No food or liquids should be consumed within 6 hours prior to the time of surgery. This includes even water, candy, or chewing gum. Anything in the stomach increases the chances of an anesthetic complication. Smokers should make every effort to stop
 smoking , or at least reduce the number of cigarettes. This will help to reduce postoperative
 coughing and bleeding. Difficulty with tissue healing has also been noted in smokers during the postoperative period. Any illness prior to the day of surgery should be reported to the surgeon&amp;#39;s office as soon as possible. If illness occurs the day of surgery it is best to proceed to the surgical facility as planned and be evaluated to decide if surgery is safe.
 What happens the day of Rhinoplasty Surgery? It is important to check in with the surgical facility on time. Bring all papers and forms including any preoperative orders and history sheets. Wear comfortable loose fitting clothes that do not have to be pulled over the head. Leave all jewelry and valuables at home. Remove all make-up with a cleansing cream. Thoroughly wash the face with soap and water and do not apply makeup or creams. Do not take any medication unless instructed to do so. Usually, a nurse will start an intravenous infusion line (IV) in the pre-operative holding room and a medication may be given for relaxation. What happens during rhinoplasty surgery? In the 
operating room, the anesthesiologist will usually use a mixture of a
 gas and an 
intravenous medication. Continuous monitoring during the procedure usually 
includes a pulse oximeter (oxygen saturation) and
 EKG (cardiac rhythm). The 
surgical team is prepared for any emergency. In addition to the surgeon and the 
anesthesiologist, there will be a nurse and a surgical technician in the room. 
Depending on what is required and what additional procedures are performed, the 
surgery may take one to several hours. The surgeon normally talks with any 
family or friends once the 
patient is safely in the recovery room. What happens after rhinoplasty surgery? Patients are monitored after surgery in the recovery room by a 
nurse. A patient is able to go home the same day as the surgery once 
fully recovered from the anesthetic. This usually takes several 
hours. Transportation home will need to be arranged. A responsible 
adult should be in the same residence overnight for help on short 
notice. At home the patient should have bed rest with the head elevated on 
2-3 pillows.
 Edema and swelling are minimized by 
keeping the head elevated above the heart. An assistant should be available for 
out of bed excursions to the bathroom. Straining should be avoided. If 
constipated, take a stool softener or a gentle
 laxative . Swelling 
and bruising of the nose, upper lip, cheeks, or around 
the eyes for several days after surgery is a normal occurrence. This 
will gradually go away over the next 7 to 10 days. Ice on the face,
 bridge of the nose, and eyes as much as tolerated will help to 
minimize these problems. This will also help with postoperative edema 
and
 pain . Some patients have found frozen vegetables in packages (for 
example, bags of frozen peas) to be a convenient ice pack which 
conforms to the face. A nasal 
splint or cast will cover the outside of the nose, and 
will usually be removed one week following surgery. As swelling 
subsides, the splint tends to fit less tightly. If the cast gets wet 
it may come off prematurely; this is usually not a problem and does 
not affect the outcome of the procedure. Moderate bleeding from the nose is normal, and will gradually 
decrease. The gauze dressing ("mustache dressing") will collect blood 
and should be changed only when saturated. It is not unusual to 
change these dressing every hour during the first 24 hours after 
surgery. This dressing will usually not be needed after a few days. 
Do not take aspirin, aspirin-containing medications, or non-steroidal 
anti-inflammatory medications (such as Advil) for 3 weeks following 
surgery. It is best 
to eat a light, soft, and cool
 diet as tolerated after recovery from the 
anesthetic. Avoid hot liquids for several days. It is best to go slowly with 
food immediately after the procedure to prevent postoperative
 nausea and
 vomiting . Patients occasionally vomit one or two times immediately after surgery; if it persists, 
medication to settle the stomach may be prescribed. It is important 
to remember that a good overall
 diet with ample rest promotes 
healing. Antibiotics 
are prescribed after surgery. It is important to finish all the pills that have 
been ordered. Some form of a
 narcotic will also be prescribed (usually
 vicodin ) 
which is to be taken as needed. If narcotics are taken, it is important not to 
drive or engage in activities where impaired judgment could cause injury. In 
some situations steroids may be prescribed to be taken either preoperatively 
and/or postoperatively. It is very important to take this medication as 
prescribed, and not discontinue it prematurely. An anti-emesis medication such 
as phenergan may be prescribed for
 nausea or
 vomiting postoperatively. Possible 
drug reactions to any of these medications, such as a
 rash , should be reported 
to the doctor as soon 
as noticed. No other medications, either prescribed or over-the-
counter, should be taken without the knowledge of your doctor.
 What is the post-operative care for rhinoplasty? In most situations, packs will have been placed in the nose to control postoperative bleeding. The packing material will be removed at a scheduled postoperative visit. Arrangements should be made for someone else to drive to and from the office for this first visit. Eat a light meal before this visit and avoid taking excessive pain medications. Immediately after the nasal packs are removed, a saline nasal spray such as "Ocean Spray" is used several times per day to prevent crusts from forming in the nose. Several subsequent office visits are necessary to assess healing, remove crusts, and ensure a speedy recovery. The nose is usually tender after surgery, so a spray of special numbing medication is used before removing crusts. After the packing has been removed, breathing through the nose is acceptable, but do not blow or sneeze through it for 7-10 days. Any sneezes should be channeled through the open mouth. Expect some light blood-tinged drainage from the nose for several days. If bleeding becomes excessive, apply ice and rest quietly with head elevated while holding the nose. If bleeding continues, call the doctor. Rest for the first week following surgery. Avoid excessive talking, smiling, hard chewing, strenuous activities, lifting heavy objects, bumping the nose, and bending over. Try not to rest glasses on the bridge of the nose until soreness and swelling subside.
 Contact lenses can be worn once eye swelling and any irritation have resolved. Alcohol and
 tobacco should be avoided because they may prolong swelling and healing. Smoke, dust, and fumes may irritate the nose and cause an infection. Facial tanning is discouraged for 6 months after surgery. Number 15 or greater sun block is recommended during any sun exposure. Make-up may be worn anytime after surgery. Lubricate the nostrils, as instructed, with a Q-tip and Vaseline to soften harden crusts. Peroxide helps to loosen crusts. After several days a few of the absorbable
 sutures may become noticeable. Be gentle while brushing the upper
 teeth . They will often be tender for several weeks, and there may some numbness of the teeth and palate for several months. Exercise and
 swimming may be resumed after 3 weeks if there are no bleeding problems. Diving should be postponed for two months. It is advisable not to schedule travel for three weeks following surgery to allow for proper postoperative recovery and healing. 
COMPLCATIONS:  This surgery, like any surgery, may involve risks of unsuccessful results, complications, or injury from both known and unforeseen causes. Because individuals differ in their response to surgery, their anesthetic reactions, and their healing outcomes, ultimately there can be no guarantee made as to the results or potential complications. The following complications have been reported in the medical literature. This list is not meant to be inclusive of every possible complication. Although many of these complications are rare, all have occurred at one time or another in the hands of experienced surgeons practicing the standard of community care.</first>
</file1>