<file1>
<first>Sleep Disorders: Hypersomnia
Introduction to Hypersomnia Hypersomnia, or excessive sleepiness, is a condition in which a person has trouble staying awake during the day. People who have hypersomnia can fall asleep at any time; for instance, at work or while they are driving. They may also have other
 sleep -related problems, including a
 lack of energy and trouble thinking clearly. According to the National
 Sleep Foundation, up to 40% of people have some symptoms of hypersomnia from time to time. What Causes Hypersomnia? There are several potential causes of hypersomnia, including: The sleep  disorders
 narcolepsy (daytime sleepiness) and
 sleep apnea (interruptions of
 breathing during sleep)
 Not getting enough sleep at night (sleep deprivation)
 Being
 overweight Drug or
 alcohol abuse A
 head injury or a neurological disease, such as
 multiple sclerosis Prescription
 drugs , such as tranquilizers
 Genetics (having a relative with hypersomnia)
 How Is Hypersomnia Diagnosed? If you consistently feel drowsy during the day, talk to your doctor. In making a diagnosis of hypersomnia, your doctor will ask you about your sleeping habits, how much sleep you get at night, if you wake up at night, and whether you fall asleep during the day. Your doctor will also want to know if you are having any emotional problems or are taking any medications that may be interfering with your sleep. Your doctor may also order some tests, including blood tests, 
computed tomography (CT) scans, and a sleep test called polysomnography. In some cases, an additional
 electroencephalogram (
 EEG ), which measures the electrical activity of the brain, is needed. How Is Hypersomnia Treated? If you are diagnosed with hypersomnia, your doctor can prescribe various drugs to treat it, including stimulants,
 antidepressants , as well as several newer medications (for example,
 Provigil and Xyrem). If you are diagnosed with sleep apnea, your doctor may prescribe a treatment known as continuous positive
 airway pressure, or
 CPAP . With CPAP, you wear a mask over your nose while you are sleeping. A machine that delivers a continuous flow of air into the nostrils is hooked up to the mask. The pressure from air flowing into the nostrils helps keep the airways open. If you are taking a medication that causes drowsiness, ask your doctor about changing the medication to one that is less likely to make you sleepy. You may also want to go to bed earlier to try to get more sleep at night, and eliminate alcohol and
 caffeine .
</first>
</file1>