<file1>
<first>Smoking and Heart Disease
Smoking and Heart Disease Introduction Most people associate
 cigarette smoking with
 breathing problems and
 lung cancer . But did you know that
 smoking is also a major cause of
 heart disease for 
men and women? About 20% of all deaths from
 heart disease in the U.S. are directly related 
to cigarette
 smoking . That's because smoking is a major cause of coronary artery 
disease. A person's risk of
 heart disease and
 heart attack greatly increases with the 
number of cigarettes he or she smokes. Smokers continue to increase their risk 
of heart attack the longer they smoke. People who smoke a pack of cigarettes a 
day have more than twice the risk of heart attack than nonsmokers. Women who 
smoke and also take
 birth control pills increase several times their risk of 
heart attack,
 stroke , and
 peripheral vascular disease . Cigarette smoke not only affects smokers. When you smoke, the people around 
you are also at risk for developing health problems, especially children.
 Environmental tobacco smoke (also called passive smoke or
 secondhand smoke ) 
affects people who are frequently around smokers.
 Secondhand smoke can cause 
chronic respiratory conditions,
 cancer , and heart disease. It is estimated that 
around 35,000 nonsmokers die from heart disease each year as a result of 
exposure to environmental
 tobacco smoke.
 How Does Smoking Increase Heart Disease Risk? The
 nicotine present in smoke causes heart disease by: Decreasing oxygen to the heart.
 Increasing
 blood pressure and heart rate.
 Increasing blood clotting.
 Damaging to cells that line
 coronary arteries and other blood vessels. How Can Quitting Smoking Be Helpful? Now that you know how smoking can be harmful to your health and the health of 
those around you, here are some ways quitting can be helpful. If you quit 
smoking, you will: Prolong your life.
 Reduce your risk of disease (including heart disease, heart attack, 
 high 
blood pressure,
 lung cancer , throat
 cancer ,
 emphysema , ulcers,
 gum disease , and 
other conditions).
 Feel healthier. After quitting, you won't
 cough as much, you'll have fewer 
sore throats and you will increase your stamina.
 Look better. Quitting can help you prevent face
 wrinkles , get rid of 
stained
 teeth , and improve your skin.
 Improve your sense of taste and smell.
 Save money.
 How to Quit Smoking There's no one way to quit smoking that works for everyone. To quit, you must 
be ready both emotionally and mentally. You must also want to quit smoking for 
yourself and not to please your friends or family. It helps to plan ahead. This 
guide may help get you started. What Should I Do First to Stop Smoking? Pick a date to stop smoking and then stick to it. Write down your reasons for quitting smoking. Read over the list every day, 
before and after you quit. Here are some tips to think about. Write down when you smoke, why you smoke, and what you are doing when you 
smoke. You will learn what triggers you to smoke.
 Stop smoking cigarettes in certain situations (such as during your work 
break or after dinner) before actually quitting.
 Make a list of activities you can do instead of smoking. Be ready to do 
something else when you want to smoke.
 Ask your doctor about using
 nicotine gum or patches. Some people find these 
aids helpful.
 Join a
 smoking cessation support group or program. Call your local chapter 
of the American Lung Association. How Can I Avoid Smoking Again? Don't carry a lighter, matches, or cigarettes. Keep all of these smoking 
reminders out of sight.
 If you live with a smoker, ask that person not to smoke in your presence, 
or better yet, to quit with you.
 Don't focus on what you are missing. Think about the healthier way of life 
you are gaining.
 When you get the urge to smoke, take a deep breath. Hold it for 10 seconds 
and release it slowly. Repeat this several times until the urge to smoke is 
gone.
 Keep your hands busy. Doodle, play with a pencil or straw, or work on a 
computer.
 Change activities that were connected to smoking cigarettes. Take a walk or 
read a book instead of taking a cigarette break.
 When you can, avoid places, people, and situations associated with smoking. 
Hang out with nonsmokers or go to places that don't allow smoking, such as the 
movies, museums, shops, or libraries.
 Don't substitute food or
 sugar -based products for cigarette smoking. Eat 
low-calorie, healthful foods (such as carrot or celery sticks,
 sugar -free hard 
candies) or chew gum when the urge to smoke strikes so you can avoid weight 
gain.
 Drink plenty of fluids, but limit alcoholic and
 caffeinated beverages . They 
can trigger urges to smoke.
 Exercise . Exercising will help you relax.
 Get support for quitting. Tell others about your milestones with pride.
 Work with your doctor to develop a plan using over-the-counter or 
prescription nicotine-replacement aids.
 How Will I Feel When I Quit Smoking? You may crave cigarettes, be irritable, feel very hungry,
 cough often, 
get
 headaches , or have
 difficulty concentrating . These symptoms of withdrawal occur 
because your body is used to nicotine, the active addictive agent within 
cigarettes. When withdrawal symptoms occur within the first two weeks after quitting, 
stay in control. Think about your reasons for quitting. Remind yourself that 
these are signs that your body is healing and getting used to being without 
cigarettes. The withdrawal symptoms are only temporary. They are strongest when you first 
quit but will usually go away within 10 to 14 days. Remember that withdrawal 
symptoms are easier to treat than the major diseases -- like heart disease and 
lung
 cancer -- that smoking can cause. You may still have the desire to smoke, since there are many strong 
associations with smoking. People may associate smoking with specific 
situations, with a variety of emotions or with certain people in their lives. 
The best way to overcome these associations is to experience them without 
smoking cigarettes. If you relapse do not lose hope. Seventy-five percent of 
those who quit smoke again. Most smokers quit three times before they are 
successful. If you relapse, don't give up! Plan ahead and think about what you 
will do next time you get the urge to smoke. The good news is your risk of heart disease is cut in half after quitting 
tobacco for one year. After 15 smoke free years, your risk is similar to that of 
a person who has never smoked. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>