<file1>
<first>Smoking During Pregnancy

ABOUT: Tobacco smoking in
 pregnancy is dangerous for both mother and baby. The 
harmful chemicals from
 tobacco smoking are passed directly to the baby through 
the mother's bloodstream. Effects of
 smoking and exposure to
 secondhand smoke during pregnancy include increased risk of stillbirth and
 miscarriage , an 
increased risk of low birth weight, and an increased risk of premature delivery. Secondhand smoke also poses health risks for mother and baby. Babies exposed 
to secondhand smoke in the home have a higher risk of 
 sudden infant death 
syndrome (
 SIDS ). There is no safe limit for tobacco smoke exposure in 
pregnancy. Nicotine replacement products have not been studied in
 pregnant women. How does smoking
affecta pregnant woman and her baby? Tobacco
 smoking affects both mother and baby and poses health risks to both. 
Smoking during pregnancy puts the baby at risk for health problems during the 
pregnancy and after the baby is born. Nicotine and all the harmful (and
 cancer -causing) products inhaled from the tobacco enter the bloodstream of the 
mother and are passed directly into the baby's circulation through the placenta. 
Tobacco smoke contains over 7,000 harmful chemicals, over 70 of which are known 
to be carcinogenic (
 cancer causing). Some of the known health effects on the baby include: A decreased supply of oxygen available to the baby Increased risk of 
miscarriage and stillbirth Increased risk of poor growth and low birth weight Increased risk of premature delivery Increase in the heart rate of the baby Increased risk of
 breathing problems in the baby These risks to the baby increase with the number of cigarettes smoked during 
pregnancy. Of course, tobacco smoking is also harmful to the mother, increasing 
her risk of cancers,
 cardiovascular disease ,
 emphysema , and other conditions.
 Is any amount of smoking safe in pregnancy? While the health risks increase with an increased amount of smoking, there is 
no known safe limit for tobacco smoking in pregnancy. All smoking can have 
serious health consequences for the baby. 
RISKS:  Secondhand smoke is breathing tobacco smoke from being near a smoker. It also 
increases the risk of
 cardiovascular disease and cancers. The risks of smoking 
during pregnancy apply to pregnant women who breathe secondhand smoke as well. For babies exposed to secondhand smoke, there is an increase in risk for 
developing
 asthma attacks, breathing problems, 
ear infections, impaired lung 
development, and
 coughing . Children exposed to secondhand smoke require more 
ear 
tube surgeries than those who are not exposed. One study showed that exposure to 
secondhand smoke was associated with lower IQs in children. Sudden infant death 
syndrome is more common in babies born to women who smoked during pregnancy as 
well as in babies exposed to secondhand smoke. Can
nicotine replacement productsbe used during pregnancy to quit smoking? Nicotine replacement products result in a buildup of nicotine in the 
bloodstream in those who use them, decreasing the cravings and withdrawal 
symptoms for those trying to quit. However, the 
nicotine in the bloodstream 
directly enters the fetal circulation from the mother, and these products and 
their potential risks to the baby have not been studied in pregnant women. The 
American College of Obstetrics and Gynecology recommends that these products be 
used in pregnancy only when non-drug methods such as counseling have failed, and 
when the increased chance of quitting smoking with these products outweighs the 
unknown risks of nicotine use during pregnancy.
</first>
</file1>