<file1>
<first>Snake Bite (Snakebite)
What is a venomous (
poisonous) snake bite? A venomous (poisonous) snake bite is a bite or a puncture
 wound made by a snake that is capable of injecting, secreting, or spitting a toxin into the penetrated skin wound or, mucus membranes or the eyes where the toxin can be absorbed. In North America, there are about 25 species of snakes able to secrete toxin. However, non-native poisonous species are present in zoos and held in private homes or other areas by snake collectors. Consequently, almost any type of venomous snake bite can be encountered in the US. About 7,000 snake bites are reported in the US per year, but because snake bites are not required to be reported, it is estimated that up to 45,000 bites per year may occur with about 8,000 by poisonous snakes. The most common venomous snakes in the US are: rattlesnakes, copperheads, cottonmouths/water moccasins, and coral snakes. What is a nonvenomous (nonpoisonous) snake bite? A nonvenomous (nonpoisonous) snake bite is a bite or puncture wound made by a snake that is incapable of secreting a toxin. This should be distinguished from a dry bite. A dry bite is a bite by a venomous snake that does not inject any toxin. Even bites that are from a nonvenomous snake or are dry need to be evaluated as they can lead to significant tissue damage or infections.
 
SYMPTOMS:  The symptoms of a venomous snakebite depend on the type of toxin(s) secreted into the bite or puncture wound, and in part, on how much toxin is present in the tissue. The types of symptoms produced can be grouped into four groups: Cardiotoxins: act on heart tissue Neurotoxins: act on nervous system tissue Cytotoxins: act on tissue at the site of the bite or on tissue that directly absorbs the toxin Hemotoxins: act on the blood coagulation system and may cause
 internal bleeding Some toxins may cause more than one of these effects. Because of the various symptoms that can occur with venomous snake bites, the potential signs and symptoms to look for, as listed by the CDC include the following: A pair of puncture marks at the wound Redness and swelling around the bite Severe
 pain at the site of the bite Nausea and
 vomiting Labored
 breathing (in extreme cases, breathing may stop altogether) Disturbed vision Increased salivation and
 sweating Numbness or tingling around the face and/or limbs Symptoms from these toxins are somewhat variable and may occur quickly or they may be delayed for hours, depending on the toxin type and the amount absorbed. In general, small children are more vulnerable to snake bites because the relative larger amount of toxin absorbed in relation to their smaller body size can make the toxin effect more potent. Identification of the snake helps emergency health care professionals to both anticipate the potential symptoms, and it allows for more rapid and appropriate treatment of the venomous snake bite. A detailed description of the snake, a picture of the snake, or the snake itself (ideally dead!) will help identify the type of snake and the type of toxin. Time should not be wasted, however, in transporting the patient to an appropriate health care facility and do not put others in jeopardy of getting bitten. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Any snake bite needs emergency evaluation. Identification of fang or bite marks is done, even if the snake is non-venomous, to determine 
local
 trauma or tissue 
damage at the site of the bite. Identification of the snake type by 
description or picture, along with the circumstances of the bite and the surrounding environment 
usually provides the health care professional a working diagnosis. For example, 
a snake bite occurring in dry west 
Texas is likely a
 rattlesnake bite , while a snake bite in a swampy area of the 
US is likely a water moccasin. A zookeeper or private snake 
owner/collector who is bitten will likely know the exact type of snake that caused the bite 
or toxic spray (spitting cobras).
 
TREATMENT:  There are two phases in the treatment of snake bites. In the past there have been many home remedies and treatments, along with 
snake bite kits and other treatment methods, many of which have been shown to 
make the effects of the snake bite worse. Consequently, the CDC has issued guidelines, used after the 
threat of additional bites to the patient or others is eliminated, about what to
 DO and what
 NOT TO DO if a snakebite occurs. The following are the 
recommendations made by the CDC: Seek medical attention as soon as possible (dial 911 or call local Emergency 
Medical Services) Try to remember the color and shape of the snake, which can 
help with identification and treatment of the snake bite. Keep still and calm. This can slow down 
the spread of venom. Inform your supervisor (if the bite occurs at work). Apply
 first aid if you cannot get to the hospital right away.
 Lay or sit down with the bite below the level of the heart. Wash the bite 
with soap and water. Cover the bite with a clean, dry dressing. Do
 NOT do any of the following: Do not pick up the snake or try to trap it. Do not wait for symptoms to 
appear if bitten, rather seek immediate medical attention. Do not apply a tourniquet. Do not slash the wound with a knife. Do not suck out the venom. Do not apply ice 
or immerse the wound in water. Do not drink alcohol as a painkiller. Do not 
drink
 caffeinated beverages . Not included in the CDC recommendation is the bite 
of the Australian elapid snake, also termed a sea snake, which
 is emergently 
treated with a pressure bandage at the bite site with splinting and extremity 
immobilization. Others suggest no use of electric shocks for any snake bite. The second phase of treatment consists of stabilization and supportive care, 
and when medically indicated, administration of antitoxin (antivenin) specific for the snake species and a
 tetanus booster vaccine. A good practice is to call your local
 poison control center or the 
national Poison Help Line (1-800-222-1222), and also to consult a toxicologist and a 
surgeon to help care for the patient. Certain patients may require surgical 
treatment and admission to the hospital. The treatment of non-venomous snake bites includes local
 wound care at the 
site of the bite, removing snake
 teeth if left in the bite site, attending to 
any trauma at the bite 
site, and a tetanus booster if 
needed. Some wounds may become infected and require additional treatment with 
antibiotics.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  The complications of venomous snake bites can range from mild to severe. 
Complications include
 pain and swelling at the bite site, vision damage (from sprays especially),
 compartment syndrome (localized severe swelling that can damage or destroy nerves and 
blood vessels, leading to muscle necrosis), infection, limb loss,
 gangrene ,
 sepsis , internal bleeding, cardiac damage, respiratory compromise,  
and even death. 
PREVENTION:  Many snake bites can be prevented as most snakes are not aggressive toward 
humans unless they sense danger. Consequently, avoidance of snakes usually 
prevents a bite, so people should not try to handle, capture or threaten (for 
example, tease with a stick) any snake. Statistical studies suggest that about 
40% of all snake bites in the US occur in people that consumed alcohol
 drinks . If a 
person&amp;#39;s workplace involves areas known to be a habitat of snakes, wearing 
protective boots, 
thick pants, and wearing gloves may reduce the chances of a snake bite; or at least 
it may reduce 
the bite trauma and the amount of venom distributed. What is the prognosis for a venomous snake bite? Most snake bites, when quickly and appropriately treated, have a good 
prognosis. If left untreated for various increasing lengths of time the 
prognosis usually diminishes while the complications increase. Deaths are 
unlikely as fewer than 10 deaths per year are due to snakebites in the US.
</first>
</file1>