<file1>
<first>Natural and Home Remedies That Soothe and Get Rid of a Sore Throat
What types of naturtal and home remedies soothe sore throat pain? Various
 sore throat remedies can be used at home to help soothe 
 sore throat  pain and other symptoms. Listed are 25 home remedies. Some of these may be familiar, like drinking warm liquids with honey and lemon or gargling with salt water. Check out the other remedies to soothe a
 sore throat including using roots and leaves like marshmallow slippery elm, or eating frozen foods. Sage/Echinacea throat spray A 2009 study showed an
 Echinacea /sage throat spray was as effective as a spray using typical numbing agents chlorhexidine/
 lidocaine . Sage is antibacterial and antiseptic, and Echinacea can have immune-boosting effects. Combined, these herbs can make for an effective throat spray that can provide fast
 pain relief. Apple cider vinegar Vinegar is acidic and can kill bacteria in the throat, and also coat and soothe a sore throat. It may also loosen phlegm that may be irritating the throat. Use as a gargle - mix 1 teaspoon of apple cider vinegar with 8 ounces of water. This also can be combined with 1 teaspoon of salt for a saltwater vinegar gargle (gargling with warm salt-water remedy). You also can add 1 tablespoon of apple cider vinegar with 1 tablespoon of honey to your tea (see gargling with warm water remedy). Raw garlic Garlic has antiseptic properties, and it may help relieve sore throat
 pain . When crushed, raw garlic releases a compound called allicin that has antibacterial, antifungal, and antiviral properties. The best way to use garlic for sore throats is simply to chew on a raw clove, or take a slice and suck on it for 15 minutes. This may be hard for most people to handle. To make the raw garlic easier to ingest, you can mince it and add some honey or olive oil. Blend some with other veggies and make vegetable juice. Add it to a little salsa. The key is to eat it raw and as soon as possible after crushing for the allicin to be effective. Honey Honey may be added to hot water or tea and lemon to help sooth a sore throat. Honey has some antibacterial properties and may help ease sore throat due to infection. There are also studies that show it may help ease a
 cough , which can contribute to sore throat pain. Do not give honey to children and toddlers under 1 year of age, as it may be contaminated with
 Clostridium botulinum spores that may cause infantile
 botulism . Throat Coat tea Throat Coat is an herbal tea sold to provide sore throat relief. Throat Coat herbal tea contains
 licorice root, elm inner bark, marshmallow root, and licorice root aqueous dry extract and is sold to help relieve sore throat. A small study showed it helped reduce sore throat pain for 30 minutes after drinking it.
 Peppermint essential oil Once again, this is not the candy, but the plant. The main component of peppermint is menthol, which is believed to act as a
 decongestant by thinning mucus. Peppermint may soothe a sore throat, and ease a dry
 cough . Drink peppermint tea, or add some
 peppermint oil to a diffuser, or rub some peppermint essential oil on the chest (it may need to be diluted if the oil is strong). Licorice Sorry kids, not the candy, but the herb. A 2009 study in the journal Anesthesia &amp; Analgesia found a licorice gargle helped reduce post-operative sore throat pain. In addition to soothing a sore throat, it is believed that licorice root may also help loosen congestion and reduce inflammation, which can also help you feel better. You can gargle with it, chew a piece of licorice root, or drink licorice tea. Marshmallow root This is not the confection, but the herb. Like slippery elm, marshmallow root is a demulcent, and marshmallow root can soothe a sore throat by coating the irritated tissues of the throat. It may also loosen mucus and help with cough that may accompany or aggravate a sore throat. Marshmallow root may be taken as a tea. Slippery Elm Also known as Indian elm, moose elm, and sweet elm, slippery elm is believed to help coat the throat. It is considered a demulcent, which means it can help relieve irritation of the mucous membranes in the mouth by forming a protective film. Slippery elm can be particularly effective when used in a lozenge as it can help prolong the pain-relieving effects. It may also be taken as a tea. Acupuncture Acupuncture may help relieve sore throat pain; however, studies have shown mixed results. Practitioners claim there is a "sore throat"
 acupuncture point found on the hand that can provide fast relief from sore throat pain. Before using any herbal or alternative remedy, consult your doctor as some
 supplements can interact with prescription medications. Ask your child&amp;#39;s pediatrician what home remedies are effective for
 babies and toddlers, and women who are
 pregnant should talk to their obstetricians about the best choices to use during
 pregnancy . Frozen foods Eating frozen foods such as popsicles or sorbet can help alleviate sore throat symptoms. The cold temperatures can help ease the pain of a sore throat quickly, and many of these frozen foods are softer and easier to swallow. Non-dairy frozen items are preferred because in some individuals dairy products can more mucous, which can further irritate the throat. If dairy products do not irritate your throat, try low-fat ice cream, without added chips, nuts, or chunks that could scratch and irritate your sore throat.
 Eat chicken soup Grandma was right on this one! It&amp;#39;s warm and helps moisten the throat. Just like drinking hot tea, hot soup can be soothing on a sore throat and can help thin sinus mucus. It also helps keep you hydrated (but stick with low sodium soups) and according to a study in the
 Chest Journal, it may even contain anti-inflammatory substances that could help reduce cold symptoms. Warm saltwater gargle Rinse the mouth with a warm saltwater gargle (1 teaspoon of salt in 8 ounces of water) and then spit it out. Don&amp;#39;t swallow the salt, and don&amp;#39;t use too much salt, as this could further dry out the sensitive throat membranes. Gargling with saltwater is an easy and economical way to help cleanse the throat and loosen phlegm. Gargle frequently to relieve symptoms of throat irritation caused by
 postnasal drip . A 2005 study in the
 American Journal of Preventive Medicine found that gargling with saltwater may even help prevent
 upper respiratory tract infections . Drink warm liquids Drinking warm liquids such as
 caffeine -free tea with lemon and honey, warm water with lemon and honey, or warm soup broth can be soothing on a sore throat. Hot fluids also help thin sinus mucus, which allows for better drainage and decreased stuffiness, according to the American Osteopathic Association. Warm
 beverages also help keep you hydrated, which is important when you are feeling sick. Suck on ice chips Sucking on ice chips can help cool the throat, easing pain and inflammation. When the ice melts it helps hydrate you, which can also reduce congestion and keep the throat moist. Before using any herbal or alternative remedy, consult your doctor as some
 supplements can interact with prescription medications. A humidifier Use a humidifier to moisten dry air and keep your throat moist, or lean over the sink with hot
 running water and drape a towel over your head and inhale. You also can take a long, steamy shower. The moist air can help soothe your swollen sore throat, and may help if you are hoarse. Moist air also can help keep the nasal secretions from drying out, which can be uncomfortable. Humidifiers are good to use when babies and toddlers have dry sore throats, to help keep their throats moist. However, make sure you clean the humidifier and put fresh water in it regularly, so it does not become a breeding ground for more bacteria. A warm compress Use a warm compress on the neck – keeping the throat warm may help soothe tender
 lymph nodes . You can use a warm heating pad or hot water bottle, or make your own warm compress by wetting a towel with hot water (wring the excess water out before placing on your neck). Throat spray Use throat spray with anesthetic to help relieve symptoms fast. The most commonly used anesthetics in the
 over-the-counter throat sprays are phenol and benzocaine, which work by numbing the throat. These sprays won&amp;#39;t cure a sore throat or shorten the duration of a cold, but they may provide instant temporary relief from sore throat pain. Lozenges or cough drops Suck on lozenges or cough drops to keep the throat moist. Some brands have topical anesthetics, which will ease throat pain at least temporarily and last longer than sprays. Lozenges with menthol also can feel refreshing and ease sore throat symptoms.
 Young children and toddlers should not be given lozenges as they can be a choking hazard. Hard candy Like lozenges or cough drops, hard candies can help because they stimulate the production of saliva and help keep the throat moist and lubricated, which can ease the soreness from a dry sore throat. Hard candies are often preferred for children 5 years and older and adolescents. They can be as effective as medicated lozenges and sprays, and are less likely to have unwanted side effects. Moreover, like lozenges or cough drops, do not give young children or toddlers hard candies, as they can be a choking hazard. Zinc lozenges Studies have shown that zinc lozenges may shorten the duration of a cold, and may reduce the severity of cold symptoms including sore throat. Be careful if using zinc nasal sprays or gels. There are some reports of loss of smell with the use of zinc sprays or gels. Use for less than 5 days is usually safe and may shorten the duration of a cold. Also, like regular lozenges, zinc lozenges can help keep the throat moist, which may alleviate soreness. Young children should not be given lozenges. Drink plenty of fluids Stay hydrated! When you are sick with a sore throat, staying hydrated can help ease congestion, thin mucus secretions, and keep the throat moist. Moreover, if your sore throat is accompanied by a
 fever , you may become dehydrated so you need to replenish lost fluids. Cold ice water can help soothe the throat, as can hot beverages. Avoid alcohol and
 caffeinated drinks such as coffee or colas, because they can dehydrate you. Rest Sleep is important in the recovery process. Getting a good night&amp;#39;s
 sleep helps the body&amp;#39;s immune system fight off
 viruses and bacteria that can cause a sore throat. Rest also applies to the voice. Don&amp;#39;t speak if unless it&amp;#39;s necessary. Use texting or email to communicate until the throat feels better.
 Quit smoking If you smoke, there are plenty of reasons to quit, including easing a sore throat. Inhaling smoke from cigarettes, cigars, or pipes can cause a dry, irritated, and swollen throat, in addition to a cough, which can also irritate the throat. The chemicals from the smoke irritate the tissues, and the heat generated by these smoked tobacco products also leads to a sore throat.
 Secondhand smoke also can cause a sore throat, so avoid being around anyone who is
 smoking if you have a sore throat. Over-the-counter (OTC) pain medications for sore throat pain OTC pain medications such as
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ) or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory
 drugs (
 NSAIDs ) such as
 ibuprofen (
 Advil or
 Motrin ) or
 naproxen (
 Aleve ) can help relieve the pain and inflammation caused by a sore throat. They may also help reduce an accompanying
 fever if the sore throat is caused by an infection. Note: Do not give
 aspirin to children because of its link to Reye&amp;#39;s syndrome, a disorder that can cause
 brain damage and death.
</first>
</file1>