<file1>
<first>Stapled Hemorrhoidectomy
What are hemorrhoids? Hemorrhoids  are defined as an abnormally enlarged vein, mainly due to persistent increase in venous pressure, occurring within or just outside the anal sphincter of the rectum. The anal canal is the last four centimeters through which stool passes as it goes from the rectum to the outside world. The anus is the opening of the anal canal to the outside world. Although most people think
 hemorrhoids are abnormal, they are present in everyone. It is only when the hemorrhoidal cushions enlarge that
 hemorrhoids can cause problems and be considered abnormal or a disease. Although hemorrhoids occur in everyone, they become large and cause problems in only 4% of the general population. Hemorrhoids that cause problems are found equally in men and women, and their prevalence peaks between 45 and 65 years of age. What is stapled hemorrhoidectomy? Stapled hemorrhoidectomy is surgical technique for treating hemorrhoids, and is the treatment of choice for third-degree hemorrhoids (hemorrhoids that protrude with straining and can be seen on physical exam outside the anal verge. Persistent or intermittent manual reduction is necessary). Stapled hemorrhoidectomy is a misnomer since the surgery does not remove the hemorrhoids but, rather, the abnormally lax and expanded hemorrhoidal supporting tissue that has allowed the hemorrhoids to prolapse downward. For stapled hemorrhoidectomy, a circular, hollow tube is inserted into the anal canal. Through this tube, a suture (a long thread) is placed, actually woven, circumferentially within the anal canal above the internal hemorrhoids. The ends of the suture are brought out of the anus through the hollow tube. The stapler (a disposable instrument with a circular stapling device at the end) is placed through the first hollow tube and the ends of the suture are pulled. Pulling the suture pulls the expanded hemorrhoidal supporting tissue into the jaws of the stapler. The hemorrhoidal cushions are pulled back up into their normal position within the anal canal. The stapler then is fired. When it fires, the stapler
 cuts off the circumferential ring of expanded hemorrhoidal tissue trapped within the stapler and at the same time staples together the upper and lower edges of the cut tissue. Who is a good candidate for stapled hemorrhoidectomy? Stapled hemorrhoidectomy, although it can be used to treat second degree hemorrhoids (hemorrhoids that extend outside the anus after a bowel movement or straining, but return inside by themselves), usually is reserved for higher grades of hemorrhoids - third and fourth degree. Third degree hemorrhoids can be pushed back into the anus with a finger after a bowel movement. Fourth degree hemorrhoids are always outside. If in addition to internal hemorrhoids there are small external hemorrhoids that are causing a problem, the external hemorrhoids may become less problematic after the stapled hemorrhoidectomy. Another alternative is to do a stapled hemorrhoidectomy and a simple excision of the external hemorrhoids. If the external hemorrhoids are large, a standard surgical hemorrhoidectomy may need to be done to remove both the internal and external hemorrhoids.
 Pictures of stapled hemorrhoidectomy procedure What happens to the staples from a stapled hemorrhoidectomy? During stapled hemorrhoidectomy, the arterial blood vessels that travel 
within the expanded hemorrhoidal tissue and feed the hemorrhoidal vessels are 
cut, thereby reducing the blood flow to the hemorrhoidal vessels and reducing 
the size of the hemorrhoids. During the healing of the cut tissues around the 
staples,
 scar tissue forms, and this scar tissue anchors the hemorrhoidal 
cushions in their normal position higher in the anal canal. The staples are 
needed only until the tissue heals. After several weeks, they then fall off and pass in the stool unnoticed. Stapled hemorrhoidectomy is designed primarily to treat internal hemorrhoids, but if external hemorrhoids are present, they may be reduced as well. How long does stapled hemorrhoidectomy take? Stapled hemorrhoidectomy is faster than traditional hemorrhoidectomy, taking approximately 30 minutes. It is associated with much less
 pain than traditional hemorrhoidectomy and patients usually return earlier to work. Patients often sense a fullness or pressure within the rectum as if they need to defecate, but this usually resolves within several days. The risks of stapled hemorrhoidectomy include bleeding, infection, anal fissuring (tearing of the lining of the anal canal), narrowing of the anal or rectal wall due to scarring, persistence of internal or external hemorrhoids, and, rarely,
 trauma to the rectal wall. Stapled hemorrhoidectomy may be used to treat patients who have both internal and external hemorrhoids; however, it also is an option to combine a stapled hemorrhoidectomy to treat the internal hemorrhoids and a simple resection of the external hemorrhoids.
</first>
</file1>