<file1>
<first>Stool Color, Changes in Color, Texture, and Form
Stool color, texture, and form changes facts 
SYMPTOMS:  Changes in stool color alone do not cause symptoms. The underlying cause of the change in stool color, texture, or form is responsible for any symptoms. What does it mean when your stool color changes in color, texture, or form? Bowel movements are usually light to dark brown in color, and there is moderate variation among individuals with respect to stool color, quantity, and form. When these changes in stool do occur, it can mean that there may be an illness affecting the gastrointestinal (GI) tract or the entire body.
 What is the color of normal stool? Stool (feces, poop) color is most commonly brown. When stool color changes, a person, parent, or
 caregiver often becomes concerned. The presence of the
 bilirubin in the bile (a breakdown product of the
 hemoglobin in
 red blood cells that are normally destroyed after a useful life of several weeks) is generally responsible for stool color. Bilirubin concentration can vary the color of stool from light yellow to almost black. Changes in the chemical structure of the bilirubin can cause stool to turn green or yellow.
 Yellow stool also may occur if stool is dilute or there is a reduction in the amount of bilirubin that is produced by the liver. Bacteria and
 digestive enzymes in the intestine can act on the bilirubin and change its color. Most stool-to-stool changes in color have little meaning. However, some changes, particularly if the changes are consistent over time and not present in only one stool may mean something needs to be investigated.
 What are the causes of stool color, texture, and form changes? In most cases, stool color changes are not symptoms of disease. Changes in stool color may be due to: Diarrhea may cause green or yellow stools. Some foods (beets, Jell-O, licorice, green leafy vegetables) A few
 over-the-counter (OTC) and prescription medications Diseases affecting the liver, pancreas, and intestines Bleeding from the intestinal tract Green stools If stool passes through the intestine too quickly, there might not be enough time for bile to be digested and broken down to provide the normal brownish stool color. Normally, bacteria in the intestine chemically change bile to a greenish-brown color. It takes time for the bile to be fully changed in the intestine and become brown again, and if the transit time is short, for example, when a person has diarrhea, the stool remains green colored. Green stools may be a normal variant. A
 diet rich in green vegetables, especially spinach, or
 Iron supplements also may cause green stools, though iron often turns stool black.
 Yellow, greasy, and foul smelling stool There are a variety of reasons why stool will be yellow, greasy, and foul smelling. It can be due to the intestine&amp;#39;s inability to digest and absorb fat because of diseases of the intestinal lining (such as in
 celiac disease and
 cystic fibrosis ) because the pancreas is unable to manufacture adequate digestive enzymes (such as with
 chronic pancreatitis or
 pancreatic cancer that blocks the pancreatic duct, or there is not enough bile being delivered to the intestine (such as in
 cancer of the liver or bile ducts that are blocked). The yellowness, greasiness, and foul smell is due to the undigested fat.
 Bright red stools Black tarry stools Black stools are a worrisome symptom because it may be due to a large amount of bleeding into the GI tract, most often from the upper GI tract including the esophagus, stomach, and duodenum. Red blood cells are broken down by digestive enzymes in the intestine and turn the stool black. These stools tend to be tarry (sticky), and foul smelling.
 This can be a medical emergency; black
 tarry stools should not be ignored. Blood from
 nosebleeds or from dental procedures or mouth injuries can be swallowed and may be the cause of
 black stool , but the amount of bleeding usually is not substantial enough to do this.
 Light-colored white or clay-colored stools White-or clay colored stool are often seen with diseases of the liver or bile ducts. It also may be caused by
 pancreatic cancer that blocks the bile ducts. Lack of bile causes stool to lose its brown color and leaves it appearing pale. Maroon stools Maroon colored stools are often due to bleeding in the GI tract. The source of bleeding for red stools is the upper GI tract (esophagus, stomach, duodenum), while the colon is the source for bright red blood. Maroon stools, which is caused by partial
 digestion of the blood in the intestine often arises from the small intestine (jejunum, ileum) and proximal colon, but the color also depends in part on how rapidly the blood travels through the intestines. The faster the stool moves through the GI tract, the brighter red the color. This can be an emergency. In children with
 intussusception , where one portion or the intestine telescopes into another part, causing a temporary obstruction, stools may be described as currant jelly in color and consistency.
 Mucous in the stool Mucous in the stool may be normal, and it may cover segments of formed feces. However, it also can occur in people with
 inflammatory bowel disease or
 cancer . Mucous that is also associated with blood and/or
 abdominal pain should not be ignored and requires medical attention. People with
 irritable bowel syndrome (
 IBS ) also can have mucous in the stool. Drugs that change stool color The most common medications that change the color of stool are the
 drugs that turn the stool black - and include iron and bismuth (contained in Pepto-Bismol and
 Kaopectate ). Nevertheless, a large number of other drugs have been associated with changes in the color of stool to black or other colors. Practically, the importance of this fact is that the any new drugs or
 dietary supplements need to be considered as the cause of any change in stool color.
 Stool that floats Most stool floats because it contains an excessive amount of
 gas . By itself, it is normal and has little meaning. Changes in diet can lead to stool that floats, but as an isolated symptom, no action needs to be taken, and often it resolves spontaneously. Stool does not float because of an increased amount of fat. (Fat in stool causes oil droplets in the toilet bowl.) Any condition that causes increased amounts of gas to form in the intestines theoretically may lead to floating stool, especially in conditions where there is malabsorption of nutrients such as with
 lactose intolerance ,
 celiac disease , cystic fibrosis, and short bowel syndrome.
 Changes in the size and shape of stool People have their own size, shape, and stool consistency. It is the change in stool pattern that matters more than the absolute size and shape of stool. Narrow stool, sometimes called pencil-thin, may occur occasionally and is of no concern. People with
 irritable bowel syndrome (
 IBS ) may develop thinner stools. Nevertheless, a person with "normal" stools that has a new change in the diameter, length, width (caliber) of the bowel movement should consult his/her health-care professional. This may be a sign of a narrowed or scarred colon, perhaps due to a
 tumor , but the health-care professional may want further information about accompanying symptoms or tests. It is not unusual to have two or even three stools in a morning. The first stool will usually have a more solid form because it has been in the colon (where water is absorbed) the longest. The second stool will be looser, and if there is a third stool, it will the loosist. Another change in stool form that often requires evaluation is the development of looser or firmer than normal stools. At one end of the spectrum is
 constipation and at the other end is diarrhea, but even if the change does not reach these levels, consistent, milder changes in either direction need to be evaluated.
 Which type of doctors treat stool color changes? Most often, people will contact their primary care health-care professional with questions about the color of their stool. These include health-care professionals who care for infants and children. Depending upon the cause of the stool color change, certain specialists may need to be involved. For example, for red or black stool due to bleeding, a gastroenterologist may be needed to perform endoscopy, to look for a bleeding source in the stomach or intestine. Gastroenterologists are the specialist that helps manage other diseases of the intestinal tract, including Crohn&amp;#39;s Disease,
 pancreatitis , and celiac disease, that can cause color changes because of poor absorption of nutrients from the diet. 
DIAGNOSIS:  In most cases, a diagnosis, if any, cannot be made by stool color alone. The patient and the doctor need to consider other symptoms, past medical history, dietary changes, and medications to help decide what has caused the stool to change color. Physical examination will be important to help decide the significance of the stool color. Stool may be tested to look for blood, fat, or infection. Blood tests may be necessary depending upon the clinical situation. Depending on the change in color, it may be necessary to evaluate the pancreas, liver or GI tract. When should I contact my doctor about stool color or texture changes? Aside from black, red, or maroon stools that may mean bleeding is a possibility, and require urgent assessment and treatment, most color changes are not an emergency. The significance is determined based on other symptoms that might be present. Women who are
 pregnant often note changes in their bowel pattern. Stool can turn black because of iron and vitamin
 supplements . Iron can also turn stool greenish. As the uterus enlarges and increases pressure within the pelvis,
 constipation may occur and
 hemorrhoids can develop and cause blood in the stool. If there is no underlying problem, stool color changes are often due to changes in the diet and will resolve in a couple of days. If this is not the case and changes persist, it is appropriate to contact your health-care professional and seek medical attention. Contact your doctor if you have stool color changes and have associated symptoms such as
 vomiting , diarrhea,
 fever , or
 abdominal pain . It is important to remember that every person is different and changes in bowel habit be it color, size, frequency, or consistency (hard or soft) may be normal for one person or a sign of a potential problem for another. Stool color chart</first>
</file1>