<file1>
<first>Sudden Cardiac Arrest (Sudden Cardiac Death)
Introduction to sudden cardiac arrest A natural disaster hits, the power goes off and the lights go out. It's a common scene that plays out during hurricane and tornado seasons, and it's very similar in trying to explain
 sudden cardiac arrest . The heart sustains an insult, the electricity is short circuited, the heart can't pump, and the body dies. The heart is an electrical pump, where the electricity is generated in special
 pacemaker cells in the upper chamber, or
 atrium , of the heart. This electrical spark is carried through pathways in the heart so that all the muscle cells contract at once and produce a heart beat. This pumps blood through the
 heart valves and into all the organs of the body so that they can do their work. This mechanism can break down in a variety of ways, but the final pathway in sudden death is the same: the electrical system is irritated and fails to produce electrical activity that causes the heart to beat. The
 heart muscle can't supply blood to the body, particularly the brain, and the body dies. Ventricular
 fibrillation (V Fib) is the most common reason for sudden death in patients. Without a coordinated electrical signal, the bottom chambers of the heart (ventricles) stop beating and instead, jiggle like Jello. Ventricular Fibrillation is treated with electrical
 shock , but for it to be effective, the shock usually needs to happen within less than four to six minutes, not only for it to be effective, but also to minimize
 brain damage from lack of blood and oxygen supply. Automatic external defibrillators (AEDs) are commonly available in public places to allow almost anybody to treat sudden death. Less commonly, the heart can just stop beating. The absence of a heart beat is known as asystole (asystole: a=no + systole=beat). 
CAUSES:  Sudden death is most often caused by
 heart disease . When blood vessels narrow, the heart muscle can become irritated because of lack of blood supply. In
 heart attack (
 acute myocardial infarction ), a blood vessel becomes completely blocked by a
 blood clot , and there is enough irritability of the muscle to cause ventricular fibrillation. In fact, the reason many people with
 chest pain are admitted to the hospital is to monitor their heart rate and rhythm for signs that might lead to 
ventricular fibrillation. Sudden death may also be the first 
sign or symptom of
 heart disease . Congestive heart failure and heart valve problems, like
 aortic stenosis (narrowing of the
 aortic valve ) also increase the risk of sudden cardiac arrest. Cardiomyopathy is a broad category of
 heart disease where the heart muscle does not contract properly for whatever reason. Often it is ischemic, where part of the heart muscle doesn't get an adequate blood supply for a prolonged period of time and no longer can efficiently pump blood. People whose ejection fractions (the amount of blood pumped out of the heart with each heart beat) is less than 30% are at greater risk for sudden death (a normal ejection fraction is above 50%). In some people, cardiomyopathy may develop in the absence of ischemic heart disease. Inflammation of the heart muscle, known as
 myocarditis (myo=muscle + card=heart + itis= inflammation), can also cause rhythm disturbances. Diseases like
 sarcoidosis ,
 amyloidosis , and infections can cause inflammation of the heart muscle. Some people are born with electrical conducting systems that are faulty, which place them at higher risk for rhythm disturbances. Some are due to the wiring, or electrical conduction system, like
 Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome , while others are due to the structural basic structural problems within the heart, like
 Marfan syndrome . Pulmonary
 embolus or a
 blood clot to the lung, can also cause sudden death. Clots form in the leg or arm and may break off and flow to the lung where they decrease the lung's ability to get oxygen from the air to the body. Risk factors for
 blood clots include surgery, prolonged immobilization (for example, hospitalization, long car rides or plane trips),
 trauma , or certain diseases like
 cancer . Blunt chest trauma, such is in a motor vehicle accident, may result in ventricular fibrillation. (please see commotio cordis below)
 What about sudden cardiac arrest in the young? In younger people, sudden death is a rare event, but since it often involves people involved in athletics, cases are often reported in the press. The most common cause is
 hypertrophic cardiomyopathy (hypertrophy=to grow abnormally large + cardio=heart + myopathy = diseased muscle). This disease is often hereditary, and the walls of the ventricle are larger than they should be. This makes the pumping chamber of the heart smaller, and the heart has to work harder to pump blood out of the heart. As well, the thickened muscle narrows the space for the blood to flow through the
 aortic valve and to the rest of the body. During
 exercise , this decreased blood flow can irritate the heart muscle itself and cause ventricular fibrillation, collapse, and sudden death. Anomalous
 coronary arteries can also cause sudden death in the young. The heart is a muscle itself, and like any muscle, it needs blood supply to provide oxygen for it to work. Normally, the coronary arteries lie on the surface of the heart. Anomalous arteries dive into the heart muscle itself and may be occluded when the heart muscle that surrounds the abnormally placed artery squeezes aggressively, as with
 exercise , shutting off blood supply to part of the heart. This irritates the electrical system and can cause ventricular fibrillation and sudden death. The pre-participation athletic physical examination is a useful tool to screen children andadolescents for their risk of sudden cardiac arrest. Commotio cordis is a situation in which the heart stops when the chest is hit by an object. News stories occasionally report of baseball players who are hit in the chest by a ball and collapse because their heart stops beating. The heart sits behind the breastbone, and the electrical system can be short circuited when a direct blow is sustained.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Cardiac arrest symptoms and signs are not subtle: The heart stops beating and blood is not supplied to the body. Almost immediate
 loss of consciousness occurs, and the affected person will not be able to be aroused. The person will fall or slump over. No pulse will is felt (palpable). There will be no signs of
 breathing . 
DIAGNOSIS:  Sudden cardiac arrest is an unexpected death in a person who had no known previous diagnosis of a fatal disease or condition. The person may or may not have heart disease. 
TREATMENT:  The vast majority of people whose heart stops beating unexpectedly have ventricular fibrillation. The definitive treatment for this is
 defibrillation using electricity to shock the heart back into a regular rhythm. With technological advances, AEDs are now a routine sight wherever people congregate. Communities which institute public CPR education, use of AEDs, and rapid activation of 911 emergency medical services have dramatically increased survival rates from sudden cardiac arrest. Unfortunately, because the brain is so sensitive to the lack of oxygen and blood flow, unless treatment occurs within four to six minutes, there is a high risk of some permanent brain damage. Should the patient survive to be transported to the hospital, the reason for collapse and sudden death will need to be diagnosed. Regardless, the ABCs of resuscitation will be re-evaluated.
 A irway,
 B reathing, and
 C irculation (heart beat and
 blood pressure ) will be supported, and admission to an intensive care unit is most likely. Diagnostic tests may include repeated electrocardiograms (EKGs),
 echocardiogram (ultrasounds of the heart), and
 cardiac catheterization and electrophysiologic studies, in which the electrical pathways of the heart are mapped. Recent research involving the treatment of survivors of cardiac arrest suggests that prompt institution of
 hypothermia (cooling of the body) may prevent or lessen the degree of
 brain injury . Survivors of sudden cardiac arrest are often candidates for
 implantable cardiac defibrillators .
 
PREVENTION:  Death is best treated by
 prevention . Most sudden death is associated with heart disease, so the at-risk population remains males older than 40 years of age who 
smoke, have
 high blood pressure , and
 diabetes (the risk factors for heart attack). Other risks include
 syncope (
 fainting or loss of consciousness) and known heart disease. Syncope, or loss of consciousness, is a significant risk factor for sudden death. While some reasons for passing out are benign, there is always a concern that the reason was an abnormal heart rhythm that subsequently spontaneously corrected. The fear is that the next episode will be a sudden cardiac arrest. Depending on the healthcare provider's suspicion based on the patient's history, physical examination, laboratory tests, and
 EKG , the healthcare practitioner may recommend inpatient or outpatient heart monitoring to try to find a clue as to whether the passing out was due to a deadly heart rhythm. Unfortunately, the potentially suspect rhythm may not recur and depending on the situation, prolonged outpatient monitoring lasting weeks and months may be necessary. Use of electrophysiologic testing may help identify high risk patients (the electrical pathways are mapped using techniques similar to heart catheterization). In people with symptoms of
 chest pain , aside from making the diagnosis, monitoring both the heart rate and rhythm are emphasized. The purpose of watching people with chest
 pain in a hospital setting is to prevent sudden cardiac arrest. Using implantable defibrillators in high risk patients, especially those with markedly decreased ejection fractions can reduce the incidence of sudden cardiac arrest. These devices are placed under the skin in the chest wall and have wires that are attached to the heart itself. When they detect ventricular fibrillation, a shock is automatically delivered to the heart, restoring a heart beat and averting sudden death.
 What is the prognosis for sudden cardiac arrest? The frequency of sudden cardiac arrest is related to the frequency of
 coronary artery disease . If public health initiatives work to decrease risk the factors for heart disease, the risk for sudden death should decrease as well. In the adolescent population, increased awareness of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and appropriate screening may decrease the frequency of sudden death. Public education and widespread availability of AEDs will increase survival.
</first>
</file1>