<file1>
<first>First Aid for Seizures

ABOUT: Epilepsy is a medical condition that produces chronic
 seizures . Causes of
 epilepsy include brain diseases, illness, genetic disorders, or injury, but the cause of many
 seizure disorders is unknown. Common
 symptoms of seizures include unconsciousness, muscle contractions and convulsions, clouded awareness,
 weakness , loss of sensation, strange sensation in the stomach, lip smacking, fidgeting,
 confusion , and sleepiness after the
 seizure . There are many different
 types of seizures (e.g.
 grand mal , febrile), from a
 first aid point of view the underlying type of
 seizure or trigger has limited importance. First aid for
 seizures is aimed at keeping the person safe until the seizure stops on its own. Stay calm, loosen anything around the person&amp;#39;s neck, do not restrain them or put anything in their mouth, clear the area around them, and stay with them after the seizure stops. Call 911 if the seizure lasts longer than 5 minutes, the person has another seizure, does not wake up, or has another medical condition. Some seizures can be prevented by taking prescribed seizure medication regularly, checking for
 drug interactions , avoiding alcohol, and avoiding seizure triggers. What is the definition of an epileptic seizure? Epilepsy , or seizure disorder, is a medical condition that produces seizures. 
A seizure usually involves convulsions and sometimes leads to loss of 
consciousness.
 
CAUSES:  Seizures occur due to a malfunction of the brain's electrical system. Some 
seizures are caused by brain diseases, tumors, 
genetic conditions, or other 
illnesses or disorders that can be diagnosed (symptomatic seizures). When the 
cause for the seizures is unknown, they are referred to as idiopathic or 
cryptogenic seizures. Seizure causes are also sub-classified into acute (an active cause, such as 
an active brain disease) or remote (caused by a previous event, such as injury). Some people with seizure disorders have triggers that cause their seizures. 
Common seizure triggers include foods or medications, hormones,
 stress , 
lack of
 sleep , or sensitivity to light. 
SYMPTOMS:  Generalized seizure symptoms include unconsciousness, muscle contractions and 
convulsions (which may appear as very dramatic jerking movements), tongue or lip 
biting,
 incontinence , and clouded awareness. There may be weakness or loss of 
sensation. These symptoms may be brief or last a longer period of time. Some seizures only cause minor or mild symptoms and can be localized to a 
specific area of the body. These are called partial seizures. Symptoms of a
 partial seizure may include an aura (a warning symptom, often a strange 
sensation in the stomach), lip smacking, fidgeting, lack of awareness of 
surroundings, confusion, and sleepiness after the seizure. These symptoms 
typically last 30 seconds to 2 minutes.
 What
first aidshould be done for an epileptic seizure? First aid for a seizure is aimed at keeping the person safe until the seizure stops on its own. Most seizures last from 30 seconds to 2 minutes. 
PREVENTION:  There may be some ways to prevent seizures in some people. Sometimes, there is no way to prevent seizures and a person may have a seizure even if they follow all of the doctor&amp;#39;s recommendations. Anticonvulsant medication helps manage seizures in many patients. Take all prescribed medication regularly. Do not stop taking medications or change the dose without consulting a doctor. Avoid alcohol as it may interact with anticonvulsant medication, making it less effective. Consult a doctor before taking any other medications, including over-the-counter
 drugs , or
 supplements as there may be drug interactions. Avoid any known seizure triggers such as foods or medications, hormones,
 stress , lack of
 sleep ,
 dehydration , or sensitivity to light.
</first>
</file1>