<file1>
<first>Your Guide to Masturbation
Introduction to Masturbation Masturbation is the self-stimulation of the genitals to achieve sexual 
arousal and pleasure, usually to the point of
 orgasm (sexual climax). It is 
commonly done by touching, stroking, or massaging the penis or clitoris until an 
orgasm is achieved. Some women also use stimulation of the vagina to masturbate 
or use "sex toys," such as a vibrator. Who Masturbates? Just about everybody. Masturbation is a very common behavior, even among 
people who have sexual relations with a partner. In one national study, 95% of 
males and 89% of females reported that they have masturbated. Masturbation is 
the first sexual act experienced by most males and females. In young children, 
masturbation is a normal part of the growing child's exploration of his or her 
body. Most people continue to masturbate in adulthood, and many do so throughout 
their lives. Why Do People Masturbate? In addition to feeling good, masturbation is a good way 
of relieving the sexual tension that can build up over time, especially for 
people without partners or whose partners are not willing or available for sex. 
Masturbation also is a safe sexual alternative for people who wish to avoid
 pregnancy and the 
dangers of
 sexually transmitted diseases . It also is necessary when a man must 
give a semen sample for
 infertility testing or for sperm donation. When 
sexual dysfunction is present in an adult, masturbation may be prescribed by a sex 
therapist to allow a person to experience an orgasm (often in women) or to delay 
its arrival (often in men). Is Masturbation Normal? While it once was regarded as a perversion and a sign of a mental problem, 
masturbation now is regarded as a normal, healthy sexual activity that is 
pleasant, fulfilling, acceptable and safe. It is a good way to experience sexual 
pleasure and can be done throughout life. Masturbation is only considered a problem when it inhibits sexual activity 
with a partner, is done in public, or causes significant distress to the person. 
It may cause distress if it is done compulsively and/or interferes with daily 
life and activities. Is Masturbation Harmful? In general, the medical 
community considers masturbation to be a natural and harmless expression of 
sexuality for both men and women. It does not cause any physical injury or harm to the body, and can be 
performed in moderation throughout a person's lifetime as a part of normal 
sexual behavior. Some cultures and religions oppose the use of masturbation or 
even label it as sinful. This can lead to guilt or shame about the behavior. Some experts suggest that masturbation can actually improve
 sexual health and 
relationships. By exploring your own body through masturbation, you can 
determine what is erotically pleasing to you and can share this with your 
partner. Some partners use mutual masturbation to discover techniques for a more 
satisfying sexual relationship and to add to their mutual intimacy. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>