<file1>
<first>Senior Sex

ABOUT: *
ABOUT: medically edited by:
 Charles Patrick Davis, MD, PhD Normal
 aging causes physical changes in men and women that may affect their ability to have and enjoy sex. Age related problems that may affect sex may include vaginal changes,
 erectile dysfunction ,
 arthritis ,
 chronic pain ,
 diabetes ,
 heart disease ,
 dementia ,
 incontinence ,
 stroke ,
 depression ,
 hysterectomy ,
 mastectomy ,
 prostatectomy , alcohol consumption, and several types of medications commonly used to treat seniors (
 blood pressure ,
 antidepressants , 
 diabetic medications and others). Age does not protect people from
 sexually transmitted diseases . Emotional problems may interfere with sex but for some individuals,
 aging can be beneficial emotionally. Seniors can have an active, safe and fulfilling sex life; some suggestions are as follows -  make your partner a high priority, try different positions and times to have sex and take time to understand each other's changes that occur with age – seek treatment with your doctor for problems that affect your sex life and discuss methods and medications that may need to be changed or tried to improve the sex experience. Introduction to senior sex Many people want and need to be close to others as they grow older. This includes the desire to continue an active, satisfying sex life. But, with aging, there may be changes that can cause problems. What are normal changes with age? Normal aging brings physical changes in both men and women. These changes sometimes affect the ability to have and enjoy sex. A woman may notice changes in her vagina. As a woman ages, her vagina can shorten and narrow. Her vaginal walls can become thinner and also a little stiffer. Most women will have less vaginal lubrication. These changes could affect sexual function and/or pleasure. Talk with your doctor about these problems. As men get older,
 impotence (also called
 erectile dysfunction -
 ED ) becomes more common.
 ED is the loss of ability to have and keep an erection for sexual intercourse.
 ED may cause a man to take longer to have an erection. His erection may not be as firm or as large as it used to be. The loss of erection after
 orgasm may happen more quickly, or it may take longer before another erection is possible. ED is not a problem if it happens every now and then, but if it occurs often, talk with your doctor.
 
CAUSES:  Some illnesses, disabilities, medicines, and surgeries can affect your ability to have and enjoy sex. Problems in your relationship can also affect your ability to enjoy sex. Arthritis. Joint pain due to 
arthritis can make sexual contact uncomfortable. Joint replacement surgery and
 drugs may relieve this
 pain .
 Exercise , rest, warm baths, and changing the position or timing of sexual activity can be helpful. Chronic pain. Any constant
 pain can interfere with intimacy between older people.
 Chronic pain does not have to be part of growing older and can often be treated. But, some pain medicines can interfere with sexual function. You should always talk with your doctor if you have unwanted side effects from any medication. Dementia. Some people with
 dementia show increased interest in sex and physical closeness, but they may not be able to judge what is appropriate sexual behavior. Those with severe dementia may not recognize their spouse but still seek sexual contact. This can be a confusing problem for the spouse. A doctor, nurse, or social worker with training in dementia care may be helpful. Diabetes. This is one of the illnesses that can cause ED (
 impotence ) in some men. In most cases, medical treatment can help. Less is known about how
 diabetes affects sexuality in older women. Women with
 diabetes are more likely to have vaginal yeast infections, which can cause
 itching and irritation and make sex uncomfortable or undesirable. Yeast infections can be treated. Heart disease. Narrowing and
 hardening of the arteries can change blood vessels so that blood does not flow freely. As a result, men and women may have problems with orgasms, and men may have trouble with erections. People who have had a
 heart attack , or their partners, may be afraid that having sex will cause another attack. Even though sexual activity is generally safe, always follow your doctor's advice. If your heart problems get worse and you have
 chest pain or
 shortness of breath even while resting, talk to your doctor. He or she may want to change your treatment plan. Incontinence. Loss of bladder control or leaking of urine is more common as we grow older, especially in women.
 Stress incontinence happens during
 exercise ,
 coughing ,
 sneezing , or lifting, for example. Because of the extra pressure on your abdomen during sex, incontinence might cause some people to avoid sex. The good news is that this can usually be treated. Stroke. The ability to have sex is sometimes affected by a
 stroke . A change in positions or medical devices may help people with ongoing
 weakness or
 paralysis to have sex. Some people with paralysis from the waist down are still able to experience orgasm and pleasure. Depression. Lack of interest in activities you used to enjoy, such as intimacy and sexual activity, can be a symptom of
 depression . It's sometimes hard to know if you're
 depressed . Talk with your doctor.
 Depression can be treated.
 What Else May Cause Sexuality Problems? Surgery. Many of us worry about having any kind of surgery - it is especially troubling when the genital area is involved. Happily, most people do return to the kind of sex life they enjoyed before having surgery. Hysterectomy is surgery to remove a woman's uterus. Often, when an older woman has a hysterectomy, the ovaries are also removed. The surgery can leave both women and men worried about their sex lives. If you're afraid that a hysterectomy will change your sex life, talk with your gynecologist or surgeon. Mastectomy is surgery to remove all or part of a woman's breast. This surgery may cause some women to lose their sexual interest or their sense of being desired or feeling feminine. In addition to talking with your doctor, sometimes it is useful to talk with other women who have had this surgery. Programs like the American
 Cancer Society's (ACS) "Reach to Recovery" can be helpful for both women and men. If you want your breast rebuilt (reconstruction), talk to your
 cancer doctor or surgeon. Prostatectomy is surgery that removes all or part of a man's prostate because of
 cancer or an
 enlarged prostate . It may cause
 urinary incontinence or ED. If removal of the
 prostate gland is needed, talk to your doctor before surgery about your concerns. Medications. Some drugs can cause sexual problems. These include some blood pressure medicines,
 antihistamines , antidepressants, tranquilizers,
 appetite suppressants ,
 diabetes drugs , and some 
ulcer drugs such as
 ranitidine (
 Zantac ). Some can lead to
 impotence or make it hard for men to ejaculate. Some drugs can reduce a woman's sexual desire. Check with your doctor. She or he can often prescribe a different drug without this side effect. Alcohol. Too much alcohol can cause erection problems in men and delay orgasm in women.
 Am I too old to worry about safe sex? Age does not protect you from sexually transmitted diseases. Older people who are sexually active may be at risk for diseases such as
 syphilis ,
 gonorrhea ,
chlamydial infection,
 genital herpes ,
 hepatitis B ,
 genital warts , and
 trichomoniasis . Almost anyone who is sexually active is also at risk of being infected with
 HIV , the virus that causes
 AIDS . The number of older people with
 HIV/AIDS is growing. You are at risk for
 HIV/AIDS if you or your partner has more than one sexual partner or if you are having unprotected sex. To protect yourself, always use a
 condom during sex. For women with
 vaginal dryness , 
lubricated
 condoms or a water-based lubricating jelly with condoms may be more comfortable. A man needs to have a full erection before putting on a condom. Talk with your doctor about ways to protect yourself from all 
sexually transmitted diseases. Go for regular checkups and testing. Talk with your partner. You are never too old to be at risk.
 Can emotions play a part? Sexuality is often a delicate balance of emotional and physical issues. How you feel may affect what you are able to do. Many older couples find greater satisfaction in their sex life than they did when they were younger. They have fewer distractions, more time and privacy, no worries about
 getting pregnant , and intimacy with a lifelong partner. Some older people are concerned about sex as they age. A woman who is unhappy about how her looks are changing as she ages may think her partner will no longer find her attractive. This focus on youthful physical
 beauty may get in the way of her enjoyment of sex. Men may fear that ED will become a more common problem as they age. Most men have a problem with ED once in awhile. But, if you worry too much about that happening, you can cause enough
 stress to trigger ED. Older couples face the same daily stresses that affect people of any age. They may also have the added concerns of age, illness, retirement, and other lifestyle changes, all of which may lead to sexual difficulties. Try not to blame yourself or your partner. You may find it helpful to talk to a therapist. Some therapists have special training in helping with sexual problems. If your male partner is troubled by ED or your female partner seems less interested in sex, don't assume he or she is no longer interested in you or in sex. Many of the things that cause these problems can be helped. What can I do to have an active sex life as I age? There are things you can do on your own for an active sexual life. Make your partner a high priority. Take time to enjoy each other and to understand the changes you both are facing. Try different positions and new times, like having sex in the morning when you both may be well rested. Don't hurry—you or your partner may need to spend more time touching to become fully aroused.
 Masturbation is a sexual activity that many older people, with and without a partner, find satisfying. Don't be afraid to talk with your doctor if you have a problem that affects your sex life. He or she may be able to suggest a treatment. For example, the most common sexual difficulty of older women is
 painful intercourse caused by
 vaginal dryness . Your doctor or a pharmacist can suggest over-the-counter vaginal lubricants or moisturizers to use. Water-based lubricants are helpful when needed to make sex more comfortable. Moisturizers are used on a regular basis, every 2 or 3 days. Or, your doctor might suggest a form of vaginal
 estrogen . If ED is the problem, it can often be managed and perhaps even reversed. There are pills that can help. They should not be used by men taking medicines containing
 nitrates , such as
 nitroglycerin . The pills do have possible side effects. Other available treatments include vacuum devices, self-injection of a drug, or
 penile implants . Physical problems can change your sex life as you get older. But, you and your partner may discover you have a new closeness. Talk to your partner about your needs. You may find that affection 
- hugging, kissing, touching, and spending time together - can make a good beginning.
</first>
</file1>