<file1>
<first>Shaken Baby Syndrome (Abusive Head Trauma)

ABOUT: Inflicted
 trauma (especially shaken baby syndrome) is a leading cause of childhood (especially infant) mortality. There are several risk factors associated with an increased risk for shaken baby syndrome. Multiple behavioral symptoms and physical signs enable physicians to establish the diagnosis of shaken baby syndrome. Successful treatment for shaken baby syndrome demands accurate diagnosis and removal of the infant (and any siblings) from the household in which the abuse occurred.  Then, supportive care provides the mainstay of medical management. Some victims of shaken baby syndrome may have either long-term or permanent consequences due to the type of abuse they experience. Classes for parents discussing normal infant temperament and behavior may help expectant mothers and fathers have  realistic expectations, thereby lessening the
 stress of their
 newborn 's frustrating conduct. What is shaken baby syndrome? Dr. Robert Reece provided one definition of shaken baby syndrome (also called the shaken impact syndrome). He described the syndrome as "the constellation of signs and symptoms resulting from violent shaking or shaking and impacting the head of an infant or small child." The alternative descriptive phrase "abusive head trauma" serves as an umbrella term implying injury to the skull, brain, and spinal cord as a result of shaking and/or trauma to the head. Implicit in any terminology is that an adult purposefully inflicts such trauma on the infant. Research indicates that very young children (ages 4 and younger) are the most frequent victims of child fatalities. Although more recent statistics are not yet available, the National
 Child Abuse and Neglect Data System (NCANDS) data for 2010 demonstrated that children younger than 1 year accounted for 47.7 percent of fatalities; children younger than 4 years accounted for nearly four-fifths (79.4 percent) of fatalities. These children are the most vulnerable for many reasons, including their dependency, small size, and inability to defend themselves. Of these lethal events, inflicted head trauma is the primary cause of such mortality. Amazingly, the most frequent etiology (cause) of fatal
 head injury to children below 2 years of age is inflicted head trauma. Inflicted head trauma is a subset of the larger problem of child abuse (lethal and nonlethal). Unfortunately, solid statistics are limited regarding the incidence of shaken baby syndrome. This partially is due to various terms used in medical and hospital records as well as under-recognition of shaken baby syndrome since symptoms and signs may be more subtle than those of general body injury seen in globally battered children. CDC statistics reflect the broad problem of physical violence against children, reporting approximately 122,500 victims, of whom 840 died. Of those who died, 60% were boys.
 
CAUSES:  The first few months of childhood are tremendously stressful to new parents. 
Mothers (who often carry more than their fair share of this newly acquired 
responsibility) are struggling to recover from
 pregnancy , labor, and delivery as 
well as deal with an individual who is completely dependent upon them.
 Breastfeeding mothers may carry an even larger responsibility since they are 
uniquely responsible for their infant's
 nutrition . Studies of normal and healthy 
infants have demonstrated that the number of minutes per day spent crying 
increases weekly during the first two months of life, stabilizes for three to 
four weeks, 
and then drops remarkably. This mixture of physical and emotional parental 
exhaustion, coupled with what seems to be never-ending crying, can push many 
over the edge. High-risk infants (premature
 babies , those with chronic medical conditions, etc.) 
commonly extract an even higher toll on parents. This may be due to the more 
demanding requirements of such children and/or a belief of an increase in infant 
vulnerability. For some caregivers, physical punishment represents the only way 
to free themselves of their frustrations. 
RISKS:  Risk factors for shaken baby syndrome (as well as other types of 
inflicted trauma on children) may be conceptualized into two broad categories: Family risk factors Infant risk factors 
SYMPTOMS:  The symptoms and signs of shaken baby syndrome have an extremely broad 
range to display. This range is due to the nature of the inflicted trauma, 
including the frequency, duration, and whether the result of a single event or 
multiple events. Behavioral changes may include the following: Physical changes associated with shaken baby syndrome may include the 
following: It is crucial to note that many studies have demonstrated that 20%-50% of 
children who sustain shaken baby syndrome have evidence of other episodes of 
inflicted trauma, such as intentional
 burns , broken bones (most commonly rib and 
the long bones of the arms and legs), and/or bruising not consistent with routine 
and age-appropriate injury.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  A classic triad most commonly seen consists of (1) single or multiple 
subdural hematomas (localized bleeding outside of the brain substance), (2) 
diffuse and multi-depth retinal hemorrhages, and (3) diffuse
 brain injury without 
a reasonable explanation for such severe (and often repeated) trauma. Several 
agencies, including the American Academy of
 Pediatrics , recommend that the term
 shaken baby syndrome be replaced with
 abusive head trauma . Such a change 
broadens the various mechanisms of injury commonly seen besides shaking. Blunt 
head trauma is commonly seen in addition to shaking. Common mechanisms of direct 
blows to the head include punching the infant, hitting the head or face with a 
hard object (for example, wooden spoon), or slamming the infant's head against the wall 
or floor. Because children may not present for evaluation with evidence of trauma 
(bruising, lacerations, etc.), a high index of suspicion must be maintained by 
those responsible for evaluating such children. Missed cases of shaken baby 
syndrome may be incorrectly diagnosed as viral infection (especially
 gastroenteritis , in which children will be lethargic and have a history of 
repeated
 vomiting ) or accidental head injury (for example, fell while being carried by a 
parent, rolled off of a bed, or abuse by an older sibling). Multiple studies have 
demonstrated that, while the duration of shaking necessary to inflict such 
substantial trauma may be accomplished in 15-20 seconds, adult strength is 
necessary to inflict such damage (for example, parental perpetrators may attempt to 
blame a childhood sibling as the culprit). Likewise, rolling off of a bed or 
couch or being held during a parental fall are extremely unlikely to cause such 
injury. Documentation of old skeletal fractures, burns (commonly
 cigarette or 
hot water immersion), healing
 bruises , or ligature injury may be discovered 
during an investigation. Those most likely to inflict trauma on an infant tend to be the father (50%), 
stepfather, male partner of the mother (20%), female babysitters (17%), and 
the mother (12%).
 
TREATMENT:  The first step in successful treatment for shaken baby syndrome demands 
accurate diagnosis and removal of the infant (and any siblings) from the 
household in which the abuse occurred. Once diagnosed, supportive care provides 
the mainstay of medical management. Neurosurgical procedures may be indicated as 
well as orthopedic management of bone fractures. Eye specialists 
(ophthalmologists) are critical in the evaluation and monitoring of retinal 
hemorrhages. Once the infant is medically stable, a series of developmental 
evaluations are necessary to provide a baseline at the time of diagnosis. Follow-up evaluations monitor for long-term side effects 
of head trauma. The perpetrator will need to undergo psychological evaluation. What are complications and long-term effects of shaken baby syndrome? Neurologic 
side effects of either shaking or blunt skull trauma may span from developmental 
delays,
 seizure disorders , visual impairment, and
 blindness to death. Orthopedic 
consequences of inflicted trauma range from the need for recurrent surgery to 
permanent loss of function if the back (and thus spinal cord) is involved. 
Scarring of the skin is a common side effect of inflicted burns.
 Plastic and 
reconstructive surgery may be necessary depending on the nature of the trauma 
(for example, immersion into hot water). Emotional side effects may be obvious or subtle 
and may not necessarily be present or detectable at the time of diagnosis. 
Counseling and psychological support and intervention may require repeated or 
long-lasting attention.
 What is the prognosis of shaken baby syndrome? The primary predictor for an optimal prognosis is establishing the diagnosis 
and thus removing the child (and any siblings) from the abusive home. The nature 
of the neurological injuries help shape realistic prognostic expectations. The 
"plastic" nature of the immature brain and peripheral nervous system allow those 
counseling caregivers of children who have sustained shaken baby syndrome to 
be more optimistic than those counseling after adult
 traumatic brain injury . One 
study found that approximately one-third of those who suffered abusive head injury have no discernable side 
effect; unfortunately, such a statistic implies that two-thirds of such victims will have 
residual long-term complications. 
PREVENTION:  Many studies have determined that what is felt to be incessant crying is the 
primary stimulus leading to a frustrated
 caregiver loosing control. Expectant 
parents must be counseled regarding the nature of crying and various management 
strategies for both the infant and themselves. It is important to underscore 
that many times there is no obvious or discernable cause for the infant's 
crying. Likewise, it is important for parents and all caregivers to understand 
that allowing an infant to cry for a reasonably short period (10-15 minutes) 
does not lead to short- or long-term physical or emotional-health issues. Most 
importantly, those caring for children must be assured that asking for help is 
an excellent strategy when they find themselves "at the end of their rope." What can caregivers or parents do to calm a crying baby? Most caregivers will initiate a series of approaches in an effort to address 
a crying infant. Reviewing the feeding schedule and checking for a soiled
 diaper are common. Consideration of health problems (an
 ear infection or upper 
respiratory infection), the need to
 burp the child, or infant
 tiredness or 
boredom can all be considered. For infants who seem to have crying in 
association with feeding or evidence of 
gastroesophageal reflux (GER), a 
discussion with their pediatrician is in order. Breastfed infants may cry in 
response to certain foods (for example,
 caffeinated beverages ) ingested by their mother. 
Rarely, infants will have continuous crying if a long hair (most commonly from a 
parent) has accidently wrapped around a toe or finger. Diagnosis is considered 
if prominent swelling and skin discoloration is noted at the site of the 
ligature. Various approaches to the crying infant are commonplace. These include 
picking up the baby and socially interacting with the child,
 walking and rocking 
the child, addressing the possibility of hunger or a soiled diaper, and a quick 
visual survey of the infant to confirm no unusual changes exist. It is important 
for parents to accept that the majority of the time their investigation will be 
fruitless in determining causation of their infant's crying. The fact that he or 
she 
cries is not an indictment of their
 parenting skills. There is generally no 
hidden management secret other than time and patience.
</first>
</file1>