<file1>
<first>Shingles and Pregnancy

ABOUT: Shingles is a painful, blistering 
 skin
 rash that results from reactivation of infection with the
 varicella zoster virus (VZV), the virus that causes
 chickenpox . The
 rash of
 shingles can be extremely 
painful and typically occurs over the area of one nerve. Antiviral medications are used to treat
 shingles . These
 drugs are safe to use in
 pregnancy . Other medications to manage
 shingles can include
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol and others) for
 pain relief or
 antihistamines for
 itching . Complications from shingles occur most 
often in older adults and are less common in
 pregnant women. Shingles in pregnancy typically heals 
without long-term problems for mother or baby. What is shingles? Shingles is a painful skin rash caused by reactivation of prior infection with the same virus that previously caused
 chickenpox , known as
 varicella zoster virus (VZV). VZV belongs to the
 herpes family of
 viruses , but it is not the same virus that causes
 genital herpes or
 cold sores on the mouth. When a person is infected with VZV in childhood, they typically develop
 chickenpox , but after the illness resolves the VZV remains in a dormant state in the nervous system and is never fully cleared from the body. Under certain circumstances, such as emotional
 stress , immune deficiency (from
 AIDS or
 chemotherapy ), or with
 cancer , the virus reactivates and causes the skin and nerve inflammation known as shingles. Shingles occurs most commonly in people over the age of 60, but anyone who has ever had chickenpox is at risk, including pregnant women. It has been estimated that up to 1,000,000 cases of shingles occur each year in the U.S. What do shingles look like? 
SYMPTOMS:  The hallmark symptom of shingles is a painful, blistering rash.
 Pain from 
shingles may be severe in intensity. The pain, or a tingling sensation in some 
cases, may precede the development of the actual rash, making the cause of the 
pain hard to ascertain. 
Small
 blisters form on a red base, and new
 blisters continue to appear for 3 to 5 days. The rash follows the path of individual nerves, 
and typically presents in a band-like pattern on one side of the body. After the 
blisters rupture, they begin to crust over and heal. The entire outbreak from 
onset to healing takes about 3 to 4 weeks. Fever ,
 headache ,
 chills , and
 nausea can sometimes accompany the painful skin 
rash. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The characteristic rash of shingles typically suggests the diagnosis, and in 
most cases, no specific diagnostic tests are required. In cases in which there 
is pain but no apparent rash, the diagnosis can be very difficult. Laboratory 
testing to detect the genetic material or surface proteins of the VZV can be 
used in atypical or difficult cases. 
TREATMENT:  Treatment for shingles is generally prescription or over-the-counter antiviral, pain, and 
antihistamine medication. Antiviral medication to treat shingles The prescription antiviral medications typically used to treat shingles are 
safe to take during pregnancy. These drugs include
 acyclovir (
 Zovirax ),
 valacyclovir (
 Valtrex ), or
 famciclovir (
 Famvir ). Antiviral medications can 
reduce the severity and duration of the rash if started early (within 72 hours 
of the appearance of the rash).
 Pain medication to treat shingles Pain medications, such as acetaminophen, can also be used for pain relief, 
although these will not affect the progression of the blisters and rash. 
Pregnant women should discuss any pain relief medications with their health care 
professional. Pregnant women should not take 
nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory 
medications (
 NSAIDs ) like
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ,
 Motrin ,
 Nuprin , etc.) late in the pregnancy. Antihistamine medication to treat shingles Antihistamines such as
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) can help reduce any 
associated
 itching . Other home remedies for itching include oatmeal baths and
 calamine lotion . Many women find that applying cool cloths or compresses 
provides relief as well. Keeping the affected areas covered with clean gauze and 
wearing loose clothing can help speed healing and prevent secondary infection of 
the affected skin. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Postherpetic neuralgia is the most common complication of shingles. This 
condition develops in about 20% of people who have shingles and is characterized 
by persistent pain at the affected site after the rash has disappeared. It goes 
away by 4 months after the initial rash in most people. This complication is 
less common in pregnant women since it rarely occurs in people under 40 years of 
age. Postherpetic neuralgia is more common in people over 60 who do not receive 
treatment for shingles. Shingles that affects the eye is another uncommon condition. It is essential 
to see a doctor if you develop shingles around the eye area. In very rare cases, 
the virus can spread to the brain and membranes around the central nervous 
system. Other potential complications include
 hearing or 
balance problems and
 weakness of the muscles on one side of the face, known as
 Ramsay Hunt syndrome . 
All of these complications, like postherpetic neuralgia, are more common in 
older adults and affect pregnant women less commonly. Sometimes, secondary
 bacterial infections develop at the site of the rash. 
These can be treated with antibiotics, and antibiotics can be chosen that are 
safe for use in pregnancy.
 What is the outlook (prognosis) for shingles in pregnancy? Most cases of shingles heal without a risk of serious complications or 
long-term problems. 
PREVENTION:  If you have had chickenpox in the past, you have been infected with the VZV and there is no absolute way to prevent shingles. However, you cannot catch shingles from someone else who has shingles or chickenpox if you have had chickenpox or have immunity to the chickenpox virus. However, pregnant women who have not had chickenpox may catch chickenpox from someone with shingles or chickenpox. Chickenpox infection during pregnancy can be dangerous to the unborn baby, so it is important to avoid contact with people with shingles or chickenpox if you have not had the condition or the vaccine. Children in the US today are typically vaccinated against the VZV (
 chickenpox vaccine ). A vaccine to prevent shingles (
 Zostavax ) is also available that reduces the incidence of shingles by about 50%, but the vaccine cannot be taken by pregnant women. Women who receive the Zostavax vaccine should wait at least 3 months before attempting pregnancy.
</first>
</file1>