<file1>
<first>Medical Shock

ABOUT: Shock is a life-threatening medical condition and is a medical 
 emergency. If shock is suspected call 911 or get to an emergency department 
 immediately. The main symptom of shock is
 low blood pressure . Other symptoms include 
 rapid, shallow
 breathing ;
 cold , clammy skin; rapid, weak pulse;
 dizziness ,
 fainting , or
 weakness . There are several types of shock: septic shock caused by bacteria,
 anaphylactic shock caused by hypersensitivity or
 allergic reaction , 
 cardiogenic shock from heart damage, hypovolemic shock from blood or fluid 
 loss, and neurogenic shock from spinal cord
 trauma . Treatment for shock depends on the cause. Tests will determine the 
 cause and severity. Usually IV fluids are administered in addition to 
 medications that raise
 blood pressure .
 Septic shock is treated with antibiotics and fluids. Anaphylactic shock is treated with
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ), epinephrine (an "Epi-pen"), and steroid medications (
 solu-medrol ). Cardiogenic shock is treated by identifying and treating the 
  underlying cause. Hypovolemic shock is treated with fluids (saline) in minor cases, 
  and blood transfusions in severe cases. Neurogenic shock is the most difficult to treat as spinal cord 
  damage is often irreversible. Immobilization, anti-inflammatories such 
  as steroids and surgery are the main treatments. Shock
 prevention includes learning ways to prevent
 heart disease , 
 injuries,
 dehydration and other causes of shock.
 What is shock? Shock is a life-threatening medical condition as a result of 
insufficient blood flow throughout the body. Shock often accompanies severe 
injury or illness. Medical shock is a medical emergency and can lead to other 
conditions such as lack of oxygen in the body's tissues (
 hypoxia ),
 heart attack (
 cardiac arrest ) or organ damage. It requires immediate treatment as symptoms 
can worsen rapidly. Medical shock is different than emotional or psychological shock that can 
occur following a traumatic or frightening emotional event. What are the types of shock? Septic shock results from bacteria multiplying in the blood and releasing 
toxins. Common causes of this are
 pneumonia ,
 urinary tract infections , 
skin infections (
 cellulitis ), intra-abdominal infections (such as 
a
ruptured
 appendix ), and
 meningitis . Anaphylactic shock is a type of severe hypersensitivity or
 allergic reaction. 
Causes include
 allergy to 
insect stings, medicines, or 
foods (nuts, berries, 
seafood), etc. Cardiogenic shock happens when the heart is damaged and unable to supply 
sufficient blood to the body. This can be the end result of a heart attack or
 congestive heart failure . Hypovolemic shock is caused by severe blood and fluid loss, such as from 
traumatic bodily injury, which makes the heart unable to pump enough blood to 
the body, or severe
 anemia where there is not enough blood to carry oxygen through the body. Neurogenic shock is caused by
 spinal cord injury , usually as a result 
of a traumatic accident or injury.
 
CAUSES:  There are several main causes of shock: Heart conditions (heart attack,
 heart failure ) Heavy internal or external bleeding, such as from a serious injury 
 or rupture of a blood vessel Dehydration , 
 especially when severe or related to
 heat illness. Infection (septic shock) Severe allergic reaction (anaphylactic shock) Spinal injuries (neurogenic shock) Burns Persistent
 vomiting or
 diarrhea 
SYMPTOMS:  Low blood pressure and rapid heart rate (tachycardia) are the key signs of shock. Symptoms of all types of shock 
include: Rapid, shallow breathing Cold, clammy skin Rapid, weak pulse Dizziness or
 fainting Weakness Depending on the type of shock the following symptoms may also be observed: Eyes appear to stare Anxiety or agitation Seizures Confusion or unresponsiveness Low or no urine output Bluish lips and fingernails Sweating Chest pain When should I seek medical care for shock? Medical shock is a medical emergency. If you suspect shock after an injury, even if the person seems 
stable, call 
911 or get them to an emergency department immediately. Prompt treatment can 
save a person's life. The sooner shock is treated, the better. When treated quickly there is less 
risk of damage to a person's vital organs. 
TREATMENT:  Depending on the type or the cause of the shock, treatments differ. In 
general, fluid resuscitation (giving a large amount of fluid to raise blood 
pressure quickly) with an IV in the ambulance or emergency room is the 
first-line treatment for all types of shock. The doctor will also administer 
medications such as epinephrine, norepinephrine, or dopamine to the fluids to try 
to raise a patient's blood pressure to ensure blood flow to the vital organs. Tests (for example, X-rays, blood tests, 
EKGs) will determine the underlying cause 
of the shock and uncover the severity of the patient's illness. Septic shock is treated with prompt administration of antibiotics depending 
on the source and type of underlying infection. These patients are often 
dehydrated and require large amounts of fluids to increase and maintain blood 
pressure. Anaphylactic shock is treated with
diphenhydramine (Benadryl), 
epinephrine 
(an "Epi-pen"), steroid medications
 methylprednisolone (Solu-
 Medrol ), 
and sometimes a H2-Blocker medication (for example,
 famotidine [
 Pepcid ],
 cimetidine [
 Tagamet ], etc.). Cardiogenic shock is treated by identifying and treating the underlying 
cause. A patient with a heart attack may require a surgical procedure called a
 cardiac catheterization to unblock an artery. A patient with congestive heart 
failure may need medications to support and increase the force of the heart's 
beat. In severe or prolonged cases, a
 heart transplant may be the only 
treatment. Hypovolemic shock is treated with fluids (saline) in minor cases, but may 
require multiple blood transfusions in severe cases. The underlying cause of the 
bleeding must also be identified and corrected. Neurogenic shock is the most difficult to treat. Damage to the spinal cord is 
often irreversible and causes problems with the natural regulatory functions of 
the body. Besides fluids and monitoring, immobilization (keeping the spine from 
moving), anti-inflammatory medicine such as steroids, and sometimes surgery are 
the main parts of treatment. Self-Care at Home Call 911 for immediate medical attention any time a person has symptoms of 
shock. Do not wait for symptoms to worsen before calling for help. Stay with the 
person until help arrives, and if possible, stay on the line with the 911 
 dispatcher because they may have specific instructions for you. While waiting for help or on the way to the emergency room, check the 
person's
 a irway,
 b reathing and
 c irculation (the
 ABCs ). Administer CPR if you are trained. 
If the person is breathing on his or her own, continue to check breathing every 
 2 minutes until help arrives. Do NOT move a person who has a known or suspected spinal injury (unless 
 they are in imminent danger of further injury). Have the person lie down on his or her back with the
 feet elevated above 
the head (if raising the legs causes
 pain or injury, keep the person flat) to 
increase blood flow to vital organs. Do not raise the head. Keep the person warm and comfortable. Loosen tight clothing and cover them 
with a blanket. Do not give fluids by mouth, even if the person complains of
 thirst . There 
is a choking risk in the event of sudden
 loss of consciousness . Give appropriate
 first aid for any injuries. Direct pressure should be applied to any
 wounds that are bleeding 
 significantly.
 
PREVENTION:  Learn ways to prevent
 heart disease , injuries, dehydration and other causes 
of shock. If you have a known
 allergy , carry an epinephrine pen, which your doctor can 
prescribe. Avoid severe
 allergy triggers. What is the outlook for shock? Prompt treatment of medical shock is essential for the best outcome. Moreover, 
the outlook depends on the cause of the shock, the general health of the 
patient, and the promptness of treatment and recovery. Generally,
 hypovolemic shock and anaphylactic shock respond well to medical 
treatment if initiated early. Septic shock is a serious condition with a mortality rate of 24% 
 to 50% 
according to some estimates. The sooner the infection is treated and fluids are 
administered, the greater the chances of success. Hospitals are now developing 
 and utilizing specific protocols to identify and aggressively treat septic 
 shock patients. Cardiogenic shock has a poor prognosis, with only 1/3 of patients surviving. 
Because this type of shock results from injury or dysfunction of the heart it is 
often difficult to treat and overcome. Spinal shock also has a very poor prognosis because the spinal cord mediates 
so many important bodily functions. There are currently very few effective 
treatments but medical research is making advances in the treatment of spinal 
injuries.
</first>
</file1>