<file1>
<first>Motion Sickness Symptoms, Remedies, Treatment, and Cure
What should you know about motion sickness? Motion sickness is the feeling you get when the motion you sense with your inner ear is different from the motion you visualize. It is a common condition that occurs in some people who travel by car, train, airplane, or boat. Many people suffer from this condition if they ride on a roller coaster or other similar amusement park rides. Motion sickness progresses from a feeling of uneasiness to
 sweating and/or
 dizziness . This is usually quickly followed by
 nausea and/or
 vomiting . 
SYMPTOMS:  The signs and symptoms of motion sickness usually begin with a feeling of uneasiness followed by cold sweats and
 dizziness . Some people may exhibit
 pale skin and increased saliva production along with
 headache and
 fatigue .
 Nausea and
 vomiting usually occur after these initial symptoms. 
CAUSES:  Motion sickness is caused by the mixed signals sent to the brain by the eyes and the inner ear (semicircular canals). If you cannot see the motion your body&amp;#39;s feeling, or conversely, if you cannot feel the motion your eyes see, then it is likely that the brain will get mixed signals and the person will develop some aspect or symptom of motion sickness. Who gets motion sickness? Although
 pregnant women and children are more susceptible to motion sickness, almost anyone that is traveling is at risk for motion sickness. For those people who travel on boats, seasickness can be considered a form of motion sickness. Other risk factors include the: Person&amp;#39;s fear or
 anxiety about traveling Mode of travel Poor ventilation in the traveling vehicle The inability to see out of a window to aid orientation Do you need to see a doctor to treat motion sickness? Most people with motion sickness do not need to see their doctor to treat it. Usually, laboratory testing is not required. What
home remedieshelp motion sickness go away? Before taking these medications, read the precautions because many of these
 drugs have side effects, for example, drowsiness,
 dry mouth , blurry vision, and occasionally disorientation. Treatment for motion sickness can consist of medical treatment, simple changes in the environment , for example, get fresh air. Some people with motion sickness respond well to biofeedback training and relaxation techniques. Herbs for to treat motion sickness are
 ginger , peppermint, and tea. Some people respond to
 acupuncture . People who drive vehicles or operate heavy equipment should not take these medications. What
drugsmake sickness go away permanently? Most people with motion sickness can prevent it by taking medications that you put on the skin if you are if you are prone to motion sickness; however, most drugs used to treat motion sickness can help prevent it because it cannot be cured.
 Over-the-counter medications, and occasionally prescription medications, are used to relieve and in some cases prevent motion sickness. Some of the more common medications that can be used for motion sickness include: scopolamine (transdermal patches,
 Transderm-Scop ) dimenhydrinate (Dramamine) meclizine (
 Antivert ,
 Bonine ,
 Meni-D ,
 Antrizine ) promethazine (Phenergan,
 Phenadoz ,
 Promethegan ) diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) cyclizine (Marezine) When should I call a doctor for motion sickness? Most people with motion sickness do not need to see a doctor to treat it unless the person begins to get
 dehydration from persistent and intractable vomiting. For most people with motin sickness the symptoms slowly decrease and then disappear. 
PREVENTION:  Most people with motion sickness can be prevent it by taking the medications because if you put on the skin if you are prone to motion sickness. Most drugs used to treat motion sickness will help prevent motion sickness rather than to cure it. There are other ways to reduce or prevent motion sickness without the use of medication. The following is a list of suggestions that may help reduce or prevent motion sickness: Eat light meals or snacks 24 hours before traveling, and try to avoid big or high fat content meals Sit toward the front of an aircraft for a smoother ride If you&amp;#39;re on a boat, ask for a cabin on the upper deck toward the front of the boat, and keep your eyes fixed as much as possible on the horizon or land During car travel, sit in the front seat of the car and keep your eyes on the horizon, and rest your head against the seat back and try to hold relatively still On planes, trains and cars, turn the air vents toward your face Avoid
 smoking Short, shallow and rapid
 breathing can often contribute to motion sickness symptoms, therefore concentrate on maintaining slow and deep breathing There are companies that market bracelets and bands that claim that they can prevent motion sickness using acupressure technology against certain pressure points, so that the transmission of nausea is blocked before it can be registered by the brain. Though these products may work for some people, most evidence is anecdotal and large studies have not been conducted to prove efficacy.</first>
</file1>