<file1>
<first>Sleep and Sleep Disorders in Children and Teenagers
How much sleep do children need? Just as with adults, the amount of
 sleep children need varies with both age and unique needs of the individual. Below are general guidelines for children of various ages. 
If your child is happy and thriving, but needs more or fewer hours of
 sleep than indicated 
below - rest assured they will remain healthy. The National Sleep Foundation&amp;#39;s 
2015 Guidelines recommend the following for sleep in children and
 teens . Can a lack of sleep impact a child's behavior? The symptoms of a lack of sleep are often obvious to watchful parents. Some of these tell-tale signs include: recurrently falling asleep in the car (excluding young infants); requiring extreme stimulation and repetitive reminders to get up in the morning; behavioral abnormalities such as excessive emotionalism, aggression, and crankiness; and an older child's (over 8 years of age) recurrent need for an afternoon nap. What is sleep hygiene? A common definition of sleep hygiene is
 "all behavioral and environmental factors that precede sleep and may interfere with sleep." Daytime sleepiness and trouble sleeping may be a reflection of poor sleep hygiene. Detailed specifics are listed below. General areas to consider include: Personal habits: Establish consistent routines around bedtimes and awakening times Sleep environment: The bedroom should be a slightly cooler temperature 
(between 60 F to 67 F or 15.5 C to 19.4 C), and eliminate any distracting noise in the bedroom Getting ready for bed: Establish a calming pre-sleep ritual (for example, reading, not watching TV) and Miscellaneous: Examples include limiting intake of foods/liquids/medications which may disrupt a restful sleep What are some common sleep disorders in children? The University of Michigan's
 Sleep Disorders program includes five issues that may be disruptive of good sleep practices. These include: Sleep Apnea symptoms in children Sleep apnea is an extremely serious sleep pathology in which the child will struggle to 
breath and possibly stop
 breathing . This process most commonly is a consequence 
of an enlarged tonsil and adenoid tissues that obstruct the child's upper
 airway . Parents of such children will report that it sounds as if their child is being choked during sleep. Complications of sleep apnea include reduced oxygen to the brain and strain of the right side of the heart. If you believe your child may have sleep apnea, you should discuss your concerns with your child's pediatrician. An evaluation by and ENT (ears-nose-throat) specialist is often indicated. It is helpful to either audio/video 
record such an episode prior to such an evaluation. Parasomnia symptoms in children Parasomnias are disruptive sleep related events. They include several infrequent events (
 periodic limb movement disorder ,
 restless leg syndrome ) and more common events (
 teeth grinding , night terrors, and
 nightmares , sleepwalking, and
 bedwetting ). Periodic limb movement disorder occurs while asleep and is characterized by repetitive leg and (occasionally) arm movement that persist throughout the night. The child or teenager does not complain of any discomfort or abnormal sensations. In contrast,
 restless leg syndrome occurs while awake and affected individuals often describe a sensation of their legs "falling asleep." Nightmares occur during REM (dreaming period) sleep and thus are more common later in the night. The child acts scared but may be comforted by their parents. Such children will often be able to remember their dream. Simple parental reassurance and comforting is effective. In contrast, night terrors occur in non-
 REM sleep and thus generally within the first 4 hours of sleep. The child may become very violent with crying out in a confused manner as well as thrashing of arms and legs. Routine comforting of the child is not helpful and the child will be confused and bewildered if awakened. Generally, the child will rapidly return to a "normal" sleep with no memory of the events in the morning.
 Confusional arousal symptoms in children Confusional arousals are a variant of night terrors in older infants and toddlers that occur during the first half of the nighttime sleep sequence. It is felt that the child is so deeply asleep and the normal waking pattern at the end of the sleep cycle is suppressed. The major distinguishing point of confusional arousals versus night terrors is that the former gradually build from moaning, to crying out, and may culminate in the child standing and yelling out apparent random words or phrases. Conversely, night terrors tend to have an acute onset with the very rapid development of thrashing and yelling (commonly for the parents or caregivers). Confusional arousal and night terrors share several key points important for the child: Don't try to awaken the child. They are asleep and if awakened, will have difficult time falling back to sleep. Anything that upsets the normal sleep rhythms (illness, not sleeping in their own home, and disrupted naps) may trigger either pattern. Night terror symptoms in children Night terrors are somewhat rare events that have their highest frequency in children 4 to 12 years of age. They are commonly outgrown by adulthood, though some adults manifest the same brain
 EEG ("brain wave") changes during sleepwalking. Night terrors differ from nightmares (see previously). Night terrors manifest themselves with the person bolting upright in bed, screaming and thrashing about and stare blankly at the concerned adult who has come to investigate. They tend to occur during the first third of the child's sleep cycle. Children characteristically do not "calm down" when their parent attempts to soothe what appears to be a fearful experience. EEG studies demonstrate that the child is not awake (i.e. he/she is asleep), and if awakened, has no knowledge or memory of the immediately preceding events. The duration of night terror episodes is short lived. Some authorities believe that night terrors may be a response to sleep deprivation,
 stress ,
 fever , or
 fatigue .
 Narcolepsy symptoms in children Narcolepsy is more common in adults than children. It has been defined as "a chronic sleep disorder characterized by overwhelming daytime drowsiness and sudden attacks of sleep. Narcolepsy is a chronic condition for which there is no cure." Research has shown that narcolepsy is not a type of
 seizure ,
 fainting episode, or psychological illness. Symptoms of narcolepsy include: Excessive daytime sleepiness: affected individuals have an uncontrollable need to sleep during the day; Sudden loss of muscle tone (Cataplexy): this may range from slurred speech to total collapse of all voluntary muscles. Emotional stimulation (often positive by nature, for example, laughter) may trigger such an attack; Sleep paralysis: Characterized by a temporary (1-2 minutes) period of the inability to speak or move when falling asleep or waking; Vivid or frightening hallucinations which occur most commonly during REM (dreaming) sleep. Sleepwalking symptoms in children The onset of sleepwalking (somnambulism) typically presents in prepubertal children most frequently at age 11 to 12, and occurs more often in boys than girls. The overall incidence of sleepwalking is approximately 18%. Like night terrors, the individual is difficult to arouse during the event 
and does not remember the experience. Sleepwalking most commonly occurs during the first third of the sleep cycle. Some sleepwalkers may also mumble during sleepwalking episodes and occasionally obscene words may be uttered. Medications are rarely necessary to manage sleepwalking episodes. Ensuring a safe environment (protection against falls 
or
 walking out of the house) and maintenance of good sleep habits (avoiding sleep deprivation) are important considerations to prevent sleepwalking.
 Do teenagers have the same sleep requirements as younger children? Most teens need about 8 to 10 hours of sleep per day. Some studies have indicated that they have a different internal "sleep clock" than those younger or older than them. Researchers have demonstrated that teens are truly "night owls," and if left to their own devices, would spontaneously wake from a good night's sleep anywhere from 9:00 am to 10:00 am. High school teachers who have classes before this time period have empiric experience to second this observation. Younger children may need anywhere from 12-15 hours (infant: 2 naps plus nighttime long block) to 
9-11 hours (middle school child). How can I teach my child or teenager healthy sleep habits and good sleep hygiene? Primary to establishing good sleep habits is a realization that sleep is a normal and necessary function. However, just as 
with other normal and necessary functions (for example, eating, toilet training, etc.), a battle may develop between parents and their child in this area. All children older than 5 to 6 months of age need to master the ability to self-soothe and relax in order to successfully fall asleep. Depriving them of this skill by either feeding or rocking them to sleep, reading until the child falls asleep, or lying down with the child in order 
to facilitate falling asleep, is a recipe for frustration - both for the child and the parent. Tired children (of any age) intuitively know when they are tired and, if provided the proper environment, will easily and quickly fall asleep. When they awaken during the middle of the night they are capable of falling back to sleep without parental intervention. In this circumstance, both child and parents awake refreshed the next morning. What are some ways I can help my child or teenager get a better night's sleep? These "do's" are adapted from "
 Sleep Problems : Your Child" University of Michigan Health Care System 
and "Healthy Sleep Tips" from the National Sleep Foundation. What are some "don&amp;#39;ts" for getting my child or teen to sleep? These "don&amp;#39;ts" are adapted from "Sleep Problems: Your Child" University of Michigan Health Care System.</first>
</file1>