<file1>
<first>Trigeminal Neuralgia
Introduction to trigeminal neuralgia (TN) The brain is connected to the body by the spinal cord with spinal nerves sending and receiving impulses and messages to and from the brain. However, there are twelve cranial nerves that directly connect to the body. These nerves are involved with the muscle and sensory function of the head and neck. (The exception is cranial nerve X or the vagus nerve, which is also responsible for the parasympathetic system of the chest and abdomen). The trigeminal nerve (cranial nerve V) is so named because it has three (tri) branches responsible for face sensation; one branch also regulates chewing. The ophthalmic branch (V
 1 ) is responsible for sensation from the
 scalp , forehead, upper
 eyelid and tip of the nose. The maxillary branch (V
 2 ) sensation covers the lower eyelid, the side of the nose, the upper lip and cheek, and the upper
 teeth and gums. The mandibular branch (V
 3 ) is responsible for sensation of the lower teeth and gums, lower lip, chin, jaw, and part of the ear. It is also responsible for supplying the muscles involved with chewing (mastication), those muscles involved with chewing. What is trigeminal neuralgia (TN)? Trigeminal neuralgia is inflammation of the trigeminal nerve, causing intense facial
 pain . It is also known as tic douloureax because the intense
 pain can cause patients to contort their face into a grimace and cause the head to move away from the pain. The obvious movement is known as a tic. The pain of trigeminal neuralgia is intense and may be an isolated episode or may be occur every few hours, minutes, or seconds. There can be months or years between attacks, but in some patients whose pain is not well controlled; it can lead to a
 chronic pain syndrome, affecting activities of daily life and cause
 depression . Though it can affect people of any age, trigeminal neuralgia tends to afflict people older than 60 years of age. It affects the right side of the face five times more often than the left. 
CAUSES:  Most often, the cause of trigeminal neuralgia is idiopathic, meaning the 
cause is not known. There are some instances when the nerve can be compressed by 
nearby blood vessels, aneurysms, or tumors. There are inflammatory causes of trigeminal neuralgia because of systemic 
diseases including
 multiple sclerosis ,
 sarcoidosis , and
 Lyme disease . There also 
is an association with collagen vascular diseases including
 scleroderma and
 systemic lupus erythematosus .
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of trigeminal neuralgia include an acute onset of sharp, stabbing 
pain to one side of the face. It tends to begin at the angle of the jaw and 
radiate along the junction lines; between the ophthalmic branchV
 1 and maxillary 
branch V
 2, or the maxillary branch V
 2 and the mandibular branch V
 3 . The pain is severe and described as an electric
 shock . It may be made worse 
by light touch, chewing, or
 cold exposure in the mouth. In the midst of an 
attack, affected individuals shield their face trying to protect it from being touched. This 
is an important diagnostic sign because with many other pain syndromes like a
 toothache , the 
person will rub or hold the face to ease the pain. While there may be only one attack of pain, the person may experience 
recurrent sharp pain every few hours or every few seconds. Between the attacks, 
the pain resolves completely and the the person has no symptoms. However, because 
of fear that the intense pain might return, people can be quite distraught. 
Trigeminal neuralgia tends not to occur when the person is asleep, and this 
differentiates it from migraines, which often waken the 
person. After the first episode of attacks, the pain may subside for months or years 
but there is always the risk that trigeminal neuralgia will recur without 
warning. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Idiopathic trigeminal neuralgia is a clinical diagnosis and often no testing 
is required after the health care professional takes a history of the situation 
and performs a physical examination which should be normal. It is important to remember that the neurologic exam must be normal. There 
are two specific areas to test. There can be no muscle
 weakness ; V
 3 is 
responsible for chewing and there can be no jaw or facial weakness found. The corneal reflex controlled by V
 1 must be present. When the
 cornea or 
covering of the eye is touched, the eye blinks in response. If these two 
findings are not normal, the search should begin for an inflammatory or 
compression cause of the trigeminal nerve. Some clinicians may order an
 MRI to 
help diagnose other conditions that may cause trigeminal neuralgia. The International
 Headache Society has established criteria for making the 
diagnosis and includes the following: 
TREATMENT:  Idiopathic trigeminal neuralgia most often is treated with good success using 
a single anticonvulsant medication such as
 carbamazepine (
 Tegretol ). Gabapentin (
 Neurontin , Gabarone),
 baclofen and
 phenytoin (
 Dilantin ,
 Dilantin-125 ) may be used as second line
 drugs , often in 
addition to carbamazepine. In many patients, as time progresses, carbamazepine 
becomes less effective and these drugs can be used in combination to control the 
pain. Should pain persist and medication fail to be effective, surgery or
 radiation therapy may be other treatment options. Lamotrigine (
 Lamictal ) may be prescribed for
 multiple sclerosis patients who 
develop trigeminal neuralgia.
</first>
</file1>