<file1>
<first>Tennis Elbow

ABOUT: Tennis elbow is tendinitis of the outer elbow. Strain of an elbow tendon causes tennis elbow. Risks of tennis elbow include activities that can strain the elbow. Tennis elbow symptoms include dull
 pain and tenderness at the outer elbow often with a sensation of
 weakness and
 stiffness . A physician uses a patient&amp;#39;s history and physical examination to diagnose tennis elbow. The standard treatment for tennis elbow involves measures to reduce the local inflammation. The prognosis for tennis elbow is excellent. It&amp;#39;s possible to prevent tennis elbow by avoiding activities that strain the elbow. What is tennis elbow? Tennis elbow is inflammation of the tendon at the outer portion of the elbow, leading to
 pain . Classically, tennis elbow is a strain injury to this tendon from hitting a backhand shot at tennis. The medical term for tennis elbow is lateral
 epicondylitis because it involves inflammation at the insertion point of the tendon at the outer portion of the humerus bone at the elbow joint (the epicondyle). Most people with lateral epicondylitis actually acquire it from activities other than playing tennis. In contrast, when the tendon that attaches at the inner portion of the elbow is inflamed, the condition is referred to as medial epicondylitis (or "golfer&amp;#39;s elbow" because golfers commonly injure this area after striking the ground to take a deep divot). 
CAUSES:  A strain injury to the tendon at the outer portion of the elbow causes tennis elbow. While this can occur by straining during a backhand tennis shot, it can also occur from many repetitive activities that can strain the elbow. These activities include using a screwdriver or work that includes similar motions, Frisbee disc throwing, and lifting objects by extending the wrist, etc.
 
RISKS:  Risks of tennis elbow include any activity that can strain the elbow joint. Such activities include tennis, falling onto the extended upper extremity, using a screwdriver when unaccustomed, casting a fishing net, etc. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of tennis elbow include dull pain and tenderness at the outer elbow. There can be elbow stiffness and a sensation of weakness. Typically with tennis elbow, people retain the full range of motion of the elbow and there is no significant swelling or discoloration. Holding a beverage cup or
 shaking hands can bring on the pain. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Physicians diagnose tennis elbow based on the history of outer
 elbow pain and tenderness often with recent repetitive-use injury. Tenderness at the outer elbow with normal range of motion of the elbow joint assures the diagnosis. Generally, no radiology testing is necessary.
 MRI scanning can illustrate inflammation of the outer elbow. 
TREATMENT:  Resting the elbow and employing measures to reduce the local inflammation are effective treatments for tennis elbow. Cold application several times daily and anti-inflammatory medications (such as
 ibuprofen [
 Advil ] or
 naproxen [
 Aleve ]) can be helpful. Physical therapy and rehabilitation exercises for the elbow that are guided by therapists can be helpful for persisting pain and inflammation. For tennis elbow that is resistant to these measures, local
 cortisone injection can be beneficial. Rarely, surgical repair of the injured tendon is considered.
 What is the outlook (prognosis) for tennis elbow? Tennis elbow most often has a complete recovery with conservative measures, particularly by resting the joint and avoiding reinjury. 
PREVENTION:  Avoiding strain injury of the elbow joint can prevent tennis elbow. Tennis players can benefit by proper instruction in hitting techniques. Tennis elbow straps can be used to minimize the risk of injury to the elbow tendons. Exercises that strengthen the involved muscles can be helpful to avoid a reoccurrence once symptoms have disappeared.
</first>
</file1>