<file1>
<first>Erectile Dysfunction: Testosterone Replacement Therapy
Testosterone deficiency introduction Testosterone is a hormone produced by the testicles and is responsible for the proper development of male sexual characteristics. Testosterone is also important for maintaining muscle bulk, adequate levels of
 red blood cells , 
memory, bone growth, sense of well-being and sexual function. Inadequate production of testosterone is not a common cause of
 erectile dysfunction ; however, when
 ED does occur due to decreased testosterone production, testosterone replacement therapy may improve the problem. 
CAUSES:  As a man ages, the amount of testosterone in his body gradually declines. This natural decline starts after age 30 and continues throughout life. Other causes of lowered testosterone levels include: Injury, infection, or loss of the testicles. Chemotherapy or
 radiation treatment for
 cancer . Genetic abnormalities such as Klinefelter's Syndrome (extra X chromosome). Hemochromatosis (too much iron in the body). Dysfunction of the
 pituitary gland (a gland in the brain that produces many important hormones). Inflammatory diseases such as
 sarcoidosis (a condition that causes inflammation of the
 lungs ). Medications, especially hormones used to treat
 prostate cancer and corticosteroid
 drugs . Chronic illness. Chronic
 kidney failure . Liver cirrhosis . Stress . Alcoholism Chronic pain and use of narcotics for
 pain contol. HIV and
 AIDS The significance of age-related testosterone decline is controversial and poorly understood.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Without adequate testosterone a man may lose his sex drive, experience
 erectile dysfunction , feel
 depressed , have a decreased sense of well-being, and have
 difficulty concentrating . What changes occur in the body due to testosterone deficiency? Decrease in muscle mass, with an increase in body fat and
 weight gain Changes in
 cholesterol levels . Decrease in
 hemoglobin and possibly mild
 anemia . Fragile bones (
 osteoporosis ). Decrease in body hair. Changes in
 cholesterol levels and
 lipid levels. How do I find out if I have a testosterone deficiency? The only accurate way to detect the condition is to have your doctor measure the amount of testosterone in your blood. Because testosterone levels fluctuate throughout the day, several measurements will need to be taken to detect a deficiency. Doctors prefer, if possible, to test levels early in the morning since this is when testosterone levels are at their highest. How is testosterone deficiency treated? Testosterone deficiency can be treated by: Intramuscular injections, generally every two or three weeks Testosterone patch worn either on the body or on the scrotum (the sac that contains the testicles) Testosterone gel Mucoadhesive material applied above the
 teeth twice a day Injectible pellets Each of these options provides adequate levels of hormone replacement; however, they all have different advantages and disadvantages. Talk to your doctor to see which approach may be right for you.
 Who shouldn't take testosterone replacement therapy? Men who have
 prostate cancer or
 breast cancer should not take testosterone replacement therapy. All men considering testosterone replacement therapy should undergo a thorough
 prostate cancer screening prior to starting this therapy with a rectal exam and
 PSA test . What are the side effects of testosterone replacement therapy? In general,
 hormone replacement therapy is safe. Possible side effects 
include: Acne or oily skin. Mild fluid retention. Stimulation of prostate tissue, with perhaps some increased urination symptoms such as a decreased stream or frequency. Breast enlargement. Worsening of
 sleep apnea (a
 sleep disorder that results in frequent night time awakenings and daytime sleepiness). Decreased testicular size. Laboratory abnormalities that can occur with hormone replacement include: Changes in cholesterol and lipid levels. Increase in red blood cell count. Decrease in sperm count, producing
 infertility (especially in younger men). Increase in PSA If you are taking hormone replacement therapy, regular follow-up appointments with your doctor are important. Like any other medication, directions for administering testosterone should be followed exactly as your doctor orders. If you are unsure or have any questions about testosterone replacement therapy, ask your doctor.
</first>
</file1>