<file1>
<first>Diabetes Urine Tests

ABOUT: Urine tests may be done in people with
 diabetes to evaluate severe
 hyperglycemia (severe
 high blood sugar ) by looking 
for ketones in the urine. Ketones are a metabolic product 
produced when fat is metabolized. Ketones increase when there is insufficient
 insulin to use
 glucose for energy. Urine tests are also done to look for 
the presence of
 protein in the urine , which is a sign of kidney damage. Urine glucose measurements are less 
reliable than
 blood glucose measurements and are not used to diagnose
 diabetes or evaluate
 treatment for diabetes . They may be used for screening purposes. Testing for ketones is most common in 
people with
 type 1 diabetes . Both people with
 type 1 diabetes and
 type 2 diabetes typically have microalbumin testing. What are urine tests for diabetes? Urine tests are tests performed in a clinical laboratory or at home using 
self-test kits and a sample of the patient's urine. Urine tests can be performed 
for a variety of reasons, but in people with
 diabetes , they are most commonly 
used to look for ketones or microalbumin (see below). Urine glucose (
 sugar ) can 
also be measured, but this is less valuable than blood glucose levels for 
diagnosis and monitoring of diabetes, so this is not commonly done as a way to 
monitor blood glucose status.
 Ketonetest This test detects the presence of ketones, which are 
byproducts of
 metabolism that form in the presence of severe hyperglycemia 
(elevated
 blood sugar ). Ketones are formed from fat that is burned by the body 
when there is insufficient insulin to allow glucose to be used for fuel. When 
ketones build up to high levels, ketoacidosis (a serious and life-threatening 
condition) may occur. Ketone testing can be performed both at home and in the clinical laboratory. 
Ketones can be detected by dipping a test strip into a sample of urine. A color 
change on the test strip signals the presence of ketones in the urine. Ketones 
occur most commonly in people with type 1 diabetes, but uncommonly, people with
 type 2 diabetes may test positive for ketones. Microalbumintest The microalbumin test detects microalbumin, a type of 
protein, in the urine. Protein is present in the urine when there is damage to 
the kidneys. Since the damage to blood vessels that occurs as a complication of 
diabetes can lead to kidney problems, the microalbumin test is done to check for 
damage to the kidneys over time. 
DIAGNOSIS:  While urine tests can show signs that may signal diabetes, such as elevated
 sugar or ketones, the diagnosis of diabetes is made on the basis of blood tests. Urine tests may be done in some cases as back-up testing or for screening to see if blood tests should be done, but the diagnosis of diabetes is made after blood glucose testing.
 When are urine tests used in people with diabetes? The ketone test is generally recommended for people with type 1 diabetes. Those with type 1 diabetes should test their urine for ketones when they are ill, especially if they have
 vomiting and
 nausea .
 Pregnant women with type 1 diabetes may also be advised to test their urine for ketones. Ketone testing is also done when the blood sugar is noted to be very high (over about 240 mg/dL). Your doctor can advise you specifically about recommended testing practices for your individual situation. Sometimes, people with type 2 diabetes may be advised to check their urine for ketones. Those with type 2 diabetes should discuss with their doctor whether ketone testing is necessary and under what circumstances. The microalbumin test is done once per year starting at the time of diagnosis in people with type 2 diabetes. Even though protein in the urine is a sign of long-term damage to the kidneys, many people have type 2 diabetes without knowing it, so it is unclear how long they have had the condition. In people with type 1 diabetes, the micoalbumin test may not be performed until the condition has been present for up to 5 years.
</first>
</file1>