<file1>
<first>Tetrahydrobiopterin Deficiency
What is tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency is a rare disorder that increases the levels of several substances, including phenylalanine, in the blood. Phenylalanine is a building block of proteins (an amino acid) that is obtained through the
 diet . It is found in all proteins and in some
 artificial sweeteners . If tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency is not treated, phenylalanine can build up to harmful levels in the body, causing intellectual disability and other serious health problems. 
SYMPTOMS:  High levels of phenylalanine are present from early infancy in people with untreated tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency. Infants with this condition appear normal at birth, but medical problems ranging from mild to severe become apparent over time. The signs and symptoms of this condition can include: intellectual disability,
 progressive problems 
with development,
 movement disorders,
 difficulty swallowing ,
 seizures ,
 behavioral problems, and
 an inability to control body temperature.
 How common is tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? This condition is very rare, affecting about 1 per 
million newborns. In most parts of the world, tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency 
accounts for only 1 percent to 2 percent of all cases of elevated phenylalanine 
levels. The remaining cases are caused by a similar condition called
 phenylketonuria (PKU). In certain countries, including Saudi Arabia, Taiwan, China, and Turkey, it is more common for elevated levels of phenylalanine to be caused by tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency. What genes are related to tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency can be caused by mutations in one of several genes, including GCH1, PCBD1, PTS, and QDPR. These genes provide instructions for making enzymes that help produce and recycle tetrahydrobiopterin in the body. Tetrahydrobiopterin (also known as BH4) is a molecule that helps process several amino acids, including phenylalanine. It is also involved in the production of 
chemicals called neurotransmitters, which transmit signals between nerve cells 
in the brain. If one of the enzymes fails to function correctly because 
of a gene mutation, little or no tetrahydrobiopterin is available to help 
process phenylalanine. As a result, phenylalanine can build up in the blood and 
other tissues. Because nerve cells in the brain are particularly sensitive to 
phenylalanine levels, excessive amounts of this substance can cause
 brain damage . Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency can also alter the levels of certain neurotransmitters, which disrupts normal brain function.
 How do people inherit tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? This condition is inherited in an autosomal recessive 
pattern, which means both copies of the gene in each cell have mutations. The 
parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive condition each carry one copy of the mutated gene, but they typically do not show signs and symptoms of the condition. What other names do people use for tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? HPA
 BH4 Deficiency
 Hyperphenylalaninemia caused by a defect in biopterin
 metabolism Hyperphenylalaninemia, Non-Phenylketonuric
 Non-Phenylketonuric Hyperphenylalaninemia Source: Genetics Home Reference, National Library of 
Medicine, National Institutes of Health
</first>
</file1>