<file1>
<first>The Digestion Process (Organs and Functions)
Digestion
definition The energy required for all the processes and activities that take place in 
our bodies is derived from the foods we ingest. The digestive system allows us 
to utilize food from such diverse sources as meat from an animal and the roots 
of a plant, and utilize them as an energy source. Whether it is the ability to 
coordinate the chewing of the food without injuring our tongue and lips or the 
propulsion of the food from the stomach into the duodenum while releasing the 
appropriate enzymes, our digestive system allows us to manage the process 
without much thought and often while performing other tasks. What is digestion? The process of digestion is a fascinating and complex one that takes the food 
we place in our mouth and turns it into energy and waste products. This process 
takes place in the gastrointestinal tract, a long, connected, tubular structure 
that starts with the mouth and ends with the anus. The food is propelled forward 
within the system, altered by enzymes and hormones into usable particles and 
absorbed along the way. Other organs that support the digestive process are the
 liver , gallbladder, and pancreas. The time it takes for food to travel from 
entering the mouth to be excreted as waste is around 30 to 40 hours. The mouth The mouth is the entry point for food, but the digestive system often gets 
ready before the first piece of food even enters our mouth. Saliva is released 
by the salivary glands into our oral cavity when we smell food. Once the food 
enters the mouth, chewing (mastication) breaks food into smaller particles that 
can be more easily attacked by the enzymes in saliva. Our
 teeth can perform a 
cutting as well as grinding function to accomplish this task. The tongue assists 
in mixing the food with the saliva and then the tongue and roof of the mouth 
(soft palate) help move the food along to the pharynx and
 esophagus .
 The pharynx and esophagus The pharynx (throat) is the transition area from the mouth to the esophagus. 
From the pharynx there are two paths that the food bolus can take; 1) the wrong 
path, which is down the windpipe into the
 lungs , or 2) the correct path into the 
esophagus and then the stomach. The act of swallowing is a complex process that 
closes the windpipe (to protect our lungs) and moves food into the esophagus. 
This process is mostly automatic (reflex) but it is also partially under our 
direct control. Once it enters the esophagus, food is moved down the esophagus and into our 
stomach. The esophagus is a muscular tube that contracts in a synchronized 
fashion (peristalsis) to move food down towards the stomach. While the muscles 
behind the food product contract, the muscles ahead of the food relax, causing 
the forward propulsion of the food. Peristalsis is the main mechanism by which 
food moves through our digestive system. Once the food approaches the stomach, a muscular valve (the lower esophageal 
sphincter) relaxes and lets the food pass into the stomach. This sphincter has 
the important function of closing the stomach so no food or stomach acid 
reenters the esophagus (and therefore avoiding
 heartburn or regurgitation). The stomach and small intestine From glands that line the stomach, acid and enzymes are secreted that 
continue the breakdown process of the food. The stomach muscles further mix the 
food. At the end of this process, the food you placed in your mouth has been 
transformed to a thick creamy fluid called chyme. This thick fluid is then pushed into the duodenum (the first part of the 
small intestine). With the help of enzymes from the pancreas and bile from the 
liver, further breakdown of the food occurs in the small intestine. The small intestine has three segments. The first segment is the duodenum where 
further breakdown of the food takes place. The next two parts of the small 
intestine (jejunum and ileum) are mostly responsible for the absorption of 
nutrients from the processed food into the bloodstream through the walls of the 
intestine. After the small intestine, the leftover waste leaves the upper 
gastrointestinal tract (upper GI tract) which is made up of everything above the
 large intestine , and moves into the large intestine or colon (the beginning of 
the
 lower GI tract).
 The colon, rectum, and anus The role of the lower GI tract is to solidify the waste product (by absorbing 
water), store the waste product until it can be evacuated (going to the 
bathroom) and help with the evacuation process. The large intestine (colon) has four parts: All together the colon is approximately 7
 feet long and connects to the rectum. Here as in most other parts of the GI 
system, the waste product is moved along by peristalsis. As the waste product 
passes through the colon, water is absorbed and stool is formed. The stool from the colon is stored in the rectum. The anal sphincter provides 
the control over releasing stool or holding it. Once stool arrives in the 
rectum, a feedback to the brain makes the person aware of the need for a bowel 
movement. Voluntary control over the anal sphincter lets us hold the stool until 
we go to the toilet. Three accessory digestive organs (pancreas, liver, gallbladder) Three other organs are instrumental in the digestive process.</first>
</file1>