<file1>
<first>Thyroiditis

ABOUT: *
ABOUT: medically edited by:
 Charles Patrick Davis, MD, PhD Thyroiditis is inflammation or swelling of the
 thyroid gland. There are several types off thyroiditis; Hashimoto's, postpartum, silent or painless and subacute. Symptoms of
 Hashimoto's thyroiditis may include
 fatigue ,
 depression ,
 cold intolerance,
 weight gain ,
 dry skin and hair,
 muscle cramps ,
 constipation , decreased
 concentration and sleepiness,
 leg swelling , puffy eyes; severe symptoms include a slow heart rate, low body temperature,
 heart failure and
 coma – cause is suspected immune mediated reaction. Postpartum thyroiditis may have two phases; phase one occurs about 1 to 4 months after giving birth when
 symptoms of hyperthyroidism occur and phase two that starts 4 
 to 8 months after delivery when the patient develops hyperthyroiditis symptoms – most women with postpartum thyroiditis return to normal function after 12 
 to 18 months and not all women go through phase two. Silent or painless thyroiditis develops like postpartum thyroiditis, but the person is not
 pregnant . Symptoms of subacute thyroiditis can be the same as postpartum thyroiditis, but it may also include neck, jaw, or ear
 pain . In contrast to other
 thyroid types, subacute thyroiditis can be caused by infection. What is thyroiditis? Thyroiditis (thy-roi-DY-tiss) is inflammation, or swelling, of the thyroid. 
There are several types of thyroiditis, one of which is Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
 Postpartum thyroiditis symptoms and signs Like Hashimoto&amp;#39;s thyroiditis, postpartum thyroiditis seems to be caused by a problem with the immune system. In the United States, postpartum thyroiditis occurs in about 5 to 10 percent of women. The first phase starts 1 to 4 months after giving birth. In this phase, you may get symptoms of
 hyperthyroidism because the damaged thyroid is leaking thyroid hormones out into the bloodstream. The second phase starts about 4 to 8 months after delivery. In this phase, you may get
 symptoms of hypothyroidism because, by this time, the thyroid has lost most of its hormones. Not everyone with postpartum thyroiditis goes through both phases. In most women who have postpartum thyroiditis, thyroid function returns to normal within 12 to 18 months after symptoms start. Risk factors for postpartum thyroiditis include having: An autoimmune disease, like
 type 1 diabetes A personal history or family history of
 thyroid disorders Having had postpartum thyroiditis after a previous
 pregnancy Silent or painless thyroiditis symptoms and signs Symptoms are the same as in postpartum thyroiditis, but they are not related to having given birth.
 Subacute thyroiditis Symptoms are the same as in postpartum and silent thyroiditis, but the 
inflammation in the thyroid leads to
 pain in the neck, jaw, or ear. Unlike the 
other types of thyroiditis, subacute thyroiditis may be caused by an infection.</first>
</file1>