<file1>
<first>Laser Tattoo Removal
Introduction It is estimated that close to 10% of the U.S. population 
has some sort of
 tattoo . Eventually, as many as 50% of them want to have laser 
tattoo removal. There is good news for those who have an unwanted body design. 
Newer laser tattoo removal techniques can eliminate your tattoo with minimal 
side effects. Here's how it works: lasers remove tattoos by breaking up the 
pigment colors of the tattoo with a high-intensity light beam. Black tattoo pigment absorbs all laser wavelengths, making it the easiest to treat. Other colors can only be treated by selected lasers based upon the pigment color. Who Can Benefit 
From Laser Tattoo Removal? Because each tattoo is unique, removal techniques 
must be tailored to suit each individual case. In the past, tattoos could be 
removed by a wide variety of methods but, in many cases, the
 scars were more 
unsightly than the tattoo itself. Patients with previously treated tattoos may 
also be candidates for laser therapy. Tattoos that have not been effectively 
removed by other treatments or through home remedies may respond well to laser 
therapy providing the prior treatments did not result in excessive scarring. How 
Do I Find a Reputable Doctor to Do Laser Tattoo Removal? To have a tattoo removed, you want to make sure you find a reputable dermatologist or
 cosmetic surgery center to ensure proper treatment and care. If possible, you should obtain a recommendation from your family doctor for a dermatologist or skin surgery center that specializes in tattoo removal. What Can I Expect During Laser Tattoo Removal? Depending on 
the size and color of your tattoo, the number of treatments will vary. Your 
tattoo may be removed in two to four visits, though many more sessions may be 
necessary. You should schedule a consultation, during which time a trained 
professional will evaluate your personal situation and advise you on the 
process. Treatment with the laser varies from patient to patient depending on 
the age, size and type of tattoo (amateur or professional). The color of the patient's skin, as well as the depth to which the tattoo pigment extends, will 
also affect the removal technique. In general, this is what will happen during 
an office visit for tattoo removal using the newer lasers: Protective eye shields are placed on the patient. The skin's reaction to the laser is tested to 
  determine the most effective energy for treatment. The treatment itself consists of placing a hand piece 
  against the surface of the skin and activating the laser light. As many 
  patients describe it, each pulse feels like a grease splatter or the snapping 
  of a rubber band against the skin. Smaller tattoos require fewer pulses while larger 
  ones require more. In either case, the tattoo requires several treatments and 
  multiple visits. At each treatment, the tattoo should become progressively 
  lighter. Immediately following treatment, an ice 
pack is applied to soothe the treated area. The patient will then be asked to 
apply a topical antibiotic cream or ointment. A bandage or patch will be used to 
protect the site and it should likewise be covered with a sun block when out in 
the sun. Most patients do not require any anesthesia. However, depending on the 
location of the tattoo and the
 pain threshold for the patient, the physician may 
elect to use some form of anesthesia (topical anesthesia cream or painkiller 
injections at the site of the procedure).
 What Are the Possible Side Effects of Laser Tattoo Removal? There are minimal side effects to laser tattoo 
removal. However, you should consider these factors in your decision: The tattoo removal site is at risk for infection. You 
  may also risk lack of complete pigment removal, and there is a slight chance 
  that the treatment can leave you with a permanent scar. You may also risk hypopigmentation, where the treated 
  skin is paler than surrounding skin, or
 hyperpigmentation , where the treated 
  skin is darker than surrounding skin. Cosmetic tattoos like lip liner, 
eyeliner and eyebrows may darken following treatment with tattoo removal lasers. 
Further treatment of the darkened tattoos usually results in fading. Is Laser 
Tattoo Removal Safe? Thanks to newer technology, laser tattoo removal has become much more effective with very little risk of scarring. Laser treatment is often safer than many traditional methods such as excision,
 dermabrasion or salabrasion (using moist gauze pads saturated with a salt solution to abrade the tattooed area) because of its unique ability to selectively treat pigment involved in the tattoo. In many cases, certain colors may be more effectively removed than others. It is known that blue/black tattoos respond particularly well to laser treatment -- the response of other colors is under investigation. Remember, the information provided here is designed to provide general information only and is not a replacement for a doctor's advice. For details pertaining to your specific case, please arrange a consultation with a physician experienced in the use of tattoo lasers.
 Does 
Insurance Cover Laser Tattoo Removal? Since tattoo removal is a personal option 
in most cases and is considered a cosmetic procedure, most insurance carriers 
will not cover the process unless it is medically necessary. Physicians or 
surgery centers practicing tattoo removal may also require payment in full on 
the day of the procedure. If you are considering tattoo removal, be sure to 
discuss associated costs up front and obtain all charges in 
writing before you undergo any treatment. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>