<file1>
<first>Biological Therapy
What is biological therapy? Biological or biologic therapy is treatment designed to stimulate or restore the ability of the body&amp;#39;s immune (natural internal defense) system to fight infection and disease. Biological therapy is also called biotherapy or
 immunotherapy and is commonly used to treat different kinds of cancers, as well as other conditions. How does biological therapy work? Biological therapy is a form of treatment that uses portions of the body&amp;#39;s natural immune system to treat a disease. Biological therapy is also used to protect the body from some of the side effects of certain treatments. Biological therapy often involves the use of substances called biological response modifiers (BRMs). The body normally produces these substances in small amounts in response to infection and disease. Using modern laboratory techniques, scientists can produce BRMs in large amounts for use in the treatment of
 cancer and other diseases, such as
 rheumatoid arthritis and
 Crohn&amp;#39;s disease . Biological therapy may also target specific molecules on
 cancer cells to destroy the cells, or it may target proteins that facilitate the growth of
 cancer cells. Depending on the agent, biological therapies can be given by mouth, intravenously, or as an injection.
 What are examples of biological therapies? Monoclonal antibodies,
 interferon , interleukin-2 (IL-2), and several types of colony-stimulating factors (CSF, GM- CSF, G-CSF) are forms of biological therapy. For example, interleukin-2 and interferon are two examples of BRMs being tested for the treatment of advanced
 malignant melanoma . Monoclonal antibodies are a common type of biological therapy for many different cancers and other conditions. These are laboratory-produced antibodies that are designed to attack specific proteins expressed by abnormal cells. Examples of monoclonal antibody
 drugs include
 rituximab , which is used to treat
 non-Hodgkin&amp;#39;s
 lymphoma , alemtuzumab (
 Campath ) to treat
 chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), and ipilimumab (Yervoy) for metastatic
 melanoma . Other kinds of monoclonal antibodies used to treat cancers target proteins that are responsible for cell growth. Examples of these drugs include bevacizumab (
 Avastin ), which targets vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), cetuximab (Erbitux) and panitumumab (Vectibix) to target the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR), and
 trastuzumab (
 Herceptin ) and pertuzumab (Perjeta) to target the human epidermal growth factor receptor- 2 (HER-2). Modes of biologic therapy that involve blocking the action of specific proteins of inflammation, called
 tumor necrosis factor (TNF), are being used for the treatment of a number of diseases, including
 rheumatoid arthritis and Crohn&amp;#39;s disease.
 Etanercept (
 Enbrel ) and
 infliximab (
 Remicade ) are examples of commercially available injectable TNF-blocking treatments for patients with severe
 rheumatoid arthritis . Biological therapy is a very active and exciting area of cancer research. What type of specialists administer biological therapy? Biological therapies are prescribed by specialists who treat cancers (oncologists or hematologist-oncologists), as well as other specialists, including rheumatologists and gastroenterologists.
 What are the
side effectsof biological therapy? The side effects of biological therapy depend on the type of treatment. Side effects include
 flu -like symptoms such as
 chills ,
 fever , muscle
 aches ,
 weakness ,
 loss of appetite ,
 nausea ,
 vomiting , and
 diarrhea . Some patients develop a
 rash , and some bleed or
 bruise easily. In addition, interleukin therapy can cause swelling. Depending on how severe these problems are, hospitalization during treatment may be required for some patients. Side effects are usually short-term and gradually subside after treatment ends. The long-term side effects of the various currently available biological therapies will be better defined with future research from which will also surely emerge new and valuable forms of these treatments.
</first>
</file1>