<file1>
<first>12 Foods to Eat for Constipation Relief
What is constipation? 
CAUSES:  1. Beans for constipation relief Beans have more than 10 grams of fiber per cup serving that&amp;#39;s more than almost any other fiber source. Beans have a great mixture of soluble and insoluble fiber, both of which helps the food keep moving through the
 intestines to relieve constipation. Take your pick: baked beans, black-eyed peas, garbanzo beans, lima beans, pinto beans, or kidney beans. Add any of these to salads, soups, casseroles, or pasta.
 2. Kiwi for constipation relief 3. Sweet potatoes for constipation relief 4. Popcorn for constipation relief Stay away from movie theater popcorn or popcorn laden with butter as the high fat content not only contains lots of calories, the fat can cause constipation.
 5. Nuts and seeds for constipation relief Nuts are a filling food that is also packed with fiber to help ease constipation. Almonds, pecans, and walnuts have more fiber than other nuts. Just 1 ounce of almonds (about 23 nuts) contains 3.5 g fiber, 1 ounce of pecans (about 19 halves) contains 2.7 g fiber, and 1 ounce of walnuts (14 halves) has 1.9 g fiber. Seeds are another good fiber-filled choice for constipation relief. A scant 1 tablespoon of sesame seeds contains 1.1 g fiber, while 1 ounce of pumpkin seeds (about 85 seeds) has a whopping 5 g fiber. Sprinkle seeds on top of salads for added fiber and crunch. Remember that nuts and seeds are high in calories, so keep portions small. Choose nuts and seeds that are raw or dry roasted, rather than roasted in oil.
 6. Whole grain bread for constipation relief Whole grains have lots of fiber, which is a good choice not only for the bowels, but also the heart. Researchers at the University of Finland in Helsinki found whole grain rye bread to be better than wheat bread and laxatives for relieving constipation. They reported their findings in the Journal of
 Nutrition in 2010. Their subjects ate enough slices (12.3 grams each) to get 30 grams of fiber a day, but you don&amp;#39;t have to eat that much for it to work. Arabinoxylan, the main component of dietary fiber in rye, helps keep food moving through the intestine. Ezekiel bread is another good choice for relief of constipation. It is bread made of sprouted whole grains and legumes, which provides a good dose of fiber and nutrients.
 7. Pears, plums, and apples for constipation relief 8. Berries for constipation relief 9. Flaxseed for constipation relief 10. Broccoli for constipation relief 11. Dried fruit for constipation relief Just remember that while dried fruit has more fiber than fresh fruit, it also has more calories.
 12. Prunes for constipation relief</first>
</file1>