<file1>
<first>15 Foods That Cause Constipation
What is the definition of constipation? Constipation  is a common problem where people find it difficult to have bowel movements. Constipation medically is defined as less than three bowel moments per week. If a person has less than one bowel movement per week, they are considered to have severe
 constipation . Symptoms of
 bloating , 
 gas , or pain passing bowel movements may accompany
 constipation . 
CAUSES:  Just as there are many foods you can eat to help prevent or relieve your constipation, there are foods that can have a binding effect that can make your constipation worse. These are 16 foods to avoid when you are constipated. Bananas Bananas are a conundrum when it comes to constipation foods to avoid. It&amp;#39;s a matter of timing: Unripe bananas can cause constipation; ripe bananas can help relieve constipation. Unripe or under-ripe green bananas cause constipation because they still have a lot of starch, which can be hard for the body to digest. Bananas also contain dietary 
 fiber (pectin), which draws water from the
 intestines toward the
 stool . If someone is already dehydrated, this can make constipation worse. Babies can also get constipated if they eat too many bananas. Moderation and a variety of fruits and veggies for your little one is the key. Chewing gum It is  not true that if you swallow a piece of gum it takes seven years to digest. However, it is true that if you swallow many pieces of gum in a short time, or if you swallow several pieces of gum with other indigestible foods such as seeds, this can create a mass that in rare cases, blocks the digestive tract. This blockage can cause constipation. Children under age 5 should not chew gum at all, and if you do chew gum, stick to just one or two pieces a day – and throw it out when you’re done chewing. Caffeine Like bananas,
 caffeine can go either way. Caffeine is a stimulant that can make a person have more bowel stools or in excess,
 diarrhea . If a person is dehydrated, the caffeine in coffee, black tea, colas, and
 chocolate can make the constipation worse. Gluten White rice White rice can cause constipation. There is a big difference between white rice and brown rice. White rice can lead to constipation because the husk, bran, and germ
 have been removed . That&amp;#39;s where all the fiber and nutrients are! Brown rice can help relieve constipation because the husk, bran, and germ
 have not been removed . Brown rice is a good source of whole grains and contains about 3.5 g fiber and 5 grams of protein in 1 cup. Persimmon Red meat There are plenty of reasons to avoid red meat. Red meat can make a person constipated, and it can cause constipation for several reasons. Red meat: Is high in fat, so it takes longer for the digestive tract to process it Has tough protein fibers that can be difficult for the stomach to digest Is rich in iron, which can be constipating Limit intake of red meat to avoid constipation. White bread While whole grain breads may help relieve constipation, white breads can cause or worsen it. This also applies to other products with a lot of white flour such as bagels, crackers, and pretzels. Unlike whole grains, white flour has no fiber. These foods are heavy on starch, and can back you up. Remember to choose whole grains. Alcohol Similar to caffeine, alcohol also can contribute to constipation. For example, alcohol is dehydrating, and it can slow
 digestion and irritate the bowel, which can worsen constipation symptoms. Limit alcohol intake, and alternate one alcoholic beverage with a glass of water or even a sports drink (such as Gatorade or Powerade) in between each alcoholic drink. Chocolate Chocolate is a no-no, especially for people who suffer from
 irritable bowel syndrome (
 IBS ). It is thought that the large amount of fat in chocolate can slow the digestion process. It is believed this happens by slowing down muscle contractions (peristalsis) and thus slowing foods moving through the bowel. In one study, researchers in Germany asked people who had constipation to name the foods they thought caused it. Chocolate was mentioned most frequently. Some supplements Many people take iron and
 calcium supplements because they are trying to stay healthy, but the same
 supplements could be the cause of constipation. Ideally, a healthy, balanced
 diet should provide all of the nutrients a person needs. If your doctor recommends you take these
 supplements (for example, people with
 anemia need iron, and women who are at risk for
 osteoporosis may need calcium) remember to add foods with additional fiber to your
 diet to help with constipation. Dairy products In large quantities, dairy products, such as milk, cheese, yogurt, and ice cream, can cause many people to become constipated. It could be due to the dairy itself or a combination of things. However, the lactose in dairy can cause increased gas and bloating that can make a person feel even worse if things aren&amp;#39;t moving through properly. One study of Iranian children, ages 1 to 13, found that dairy products could be the cause of their constipation. Almost all the children (80%) who eliminated cow&amp;#39;s milk and milk products from their diet had more regular bowel movements. Fast food All those burgers and fries are low-fiber and high in fat. This contributes to constipation. Not to mention fast foods often don&amp;#39;t have much nutritional value on top of it. Instead of a fast food burger and fries try these: Make burgers at home from lean ground turkey, or even better, try a veggie patty and put it on a whole grain wheat bun. Sweet potatoes are fiber-rich, with plenty of nutrients, and help relieve and prevent constipation. So swap traditional French fries for baked sweet potato fries. Leave the skin on because it has the best fiber benefits! Processed foods and frozen dinners Along with fast foods, processed foods contain little
 nutrition and usually a lot of fat. Many contain a lot of salt as well. Examples of foods to avoid include white bread, pastries, frozen meals, chips, and hot
 dogs . All of these foods can cause constipation by slowing down the
 digestive system . Try snacking on fruits and veggies and foods in their whole natural form, and make sure to drink enough water to help keep the digestive system working normally. Chips</first>
</file1>