<file1>
<first>Bocavirus Infection

ABOUT: Bocavirus are members of the
 Parvoviridae virus family that are small (20 nm), non-enveloped
 viruses with single-stranded DNA. Bocavirus is found usually in infants and children who are hospitalized with
 pneumonia or diarrheal symptoms. Bocavirus is often detected in patients who are infected with other viruses. Although some investigators suspect bocavirus to cause infection and disease, there is no definitive proof that bocavirus causes infection or disease, either alone or with other viruses. There are no diagnostic tests or medical treatments for bocavirus; researchers detect bocavirus with a
 PCR test that is not widely available. There is no
 vaccine available for bocavirus. Research in the next few years should better define what role, if any, bocavirus plays in human infections and diseases. What is bocavirus? Bocavirus (also termed HBoV or human bocavirus) is a small (20 nm in size) non-enveloped virus with a single strand of DNA that comprises its genome. The bocavirus genus is a member of the
 Parvoviridae family, and to date, three strains have been identified: HBoV, HBoV-2, and HBoV-3. Bocavirus is a new viral genus that was discovered in 2005 in upper respiratory secretions from acutely ill children. The name
 bocavirus was derived by combining the names
 bovine parvovirus with
 canine minutevirus with which bocavirus shares some genetic and structural characteristics. The ICTVdB (International Committee on Taxonomy of Viruses database) has detailed its genome and structure. Although this virus has been found worldwide in humans and animals, there is ongoing research and discussion about this virus as being a pathogen that causes infection, either alone or in conjunction with other virus types. Many investigators consider this newly discovered virus genus as an "emerging viral pathogen" because it is only proven to be associated with infections but not yet proven to be a cause of them, either alone or in conjunction with other viruses. However, another member of the
 Parvoviridae family, a parvovirus termed B19, causes
 erythema infectiosum (
 fifth disease or "slapped cheek" syndrome), hydrops fetalis (severe
 anemia in
 pregnant women), and aplastic crisis (cessation of red blood cell production) in individuals that have
 sickle cell disease . Bocavirus has not been associated with these conditions caused by parvovirus B19.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Because bocavirus is usually only found in individuals (usually infants, children, and infrequently in young adults) with lower respiratory infections or
 diarrhea , these are the following symptoms and signs associated with the presence of bocavirus: ARTI (also termed RTIs, acute respiratory tract infections), especially in infants and children Cough Wheezing Fever Cyanosis (bluish or grayish tint to skin due to lack of oxygen) Rhinorrhea (
 runny nose ) Diarrhea Vomiting The infants and children with these nonspecific symptoms often are very ill and require hospitalization. It is important to note that it is not clear yet that bocavirus is either completely or partially responsible for these signs and symptoms. Currently, most of the clinical articles that discuss bocavirus describe patients with at least several of the symptoms and signs listed above, with
 pneumonia as the major problem. Some investigators report months of bocavirus shedding (having tests demonstrate the presence of the virus in body secretions) in patients with
 cancer (
 leukemia ), but the significance of this shedding is not clear.
 How does bocavirus infection spread? Because bocavirus is a newly detected virus, many basic studies are still being planned or are ongoing. Consequently, conclusions about how the virus is spread are based on suppositions that are supported by some scientific findings, but not yet proved by scientific tests. Since the virus can be detected in high numbers in the respiratory tract and in respiratory secretions of some hospitalized patients, investigators suggest that bocavirus is mainly spread to other humans by respiratory secretions. However, it can also be found in stools (
 diarrhea ) and in blood, so these may be alternative ways for the virus to spread. Unfortunately, to date, there are no animal or viral cell culture systems to investigate bocavirus strains. It is clear, however, that from the few epidemiological studies done that bocavirus can be found worldwide in about 1.5%-19% of the population, usually in sick children. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Most investigators agree that bocavirus "infection" is a diagnosis by association as the virus has not yet proven to be definitively responsible for a disease state. There are no commercially available tests for any bocavirus strains. Researchers, however, use a
 polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to detect virus in nasopharyngeal aspirates (NPA) and samples of blood and diarrhea. These PCR tests detect the genetic material of the viruses, but the PCR tests are not widely available. Many researchers use the terms "detected bocavirus" or "associated with" instead of "definitively diagnosed with bocavirus infection" when they discuss the patients with symptoms described above. However stated, many investigators who work with these ill children clearly suspect bocavirus is playing some role in the disease process. 
TREATMENT:  There is no treatment, medical or antiviral, that is known to effectively target bocavirus strains. A few investigators suggest that since there is no definitive evidence that bocavirus causes infection or disease, either alone or in combination with other viruses, there should be no treatment directed toward bocavirus. Other investigators believe that since bocavirus strains are usually associated with patients with respiratory or gastrointestinal symptoms, treatments should be considered. Currently, the only available treatments (for example, oxygen, respiratory support, and hydration) are for the relief of symptoms since no specific anti-bocavirus treatments are available.
 What is the prognosis of bocavirus infection? The prognosis of patients with bocavirus detected is unclear because it is not known if bocavirus is responsible, alone or in part, for any disease or infection. However, when bocavirus strains are detected, they are frequently found associated (from about 45%-93% of patients tested by experienced investigators) with other viruses known to cause infections. The viruses that are identified in association with bocavirus are of several different types: RSV (
 respiratory syncytial virus ) Adenovirus Parainfluenza virus Enterovirus Herpes simplex virus As research on bocavirus progresses, other types of associated viruses are likely to be found. The prognosis for patients with these viruses is usually good, especially if patients are seen and treated by a medical
 caregiver early in the infection. However, for a few patients who develop severe symptoms with these viral infections, the prognosis may range from fair to poor. 
PREVENTION:  Bocavirus strains have not yet been shown definitively to cause infection; prevention methods await development and are likely to be investigated if these viruses are shown to participate in causing infection. Currently, there is no vaccine in development for human use.
</first>
</file1>