<file1>
<first>Broken Bone (Types of Bone Fractures)
What is a broken bone (fracture)? Bones make up the skeleton of the body. They allow us the ability to interact 
with our environment and lift out body up against gravity. Bones are attachment 
points for muscles which allows us to run, jump, sit, kneel, grasp, and 
lift. Bones also protect organs from potential damage, and the bone marrow (tissue inside of bones) is responsible for blood cell production. Bones are the body&amp;#39;s storage area for calcium. On a cellular level, calcium 
is always entering and exiting bone under the influence of the body&amp;#39;s hormones. 
Parathyroid hormone increases calcium levels in the bloodstream, meaning, that it 
regulates it&amp;#39;s release by bone and decreasing
 bone density .
 Calcitonin decreases 
blood calcium levels and helps restore calcium to bone. Calcium is needed in the 
blood stream to help muscle cells including the heart to function. Hormone 
levels will sacrifice calcium in bone to maintain blood calcium levels in a 
normal range. For that reason, 
calcium and
 Vitamin D are important to maintain 
calcium stores in the body. 
CAUSES:  When a bone has an outside force exerted upon it, like a blow or a fall, 
there is potential that it cannot withstand the amount of force and it 
breaks. That loss of integrity results in a fracture. It is important to 
remember that a fracture, break, or crack all describe the same situation, an 
injury to the bone where it has been damaged. One term is not more serious than 
another. Fracture, break, and crack all mean the same thing. Depending upon the situation, the amount of force required may not be very 
great. People with
 osteoporosis , the bones 
lack calcium and are brittle, a minor injury or even gravity may create enough of a 
force to cause a vertebral compression fracture of the back or a
 hip fracture .
 What are the most
common typesof broken bones? Fractures are usually described by their location, how the bones are aligned, whether there are associated complications with blood and nerve function, and whether the skin is intact at the injury site. The terms and definitions used in medicine to describe fractures allow health care professionals to describe exactly where in the bone the fracture is located. For a reference point, the heart is considered the center of the body and the anatomic descriptions are based on their location in reference to the heart. When describing a location on or in the body, imagine standing straight up, looking forward with the arms slightly away from your side, and the palms turned forward. Common anatomic terms used to describe fractures include the following: Proximal (closer to the center of the body) and
 Distal (further from the center): the elbow is proximal to the wrist and the wrist is distal to the elbow. Anterior (toward the front of the body) and
 Posterior (toward the back): The chest is anterior to the back and the back is posterior to the chest. Medial (toward the middle of the body) and
 Lateral (to the outer edge of the body): The ears are lateral to the nose and the nose is medial to the ears. By thinking of the body in the anatomic position, fractures can be described by their location in the bone and how the parts are aligned and related to each other. Fractures are either displaced or non-displaced, meaning that they are adequately aligned or not. Some physicians suggest that all fractures have some displacement and prefer the term "minimally displaced." The description of the fracture also includes the direction it takes within the bones. Transverse: the fracture travels across the bone Oblique: the fracture occurs at an angle Spiral: –the fracture spirals or extends down the length of the bone Comminuted: the fracture has more than two parts, multiple fragments are present. Special terms: Greenstick: In young children, the bones are not yet solid and when force is applied, it tends to bow and not break completely through. The term comes from a similar situation when trying to break a young branch off a tree. Torus: In children, when only one part of a bone buckles it is called a torus or incomplete fracture. Open fracture: An open fracture describes the situation where the bone penetrates through the skin. The skin is very important in protecting the inside of the body from infection. If the skin overlying a broken bone is damaged, whether it is cut, torn or scraped, there is potential for bacteria from the outside world to invade the broken bone and cause an infection. Fractures are classified as open (if the skin is damaged) or closed (if the skin is intact). An open fracture may require an orthopedic surgeon to wash out the fracture site to prevent
 osteomyelitis (bone infection). Depending upon circumstances, the type of fracture, the amount of contamination to the skin and
 wound , and the person&amp;#39;s condition, this procedure may take place in the operating room. Compression fracture The spine is comprised of 7 cervical, 12 thoracic, and 5
 lumbar vertebrae . 
The spine holds the body erect against gravity and to protect the spinal 
cord. Compression fractures can be caused by
 osteoporosis , injury, or
 trauma . People with
 osteoporosis lose calcium from the 
bones, and the vertebrae may become weak and unable to hold up against the forces of 
gravity, so they gradually compress over time. A compression fracture due to an injury may or may not 
     have spinal cord or nerve root irritation because of the 
     fracture. A compression fracture due to trauma most likely occurs 
     from a motor vehicle crash or fall from height. Skull fracture The purpose of the skull is to protect the brain. It is a flat bone and it takes a significant direct blow to cause a fracture. Because the main concern is an injury to the brain and not the skull injury , plain X-rays are not routinely performed to look for a skull fracture. Instead
 CT scan of the brain is recommended if there is concern about a
 brain injury . Skull fractures are often associated with localized swelling and bleeding at the site of injury. Basilar skull fractures describe damage to bone at the base of the brain. Physical findings may include bloody drainage from the ear or nose, bruising behind the ear (Battle&amp;#39;s sign), and bruising around the eyes (Raccoon eyes). With a
 depressed skull fracture, the bone is broken and fragments are pushed inward. Depending upon depth of the bony
 depression and whether there is brain tissue involvement, surgery may be required. With an
 open skull fracture, the
 scalp is lacerated and the wound may connect with the fibrous coverings of the brain (meninges). Surgery is often performed to help prevent infection.
 Stress fracture Stress fractures are the result of multiple microtraumas where the bone 
cannot tolerate and absorb repeated stresses placed upon it. It is an overuse 
injury and is often seen in the lower leg especially with runners and other 
athletes. If untreated, and if the person continues to participate in offending activity, the
 stress fracture may progress to a completed fracture. These are most often seen in 
athletes who participate in
 running , tennis, basketball, 
and other sports that involve running and jumping on hard surfaces. March fracture is the name given to a
 stress fracture of the
 metatarsal bone 
of the foot. They are described in soldiers who are forced to walk or "march" 
for prolonged distances. What are the most
common bonesthat are broken? The most common fractures involve the clavicle (collarbone), the forearm 
(radius and ulna), the wrist, the ankle and the hip. Closed fractures are 
more common than open fractures (the skin overlying the injury is 
intact and not damaged). In children, a fracture of the distal radius is most common. The break occurs 
in the radius near the wrist but usually does not involve the joint itself.
 1 Broken hand or fingers Injuries to the hands and fingers are very common because they are exposed in 
daily activities. In addition to the bones, the health care professional will be 
interested in making certain there are no tendon or nerve injuries associated with 
any broken bone(s). Because the anatomy of the hand is so complex, complicated 
fractures may be referred to an orthopedic or
 plastic hand specialist. Many of 
them will only require splinting or casting, but occasionally surgery will 
be necessary.
 Broken wrist Falling on an outstretched hand is the most common reason for a wrist 
fracture. It is often the distal radius (see illustration) that is damaged, and the fracture may 
involve more than one bone. Aside from the radius, wrist fractures may also 
include fractures of the carpal bones of the wrist (carpus), those that connect the 
radius to the long bones of the hand (
 metacarpals ). Doctors often look for fractures of the scaphoid 
bone (the bone between the bottom of the thumb and the top of the radius), 
and dislocations of the lunate (the bone next to the scaphoid bone) that may be difficult to see on plain 
X-ray. In some cases, the wrist is splinted even if X-rays are normal because upon physical examination the doctor may be concerned about a potential occult or hidden fracture 
(the fracture is so small that it does not show up on an X-ray). Depending upon the bone that is injured and it&amp;#39;s alignment, surgery may or 
may not be required. Regardless of the treatment, the goal is to have a normally 
aligned wrist, especially if the fracture involves the joint surface. Poor 
alignment may lead to
 arthritis in the future. Broken hip Hip fractures are perhaps the most common fracture seen in people 75 years 
of age or older. While falls and trauma may be the obvious cause, many times, 
people are more susceptible to hip fracture because of osteoporosis and 
sometimes the hip will break spontaneously. The hip joint is made up of the interconnection of two bones in a ball and 
socket: 1) the socket in the pelvis (acetabulum), and 2) the ball (femoral head). Hip fractures refer to the femur fracture. Almost all hip fractures require surgery and the type of surgery 
depends upon where in the femur that the fracture is located. Broken leg Each of the many bones of the lower extremity is at risk for fracture. Leg 
fractures also may involve the
 knee joint , and treatment depends upon the type of fracture. 
Similarly, fractures of the lower leg (tibia and fibula) and talus (the most 
proximal bone in the foot) may involve the ankle joint. Fractures and dislocations of the foot may be as complex as the hand. Because 
of the anatomy, they may also be more difficult to diagnosis on plain X-rays. Broken toe Broken toes are 
a common fracture and may be diagnosed by history and physical 
examination. X-rays may or may not be needed depending upon the clinical 
situation. Broken shoulder The clavicle (collarbone) fracture is one of the most commonly seen 
broken bones, fracture of the humeral head (the ball) is quite common an older 
person who falls. Depending upon the amount of comminution (into how many pieces the humeral 
head breaks) surgery may or may not be required. Initial treatment usually 
begins with a sling. The scapula or shoulder blade is a flat bone and very difficult to break. The 
mechanism is usually a direct blow. Any scapula fracture needs to be evaluated 
for related injuries. 
SYMPTOMS:  Broken bones hurt. The lining of the bone (periosteum) is rich with nerve 
endings that can cause
 pain when inflamed; and the muscles surrounding the 
fracture go into spasm to prevent movement of the fracture site, and this spasm 
may intensify the
 pain . Bones have a rich blood supply and will bleed when injured. This will cause 
swelling and the blood that seeps into the surrounding tissue will also cause 
further pain. The discoloration due to the blood can show up as 
dark red or 
purple bruise in the area of the fracture site. Because muscles and tendons may not be damaged, the person may be able to 
move the injured extremity. For that reason, just because you can move the 
injured area, doesn&amp;#39;t mean it&amp;#39;s not broken. If there is damage to a nearby artery, the 
injury may be cool and pale (distal to the injury), and if there is nerve damage, there may be numbness 
(distally). When should I call a doctor if I think I have broken a bone? Most broken bones require medical care but the urgency of that care depends 
upon the type of fracture and the circumstances. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The doctor will take a 
history of the patient&amp;#39;s injury, examine the injury, and look for potential 
     other injuries that may have occurred. The skin surrounding the injured area is inspected to look for a 
     laceration, scrape, or skin tear. The area of tenderness and swelling will be evaluated to identify the 
injured bone. The type of X-ray that is ordered depends on the 
     specific injury. Sometimes plain X-rays do not identify the injury. If the 
     doctor is still concerned, CT scan or
 MRI might be 
     ordered. Fractures may be difficult to diagnose in children because bones have not 
completely formed. Many parts of developing bone are comprised mostly of 
cartilage and have yet to have calcium deposited in them. Growing bone also has 
growth plates that may mimic or hide fractures. On occasion, the diagnosis of a 
fracture is made clinically based upon physical exam, even if the X-rays do not 
show an injury.
 
TREATMENT:  The initial treatment of a fracture begins with stabilization and 
immobilization. In the field RICE (rest, ice, compression and elevation) may 
help make the patient more comfortable and prevent the fractured bones from 
moving. Often the pain associated with a fracture is due to spasm of the muscles 
surrounding the fracture site trying to prevent movement. Splinting may help 
relieve some of that pain. Depending upon the injury, EMS providers may consider 
traction to help with stabilization and pain control. For non-open fractures, or other fractures that can be treated without emergency surgery, the 
goal is to immobilize the injury to maintain anatomic alignment to allow the 
bone to heal. Bone heals in three stages. Reactive stage: The
 blood clot that 
forms at the fracture site begins to organize and the body&amp;#39;s building blocks 
start to
 bridge the gap between the two ends of the broken bone. Repair stage: Specialized cells 
located in the outer lining of the bone (periosteum), begin to form a lattice 
work or grids of cartilage and bone, called a
 callus , which spans the fracture. 
More bone is laid down to provide strength to the area. Remodeling phase: Over the next few 
years, the body will attempt to resculpt this mass of bone into it&amp;#39;s original 
size and shape. In the emergency department, walk in clinic, or doctor&amp;#39;s office, the extremity 
is usually splinted using a combination of soft padding, casting material 
(plaster, fiberglass), and ace wraps. This splint is not circumferential like a 
cast, because a fracture has the potential for 
swelling of the surrounding tissues, and if a tight cast were in place, that 
swelling could cause complications including significant pain and potential 
blood supply issues. Once the patient is discharged, their instructions are to elevate the injury 
and ice the area, even with the splint, to help decrease swelling and 
inflammation. After a few days, once the initial swelling has resolved, a circumferential 
cast may replace the splint and will be worn until the fracture is healed. The 
time frame for healing depends upon the type of fracture and its location. 
X-rays may be used to help determine when it is time for the cast to be removed. Finger and hand fractures may be more complicated. The hand is a complex web 
of tendons, blood vessels, and nerves that allow fine motor function. What might 
be acceptable healing and alignment in an arm or leg may not be appropriate in a 
hand. Some finger injuries need nothing more than a metal splint or buddy taping 
one finger to another for support, while others will need surgery. The type of 
treatment will depend upon the type of injury. Most toe injuries heal very well own and need nothing more than buddy 
taping one toe to another for support. The treatment for rib fractures involves pain control so that the patient can 
take deep breaths and allow the lung to expand beneath the injury site to 
prevent
 pneumonia . Rib injuries are not wrapped or 
bandaged to help with pain control because this will limit their movement, and 
prevent lung expansion. Because of this, rib fractures generally take 4 to 6 weeks to heal 
and may cause pain throughout the healing process.
 What about surgery for a broken bone? The decision to operate on a fracture depends upon the type of fracture, 
whether it can heal in good alignment on its own, and whether other potential 
complications exist. Sometimes patients are taken to the operating room for a closed reduction 
(resetting of the bone) and 
splinting of the fracture. When a fracture is markedly displaced and 
misaligned, it may be too painful to move or manipulated the bone without an 
anesthetic. If it appears that the fracture is unstable and cannot be held in place and 
in good alignment with just a splint or cast, an open reduction and internal 
fixation (ORIF) may be needed. An incision is made so that the bony pieces can 
be identified and aligned. Metal plates and screws, wires or rods may be used to 
stabilize the fracture. The hardware may be left in place forever or it may be 
there only temporarily until the fracture heals. Hip fractures almost always 
require ORIF to allow the patient to heal and regain the ability to walk. Surgery may be required in situations where there is associated injury to 
arteries and nerves and they need to be repaired or decompressed. Open fractures often have to go to the operating room to be washed out to 
prevent infection of the bone (osteomyelitis). 
PREVENTION:  Many broken bones occur because of accidents in the home, at work or at play, 
and not all may be preventable. Using proper safety equipment and precautions 
may minimize the risk of injury, but it cannot be completely eliminated. As we age, there is an increased risk for falls at homes and some preventive 
steps may help reduce fall risks. These include: Make certain that lighting is adequate Shoes should not be slippery Loose rugs or uneven floors should be 
repaired High traffic areas like from the bed to 
the bath or from the kitchen to the living area need to be clear from hazards 
like excess furniture, extension cords, or boxes Bathrooms should have nonslip mats on 
the floor and in the bathtub or shower Install handrails for stairs and grab bars 
in the bathroom Bones also get old as we age and the management of osteoporosis is a 
life-long commitment. Increasing calcium content in bone will decrease the risk 
of spontaneous fracture, and also may make bone strong enough to potentially 
withstand an injury that otherwise would result in a fracture. Ways to prevent 
osteoporosis include: Increase weight bearing
 exercise Make sure you are getting the right amount of calcium and
 Vitamin D in 
the
 diet . Take
 supplements if necessary. Do not smoke Avoid excess alcohol intake What is the prognosis for a broken bone? Fractures are a common injury, but the prognosis depends upon the bone that is 
broken, the location of the break, whether any complications exist and the 
underlying medical condition of the individual. Most arm and leg fractures heal 
well, and the goal is for the person to return to their baseline level of 
activity.
</first>
</file1>