<file1>
<first>Urinary Tract Infections (UTIs) in Children
Urinary tract infections (UTIs) 
in children facts Childhood
 urinary tract infections are fairly common and are generally caused by bacteria. Routine antibiotic therapy is successful in resolving these infections. Recurrent UTIs in children may be indicative of malformation or malfunction of the urinary tract. Common symptoms and signs of UTIs in children include
 pain and urgency with urination,
 blood in the urine , abdominal/
 pelvic pain ,
 fever , flank
 pain , and
 vomiting . Some selected children who experience a
 UTI should have diagnostic studies performed. These children include children less than 2 years of age, any male child, any child who has had more than one
 UTI , or any child who has had
 pyelonephritis . Several recommendations exist to help lessen the likelihood of a child developing a
 UTI . What is a urinary tract infection (UTI)? A
 urinary tract infection is an infection of the bladder (
 cystitis ) or kidney(s) (pyelonephritis). Cystitis is considerably more common than the more severe and more serious pyelonephritis.
 What
causesurinary tract infections (UTIs) in children? Bacteria cause the large majority of urinary tract infections in children. Viral infection of the bladder is less common, while
 fungal infections of the urinary tract are rare and occur most commonly in immunocompromised individuals (for example, those with
 HIV/AIDS ,
 chemotherapy recipients). 
RISKS:  Risk factors predisposing for childhood UTIs include the following: What are
symptomsand signs of urinary tract infections (UTIs) in children? Characteristic symptoms of a
 urinary tract infection include pain with urination (
 dysuria ), urinary frequency (needing to urinate frequently), urinary urgency (feeling a compelling urge to urinate), and loss of previously established urinary control (for example,
 bedwetting ). Nonspecific but common symptoms include
 fever (especially &gt;102.2 F or 39 C) and
 abdominal pain . For some children less than 2 years of age, these more subtle problems may be the only indicator of a UTI. Associated symptoms of concern include flank pain, fever, and
 vomiting . Obvious
 blood in the urine (gross
 hematuria ) as well as a positive family history for childhood urinary tract infections (especially in siblings) are also red flags and should raise the level of concern. Interestingly, the odor and color (with the exception of obvious blood) of the urine are not predictors of a UTI. 
TREATMENT:  Most children with a UTI can be appropriately managed by their pediatrician. If kidney function is compromised, a pediatric nephrologist should be consulted. Similarly, if anatomical problems are discovered, a pediatric urologic surgeon (urologist) should help guide the child&amp;#39;s evaluation and management.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Establishing an accurate diagnosis (vs. a presumptive diagnosis) includes determining the causative bacteria of the infection, its antibiotic sensitivity profile, and determining whether any anatomical or functional risk factors are present that might predispose the child to the current infection. Such information is crucial to establish the individual&amp;#39;s risk for recurrent urinary tract infections, which can predispose to scarring of the kidney and possibly
 renal failure (end-stage
 kidney disease , requiring either
 dialysis or
 renal transplant ). The physical examination of a child with suspected
 urinary tract infection should start with the vital signs (temperature, pulse,
 breathing rate, and
 blood pressure , which is often measured with the vital signs). The presence of fever (especially over 102.2 F or 39 C) is highly correlated with the presence of a UTI. Blood pressure and assessment of height and weight provide helpful reassurance if normal or stable long-term renal function. Visual examination of the abdomen for enlargement related to potentially oversized kidney(s) or bladder is important. Tenderness during palpation of the abdomen (especially the suprapubic region containing the bladder) or the flank area (where the kidneys are situated) is very helpful in establishing the diagnosis. Examination of the genitalia is also very important to see if there is evidence of vaginal irritation (redness, discharge, evidence of
 trauma or foreign body). An uncircumcised male infant (especially with a foreskin that is difficult to retract) is more likely to experience a UTI when compared to a population of similar infant boys who have been circumcised. Lastly, consideration of other conditions that might be responsible for fever and
 abdominal pain is important. An abnormal
 urinalysis (including microscopic examination) may be indicative of a urinary tract infection. However, the urine culture is mandatory in confirming the diagnosis of a UTI. The culture provides both the exact bacterial cause as well as the antibiotic sensitivity profile to successfully treat the infection. In addition, studies have demonstrated a relatively short list of bacteria that commonly cause UTIs. A UTI caused by abnormal bacteria should be a source of concern. In a toilet-trained child, a clean-catch urine specimen should provide a reliable specimen for culture. A non-toilet-trained child or an uncircumcised boy whose tight foreskin may lead to potential urine specimen contamination should have the specimen obtained by a sterile catheterization. An alternative approach to catheterization is called "suprapubic bladder aspiration." This safe procedure involves passing a small needle through the skin into the urine-filled bladder cavity and aspiration of urine into the attached syringe. Collection of urine in a "urine bag" is not recommended. Some studies have indicated an 85% false-positive rate of UTI diagnosis with this method, prompting unnecessary laboratory and diagnostic studies as well as inappropriately prescribed antibiotic therapy. Regardless of the mechanism chosen to obtain a child&amp;#39;s urine specimen, it is very important to examine the urine as soon as possible since a delay can increase the risk of both false-negative and false-positive results. Other laboratory studies (for example,
 complete blood count ) are generally not helpful, and their nonspecific values do not provide differentiation between the more significant
 kidney infection (pyelonephritis) and a less concerning
 bladder infection (cystitis).
 Are there any
home remediesfor UTIs in children? Home remedy suggestions for UTIs in adults are legion, and unfortunately many have no scientific basis in fact. Fewer still have been shown to be safe and possibly effective in children. Those that do fulfill such criteria include the following: Perhaps the best therapy is prevention. How long do UTIs in children last? Once an effective antibiotic has been selected and administered, most patients experience a rapid and permanent resolution of their symptoms. Recurrent UTIs raise a concern regarding anatomical abnormalities of the urinary tract (for example, kidney malformation). Similarly, malfunction of the urinary tract (for example, reflux of urine from the bladder to the kidney) is another condition commonly associated with recurrent UTIs. Are UTIs in children contagious? Urinary tract infections are not
 contagious . They are not acquired by sharing a bath with another child who has a UTI. Likewise, they cannot be acquired from sitting on a contaminated toilet seat.
 
TREATMENT:  Antibiotic therapy for UTIs is based upon the sensitivity profile obtained from the urine-culture results. Cystitis (infection limited to the bladder) should respond quickly to routine oral antibiotics. Pyelonephritis may need hospitalization for intravenous administration of antibiotics along with fluid therapy if the patient is experiencing associated vomiting and
 dehydration . Oral antibiotic therapy, however, may be appropriate if these complications are not present. The American Academy of Pediatrics has issued a position statement recommending follow-up studies for children who have experienced a urinary tract infection. Children who should be further evaluated include children 2 months of age to 2 years of age who sustain their first UTI, any male child who experiences a UTI, any child 3 years and older who has had more than one UTI, and any child who has had pyelonephritis. The purpose of the studies detailed below is to accurately define the anatomy and functional physiology of these children who may be at risk for renal scarring and possible complete
 kidney failure . Renal ultrasound : This procedure helps to define the renal anatomy (kidney location, size, shape). VCUG (voiding cysto-urethrogram) : This test involves passage of a catheter into the bladder to fill it with dye. After removal of the catheter, the bladder will empty. A radiologist performs imaging studies to monitor for complete bladder emptying without obstruction and/or backward flow (reflux) of the dye from the bladder into to ureters and up to the kidneys. Renal scan : This test uses a small amount of radioactive material (radioisotope) to measure the function of the kidneys. It is designed to evaluate the functional capability of the kidneys and evaluate for possible renal scarring. IVP (intravenous pyelogram) : This is a rarely used test involving injecting dye into the bloodstream via an IV (The dye is excreted via the kidneys.) and then obtaining X-ray images. The renal
 ultrasound and renal scan have replaced the usefulness of this test.
 
PREVENTION:  There are several suggestions that have been made by pediatric urologists to lessen the likelihood of children developing urinary tract infections. These include the following: What is the prognosis for UTIs in children? Children who experience a UTI generally have an excellent prognosis. If a child&amp;#39;s UTI is associated with a red flag or high-risk characteristic (for example, male gender, usual type of bacteria, pyelonephritis, etc.), appropriate follow-up studies (renal ultrasound, renal scan, and VCUG) will help to alert the doctor about unrecognized problems. These additional studies can help avoid progressive loss of kidney function or other health issues that might not be detected.
</first>
</file1>