<file1>
<first>Urine Blockage in Newborns
Types of Defects in the Urinary Tract Hydronephrosis can result from many 
types of defects in the urinary tract. Doctors use specific terms to describe 
the type and location of the blockage. Vesicoureteral reflux (VUR) . The openings where the ureters empty urine into 
the bladder should work like valves to keep urine from backing up into the 
ureters. Sometimes the valve doesn't work properly and urine flows back into the 
kidneys. The urine may flow only a short way back into the ureters, or it may go 
all the way back to the kidneys, causing the ureters and kidneys to swell. VUR 
may occur in only one ureter or in both. Kidneys with severe reflux may not 
develop normally, and after birth kidneys with reflux may be at risk for damage 
from infections. Ureteropelvic junction (UPJ) obstruction . The point where the ureter joins 
the kidney is called the ureteropelvic junction. If urine is blocked here, only 
the kidney swells. The ureter remains at a normal size. UPJ obstruction usually 
only occurs in one kidney. Bladder outlet obstruction (BOO) . BOO describes any blockage in the urethra 
or at the opening of the bladder. The obstruction may occur in boys or girls. 
The most common form of BOO seen in newborns and during
 prenatal ultrasound examinations is posterior urethral valves (PUV). BOO caused by PUV occurs only 
in boys. Posterior urethral valves (PUV) . In boys, sometimes an abnormal fold of 
tissue in the urethra keeps urine from flowing freely out of the bladder. This 
defect may cause swelling in the entire urinary tract, including the urethra, 
bladder, ureters, and kidneys. Ureterocele . If the end of the ureter does not develop normally, it can 
bulge, creating what is called a ureterocele. The ureterocele may obstruct part 
of the kidney or the bladder. Nerve disease . Urination requires coordinated nerve signals between the 
bladder, spinal cord, and brain.
 Spina bifida and other
 birth defects that 
affect the spinal cord may interrupt nerve signals and lead to urine retention 
in newborns.
 Syndromes That May Affect the Urinary Tract In addition to defects that occur 
in a single spot in the urinary tract, some babies are born with genetic 
conditions that affect several different systems in the body. A condition that 
includes multiple, seemingly unrelated problems, is called a syndrome. Prune belly syndrome (PBS) . Occurring only in boys, PBS causes a baby to 
have an enlarged abdomen because the normal abdominal wall muscles are missing 
or very weak. The entire urinary tract is enlarged, and both testicles remain 
inside the body instead of descending into the scrotum. The skin over the 
abdomen is wrinkled, giving the appearance of a prune. Most children with PBS 
have hydronephrosis and VUR. Esophageal atresia (EA) . EA is a birth defect in which the
 esophagus is 
incomplete. The esophagus is the tube that carries food from the mouth to the 
stomach. About 30 percent of babies born with EA will have problems in other 
body systems, such as the heart or urinary tract. Congenital heart defects . Heart defects range from mild to life threatening. 
Children born with heart defects also have a higher rate of problems in the 
urinary tract than children in the general population, suggesting that some 
types of heart and urinary defects may have a common genetic cause. Diagnosis Birth defects and other problems of the urinary tract may be 
discovered before the baby is born, at the time of birth, or later, when the 
child is brought to the doctor for a
 urinary tract infection or urination 
problem. Prenatal Screening Tests during pregnancy can help determine if the baby is 
developing normally in the womb. Ultrasound. Ultrasound uses sound waves to produce a picture on a television 
screen. A wand gliding on the mother's abdomen directs harmless sound waves into 
the womb. The sound waves bounce off the baby and back into the wand to create a 
black-and-white image on the screen. Ultrasound images can even display internal 
organs within the baby, so enlarged kidneys, ureters, or bladder may be visible. Amniocentesis . In amniocentesis, the doctor inserts a needle through the 
mother's skin into the amniotic sac to collect about an ounce of amniotic fluid. 
The fluid contains genetic material from the baby that can be analyzed for signs 
of defects. Ultrasound allows evaluation of a baby's internal organs, even before birth. Chorionic villus sampling (CVS). In CVS, the doctor collects a small piece 
of tissue from the placenta using a needle passed through the mother's vagina 
and cervix. The placenta has the same genetic
 makeup as the baby.
 Most healthy women do not need all the tests. Ultrasound examinations during 
pregnancy are routine, although they are not always required and rarely 
influence treatment decisions. Amniocentesis and CVS are recommended only when a 
risk of genetic problems exists because of family history or something detected 
during an ultrasound. Amniocentesis and CVS carry a slight risk of harming the 
baby and mother, or ending the pregnancy in
 miscarriage , so those risks should 
be weighed carefully against the potential benefits of learning about the baby's 
condition. Examination of Newborn Sometimes a
 newborn does not urinate as 
expected, even though
 prenatal testing showed no sign of urine blockage. The 
baby may urinate only small amounts or not at all. An enlarged kidney may be 
felt during the newborn examination as well. Different imaging techniques are 
available to determine the cause of the problem. Ultrasound . Once the baby is born, ultrasound can be used to view the baby's 
urinary tract directly for a clearer image than could be achieved while the baby 
was in the womb. Voiding cystourethrogram (VCUG) . If the doctor suspects that urine is 
backing up into the ureters or that the bladder outlet is obstructed, a VCUG may 
be needed. In this test, a catheter is used to fill the child's bladder with 
warm liquid containing
 iodine to make it visible on an x ray. A video records 
the x-ray images of the bladder as it is filled and as the child urinates. The 
video will reveal reflux if the liquid enters the ureters and blockage of the 
bladder in the case of an obstruction, such as PUV. Nuclear scan . A nuclear scan involves injecting a very small amount of 
radioactive material, just enough to show up using a camera that captures gamma 
rays. The amount of radioactive substance used is determined by the child's 
weight. The liquid is injected into the child's bloodstream and eventually 
passes through the kidneys, where it is filtered from the blood and directed 
down the ureters to the bladder. The camera may be mounted above or below a 
table where the patient lies. The camera passes over or under the urinary tract 
as the child lies on the table. Later Diagnosis Sometimes urine blockage is not 
apparent until the child develops the symptoms of a
 urinary tract infection . 
These symptoms include fever irritability poor appetite vomiting unusual smelling urine dark urine If these symptoms persist, the child should be seen by a doctor. For any
 fever in the first 2 months of life, the child should be seen by a doctor 
immediately. The doctor will ask for a urine sample to test for bacteria. The 
doctor may also recommend imaging tests including ultrasound, VCUG, or nuclear 
scan.
 Treatment Treatment for urine blockage depends on the cause and severity of 
the blockage. Hydronephrosis discovered before the baby is born will rarely 
require immediate action, especially if it is only on one side. Often the 
condition goes away without any treatment before birth or sometimes after. The 
doctor will keep track of the condition with frequent ultrasounds. With few 
exceptions, treatment can wait until the baby is born. Prenatal Shunt If the urine blockage threatens the life of the unborn baby, 
the doctor may recommend a procedure to insert a small tube, called a shunt, 
into the baby's bladder to release urine into the amniotic sac. The placement of 
the shunt is similar to an amniocentesis, in that a needle is inserted through 
the mother's abdomen. Ultrasound guides the placing of the shunt. This fetal 
surgery carries many risks, so it is performed only in special circumstances, 
such as when the amniotic fluid is absent and the baby's
 lungs aren't developing 
or when the kidneys are very severely damaged. Antibiotics Antibiotics are medicines that kill bacteria. A newborn with 
possible urine blockage or VUR may be given antibiotics to prevent urinary tract 
infections from developing until the urinary defect corrects itself or is 
surgically corrected. Surgery If the urinary defect doesn't correct itself and the child continues 
to have urine blockage, surgery may be needed. The decision to operate depends 
upon the degree of blockage. The surgeon will remove the obstruction to restore 
urine flow. A small tube, called a
 stent , may be placed in the ureter or urethra 
to keep it open temporarily while healing occurs. Intermittent Catheterization If the child has urine retention because of 
nerve disease, the condition may be treated with intermittent catheterization. 
The parent, and later the child, will be taught to drain the bladder by 
inserting a thin tube, called a catheter, through the urethra to the bladder. 
Emptying the bladder in this way helps prevent kidney damage, overflow
 incontinence , and
 urinary tract infections .
 Hope Through Research Researchers from universities and government 
agencies are working to understand the causes of urinary birth defects and to 
find more effective treatments. Through its Pediatric Urology Program, the 
National Institute of
 Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases funds research 
into bladder and urinary tract development, prenatal interventions for urinary 
tract disorders, and bladder abnormalities associated with spina bifida. 
Additionally, the Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of
 Child Health and 
Human Development has established the Birth Defects Initiative to study the 
genetic and molecular mechanisms underlying developmental processes of the 
fetus. For More Information American Urological Association, Inc.
 1000 Corporate 
Boulevard
 Linthicum, MD 21090
 Phone: 1–866–RING–AUA (746–4282) or 410–689–3700
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet:
 www.urologyhealth.org March of Dimes
 1275 Mamaroneck Avenue
 White Plains, NY 10605
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet:
 www.marchofdimes.com Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human 
Development
 Information Resource Center
 P.O. Box 3006
 Rockville, MD 20847
 Phone: 1–800–370–2943
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet:
 www.nichd.nih.gov</first>
</file1>