<file1>
<first>Breastfeeding: Common Breastfeeding Challenges
Common breastfeeding challenges facts* *
ABOUT: medical author:
Melissa Conrad Stöppler, MD Lactation consultants are trained to help women find ways to make 
 breastfeeding work. Many women have no problems breastfeeding, while others will experience some challenges. These challenges can often be overcome. Developing a good latch is important to prevent sore nipples. Checking a baby's weight and growth is the best way to make sure he or she is getting enough milk. Engorgement refers to the feeling of
 pain or fullness in the lactating breasts. Clogged or plugged ducts are relatively common and can be relieved by
 massage , warm compresses, and frequent breastfeeding. A plugged duct feels like a tender, sore lump in the breast. Mastitis is an inflammation or infection of the breasts that can be accompanied by
 fever . Breast infections that do not heal within 24 to 48 hours may need treatment with antibiotics. Most mothers are able to make enough milk for twins, and some fully breastfeed triplets or quadruplets. Breastfeeding after breast surgery is usually possible; the extent depends upon the type of surgery and the reasons it was performed. Some health problems in
 babies can make breastfeeding more difficult. Common breastfeeding challenges overview Breastfeeding can be challenging at times, especially in the early days. But 
it is important to remember that you are not alone. Lactation consultants are 
trained to help you find ways to make breastfeeding work for you. And while many 
women are faced with one or more of the challenges listed here, many women do 
not struggle at all! Also, many women may have certain problems with one baby 
that they don&amp;#39;t have with their second or third babies. Read on for ways to 
troubleshoot problems.
 Sore nipples Many moms report that nipples can be tender at first. Breastfeeding should be 
comfortable once you have found some positions that work and a good latch is 
established. Yet it is possible to still have
 pain from an
 abrasion you already 
have. You may also have pain if your baby is sucking on only the
 nipple . Ask a lactation consultant for help to improve your baby&amp;#39;s latch. Talk to 
your doctor if your pain does not go away or if you suddenly get sore nipples 
after several weeks of pain-free breastfeeding. Sore nipples may lead to a
 breast infection , which needs to be treated by a doctor. A good latch is key, so visit the Bringing your baby to the breast to latch 
section for detailed instructions. If your baby is sucking only on the nipple, 
gently break your baby&amp;#39;s suction to your breast by placing a clean finger in the 
corner of your baby&amp;#39;s mouth and try again. (Your nipple should not look flat or 
compressed when it comes out of your baby&amp;#39;s mouth. It should look round and 
long, or the same shape as it was before the feeding.) If you find yourself 
wanting to delay feedings because of pain, get help from a lactation consultant. 
Delaying feedings can cause more pain and harm your supply. Try changing 
positions each time you breastfeed. This puts the pressure on a different part 
of the breast. After breastfeeding, express a few drops of milk and gently rub 
it on your nipples with clean hands. Human milk has natural healing properties 
and emollients that soothe. Also try letting your nipples air-dry after feeding, 
or wear a soft cotton shirt. If you are thinking about using creams, hydrogel 
pads, or a nipple shield, get help from a health care provider first. Avoid 
wearing bras or clothes that are too tight and put pressure on your nipples. Change
 nursing pads often to avoid trapping in moisture. Avoid using soap or 
ointments that contain astringents or other chemicals on your nipples. Make sure 
to avoid products that must be removed before breastfeeding. Washing with clean 
water is all that is needed to keep your nipples and breasts clean. If you have 
very sore nipples, you can ask your doctor about using non-
 aspirin pain 
relievers.
 Low milk supply Most mothers can make plenty of milk for their babies. But many mothers are 
concerned about having enough. Checking your baby&amp;#39;s weight and growth is the best way to make sure he or she 
is getting enough milk. Let the doctor know if you are concerned. For more ways 
to tell if your baby is getting enough milk, visit the How to know your baby is 
getting enough milk section. There may be times when you think your supply is low, but it is actually just 
fine: When your baby is around 6 weeks to 2 months old, your breasts may no longer 
feel full. This is normal. At the same time, your baby may nurse for only five 
minutes at a time. This can mean that you and baby are just adjusting to the 
breastfeeding process -  and getting good at it! Growth spurts can cause your 
baby to want to nurse longer and more often. These growth spurts can happen 
around 2 to 3 weeks, 6 weeks, and 3 months of age. They can also happen at any 
time. Don&amp;#39;t be alarmed that your supply is too low to satisfy your baby. Follow 
your baby&amp;#39;s lead - nursing more and more often will help build up your milk 
supply. Once your supply increases, you will likely be back to your usual 
routine. Ask for help! Let your baby&amp;#39;s doctor know if you think the baby is not 
getting enough milk.
 Oversupply of milk Some mothers are concerned about having an oversupply of milk. Having an 
overfull breast can make feedings stressful and uncomfortable for both mother 
and baby. Some women have a strong milk ejection reflex or let-down. This can happen 
along with an oversupply of milk. If you have a rush of milk, try the following: Ask for help! Ask a lactation consultant for help if you are unable to manage an oversupply of milk on your own.
 Engorgement It is normal for your breasts to become larger, heavier, and a little tender 
when they begin making more milk. Sometimes this fullness may turn into 
engorgement, when your breasts feel very hard and painful. You also may have 
breast swelling, tenderness, warmth, redness, throbbing, and flattening of the 
nipple. Engorgement sometimes also causes a low-grade
 fever and can be confused 
with a breast infection. Engorgement is the result of the milk building up. It 
usually happens during the third to fifth day after birth, but it can happen at 
any time. Engorgement can lead to plugged ducts or a breast infection, so it is 
important to try to prevent it before this happens. If treated properly, 
engorgement should resolve. Ask for help! Ask your lactation consultant or doctor for help if the engorgement lasts for two days or more.
 Plugged ducts It is common for many women to have a plugged duct at some point 
breastfeeding. A plugged milk duct feels like a tender and sore lump in the 
breast. It is not accompanied by a fever or other symptoms. It happens when a 
milk duct does not properly drain and becomes inflamed. Then, pressure builds up 
behind the plug, and surrounding tissue becomes inflamed. A plugged duct usually 
only occurs in one breast at a time. Breastfeed often on the affected side, as often as every two hours. This 
helps loosen the plug, and keeps the milk moving freely. Massage the area, 
starting behind the sore spot. Use your fingers in a circular motion and massage 
toward the nipple. Use a warm compress on the sore area. Get extra
 sleep or 
relax with your
 feet up to help speed healing. Often a plugged duct is the first 
sign that a mother is doing too much. Wear a well-fitting supportive bra that is 
not too tight, since this can constrict milk ducts. Consider trying a bra 
without underwire. Ask for help! If your plugged duct doesn't loosen up, ask for help from a lactation consultant. Plugged ducts can lead to a breast infection. Breast infection (mastitis) Even if you are taking medicine, continue to breastfeed during treatment. 
This is best for both you and your baby. Ask a lactation consultant for help if 
needed. Mastitis (mast-EYE-tiss) is soreness or a lump in the breast that can be 
accompanied by a fever and/or
 flu -like symptoms, such as feeling run down or 
very achy. Some women with a breast infection also have
 nausea and
 vomiting . You 
also may have yellowish discharge from the nipple that looks like colostrum. Or, 
the breasts may feel warm or hot to the touch and appear pink or red. A breast 
infection can occur when other family members have a cold or the flu. It usually 
only occurs in one breast. It is not always easy to tell the difference between 
a breast infection and a plugged duct because both have similar symptoms and can 
improve within 24 to 48 hours. Most breast infections that do not improve on 
their own within this time period 
need to be treated with medicine given by a doctor. Ask for help! Ask your doctor for help if you do not feel better within 24 hours of trying 
these tips, if you have a fever, or if your symptoms worsen. You might need 
medicine. See your doctor right away if: You have a breast infection in which both breasts look affected There is pus 
or blood in the milk You have red streaks near the area Your symptoms came on 
severely and suddenly
 Fungal infections A fungal infection, also called a
 yeast infection or
 thrush , can form on your 
nipples or in your breast because it thrives on milk. The infection forms from 
an overgrowth of the Candida organism. Candida exists in our bodies and is kept 
at healthy levels by the natural bacteria in our bodies. When the natural 
balance of bacteria is upset, Candida can overgrow, causing an infection. A key sign of a fungal infection is if you develop sore nipples that last 
more than a few days, even after you make sure your baby has a good latch. Or, 
you may suddenly get sore nipples after several weeks of pain-free 
breastfeeding. Some other signs of a fungal infection include pink, flaky, 
shiny, itchy or cracked nipples, or deep pink and blistered nipples. You also 
could have achy breasts or shooting pains deep in the breast during or after 
feedings. Causes of thrush include: Thrush in your baby&amp;#39;s mouth, which can pass to you An overly moist 
environment on your skin or nipples that are sore or cracked Antibiotics or 
steroids A chronic illness like
 HIV ,
 diabetes , or
 anemia Thrush in a baby&amp;#39;s mouth appears as little white spots on the inside of the 
cheeks, gums, or tongue. Many babies with thrush refuse to nurse, or are gassy 
or cranky. A baby&amp;#39;s fungal infection can also appear as a
 diaper rash that looks 
like small red dots around a main
 rash . This
 rash will not go away by using 
regular
 diaper rash creams. Fungal infections may take several weeks to cure, so it is important to 
follow these tips to avoid spreading the infection: Ask for help! If you or your baby has symptoms of a fungal infection, call both your doctor 
and your baby&amp;#39;s doctor so you can be correctly diagnosed and treated at the same 
time. This will help prevent passing the infection to each other.
 Nursing strike A nursing "strike" is when your baby has been breastfeeding well for months, 
and then suddenly begins to refuse the breast. A nursing strike can mean that 
your baby is trying to let you know that something is wrong. This does not 
usually mean that the baby is ready to wean. Not all babies will react the same 
to the different situations that can cause a nursing strike. Some babies will 
continue to breastfeed without a problem. Others may just become fussy at the 
breast, and others will refuse the breast entirely. Some of the major causes of 
a nursing strike include: Mouth pain from
 teething , a fungal infection like thrush, or a
 cold sore An
 ear infection , which causes pain while sucking Pain from a certain breastfeeding 
position, either from an injury on the baby&amp;#39;s body or from soreness from an 
 immunization Being upset about a long separation from the mother or a major 
change in routine Being distracted while breastfeeding - becoming interested in 
other things around him or her A cold or stuffy nose that makes
 breathing while 
breastfeeding difficult Reduced milk supply from supplementing with bottles or 
overuse of a pacifier Responding to the mother&amp;#39;s strong reaction if the baby has 
 bitten her Being upset about
 hearing arguing or people talking in a harsh voice 
while breastfeeding Reacting to
 stress , overstimulation, or having been 
repeatedly put off when wanting to breastfeed If your baby is on a nursing strike, it is normal to feel frustrated and 
upset, especially if your baby is unhappy. It is important not to feel guilty or 
think that you have done something wrong. Keep in mind that your breasts may 
become uncomfortable as the milk builds up. Ask for help if your baby is having a nursing strike to ensure that your baby 
gets enough milk. The doctor can check your baby&amp;#39;s
 weight gain .
 Inverted, flat, or very large nipples Some women have nipples that turn inward instead of protruding, or that are 
flat and do not protrude. Nipples can also sometimes be flattened temporarily 
due to engorgement or swelling while breastfeeding. Inverted or flat nipples can 
sometimes make it harder to breastfeed. But remember that for breastfeeding to 
work, your baby has to latch on to both the nipple and the breast, so even 
inverted nipples can work just fine. Often, flat and inverted nipples will 
protrude more over time, as the baby sucks more. Very large nipples can make it hard for the baby to get enough of the areola 
into his or her mouth to compress the milk ducts and get enough milk. Ask for help if you have questions about your nipple shape or type, 
especially if your baby is having trouble latching well.
 Breastfeeding a baby with health problems There are some health problems in babies that can make it harder to 
breastfeed. Yet breast milk and early breastfeeding are still best for the 
health of both you and your baby - even more so if your baby is premature or 
sick. Even if your baby cannot breastfeed directly from you, it&amp;#39;s best to 
express or pump your milk and give it to your baby with a cup or dropper. Some common health problems in babies are listed below. Jaundice is caused by an excess of bilirubin, a substance that is in the 
blood usually in very small amounts. In the
 newborn period, bilirubin can build 
up faster than it can be removed from the intestinal track.
 Jaundice can appear 
as a yellowing of the skin and eyes. It affects most newborns to some degree, 
appearing between the second and third day of life. The jaundice usually clears 
up by two weeks of age and is not harmful. Two types of jaundice can affect breastfed infants - breastfeeding jaundice 
and breast milk jaundice. Breastfeeding jaundice can occur when a breastfeeding baby is not getting 
enough breast milk. This can happen either because of breastfeeding challenges 
or because the mother&amp;#39;s milk hasn&amp;#39;t yet come in. This is not caused by a problem 
with the breast milk itself. Breast milk jaundice may be caused by substances in 
the mother&amp;#39;s milk that prevents bilirubin from being excreted from the body. 
Such jaundice appears in some healthy, breastfed babies after about one week of 
age. It may last for a month or more and it is usually not harmful. Your baby&amp;#39;s doctor may monitor your baby&amp;#39;s bilirubin level with blood tests. 
Jaundice is best treated by breastfeeding more frequently or for longer periods 
of time. It is crucial to have a health care provider help you make sure the 
baby is latching on and removing milk well. This is usually all that is needed 
for the infant&amp;#39;s body to rid itself of excess bilirubin. Some babies will also need phototherapy - treatment with a special light. 
This light helps break down bilirubin into a form that can be removed from the 
body easily. If you are having trouble latching your baby to the breast, it is 
important that you pump or hand express to ensure a good milk supply. The same 
is true if the baby needs formula for a short time - pumping or hand expressing 
will make sure the baby has enough milk when you return to breastfeeding. It is important to keep in mind that breastfeeding is best for your baby. 
Even if your baby experiences jaundice, this is not something that you caused. 
Your health care providers can help you make sure that your baby is eating well 
and that the jaundice goes away. Ask for help! If your baby develops jaundice once at home, let your baby's doctor know. Discuss treatment options and let the doctor know that you do not want to interrupt breastfeeding if at all possible. Some babies have a condition called gastroesophageal (GASS-troh-uh-SOF-uh-JEE-uhl) 
reflux disease (
 GERD ), which occurs when the muscle at the opening of the 
stomach opens at the wrong times. This allows milk and food to come back up into 
the
 esophagus , the tube in the throat. Some
 symptoms of GERD can include: Severe spitting up, or spitting up after every feeding or hours after eating Projectile
 vomiting , where the milk shoots out of the mouth Inconsolable crying 
as if in discomfort Arching of the back as if in severe pain Refusal to eat or 
pulling away from the breast during feeding Waking up often at night Slow weight 
gain Gagging or choking, or problems swallowing Many healthy babies might have some of these symptoms and not have
 GERD . But 
there are babies who might only have a few of these symptoms and have a severe 
case of GERD. Not all babies with GERD spit up or vomit. More severe cases of 
GERD may need to be treated with medication if the baby refuses to nurse, gains 
weight poorly or is losing weight, or has periods of gagging or choking. Ask for help! See your baby&amp;#39;s doctor if he or she spits up after every feeding and has any 
of the other symptoms mentioned here. If your baby has GERD, it is important to 
continue breastfeeding. Breast milk is more easily digested than
 infant formula . Cleft palate and
 cleft lip are some of the most common
 birth defects that 
happen as a baby is developing in the womb. A cleft, or opening, in either the 
palate or lip can happen together or separately and both can be corrected 
through surgery. Both conditions can prevent babies from forming a good seal 
around the nipple and areola with his or her mouth, or effectively remove milk 
from the breast. A mother can try different breastfeeding positions and use her 
thumb or breast to help fill in the opening left by the lip to form a seal 
around the breast. Right after birth, a mother whose baby has a cleft palate can try to 
breastfeed her baby. She can also start expressing her milk right away to keep 
up her supply. Even if her baby can&amp;#39;t latch on well to her breast, the baby can 
be fed breast milk by cup. In some hospitals, babies with cleft palate are 
fitted with a mouthpiece called an obturator that fits into the cleft and seals 
it for easier feeding. The baby should be able to exclusively breastfeed after 
his or her surgery. Ask for help! If your baby is born with a cleft palate or cleft lip, talk with a lactation 
consultant in the hospital. Breast milk is still best for your baby&amp;#39;s health. Premature birth is when a baby is born before 37 weeks gestation. Prematurity 
often will mean that the baby is born at a low birth weight, defined as less 
than five and a half pounds. Low birth weight can also be caused by 
malnourishment in the mother. Arriving early or being small can make for a tough 
adjustment, especially if the baby has to stay in the hospital for extra care. 
But keep in mind that breast milk has been shown to help premature babies grow 
and ward off illness. Most babies who are low birth weight but born after 37 weeks (full term) can 
begin breastfeeding right away. They will need more skin-to-skin contact with 
mom and dad to help keep them warm. These smaller babies may also need more 
frequent feedings, and they may get sleepier during those feedings. Many babies born prematurely are often not able to breastfeed at first, but 
they do benefit from expressed milk. You can express colostrum by hand or pump 
as soon as you can in the hospital. You can talk to the hospital staff about 
renting a hospital grade electric pump. Call your insurance company or local WIC 
Office to find out if you can get reimbursed for this type of pump. You will 
need to express milk as often as you would have breastfed, so around 8 times per 
a 24-hour period. Once your baby is ready to breastfeed directly, skin-to-skin contact can be 
very calming and a great start to your first feeding. Be sure to work with a 
lactation consultant on proper latch and positioning. Many mothers of premature 
babies find the cross cradle hold helpful.  It may take some time for you and the baby to get into a 
good routine. Did you know? If you leave the hospital before your baby, you can express milk for the hospital staff to give the baby by feeding tube.
 Breastfeeding and special situations Did you 
know? Many twin and multiple babies are smaller or born premature. Please see the 
Premature and/or low birth weight section for other tips for caring for these 
babies. Also, talk with a lactation consultant about more ways you can 
successfully breastfeed. The benefits of human milk to mothers of multiples and their babies are the 
same as for all mothers and babies - possibly greater, since many multiples are 
born early. But the idea may seem overwhelming! Yet many of these moms find 
breastfeeding easier than other feeding methods because there is nothing to 
prepare. Many mothers have overcome challenges to successfully breastfeed twins 
and more even after going back to work. It will help to learn as much as you can about breastfeeding during your
 pregnancy . You can: Take a breastfeeding class. Find Internet and print resources for parents of 
multiples. Join a support group for parents of multiples through your health 
care provider, hospital, local breastfeeding center, or La Leche League 
International. Let your health care provider and family members know that you 
plan to breastfeed. Keep in mind that even if your babies need to spend time in 
the NICU (
 neonatal intensive care unit), breastfeeding is still possible, with 
some adjustments. Find a lactation consultant with multiples experience before 
the babies are born so that you know where to turn for help. Ask her where you 
can rent a breast pump if the babies are born early. Many breastfeeding basics are the same for twins or multiples as they are for 
one baby. Learn more about these important topics: How to know your babies are getting enough milk How to troubleshoot common 
breastfeeding challenges Ways to keep milk supply up Most mothers are able to make plenty of milk for twins. Many mothers fully 
breastfeed or provide milk for triplets or quadruplets. Keep these tips in mind: Breastfeeding soon after birth and often is helpful for multiples the same 
way it is for one baby. The more milk that is effectively removed, the more milk 
a mother&amp;#39;s body will make. If the babies are born early, double pumping often 
will help the mother make more milk. The doctor&amp;#39;s weight checks can tell you if 
your babies are getting enough breast milk. For other signs that your babies are 
getting enough breast milk, see the How to know your baby is getting enough milk 
section. It helps to have each baby feed from both breasts. You can "assign" a 
breast to each baby for a feeding and switch at the next feeding. Or, you can 
assign a breast to each baby for a day and switch the next day. Switching 
breasts helps keep milk production up if one baby isn&amp;#39;t eating as well for a 
bit. It also gives babies a different view to stimulate their eyes. Breastfeeding twins and more may take practice, but you and your babies can 
find your ideal positions and routine. Keep trying different positions until you 
find ones that work for you. For some mothers and babies, breastfeeding twins at 
the same time works well. Others find individual feedings to work better. Still 
others find that it depends on the time - you may feed one baby at a time at 
night and feed two babies at the same time during the day. Lastly, as your 
babies grow, you may find that you need to change your feeding routine. Below are some positions that may work for you: Double clutch ("football") - Place both babies in the clutch hold. You will 
need pillows at your side (and maybe one on your lap) and you will place the 
babies on the pillows with their legs going toward the back of the chair or 
couch. If you are placing the babies in front of you, try to keep their whole 
bodies turned toward you, their chests against your chest. Their bodies must not 
be facing up. This is very important to help prevent
 nipple pain and to make 
sure that the babies are getting enough milk. Cradle-clutch combination - Place 
one baby (usually the easiest to latch or stay latched) in the cradle position 
and then position the second baby in the clutch position. Double cradle - Place 
the babies in front of you with their legs overlapping, making an X across your 
lap. Even though full, direct breastfeeding is ideal, many mothers of multiples 
feed their babies breast milk or some formula by bottles at times. It is 
important to work with your doctor, your baby&amp;#39;s doctor, and a lactation 
consultant to figure out what works best for your family. Breastfeeding during your next pregnancy is not a risk to either the 
breastfeeding toddler or to the new developing baby. If you are having some 
problems in your pregnancy such as uterine pain or bleeding, a history of 
preterm labor or problems gaining weight during pregnancy, your doctor may 
advise you to wean. Some women also choose to wean at this time because they 
have nipple soreness caused by pregnancy hormones, are nauseous, or find that 
their growing bellies make breastfeeding uncomfortable. Your toddler also may 
decide to wean on his own because of changes in the amount and flavor of your 
milk. He or she will need additional food and drink because you will likely make 
less milk during pregnancy. If you keep nursing your toddler after your baby is born, you can feed your 
newborn first to ensure he or she gets the colostrum. Once your milk production 
increases a few days after birth you can decide how to best meet everyone&amp;#39;s 
needs, especially the new baby&amp;#39;s needs for you and your milk. You may want to 
ask your partner to help you by taking care of one child while you are 
breastfeeding. Also, you will have a need for more fluids, healthy foods, and 
rest because you are taking care of yourself and two small children. How much milk you can produce depends on how your surgery was done and where 
your incisions are, and the reasons for your surgery. Women who have had 
incisions in the fold under the breasts are less likely to have problems making 
milk than women who have had incisions around or across the areola, which can 
cut into milk ducts and nerves. Women who have had
 breast implants usually 
breastfeed successfully. If you ever had surgery on your breasts for any reason, 
talk with a lactation consultant. If you are planning breast surgery, talk with 
your surgeon about ways he or she can preserve as much of the breast tissue and 
milk ducts as possible. Many mothers who adopt want to breastfeed their babies and can do it 
successfully with some help. Many will need to supplement their breast milk with 
donated breast milk from a milk bank or infant formula, but some adoptive 
mothers can breastfeed exclusively, especially if they have been
 pregnant before. Lactation is a hormonal response to a physical action, and so the 
stimulation of the baby nursing causes the body to see a need for and produce 
milk. The more the baby nurses, the more a woman&amp;#39;s body will produce milk. If you are adopting and want to breastfeed, talk with both your doctor and a 
lactation consultant. They can help you decide the best way to try to establish 
a milk supply for your new baby. You might be able to prepare by pumping every 
three hours around the clock for two to three weeks before your baby arrives, or 
you can wait until the baby arrives and start to breastfeed then. Devices such 
as a supplemental nursing system (SNS) or a lactation aid can help ensure that 
your baby gets enough
 nutrition and that your breasts are stimulated to produce 
milk at the same time. If you can&amp;#39;t breastfeed and still want to give your baby human milk, the best 
and only safe place to go is to a human milk bank. You should never feed your 
baby breast milk that you get directly from another woman or through the 
Internet. A human milk bank can dispense donor human milk to you if you have a 
prescription from your doctor. Many steps are taken to ensure the milk is safe. 
Donor human milk provides the same precious nutrition and disease fighting 
properties as your own breast milk. If your baby was born premature or has other health problems, he or she may 
need donated milk not only for health, but also for survival. Your baby may also 
need donated milk if she or he: Can&amp;#39;t tolerate formula Has severe
 allergies Isn&amp;#39;t thriving on formula You can find a human milk bank through the Human Milk Banking Association of 
North America External Website Policy (HMBANA). HMBANA is a multidisciplinary 
group of health care providers that promotes, protects, and supports donor milk 
banking. HMBANA is the only professional membership association for milk banks 
in Canada, Mexico and the United States and as such sets the standards and 
guidelines for donor milk banking for those areas. You can also contact HMBANA 
if you would like to donate breast milk. To find out if your insurance will cover the cost of the milk, call your 
insurance company or ask your doctor. If your insurance company does not cover 
the cost of the milk, talk with the milk bank to find out how payment can be 
made later on, or how to get help with the payments. A milk bank will never deny 
donor milk to a baby in need if they have the supply.
</first>
</file1>