<file1>
<first>Broken Toe Symptoms, Signs, Treatment, and Healing Time

ABOUT:  A commonly injured area of the foot is the small bones of the toes (phalanges). There are 26 bones in the foot; 19 are bones in the forefoot (5
 metatarsals and 14 phalanges). Trauma and the injury to the foot often causes one or more of the toe bones to break (fracture). 
SYMPTOMS:  
CAUSES:  Trauma or injury such as stubbing the toe (jammed toe) or dropping a heavy object on the toe may cause a broken toe. The location of the toes (at the front part of the
 feet ) makes them the most likely part of the foot to be injured. Prolonged repetitive movements, as in certain sports activities, can cause a type of broken type of broken toe called a
 stress fracture or hairline fracture. People with weakened bones (
 osteoporosis or other disorders) may develop stress fractures simply from wearing improper shoes.
 When to call a doctor if I think you have a broken toe Many people think that if they can walk on an injured toe, it is not broken. This may not be the case. It is common to break a toe bone and still be able to walk on it. Go to a hospital&amp;#39;s emergency department if you have following signs or symptoms. Any symptoms of a possible open (compound) fracture which include open wounds, bleeding, or drainage from near the broken toe Cold, numb, tingling, or unusual sensation in the toes Blue or gray colored skin near the injury If the injured toe appears deformed or is pointing in the wrong direction (angulated) Call a doctor if any of the following occur: If the broken
 toe pain worsens or new pain is not relieved by pain medication Sores, redness, or open wounds near the injured toe Bruising or bleeding under the toenail that causes significant pain A cast or splint is damaged or broken How can you tell if you have a broken toe? Seek medical evaluation soon after the injury to ensure proper treatment and healing. A doctor will ask questions to determine how the toe was injured and will examine the injured toe and possibly check for other injuries. A doctor may take an X-ray to evaluate if the toe is broken or fractured. X-rays are not always necessary to diagnose a broken toe, especially if the break is in one of the smaller toes. Stress fractures, due to overuse or repetitive movement, may need an
 MRI to be diagnosed. You initially may see a primary care provider (PCP) such as a family practitioner or a child’s pediatrician when you first injure your toe. You likely willbe referred to an orthopedist or orthopedic surgeon, who specializes in disorders of the musculoskelteal system, or a podiatrist, a specialist in conditions of the foot, for treatment. You also may be diagnosed with a broken toe in a hospital’s emergency department by an
 emergency medicine specialist. Radiologists will read an X-ray or MRI, though they will usually report back to your primary care physician or emergency medicine specialist and you will not directly consult with them.
 Can anything be done at home for a broken toe? Most minor toe injuries can be treated at home. If a you are unsure or suspect a fracture, seek medical attention. The following may help decrease pain and swelling from a broken toe, and to help the fracture heal properly. Rest: Avoid strenuous
 exercise , prolonged standing, or walking. Crutches may be needed, or a special shoe or boot to wear when walking to avoid putting weight on the fracture while it heals. Ice: Put ice in a
 plastic bag and apply it to the injury for 15-20 minutes every 1-2 hours for the first 1-2 days. Place a towel between the skin and the ice to protect the skin. Frozen peas or corn can also be used to ice the broken toe - they may conform to the fractured area better than ice. Elevation: To decrease swelling and pain, keep the foot raised above the level of the heart as much and as often as possible. Prop the foot up as much as possible (for example use several pillows), especially when sleeping. Reclining in a lounge chair is also helpful. In certain situations, a broken toe may need medical care such as maneuvering the toe back into place (reduction), casting, or splinting the toe. How to buddy tape a broken toe If there is a minor or small fracture in a bone of one of the small toes, a doctor may only need to tape the injured toe to the one next to it for support. This treatment is called buddy taping. Put a small piece of cotton or gauze between the toes that are taped together. (This prevents the skin between the toes from developing sores or
 blisters .) Using as little tape as necessary, loosely tape the broken toe to the toe next to it. If the toes are taped too tightly it can cause additional swelling and may cut off circulation to the injured toe. If the toe is buddy taped, it is usually safe to bathe, and then replace the tape afterward, however, check with the doctor prior to removing the tape to bathe. Always follow your doctor&amp;#39;s instructions on how to tape your broken toe.
 
TREATMENT:  Depending on the location and severity of the toe fracture, the fracture may need to be put back into place (reduced) and splinted or casted. Because it has a significant weight bearing role, fractures of the big toe are often more serious and more likely to require reduction or surgical treatment. If there is an
 open wound near the injured toe, a
 tetanus shot and antibiotic medication may also be necessary. If there is an open (compound) fracture of the toe, surgery may be necessary in some cases, and antibiotics will be given. This type of fracture should be seen by a doctor immediately. Usually only
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ) or
 ibuprofen (
 Motrin ) is needed for pain. For a severe fracture, the doctor may prescribe a stronger pain medication. Casting a broken toe Reduction for a broken toe How long does it take for a broken toe to heal? Talk to the doctor to have the broken toe evaluated to be certain it is healing properly. Call a doctor or go to an emergency department if any problems or complications develop before the scheduled appointment. The healing time for broken toes usually is take about six weeks to heal. If problems last longer than six weeks, another X-ray may be needed, or the injury should be rechecked by the doctor to evaluate how the bone is healing. Simple toe fractures usually heal well with no problems. However, a severe fracture or a fracture that goes into a joint is at risk for developing arthritis, pain, stiffness, and possibly even a deformity. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Other problems may develop as a result of the broken toe. Complications can occur immediately after the injury (minutes to days), or can develop much later (weeks to years). Inadequate treatment of a broken toe may lead to complications including foot deformities and
 chronic pain . Even when a broken toe is treated promptly, complications may arise including: Nail injury: A collection of blood may develop underneath the toenail called a subungual
 hematoma . If it is large, it may need to be drained. To drain a subungual hematoma a doctor will make a small hole in the toenail to drain the blood. If the hematoma is very large or painful, the entire toenail may need to be removed. The injury may also result in a broken toenail that may need to be trimmed or removed. Compound fracture: Rarely, the
 broken bone in a toe fracture may stick out through the skin. This is called an open or compound fracture. Emergency medical treatment and surgery may be necessary. Arthritis: After the toe fracture heals, the person may still be left with arthritis, pain, stiffness, or even deformity. Nonunion/malunion: Sometimes, the
 fractured bone will not heal completely (called a nonunion) or will heal improperly (called a malunion). Rarely, surgery may be necessary to fix this problem.
</first>
</file1>