<file1>
<first>First Aid for Burns
Introduction to burns The skin has an important role to play in the fluid and temperature regulation of the body. If enough skin area is injured, the ability to maintain that control can be lost. The skin also acts as a protective barrier against the bacteria and
 viruses that inhabit the world outside the body. The anatomy of the skin is complex, and there are many structures within the layers of the skin. There are three layers: The amount of damage that a burn can cause depends upon the type of burn, its location, its depth, and how much body surface area that it involves. How are burns classified? Burns are classified based upon their depth. A
 first degree burn is superficial and causes 
local inflammation of the skin. Sunburns often are categorized as first degree burns. The inflammation is characterized by
 pain , redness, and a mild amount of swelling. The skin may be 
very tender to touch. Second degree burns are deeper and in addition to the
 pain , redness and inflammation, there is also blistering of the skin. Third degree burns are deeper still, involving all layers of the skin, in effect killing that area of skin. Because the nerves and blood vessels are damaged, third degree burns appear white and leathery and tend to be relatively painless. Burns are not static and may mature. Over a few hours a first degree burn may involve deeper structures and become second degree. Think of a
 sunburn that
 blisters the next day. Similarly, second degree burns may evolve into third degree burns. Regardless of the type of burn, inflammation and fluid accumulation in and around the
 wound occur. Moreover, it should be noted that the skin is the body's first defense against infection by microorganisms. A burn is also a break in the skin, and the risk of infection exists both at the site of the injury and potentially throughout the body. Only the epidermis has the ability to regenerate itself. Burns that extend deeper may cause permanent injury and scarring and not allow the skin in that area to return to normal function.
 What is the significance of the amount of body area burned? In addition to the depth of the burn, the total surface area of the burn is significant. Burns are measured as a percentage of total body area affected. The
 "rule of nines" is often used, adjusted for infants and children. This calculation is based upon the fact that the surface area of the following parts of an adult body each correspond to approximately 9% of total (and the total body area of 100% is achieved): Head = 9% Chest (front) = 9% Abdomen (front) = 9% Upper/mid/low back and buttocks = 18% Each arm = 9% Each palm = 1% Groin = 1% Each leg = 18% total (front = 9%, back = 9%) As an example, if both legs (18% x 2 = 36%), the groin (1%) and the front chest and abdomen were burned, this would involve 55% of the body.
 Only second and third degree burn areas are added together to measure total body burn area. While first degree burns are painful, the skin integrity is intact and it is able to do its job with fluid and temperature maintenance. If more than15%-20% of the body is involved in a burn, significant fluid may be lost.
 Shock may occur if inadequate fluid is not provided intravenously. As the percentage of burn surface area increases, the risk of death increases as well. Patients with burns involving less than 20% of their body should do well, but those with burns involving greater than 50% have a significant mortality risk, depending upon a variety of factors, including underlying medical conditions and age.
 How important is the location of a burn? Burn location is an important consideration. If the burn involves the face, nose, mouth or neck, there is a risk that there will be inhalation injury and enough inflammation and swelling to obstruct the
 airway and cause
 breathing problems. If there are circumferential burns to the chest, as the burn progresses, the tissue involved may not allow enough motion of the chest wall to allow adequate breathing to occur. If circumferential burns occur to arms, legs, fingers, or toes, the same constriction may not allow blood flow and put the survival of the extremity at risk. Burns to areas of the body with flexion creases, like the palm of the hand, the back of the knee, the face, and the groin may need specialized care. As the burn matures, the skin may scar and shorten, preventing full range of motion of the body area. What about electrical burns? Electrical burns may cause serious injury that is not readily apparent. Often the entry and exit points for the electrical shock may not be easily identified. Electricity flows more easily through tissues in the body that are designed to deal with electricity. Nerves and muscles are "wired" for this task and often are damaged. If significant muscle damage occurs, muscle fibers break down and chemicals can be released into the bloodstream causing electrolyte disturbances and
 kidney failure . What about chemical burns? Burns can also occur when chemicals are spilled onto the body and generate a reaction that creates heat. Chemical burns may be classified by their pH or acidity. Acids are those with pH less than 7 and include common household compounds like acetic acid, hydrochloric acid, or sulfuric acid. Bases or alkali compounds have a pH greater than 7. Ammonia is a common alkali found in the home.
 First aid for burns Burns of the face, hands, and
 feet should always be considered a significant injury (although this may exclude
 sunburn . Gently clean the wound with lukewarm water. Though butter has been used as a home remedy, it should NOT be used on any burn. Rings, bracelets, and other potentially constricting articles should be removed (
 edema , or swelling from inflammation may occur and the item may cut into the skin). The burn may be dressed with a topical antibiotic ointment like Bacitracin or
 Neosporin .
 Silvadene (silver
 sulfadiazine ) topical is the preferred agent for most burns, and is available over the counter in many locations. If there is concern that the burn is deeper and may be second or third degree in nature, medical care should be accessed. Tetanus immunization should be updated if needed. Victims of electrical burns should always seek medical care.</first>
</file1>