<file1>
<first>Calcific Bursitis
What is calcific bursitis? A bursa is a thin fluid-filled sac that reduces friction forces between tissues of the body. Chronic (repeated or long-standing) inflammation of the bursa (
 bursitis ) can lead to calcification of the bursa. This is referred to as "calcific bursitis." The calcium deposits (calcification) can occur as long as the inflammation is present and remain after it has resolved. Calcific bursitis occurs most commonly at the shoulder (in the bursa adjacent to the
 rotator cuff tendons) or hip (in the bursa at the greater trochanter). 
CAUSES:  Calcific bursitis often has no direct cause that is identified and likely occurs in this setting after unnoticed strain of a joint caused local inflammation of the bursa (bursitis). Risk factors for developing calcific bursitis include joint injury (
 trauma ) and underlying diseases such as
 ankylosing spondylitis and calcium pyrophosphate dehydrate deposition disease (
 pseudogout ). 
SYMPTOMS:  Calcific bursitis may not cause any symptoms once the inflammation has subsided. Calcific bursitis typically leads to
 chronic pain ,
 stiffness , and sometimes limited range of motion of the affected joint with use or when examined. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of inflammation of the bursa (bursitis) can be made clinically based on the history and physical findings. Calcific bursitis is diagnosed when viewed with anX-ray test or
 MRI scan of the inflamed, painful bursa.
 
TREATMENT:  Treatment of the inflammation of calcific bursitis can help to prevent further calcification as well as relieve
 pain and stiffness. Treatments include medications for inflammation, cold packs, immobilization, injections of cortisone into the bursa, physical therapy, and occasionally surgery to remove the inflamed bursa and calcium deposit. What is the prognosis of calcific bursitis? When the inflammation is quieted, the long-term outlook (prognosis) is excellent. Optimal improvement can require physical therapy treatment. The calcium deposit can remain indefinitely and may not cause any problems. Significant calcium deposits can sometimes, however, cause a mechanically abrasive area of tenderness. These deposits that continue to cause symptoms are considered for surgical removal. 
PREVENTION:  The prevention of calcific bursitis involves avoiding injury and reinjury to joints and treating any underlying medical condition (if present) that might increase the chances for developing calcific bursitis.
</first>
</file1>