<file1>
<first>Bacterial Vaginosis Symptoms, Causes, Remedies, Treatment Medicine, and Cure
Bacterial vaginosis (BV) definition and facts What is bacterial vaginosis (BV)? Bacterial vaginosis also is referred to as nonspecific
 vaginitis , is a vaginal condition that can produce vaginal discharge and results from an overgrowth of certain kinds of bacteria in the vagina. In the past, the condition was called
 Gardnerella vaginitis, after the bacteria that were thought to cause the condition. However, the newer name, bacterial vaginosis, reflects the fact that there are a number of species of bacteria that naturally live in the vaginal area and may grow to excess, rather than a true infection with foreign bacteria, such as occurs with many sexually-transmitted disease (
 STDs ). The
 Gardnerella organism is not the sole type of bacteria causing the symptoms. Other kinds of bacteria that can be involved in bacterial vaginosis are
 Lactobacillus , Bacteroides, Peptostreptococcus, Fusobacterium, Eubacterium , as well as a number of other types. When these multiple species of bacteria that normally reside in the vagina become unbalanced, a woman can have a vaginal discharge with a foul odor. What are signs and symptoms of bacterial vaginosis (BV)? Many women with bacterial vaginosis have no signs or symptoms at all. When symptoms do occur, the most common include: Symptoms of bacterial vaginosis, if present, can occur any time in the
 menstrual cycle , including before, during, or after the
 menstrual period . The amount of vaginal discharge that is considered normal varies from woman to woman. Therefore, any degree of vaginal discharge that is abnormal for a particular woman should be evaluated. What causes bacterial vaginosis (BV)? Researchers have had difficulty determining exactly what causes bacterial vaginosis. At present, it seems to be that a combination of multiple bacteria must be present together for bacterial vaginosis to develop. Bacterial vaginosis typically features a reduction in the number of the normal hydrogen peroxide-producing lactobacilli in the vagina. Simultaneously, there is an increase in concentration of other types of bacteria, especially anaerobic bacteria (bacteria that grow in the absence of oxygen). As a result, the diagnosis and treatment are not as simple as identifying and eradicating a single type of bacteria. Why the bacteria combine to cause the unbalance is unknown. Certain risk factors have been identified that increase the chances of developing bacterial vaginosis. These risk factors for BV include: multiple or new sexual partners, IUDs (intrauterine devices) for
 birth control , recent antibiotic use, vaginal
 douching , and cigarette smoking . However, the role of sexual activity in the development of the condition is not fully understood, and although most experts believe that bacterial vaginosis does not occur in women who have not had sexual intercourse, others feel that the condition can still develop in women who have not had sexual intercourse. How common is bacterial vaginosis (BV)? Is it an STD or yeast infection? Can you get bacterial vaginosis (BV) from a sexual partner? The term "vaginosis" refers to a vaginal abnormality; therefore a male cannot "get" bacterial vaginosis. However, female sex partners of women with bacterial vaginosis may want to consider being evaluated because it can spread to female partners. Is bacterial vaginosis contagious (BV)? Although
 bacterial vaginosis is not considered to be a contagious condition , the role of transmissibility of bacteria among individuals is not fully understood. Since having multiple or new sexual partners increases a woman&amp;#39;s risk of developing bacterial vaginosis, this suggests that spread of bacteria among individuals may alter the balance of bacteria in the vagina and potentially predispose to development of bacterial vaginosis. However, since bacterial vaginosis also occurs in celibate women, other causative factors must also play a role in its development. It is not possible to contract bacterial vaginosis from toilet seats,
 swimming pools, or hot tubs, or from touching contaminated objects. Is there a test to diagnose bacterial vaginosis (BV)? What is the "whiff test?" When a woman notices an unusual vaginal discharge and reports this to her doctor, he or she will ask her a series of routine questions to help distinguish mild from more serious conditions. Additional issues that might indicate the presence of a more serious condition include: fever , pelvic pain , new or multiple sexual partners (especially with unprotected intercourse), and a history of sexually-transmitted infections (STDs). In addition to these questions, the doctor will perform a
 pelvic exam . During the exam, the doctor notes the appearance of the vaginal lining and cervix. The doctor will also perform a manual exam of the ovaries and uterus. The cervix is examined for tenderness, which might indicate a more serious infection. The doctor may collect samples to check for
 Chlamydia or gonorrhea infection. Examining the vaginal discharge under the microscope can help distinguish bacterial vaginosis from infections such as yeast vaginitis (vaginal
 yeast infection ,
 Candidiasis ) and
 trichomoniasis . A sign of bacterial vaginosis under the microscope is a vaginal cell called a clue cell. Clue cells are vaginal cells covered with bacteria and are believed to be the most reliable diagnostic sign of bacterial vaginosis. In addition to clue cells, women with bacterial vaginosis have fewer of the normal vaginal bacteria, called
 lactobacilli . A vaginal pH greater than 4.5 is also suggestive of bacterial vaginosis. Cultures of bacteria are generally not useful in establishing the diagnosis of bacterial vaginosis since it is caused by bacteria that are normally present in the vagina. During the diagnosis of bacterial vaginosis the doctor may perform a "whiff test" with potassium hydroxide (KOH) liquid. When a drop of KOH testing liquid used in the "whiff test" contacts a drop of the discharge from a woman with bacterial vaginosis, a certain fishy odor can result. Can bacterial vaginosis (BV) be treated and cured with home remedies? There are no home remedies or natural remedies for bacterial vaginosis. Antibiotics are the only treatment. It is important to note that douching (rinsing the interior of the vagina) will not help with BV, and here is no proven medical benefit of douching. In fact, douching may
 flush bacteria farther up the genital tract into the uterus or Fallopian tubes, potentially worsening the condition. Studies of yogurt/lactobacilli
 probiotic preparations (either taken orally or applied to the vagina), which are designed to help reestablish the lactobacilli population in the vagina, have not shown consistent results in treating bacterial vaginosis. 
TREATMENT:  Can antibiotics cure it? Bacterial vaginosis can be cured with antibiotics. Even after a woman has been cured, however, BV often recurs. A second course of antibiotics is necessary if a woman experiences recurrent bacterial vaginosis that produces symptoms. Antibiotics are the recommended treatment for bacterial vaginosis. A few antibiotic remedies are routinely used and include: metronidazole (Flagyl) taken by either oral (pill) form or vaginal
 metronidazole gel (
 Metrogel ). The oral metronidazole can cause some minor but unpleasant side effects, but is believed to be the most effective treatment. The gels do not typically cause side effects, although yeast vaginitis can occur as a side effect of the medication. vaginal
 clindamycin cream (
 Cleocin ) tinidazole (Tindamax) is an antibiotic that appears to be effective in treating bacterial vaginosis, and may have fewer side effects than metronidazole. Recurrence of bacterial vaginosis is possible even after successful treatment. More than half of those treated experience recurrent symptoms within 12 months. It is unclear why so many recurrent infections develop. With recurrent symptoms, a second course of antibiotics is generally prescribed. Treatment of bacterial vaginosis in pregnant women is recommended to decrease the risk of pregnancy-associated complications related to infection. Treatment prior to Cesarean delivery, total abdominal hysterectomy, and insertion of an IUD is also recommended by most experts. 
TREATMENT:  How is it treated during pregnancy? While up to 1/3 of cases of bacterial vaginosis may resolve on their own, it is recommended that medical treatment be given if symptoms are present or during pregnancy to avoid the development of complications. Bacterial vaginosis may recur even after successful treatment. More than half of those treated experience recurrent symptoms within 12 months. It is unclear why so many recurrences develop. With recurrent symptoms, a second course of antibiotics is generally prescribed. Recurrent bacterial vaginosis may develop in the same woman after she has been treated so it is important to see a doctor if symptoms persist or recur. Up to 50% of women who are treated will develop a recurrence of symptoms in the year following treatment. Treatment of bacterial vaginosis in pregnant women is recommended to decrease the risk of pregnancy-associated complications related to infection. Treatment prior to Cesarean delivery, total abdominal
 hysterectomy , and insertion of an
 IUD is also recommended by most experts. A return visit to your doctor is recommended if the your symptoms do not resolve after treatment with antibiotics or if symptoms return. What are the complications of bacterial vaginosis (BV)? Bacterial vaginosis can resolve completely without complications after treatment. No special follow-up is necessary if the symptoms disappear. Women with bacterial vaginosis are at increased risk for contracting
 HIV infection as well as other STDs including
 genital herpes , gonorrhea, and Chlamydia. In pregnancy, bacterial vaginosis has been linked to premature
 labor , but the exact relationship is still not clear. BV has also been linked to miscarriages and other problems, so treatment during pregnancy is advised. Can bacterial vaginosis (BV) be prevented? Because the cause and development of bacterial vaginosis is poorly understood, it can be difficult to take measures to prevent it from occurring. Reducing certain risk factors, such as limiting the number of sex partners, avoiding the use of vaginal douches, and taking all medications as directed when being treated for bacterial vaginosis, can help reduce a woman&amp;#39;s risk of developing bacterial vaginosis, and help reduce a woman&amp;#39;s risk of developing bacterial vaginosis. Which types of doctor treats bacterial vaginosis? Bacterial vaginosis is typically managed by a gynecologist. It can also be treated by primary care providers such as family practitioners, internal medicine doctors, and pediatricians.</first>
</file1>