<file1>
<first>Varicose Veins and Spider Veins

ABOUT: Veins carry blood low in oxygen content from the body to the
 lungs and heart. Varicose veins can lead to aching or even ulceration of the legs. Varicose veins can be caused be weakened valves in the veins or weakened walls of the veins, or by inflammation in the veins (
 phlebitis ). Varicose veins and
 spider veins are not dangerous (with rare exceptions). Interventions and treatments such as surgery, "ablation" by laser, radiofrequency or other technology is necessary in settings where veins cause significant symptoms that do not respond to non-interventional treatment. Treatments available for venous disease include surgery and
 sclerotherapy , among other techniques. What are veins and what is their function? Veins are blood vessels that return blood from all the organs in the body 
toward the heart. When the different organs use oxygen from the blood to perform 
their functions, they release the used blood containing waste products (such as 
carbon dioxide) into the veins. Blood in the veins is then transported to the 
heart and returned to the lungs, where the waste carbon dioxide is released and 
more oxygen is loaded by the blood and taken back to the rest of the body by the 
arteries. Veins also act as a storage for unused blood. When the body is at rest, only 
a portion of the available blood in the body circulates. The rest of the blood 
remains inactive in the veins and enters the active circulation when the body 
becomes more active and needs the additional blood to carry oxygen to the entire 
body. This storing capacity is due to the elasticity (flexibility to expand) of 
the walls of the veins. Veins have different sizes that depends their location and function. The 
largest veins are in the center of the body; these collect the blood from all 
the other smaller veins and channel it into the heart. The branches of these 
large veins get smaller and smaller as they move away from the center of the 
body. The veins closer to the skin surface are called superficial veins. The 
veins that are deeper and closer to the center of the body are called deep 
veins. There are also other veins that connect the superficial veins to the deep 
veins, and these are called perforating veins. What are varicose veins and spider veins? Veins can bulge with pools of blood when they fail to circulate the blood 
properly. These visible and bulging veins, called varicose veins, are more 
common in the legs and thighs, but can develop anywhere in the body. Large varicose veins can be visible, bulging, palpable (can be felt by 
touching), long, and dilated (greater than 4 millimeters in diameter). Small 
"spider veins" also can appear on the skin's surface. These may look like short, 
fine lines, "starburst" clusters, or a web-like maze. They are typically not 
palpable.
 Spider veins are most common in the thighs, ankles, and
 feet . They may 
also appear on the face. The medical term for spider veins is
 telangiectasias . Varicose vein and spider vein pictures Who gets varicose and spider veins? Varicose and spider veins can occur in men or women of any age, but most 
frequently affect women in the childbearing years and older people. Varicose 
veins are very common. Some estimates suggest that about 10% to 15% of men and 
most older women who have varicose or spider veins. A family history of varicose veins and older age increase one's tendency to develop 
varicose and spider veins. Other risk factors include: a sedentary lifestyle, weight gain , prolonged standing, and pregnancy . 
CAUSES:  The causes of varicose and spider veins are not entirely understood. In some instances, the absence or
 weakness of valves in the veins may cause poor venous circulation (blood flow in the veins) and lead to varicose veins. Valves inside veins normally act to ensure that blood in the veins does not flow in a backward direction (retrograde) away from the large (deep) veins and the heart. They are mainly located in perforating veins and some deep veins. In other cases, weaknesses in the vein walls may cause pooling of the blood. The walls of the blood vessels can become weaker and less competent than normal, causing the volume of blood in the veins to increase, thus leading to varicose veins. Less commonly, varicose veins are caused by such diseases as: phlebitis (inflammation of the veins), blood clots or any obstruction to blood flow in the veins, or congenital abnormalities of the veins. Venous disease (disease of the veins) is generally progressive and may not be prevented entirely. However, in some cases, wearing support hosiery, maintaining a normal weight, and regular
 exercise may be beneficial.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Many people with varicose veins do not have any physical symptoms. They may, however, have concerns over the cosmetic appearance of the varicose veins. Symptoms of varicose veins may include: aching, cramping, itching , swelling, and fatigue . Some people may complain of a dull ache and pressure sensation from varicose veins. Some less common, but more severe symptoms of varicose veins may include bleeding,
 thrombophlebitis (formation of a
 blood clot within the
 varicose vein ), skin ulceration and a weeping oozing
 dermatitis or stasis dermatitis. In long standing venous disease, the skin may become fibrotic and scarred, forming an inverted "hourglass" appearance. These complications of varicose veins should be evaluated by a doctor promptly. How are varicose veins evaluated (diagnosed)? Evaluation of varicose veins includes a thorough general physical examination 
by a doctor. This will include asking about any family history of varicose veins, 
the duration and presence of any symptoms, and any worsening or expansion of the 
varicose veins. The individual's height, weight, and other medical conditions 
need to be noted as well. In addition, general inspection and palpation (feeling the veins) and evaluation for 
the presence of any bleeding or ulceration also is typically performed. Standing up for about 5 to 10 minutes can make the veins more visible, and 
this may further aid the doctor in assessing the extent of the varicose veins. Duplex
 ultrasound visualization is very useful in evaluating of the venous system. 
Ultrasound can help in delineating the presence of any defective veins and 
pinpoint those that require intervention.
Doppler ultrasound (a device which can detect and measure blood flow) may also provide 
additional information such as the competency of and flow through the valves in 
the perforating and the deeper veins. This information is especially necessary if surgery or other procedures are being considered.
 
TREATMENT:  There are many different treatments available for varicose veins. These treatments vary based upon the size and location of the varicose veins, the presence of symptoms, and in cases of accompanying skin changes (for example, swelling, dermatitis or ulceration, for example). Briefly, potential treatments may include: leg elevation while sitting or sleeping, compression dressings with single or multilayered systems, compression stockings, sclerotherapy (injection of a liquid or foam into the vein to form a clot and permanently destroy the vessel), ablation (destruction) of abnormal veins with techniques using laser, radiofrequency or other modalities surgery (removal of the varicose veins, including "phlebectomy" or vein stripping). In general, sclerotherapy and laser therapy are helpful in treating spider veins (telangiectasias), while ablation and surgery may be a better option for larger varicose veins. No, not if varicose and spider veins are primarily a cosmetic problem. But severe cases that do not respond to compression therapy, especially those associated with ulcers and dermatitis, generally require further treatment. Thousands of people every year consider getting treatment for varicose veins and spider veins. Advertisements for treating venous disease often tout "unique," "permanent," "painless," or "absolutely safe" methods, thus making it difficult for individuals make a decision on the best treatment option. If you are uncertain about the safety or effectiveness of any treatment check with a health care professional. How can compression stockings help with varicose veins? Compression stockings work simply by squeezing the leg, thereby reducing the amount of blood and pressure in the veins. There are various brands, styles, and colors of stockings available. The degree of pressure applied around the leg should be guided by 
a health care professional.  Ideally, they should be fitted when the leg is not swollen, and they can be made-to-order for each patient.  Older or
 obese individuals often have difficulty putting on the stockings, which must be worn when the patient is standing. These stockings typically lose some degree of the compression over time  so they may need to be replaced regularly.
 What is sclerotherapy? "Sclerotherapy" involves using a fine needle to inject a substance directly into the vein. This solution irritates the lining of the vein, causing the vein to swell and the blood to clot. The vein then turns into
 scar tissue that may eventually fade from view. Sclerotherapy is typically used for spider veins and varicose veins. Veins up to 15 millimeters in diameter have been treated successfully. This is generally offered to patients who have tried compression stockings and leg elevation without much success.
Today, the substances most commonly used in the United States for sclerotherapy are hypertonic saline and sodium tetradecyl sulfate (Sotradecol), and  polidocanol (Aethoxysklerol, Asclera) is now also approved in the U.S. for sclerotherapy. With sclerotherapy, after the solution is injected, the vein's surrounding 
tissue is generally wrapped in compression bandages for several days, causing 
the vein walls to stick together. Patients whose legs have been treated are put 
on
 walking regimens, which forces the blood to flow into other veins and 
prevents the development of blood clots. This method and variations of it have 
been used since the 1920's. In most cases, more than one treatment session will 
be required. Pictures of sclerotherapytreatment Below are pictures of varicose vein and spider vein treatment. 
COMPLCATIONS:  In some patients treated with sclerotherapy, dark discoloration of the injected area may occur (
 hyperpigmentation ). This usually happens because of disintegration of the
 red blood cells in the treated blood vessel. In the majority of cases, this discoloration will completely go away within 6 months. Another potential problem is the formation of new spider veins near the area that was treated with sclerotherapy. This can happen in some patients, but these new vessels also typically disappear within 6 months. Rare complications may include the formation of an ulcer around the injection site or the formation of small blood clots in the small surface veins (superficial thrombophlebitis). Sclerotherapy is generally safe for most people for the treatment of varicose and spider veins. However, in certain groups of people, such as those individuals who are unable to walk (non-ambulatory), sclerotherapy should be avoided. Other contraindications for undergoing sclerotherapy include
 obesity , blood clots in the deeper veins,
 allergy to the sclerosing agent, pregnancy, and arterial obstruction (blocked blood flow in the artery near the varicose vein).
 
TREATMENT:  Varicose veins are frequently treated by surgically eliminating the "bad" veins. This 
forces the blood to flow through the remaining healthy veins. In vein stripping 
surgery, the problematic veins are "stripped" out by passing a flexible device 
through the vein and removing it through an incision near the groin. Smaller 
tributaries of these veins also are stripped with this device or removed through 
a series of small incisions. Those veins that connect to the deeper veins are 
then tied off. This stripping method has been used since the 1950's. This is now 
usually performed using outpatient surgical procedures and rarely requires 
general anesthesia. Spider veins cannot be removed through surgery. Sometimes, they disappear 
when the larger varicose veins feeding the spider veins are removed. The remaining 
spider veins also can be treated with sclerotherapy. For all of these procedures, the amount of
 pain an individual feels will 
vary, depending on the person's general tolerance for
 pain , how extensive the 
treatments are, which parts of the body are treated, whether complications 
arise, and other factors. Because surgery is performed under anesthesia, pain is 
not felt during the procedure. After the anesthesia wears off, there can be some 
pain at or near the incision(s). For sclerotherapy, the degree of pain will also depend on the size of the 
needle used and which solution is injected. Most people find hypertonic saline 
to be the most painful solution and experience a burning and cramping sensation 
for several minutes when it is injected. Some doctors mix a mild local anesthetic with the saline solution to minimize the pain.
 Can laser be used to treat varicose and spider veins? Spider veins and small varicose veins can be treated with laser treatment applied from the surface of the skin. The laser applies an intense energy that essentially destroys the small blood vessels in the surface of the skin. Results are variable, and multiple treatments may be necessary to have some benefit. This procedure is generally less invasive than sclerotherapy and vein stripping (no insertion of needles or catheters is required). A possible problem that may arise after laser treatment is a temporary discoloration of the skin. Larger varicose veins may be treated with endovenous (inside the vein) catheter ablation or laser surgery. This basically involves inserting a probe (or catheter) into a large vein in the lower leg (saphenous vein) and closing the vein by applying heat generated through laser. This technique has proven to be less painful, and it also has a faster recovery time compared to vein stripping surgery. 
TREATMENT:  Doctors who provide surgical treatments (vein stripping and laser ablation) include general and vascular surgeons. Sclerotherapy and laser treatment are often performed by dermatologists, though some general, vascular, and
 plastic surgeons also perform sclerotherapy treatment. 
Individuals may want to consult more than one health care practitioner prior to 
making a decision on a method of treatment. Be sure to ask the health care 
professional about his or her experience in performing the procedure you want. 
TREATMENT:  Patients should consult their doctor about the safety and potential side effects of each type of treatment. Thoroughly review any "informed consent" forms the doctor gives you explaining the risks of a procedure. For surgical removal of veins, potential side effects include those for any surgery performed under anesthesia, including
 nausea ,
 vomiting , as well as the risk of post-operative
 wound infection. Surgery may also result in scarring where small incisions are made, and the formation of blood clots is a potential complication as well. For sclerotherapy, the side effects can depend on the substance used for the injection. People with
 allergies may want to be cautious. For example, sodium tetradecyl sulfate (Sotradecol) may cause
 allergic reactions, which can occasionally be severe. Hypertonic saline solution is unlikely to cause allergic reactions. Either substance may burn the skin (if the needle is not properly inserted) or permanently mark or "stain" the skin (these brownish marks are caused by the scattering of blood cells throughout the tissue after the vein has been injected and may fade over time). Occasionally, sclerotherapy can lead to the formation of blood clots. Laser treatments can cause scarring and changes in the color of the skin.
 The most worrisome complication of all these treatments is formation of blood clots, which may require further treatments, including blood thinners or other treatment, and have a very low risk of causing death. Many factors will affect the rate at which treated varicose veins recur. These include the underlying diagnosis, the method used and its suitability for treating the particular condition, and the skill of the physician. Sometimes the body forms a new vein in place of the one removed by a surgeon. An injected vein that was not completely destroyed by sclerotherapy may reopen, or a new vein may appear in the same location as the previous one. Many studies have found that varicose veins are more likely to recur following sclerotherapy than following surgery. However, no treatment method has been scientifically established as being free from recurrences. For all types of procedures, recurrence rates increase with time. Also, because venous (vein) disease is typically progressive, no treatment can prevent the appearance of new varicose or spider veins in the future. Is one treatment for varicose veins or spider veins better than the other? The method you select for treating venous disease should be based on the physician&amp;#39;s diagnosis, the size of the veins to be treated and the patient&amp;#39;s: treatment history, age, history of
 allergies , and ability to tolerate surgery and anesthesia, among other factors. As noted above, small spider veins cannot be surgically removed and can only be treated with sclerotherapy. On the other hand, larger varicose veins may, according to many studies, be more likely to recur if treated with sclerotherapy.
 
PREVENTION:  Prevention of varicose veins may be accomplished by periodic leg elevation, avoidance of prolonged standing, and wearing elastic support hose. Regular
 exercise and control of weight can also be beneficial. These measures can prevent or slow down the progression of varicose veins.
</first>
</file1>