<file1>
<first>Balance Disorders
What is a balance disorder? A balance disorder is a condition that makes you feel unsteady or 
 dizzy, 
 as if you are moving, spinning, or floating, even though you are standing 
 still or lying down.
 Balance disorders can be caused by certain health 
 conditions, medications, or a problem in the inner ear or the brain. Our sense of balance is primarily controlled by a maze-like structure in 
 our inner ear called the
 labyrinth , which is made of bone and soft tissue. 
 At one end of the labyrinth is an intricate system of loops and pouches 
 called the semicircular canals and the otolithic organs, which help us 
 maintain our balance. At the other end is a snail-shaped organ called the 
 cochlea, which enables us to hear. The medical term for all of the parts of 
 the inner ear involved with balance is the
 vestibular system . How does the vestibular system work? Our
 vestibular system works with other sensorimotor systems in the body, 
 such as our visual system (eyes) and skeletal system (bones and joints), to 
 check and maintain the position of our body at rest or in motion. It also 
 helps us maintain a steady focus on objects even though the position of our 
 body changes. The vestibular system does this by detecting mechanical 
 forces, including gravity, that act upon our vestibular organs when we move. 
 Two sections of the labyrinth help us accomplish these tasks: the 
 semicircular canals and the otolithic organs. The semicircular canals are three fluid-filled loops arranged roughly at 
 right angles to each other. They tell the brain when our head moves in a 
 rotating or circular way, such as when we nod our head up and down or look 
 from right to left. Each semicircular canal has a plump base, which contains a 
 raindrop-shaped structure filled with a gel-like substance. 
 This structure, called the cupula, sits on top of a cluster of sensory 
 cells, called hair cells. The hair cells have long threadlike extensions, 
 called stereocilia, that extend into the gel. When the head moves, fluid 
 inside the semicircular canal moves. This motion causes the cupula to bend 
 and the stereocilia within it to tilt to one side. The tilting action 
 creates a signal that travels to the brain to tell it the movement and 
 position of your head. Between the semicircular canals and the cochlea lie the otolithic organs, 
 which are two fluid-filled pouches called the utricle and the saccule. These 
 organs tell the brain when our body is moving in a straight line, such as 
 when we stand up or ride in a car or on a bike. They also tell the brain the 
 position of our head with respect to gravity, such as whether we are sitting 
 up, leaning back, or lying down. Like the semicircular canals, the utricle and the saccule have sensory 
 hair cells. These hair cells line the bottom of each pouch, and their 
 stereocilia extend into an overlying gel-like layer. On top of the gel are 
 tiny grains made of
 calcium carbonate called otoconia. When you tilt your 
 head, gravity pulls on the grains, which then move the stereocilia. As with 
 the semicircular canals, this movement creates a signal that tells the brain 
 the head's position. Our visual system works with our vestibular system to keep objects from 
 blurring when our head moves and to keep us aware of our position when we 
 walk or when we ride in a vehicle. Sensory receptors in our joints and 
 muscles also help us maintain our balance when we stand still or walk. The 
 brain receives, interprets, and processes the information from these systems 
 to control our balance. Figure 1. Diagram of outer, middle, and inner ear. The
 outer ear is labeled
in the figure and includes the ear canal. The
 middle ear includes the eardrum
(tympanic membrane) and three tiny bones for
 hearing . The bones are called the
hammer (malleus), anvil (incus), and stirrup (stapes) to reflect their shapes.
The middle ear connects to the back of the throat by the Eustachian tube. The
inner ear (labyrinth) contains the semicircular canals and vestibule for
balance, and the cochlea for hearing. The vestibular structures of the inner ear are the vestibule (which is made
up of the utricle and saccule) and the three semicircular canals. These
structures work somewhat like a carpenter's level (a tool used to show how "level"
a horizontal or vertical surface is). That is, they work by way of the
vestibulocochlear nerve with the vestibular center in the brain to deal with
body balance and position. (The rest of the inner ear, that is, the cochlea, is
concerned with hearing.) Thus, the vestibular
 system includes the vestibule, the
semicircular canals, the vestibular branch of the vestibulocochlear nerve, and
the vestibular center in the brain. The vestibular system measures linear and rotational movement. A number of
disorders can cause this system to stop working or provide inappropriate
information. These disorders include 
Ménière syndrome,
 labyrinthitis , 
benign
paroxysmal positional
 vertigo , 
ear infections, 
tumors, or
 trauma . Each of these
conditions is discussed below.
 
SYMPTOMS:  If your balance is impaired, you may feel as if the room is spinning. You 
 may stagger when you try to walk or teeter or fall when you try to stand up. 
 Some of the symptoms you might experience are: Dizziness or
 vertigo (a spinning sensation) Falling or feeling as if you are going to fall Lightheadedness , faintness, or a floating sensation Blurred vision Confusion or disorientation Other symptoms are
 nausea and
 vomiting ,
 diarrhea , changes in heart rate 
 and
 blood pressure , and fear,
 anxiety , or 
 panic. Some people also feel 
 tired,
 depressed , or unable to concentrate. Symptoms may come and go over 
 short time periods or last for longer periods of time. 
CAUSES:  A balance disorder may be caused by viral or
 bacterial infections in the 
 ear, a
 head injury , or blood circulation disorders that affect the inner ear 
 or brain. Many people experience problems with their sense of balance as 
 they get older. Balance problems and
 dizziness also can result from taking 
 certain medications. In addition, problems in the visual and skeletal systems and the nervous 
 and circulatory systems can be the source of some posture and balance 
 problems. A circulatory system disorder, such as
 low blood pressure , can 
 lead to a feeling of dizziness when we suddenly stand up. Problems in the 
 skeletal or visual systems, such as
 arthritis or eye muscle imbalance, also 
 may cause balance problems. However, many
 balance disorders can begin all of 
 a sudden and with no obvious cause.
 What are some types of balance disorders? There are more than a dozen different balance disorders. Some of the most 
 common are: Benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV) or positional
 vertigo is a 
 brief, intense episode of
 vertigo that occurs because of a specific change 
 in the position of the head. If you have BPPV, you might feel as if you're 
 spinning when you look for an object on a high or low shelf or turn your 
 head to look over your shoulder (such as when you back up your car). You 
 also may experience BPPV when you roll over in bed. BPPV is caused when 
 otoconia tumble from the utricle into one of the semicircular canals and 
 weigh on the cupula. The cupula can't tilt properly and sends conflicting 
 messages to the brain about the position of the head, causing vertigo. BPPV 
 sometimes may result from a head injury or just from getting older. Labyrinthitis is an infection or inflammation of the inner ear that 
 causes dizziness and loss of balance. It frequently is associated with an 
 upper respiratory infection such as the
 flu . Ménière's disease is associated with a change in fluid volume within 
 parts of the labyrinth. Ménière's disease causes episodes of vertigo, 
 irregular
 hearing loss ,
 tinnitus (a 
 ringing or
 buzzing in the ear ), and a feeling of fullness in the ear. The 
 cause of this disease is unknown. Vestibular neuronitis is an inflammation of the vestibular nerve and may 
 be caused by a virus. Its primary symptom is vertigo. Perilymph fistula is a leakage of inner ear fluid into the middle ear. It 
 can occur after a head injury, drastic changes in atmospheric pressure (such 
 as when scuba diving), physical exertion, ear surgery, or 
 chronic ear 
 infections. Its most notable symptom, besides dizziness and
 nausea , is 
 unsteadiness when
 walking or standing that increases with activity and 
 decreases with rest. Some
 babies may be born with perilymph fistula, usually 
 in association with
 hearing loss that is present at birth. Mal de debarquement syndrome (MdDS) is a balance disorder in which you 
 feel as if you're continuously rocking or bobbing. It generally happens 
 after an ocean cruise or other sea travel. Usually, the symptoms will go 
 away in a matter of hours or days after you reach land. However, severe 
 cases can last months or even years.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Diagnosis of a balance disorder is difficult. There are many potential 
 causes - including medical conditions and medications. To help evaluate a balance problem, your doctor may suggest you see an 
 otolaryngologist. An otolaryngologist is a physician and surgeon who 
 specializes in the ear, nose, and throat. An otolaryngologist may request 
 tests to assess the cause and extent of the balance problem depending on 
 your symptoms and health status. The otolaryngologist may request a hearing examination, blood tests, an 
 electronystagmogram (which measures eye movements and the muscles that 
 control them), or imaging studies of your head and brain. Another possible 
 test is called posturography. For this test, you stand on a special movable 
 platform in front of a patterned screen. The doctor measures how your body 
 moves in response to movement of the platform, the patterned screen, or 
 both. How is a balance disorder treated? The first thing a doctor will do to treat a balance disorder is determine 
 if your dizziness is caused by a medical condition or medication. If it is, 
 your doctor will treat the condition or suggest a different medication. Your doctor also may describe ways for you to handle daily activities 
 that increase the risk of falling and injury, such as driving, walking up or 
 down stairs, and using the bathroom. If you have BPPV, your doctor might 
 prescribe a series of simple movements, called the Epley maneuver, to help 
 dislodge the otoconia from the semicircular canal. You begin the Epley 
 maneuver by sitting upright, with the help of a trained therapist, then 
 quickly lie down on your back, turn your head to one side, and wait for a 
 minute or two before sitting back up again (see Figure 3). For some people, 
 one session will be all that is needed. Others might need to repeat the 
 procedure several times at home to relieve their dizziness. If you are diagnosed with Ménière's disease, your doctor may recommend 
 changes in your
 diet , such as reducing the use of salt in your food and 
 limiting alcohol and
 caffeine . Not
 smoking also may help. Some anti-vertigo 
 or
 anti-nausea medications may relieve your symptoms, but they can also make 
 you drowsy. Other medications, such as the antibiotic gentamicin or
 corticosteroids , may be injected behind the eardrum to reach the inner ear. 
 Although gentamicin helps reduce dizziness, it occasionally destroys sensory 
 cells in the cochlea and causes permanent hearing loss. The risk of hearing 
 loss can be lowered if small doses of gentamicin are given off and on until 
 your symptoms decrease. Corticosteroids don't cause hearing loss; however, 
 research is underway to determine if they are as effective as gentamicin. 
 Surgery on the vestibular organ may be necessary if you have a severe case 
 of Ménière's disease. Some people with a balance disorder may not be able to fully relieve 
 their dizziness and will have to develop ways to cope with it on a daily 
 basis. A vestibular rehabilitation therapist can help by developing an 
 individualized treatment plan that combines head, body, and eye exercises to 
 decrease dizziness and nausea. To reduce your risk of injury from dizziness, avoid walking in the dark. 
 You also should wear low-heeled shoes or walking shoes outdoors and use a 
 cane or walker if necessary. If you have handrails in the home, inspect them 
 periodically to make sure they are safe and secure. Modifications to 
 bathroom fixtures can make them safer. Conditions at work may need to be 
 modified or restricted, at least temporarily. Driving a car may be 
 especially hazardous. Ask your doctor's opinion about whether it's safe for 
 you to drive.
 How do I know if I have a balance disorder? Everyone has a dizzy spell now and then, but the term “dizziness” may 
 mean something different to different people. For some people, dizziness 
 might be a fleeting sensation of spinning, while for others it's intense and 
 lasts a long time. Experts believe that more than four out of 10 Americans 
 will experience an episode of dizziness significant enough to send them to a 
 doctor. To help you decide whether or not you should seek medical help for a 
 dizzy spell, ask yourself the following questions. If you answer “yes” to 
 any of these questions, talk to your doctor. Do I feel unsteady? Do I feel as if the room is spinning around me? Do I feel as if I'm moving when I know I'm sitting or standing still? Do I lose my balance and fall? Do I feel as if I'm falling? Do I feel “lightheaded” or as if I might faint? Do I have blurred vision? Do I ever feel disoriented, such as losing my sense of time or where I 
 am? 
DIAGNOSIS:  You can help your doctor make a diagnosis and determine a treatment plan 
 by answering the questions below. Be prepared to discuss this information 
 during your appointment. 1. The best way I can describe my dizziness or balance problem is: 2. How often do I feel dizzy or have trouble keeping my balance? 3. Have I ever fallen? (When did I fall?) Under what conditions did I fall? How often have I fallen? 4. These are the medicines I take: (Include prescription medications and over-the-counter medicine, such as
 aspirin ,
 antihistamines , or
 sleep aids .) Name of medicine: How much (milligrams) and how often (times) per day: The condition I take this medicine for is: Name of medicine: How much (milligrams) and how often (times) per day: The condition I take this medicine for is: Name of medicine: How much (milligrams) and how often (times) per day: The condition I take this medicine for is: At your appointment, take a minute to write down any instructions your 
 doctor has given you. Be sure to ask any questions you have before you leave 
 the office.
 What research is being done for balance disorders? BPPV is the most common balance disorder. Because the source of the 
 problem—displaced otoconia—is located deep within the ear, doctors have had 
 to rely mainly on observation and a medical history to make a diagnosis. 
 Researchers supported by the National Institute on Deafness and Other 
 Communication Disorders (NIDCD) now have created a head-mounted apparatus 
 that uses 3-D animation to map the location of otoconia in the inner ear. 
 The apparatus is built around a pair of infrared video goggles that gather 
 data from eye and head movements and then sends it to a computer program for 
 mapping. A second computer program uses the data to develop a step-by-step 
 guide for repositioning maneuvers to dislodge the otoconia from the 
 semicircular canals. If shown to be effective in
 clinical trials , the 
 apparatus and its software programs will help doctors more accurately 
 diagnose BPPV and guide repositioning maneuvers to ensure the best possible 
 treatment. Other NIDCD-supported scientists are looking at the molecular mechanisms 
 that regulate the development of the inner ear. One research team has 
 identified a gene that encodes a protein that helps in the formation of the 
 semicircular canals and their related sensory tissue. Another team has 
 identified a family of genes, called the otopetrins, which help form 
 otoconia in mice. Findings from the mouse study could help researchers 
 determine if otoconia destroyed by
 aging , medications, infections, or trauma 
 can someday be regenerated in humans with balance problems. NIDCD-supported scientists also are experimenting with several types of 
 vestibular prostheses, or replacement parts, in balance-impaired animals. 
 Researchers hope these devices will one day be used to compensate for 
 vestibular system loss in people. One prosthesis uses a head-mounted motion sensor to mimic the ear and 
 brain's natural signaling system. The sensor measures the head's rotation 
 and sends the information to a microprocessor. The microprocessor then 
 converts the signals into electrical impulses and sends them to an electrode 
 implanted in the ear. The electrode stimulates the vestibular nerve, 
 creating a signal that helps the brain move the eyes to compensate for the 
 head's rotation. A second prosthesis is designed to simulate the movement of fluid within 
 the semicircular canal. In a normal ear, fluid changes help the brain 
 understand the movement and position of the head. The device combines 
 microcontroller circuitry with a tiny mechanical device that increases 
 normal fluid movement to provide a stronger vestibular signal to the brain. Researchers also are studying the effectiveness of different types of 
 rehabilitative exercises as a treatment option for balance disorders. In one 
 NIDCD-funded study, researchers have used virtual reality technology to 
 simulate the aisles of a grocery store. Using a real cart attached to a 
 custom-built treadmill in front of a projection screen, patients “walk” down 
 aisles, scanning virtual store shelves for items on their list. Researchers 
 are testing whether practicing in the virtual store will lessen episodes of 
 dizziness in the real world, especially in visually complex environments.
</first>
</file1>