<file1>
<first>Erectile Dysfunction: Vacuum Constriction Devices
How Do Vacuum Constriction Devices Work? To use a vacuum constriction device: Place the pump, which can be pumped by hand or run on batteries, over the penis. Pump the air out of the cylinder so that a vacuum is created. The vacuum draws blood into the shaft of the penis and causes it to swell and become erect. Once the penis is erect, with the help of lubricant, slide the retaining band down onto the lower end of the penis. Remove the pump after releasing the vacuum. Intercourse can be attempted with the constriction band in place to help
maintain the erection. The band can be left on safely for up to 30 minutes to
allow for successful intercourse. Be sure that devices brought without a prescription contains a "quick release" feature, as there have been reports of penile injuries due to devices that did not release its vacuum on-demand or released it too slowly. How Well Do Vacuum Constriction Devices Work? Studies suggest that about 50%-80% of men are satisfied with the results of
VCDs. As with any other method of treatment for
 erectile dysfunction (
 ED ),
satisfaction rates may decrease with time. Who Should Consider Using a Vacuum Constriction 
Device? Vacuum constriction devices are safe and can be used by patients with
 ED caused by many conditions, including: Poor blood flow to the penis Diabetes Surgery for prostate or
 colon cancer Psychological issues such as
 anxiety or
 depression Vacuum constriction devices should not be used by men who may have a
significant congenital
 bleeding disorder or a disorder that predisposes them to
a condition called
 priapism (a prolonged, sometime painful erection lasting
over several hours). Examples include
 sickle cell anemia , some forms of
 leukemia , and other blood conditions.
 What Are the Side Effects of Vacuum Constriction Devices? An erection obtained by the vacuum constriction device is not the same as an
erection achieved naturally. The penis tends to be purplish in color and can be
 cold or numb. Other side effects can include: A black and blue mark or small area of 
bruising on the shaft of the penis.
This is usually painless and generally will resolve in a few days. Decrease in the force of the ejaculation. The constriction band traps the
ejaculate or semen at the time of
 orgasm . This is not dangerous and usually
does not cause
 pain . The semen will usually dribble out once the constriction
band is removed. Generally, this does not interfere with the pleasure of a
climax or orgasm. How Much Does a Vacuum Constriction Device Cost? Vacuum constriction devices vary in cost from $300 to $500, depending on the
brand and type. The battery-powered versions tend to be more expensive, but
also tend to work a little more quickly. Battery-powered devices are especially
helpful for men who do not have good hand strength or coordination or who have
 arthritis . There are several devices currently on the market that work effectively.
Some of these devices can be obtained without a prescription. Does Insurance Cover Vacuum Constriction Devices? Most insurance policies, including Medicare, cover at least part of the
costs of a vacuum constriction device, especially if a medical cause for
 ED has
been documented. Medicaid, however, does not cover the device except under extreme circumstances in certain states. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>