<file1>
<first>Hydrocephalus

ABOUT: *
ABOUT: medical author:  Melissa Conrad Stöppler, MD Hydrocephalus is a condition characterized by excessive accumulation of fluid in the brain. Hydrocephalus may be congenital or acquired. Communicating hydrocephalus occurs when cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) can still flow among the ventricles. Noncommunicating hydrocephalus, also called "obstructive" hydrocephalus, occurs when the flow of CSF is blocked. Hydrocephalus affects about 1 out of every 500 children. The most obvious indication of hydrocephalus in children and infants is often a rapid increase in head circumference or an unusually large head size. Other symptoms may include
 vomiting , sleepiness, irritability, downward deviation of the eyes (also called "sunsetting"), and
 seizures . Older children and adults may experience different symptoms because their skulls cannot expand to accommodate the buildup of CSF. Symptoms in older patients may include
 headache followed by
 vomiting ,
 nausea , papilledema (swelling of the optic disk which is part of the
 optic nerve ), blurred or
 double vision ,
 urinary incontinence , lethargy, drowsiness, irritability, or other changes in personality or cognition. The causes of hydrocephalus are poorly understood. Hydrocephalus is most often treated by surgically inserting a shunt system.
 What is hydrocephalus? The term hydrocephalus is derived from the Greek words "hydro" meaning water and "cephalus" meaning head. As the name implies, it is a condition in which the primary characteristic is excessive accumulation of fluid in the brain. Although hydrocephalus was once known as "water on the brain," the "water" is actually cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)--a clear fluid that surrounds the brain and spinal cord. The excessive accumulation of CSF results in an abnormal widening of   spaces in the brain called ventricles. This widening creates potentially harmful pressure on the tissues of the brain. The ventricular system is made up of four ventricles connected by narrow passages.. Normally, CSF flows through the ventricles, exits into cisterns (closed spaces that serve as reservoirs) at the base of the brain, bathes the surfaces of the brain and spinal cord, and then reabsorbs into the bloodstream. CSF has three important life-sustaining functions: 1) to keep the brain tissue buoyant, acting as a cushion or "
 shock absorber"; 2) to act as the vehicle for delivering nutrients to the brain and removing waste; and 3) to flow between the cranium and spine and compensate for changes in intracranial blood volume (the amount of blood within the brain). The balance between production and absorption of CSF is critically important. Because CSF is made continuously,  medical conditions that block its normal flow or absorption will result in an over-accumulation of CSF.  The resulting pressure of the fluid against brain tissue is what causes hydrocephalus. What are the different types of hydrocephalus? Hydrocephalus may be congenital or acquired. Congenital hydrocephalus is present at birth and may be caused by either events or influences that occur during
 fetal development , or genetic abnormalities. Acquired hydrocephalus develops at the time of birth or at some point afterward. This type of hydrocephalus can affect individuals of all ages and may be caused by injury or disease. Hydrocephalus may also be communicating or non-communicating. Communicating hydrocephalus occurs when the flow of CSF is blocked after it exits the ventricles. This form is called communicating because the CSF can still flow between the ventricles, which remain open. Non-communicating hydrocephalus - also called "obstructive" hydrocephalus - occurs when the flow of CSF is blocked along one or more of the narrow passages connecting the ventricles. One of the most common causes of hydrocephalus is "aqueductal stenosis." In this case, hydrocephalus results from a narrowing of the aqueduct of Sylvius, a small passage between the third and fourth ventricles in the middle of the brain. There are two other forms of hydrocephalus which do not fit exactly into the categories mentioned above and primarily affect adults: hydrocephalus ex-vacuo and normal pressure hydrocephalus. Hydrocephalus ex-vacuo occurs when
 stroke or traumatic injury cause damage to the brain. In these cases, brain tissue may actually shrink. Normal pressure hydrocephalus can happen to people at any age, but it is most common among the elderly. It may result from a subarachnoid hemorrhage, head
 trauma , infection,
 tumor , or complications of surgery. However, many people develop normal pressure hydrocephalus even when none of these factors are present for reasons that are unknown.
 Who gets this hydrocephalus? The number of people who develop hydrocephalus or who are currently living with it is difficult to establish since there is no national registry or database of people with the condition.  However, experts estimate that hydrocephalus affects approximately 1 in every 500 children. 
CAUSES:  The causes of hydrocephalus are still not   well understood. Hydrocephalus may result from   inherited genetic abnormalities (such as the genetic defect that causes aqueductal stenosis) or developmental disorders (such as those associated with
 neural tube defects including
 spina bifida and encephalocele). Other possible causes include complications of premature birth such as intraventricular hemorrhage, diseases such as
 meningitis , tumors, traumatic
 head injury , or subarachnoid hemorrhage, which block the exit of CSF from the ventricles to the cisterns or eliminate the passageway for CSF into the cisterns. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of hydrocephalus vary with age, disease progression, and individual differences in tolerance to the condition. For example, an infant's ability to compensate for increased CSF pressure and enlargement of the ventricles differs from an adult's. The infant skull can expand to accommodate the buildup of CSF because the
 sutures (the fibrous joints that connect the bones of the skull) have not yet closed. In infancy, the most obvious indication of hydrocephalus is often a rapid increase in head circumference or an unusually large head size. Other symptoms may include vomiting, sleepiness, irritability, downward deviation of the eyes (also called "sunsetting"), and
 seizures . Older children and adults may experience different symptoms because their skulls cannot expand to accommodate the buildup of CSF. Symptoms may include
 headache followed by vomiting,
 nausea , papilledema (swelling of the optic disk which is part of the optic nerve), blurred or
 double vision , sunsetting of the eyes, problems with balance, poor coordination, gait disturbance, urinary
 incontinence , slowing or loss of developmental progress, lethargy, drowsiness, irritability, or other changes in personality or cognition including
 memory loss . Symptoms of normal pressure hydrocephalus include, problems with
 walking , impaired bladder control leading to urinary frequency and/or incontinence, and progressive mental impairment and
 dementia . An individual with this type of hydrocephalus may have a general slowing of movements or may complain that his or her
 feet feel "stuck." Because some of these symptoms may also be experienced in other disorders such as
 Alzheimer's disease ,
 Parkinson's disease , and
 Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease , normal pressure hydrocephalus is often incorrectly diagnosed and never properly treated. Doctors may use a variety of tests, including brain scans (CT and/or
 MRI ), a
 spinal tap or
 lumbar catheter, intracranial pressure monitoring, and neuropsychological tests, to help them accurately diagnose normal pressure hydrocephalus and rule out any other conditions. The symptoms described in this section account for the most typical ways in which progressive hydrocephalus manifests itself, but it is important to remember that symptoms vary significantly from one person to the next.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Hydrocephalus is diagnosed through clinical neurological evaluation and by using cranial imaging techniques such as
 ultrasonography , computed tomography (CT),
 magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), or pressure-monitoring techniques. A physician selects the appropriate diagnostic tool based on an individual's age, clinical presentation, and the presence of known or suspected abnormalities of the brain or spinal cord. 
TREATMENT:  Hydrocephalus is most often treated by surgically inserting a shunt system. This system diverts the flow of CSF from the CNS to another area of the body where it can be absorbed as part of the normal circulatory process. A shunt is a flexible but sturdy
 plastic tube. A shunt system consists of the shunt, a catheter, and a valve. One end of the catheter is placed within a ventricle inside the brain or in the CSF outside the spinal cord. The other end of the catheter is commonly placed within the abdominal cavity, but may also be placed at other sites in the body such as a chamber of the heart or areas around the lung where the CSF can drain and be absorbed. A valve located along the catheter maintains one-way flow and regulates the rate of CSF flow. A limited number of individuals can be treated with an alternative procedure called third ventriculostomy. In this procedure, a neuroendoscope — a small camera that uses
 fiber optic technology to visualize small and difficult to reach surgical areas — allows a doctor to view the ventricular surface. Once the scope is guided into position, a small tool makes a tiny hole in the floor of the third ventricle, which allows the CSF to bypass the obstruction and flow toward the site of resorption around the surface of the brain. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Shunt systems are not perfect devices. Complications may include mechanical failure, infections, obstructions, and the need to lengthen or replace the catheter. Generally, shunt systems require monitoring and regular medical follow up. When complications occur,   the shunt system usually   requires some type of revision. Some complications can lead to other problems such as overdraining or underdraining. Overdraining occurs when the shunt allows CSF to drain from the ventricles more quickly than it is produced. Overdraining can cause the ventricles to collapse, tearing blood vessels and causing
 headache , hemorrhage (subdural
 hematoma ), or slit-like ventricles (slit ventricle syndrome). Underdraining occurs when CSF is not removed quickly enough and the symptoms of hydrocephalus recur. In addition to the common symptoms of hydrocephalus, infections from a shunt may also produce symptoms such as a low-grade
 fever , soreness of the neck or shoulder muscles, and redness or tenderness along the shunt tract. When there is reason to suspect that a shunt system is not functioning properly (for example, if the symptoms of hydrocephalus return), medical attention should be sought immediately.
 What is the prognosis for hydrocephalus? The prognosis for individuals diagnosed with hydrocephalus is difficult to predict, although there is some correlation between the specific cause of the hydrocephalus and the outcome. Prognosis is further complicated by the presence of associated disorders, the timeliness of diagnosis, and the success of treatment. The degree to which relief of CSF pressure following shunt surgery can minimize or reverse damage to the brain is not well understood. Affected individuals and their families should be aware that hydrocephalus poses risks to both cognitive and physical development. However, many children diagnosed with the disorder benefit from rehabilitation therapies and educational interventions and go on to lead normal lives with few limitations. Treatment by an interdisciplinary team of medical professionals, rehabilitation specialists, and educational experts is critical to a positive outcome. Left untreated, progressive hydrocephalus may be fatal. The symptoms of normal pressure hydrocephalus usually get worse over time if the condition is not treated, although some people may experience temporary improvements. While the success of treatment with shunts varies from person to person, some people recover almost completely after treatment and have a good quality of life. Early diagnosis and treatment improves the chance of a good recovery. What research is being done for hydrocephalus? The National Institute of Neurological Disorders and
 Stroke (NINDS) and other institutes of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) conduct research related to hydrocephalus in laboratories and clinics at the NIH and support additional research through grants to major medical institutions across the country.  Much of this research focuses on finding better ways to prevent, treat, and ultimately cure disorders such as hydrocephalus. The NINDS also conducts and supports a wide range of fundamental studies that explore the complex mechanisms of normal and abnormal brain development.
 Where can I get more information about hydrocephalus? For more information on neurological disorders or research programs funded by the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and
 Stroke , contact the Institute's Brain Resources and Information Network (BRAIN) at: BRAIN
 P.O. Box 5801
 Bethesda, MD 20824
 (800) 352-9424
 http://www.ninds.nih.gov Information also is available from the following organizations: Hydrocephalus Association
 870 Market Street
 Suite 705
 San Francisco, CA   94102
 [email protected] http://www.hydroassoc.org
 Tel: 415-732-7040 888-598-3789
 Fax: 415-732-7044 Hydrocephalus Support Group, Inc.
 P.O. Box 4236
 Chesterfield, MO   63006-4236
 [email protected] Tel: 636-532-8228
 Fax: 314-251-5871 National Hydrocephalus Foundation
 12413 Centralia Road
 Lakewood, CA   90715-1623
 [email protected] http://nhfonline.org
 Tel: 562-924-6666 888-857-3434
 Fax: 562-924-6666
</first>
</file1>