<file1>
<first>Extensively Drug-Resistant Tuberculosis (XDR TB)
What is 
XDR TB? Extensively drug-resistant
 tuberculosis (XDR
 TB ) is a relatively rare 
type of multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR TB). It is resistant to almost all
 drugs used to treat TB, including the two best first-line drugs:
 isoniazid and 
rifampin. XDR TB is also resistant to the best second-line medications: 
fluoroquinolones and at least one of three injectable drugs (i.e., amikacin, 
kanamycin, or capreomycin). How is XDR TB spread? Drug-susceptible (regular) TB and XDR TB are spread the 
same way. TB germs are put into the air when a person with TB disease of the
 lungs or throat
 coughs , sneezes, speaks, or sings. These germs can float in the 
air for several hours, depending on the environment. Persons who breathe in the 
air containing these TB germs can become infected. TB is not spread by shaking someone's hand sharing food or drink touching bed linens or toilet 
seats sharing toothbrushes kissing
 smoking or sharing cigarettes Why is XDR TB 
so serious? Because XDR TB is resistant to the most powerful first-line and 
second-line drugs, patients are left with treatment options that are much less 
effective and often have worse treatment outcomes. XDR TB is of special concern 
for persons with
 HIV infection or other conditions that can weaken the immune 
system. These persons are more likely to develop TB disease once they are 
infected, and also have a higher risk of death once they develop TB disease.
 
RISKS:  Drug-resistant TB (MDR or XDR) is more 
common in people who: Do not take their TB medicine regularly Do not take all of their TB medicines 
as told by their doctor or nurse Develop active TB disease again, after having 
taken TB medicine in the past Come from areas of the world where drug-resistant 
TB is common Have spent time with someone known to have drug-resistant 
PREVENTION:  Avoid close contact or 
prolonged time with known TB patients in crowded, enclosed environments like 
clinics, hospitals, prisons, or homeless shelters. Can the TB vaccine (BCG) help prevent XDR TB? There is a vaccine for TB 
disease called Bacille Calmette-Guerin (BCG). It is used in some countries to 
prevent severe forms of TB in children. However, BCG is not generally 
recommended in the United States because it has limited effectiveness for 
preventing TB in adults. The effect of BCG against XDR TB would likely be 
similar to the effect on drug-susceptible TB. If I have regular (drug-susceptible) TB, how can I prevent getting 
drug-resistant TB? The most important thing is for you to continue taking all 
your TB medicines exactly as prescribed. No doses should be missed and treatment 
should not be stopped early. You should tell your health care provider if you 
are having trouble taking the medications. If you plan to travel, make sure you 
have enough medicine to last while away.
 Can XDR TB be treated and cured? Yes, in some cases. Some TB control programs 
have shown that cure is possible for an estimated 30% of affected people. 
Successful outcomes depend greatly on the extent of the
 drug resistance , the 
severity of the disease, and whether the patient's immune system is weakened. 
SYMPTOMS:  The general symptoms of TB disease include 
feelings of sickness or
 weakness ,
 weight loss ,
 fever , and
 night sweats . The 
symptoms of TB disease of the lungs may also include
 coughing ,
 chest pain , and 
coughing up blood. Symptoms of TB disease in other parts of the body depend on 
the area affected. If you have these symptoms, you should contact your doctor or 
local health department. What should I do if I have been around someone who has XDR TB? If you think 
you have been exposed to someone with TB disease, you should contact your doctor 
or local health department about getting a TB skin test or the QuantiFERON®-TB 
Gold test (QFT-G), a blood test. And tell the doctor or nurse when you spent 
time with this person. How long does it take to find out if you have XDR TB? If TB bacteria are 
found in the sputum (phlegm), the diagnosis of TB can be made in a day or two, 
but this finding will not be able to distinguish between drug-susceptible 
(regular) TB and drug-resistant TB. To determine drug susceptibility, the 
bacteria need to be grown and tested in a laboratory. Final diagnosis for TB, 
and especially for XDR TB, may take from 6 to 16 weeks.
 Is XDR TB a problem in the United States? The risk of acquiring XDR TB in the 
United States appears to be relatively low. However, it is important to 
acknowledge the ease at which TB can spread. As long as XDR TB exists, the 
United States is at risk and must address the threat. How many cases of XDR TB have been reported in the United States? In the 
United States, 49 cases of XDR TB have been reported between 1993 and 2006. Is it safe to travel where cases of XDR TB have been reported? Although MDR 
and XDR TB are occurring globally, they are still rare.
 HIV -infected travelers 
are at greatest risk if they come in contact with a person with MDR or XDR TB. All travelers should avoid high risk settings where there are no infection 
control measures in place. Documented places where transmission has occurred 
include crowded hospitals, prisons, homeless shelters, and other settings where 
susceptible persons come in contact with persons with TB disease. Air travel itself carries a relatively low risk of infection with TB of any 
kind. 
PREVENTION:  Health care providers 
can help prevent MDR and XDR TB by quickly diagnosing cases, following 
recommended treatment guidelines, monitoring patients' response to treatment, 
and making sure therapy is completed. Providers should also ensure proper implementation of infection control 
procedures to prevent exposure to TB in hospitals or health-care settings where 
TB patients are likely to be seen.
 Are immigrants putting the U.S. at increased risk for TB? Persons applying to 
enter the U.S. with immigrant or refugee visas must complete a questionnaire 
about any symptoms of TB they may have and obtain a chest radiograph. If 
positive, the person submits sputum specimens for examination for TB bacteria. 
Persons identified as having infectious TB are not granted entry to the United 
States, until they have been treated. Why haven't we heard about XDR TB before now? For some years we have seen 
isolated cases of very highly resistant TB around the world that we would today 
call XDR TB. The drugs used to treat TB have been around a long time and drug 
resistance has taken many years to develop. Over time, countries have improved 
their laboratory capacity to test for drug resistance and their ability to track 
the number of cases. All of these factors have contributed to an increase in 
reporting of cases of drug-resistant TB. With more cases being identified, the 
problem was more closely examined, defined, and given a name. 
PREVENTION:  CDC is 
collaborating with other federal agencies and international partners to raise 
awareness and enhance strategies for TB
 prevention worldwide by Strengthening TB services for people living with
 HIV/AIDS Assembling outbreak 
response teams Improving access to TB drugs Developing international TB testing 
standards Building capacity of health care providers to diagnose and treat TB Reconvening the Federal TB Task Force Providing technical assistance to expand 
TB program capacity Supporting TB communication and education efforts SOURCE:
 Centers for Disease Control &amp; Prevention</first>
</file1>