<file1>
<first>Intrathecal Baclofen Pump Therapy for Multiple Sclerosis (MS)
What is multiple sclerosis (MS)? Multiple sclerosis (
 MS ) is a disease that causes
 demyelination of the brain 
and spinal cord, or a loss of the protective covering around nerve fibers called 
axons. When this occurs, the axons (the parts of the nerve cells that transmit 
impulses to other cells) don't work well. As more areas are affected by the loss 
of myelin, different symptoms develop. The specific symptoms seen in
 MS are related to 
the area of injury in the brain or spinal cord. Patients might experience or 
describe numbness, tingling, or
 weakness . The weakness might be mild or severe 
enough to cause
 paralysis of one side of the body. In some cases, patients may 
develop loss of control of their bladder or an inability to empty their bladder. 
As
 MS progresses, some patients are left with muscle
 spasticity , which is an 
involuntary painful contraction of some muscles. What is spasticity? Spasticity 
is a condition in which muscles are exhibiting almost constant contracture or 
activity, leading to loss of range of motion, decreased function, and even
 pain . 
Spasticity occurs after an area of the brain or spinal cord has been injured, 
leading to weakness and increased tone. When an arm or leg that is affected by 
spasticity is moved by a health-care professional, there is involuntary resistance to that 
movement. Often, this spasticity is made worse when the speed (or velocity) of 
the movement increases. Spasticity is often seen in association with a brain 
injury, such as after: a
 stroke , traumatic damage to the brain or spinal cord, or in cases of MS. What is baclofen, and what are its side effects? Baclofen is a medication that works in the brain to decrease uninhibited signals that 
start in an injured area of the brain and cause spasticity. By decreasing these 
signals, the affected muscle can relax somewhat, and the symptoms of spasticity 
can be reduced.
When taken in pill form baclofen can be effective, but can lead to side effects 
such as: sleepiness, dizziness , nausea , headache , 
 or confusion . These side 
effects can limit the amount of medication that can be used to decrease the 
symptoms of spasticity. However, the medication can also be injected around the 
spinal cord, directly into the cerebral spinal fluid. When used in this way, 
only small amounts of the medication are needed, and side effects may be 
reduced.
 How is an intrathecal baclofen pump used to treat multiple sclerosis (MS)? Baclofen 
can't treat MS itself. However, this medication can be effective 
in reducing the symptoms associated with severe spasticity caused by MS. Who is a good candidate for an intrathecal baclofen pump? There are 
various selection criteria used to determine if someone with MS is a candidate for an intrathecal baclofen pump.
 The primary consideration is the presence of spasticity 
that interferes with the individual&amp;#39;s daily activities or care. If someone 
with MS has primary weakness, 
then the intrathecal baclofen pump is not an option. Other considerations 
include limited response to oral baclofen or intolerable side effects at the 
doses that are required to control the spasticity as well as a good response to 
a screening test of intrathecal baclofen administered into the cerebrospinal 
fluid. Prior to implantation of the pump, there must not be any sign of 
infection. How does an intrathecal baclofen pump work? The pump 
is implanted under the skin and is connected to a catheter (tube) that ends in 
the spinal fluid. The specific area of placement of the tubing is dependent on 
each patient and their associated symptoms. The pump has a small reservoir where 
the medication (baclofen) is placed and is programmed to deliver a specific 
amount of medication on a regular basis to the cerebrospinal fluid. The exact 
amount of medication delivered is unique to each patient and can be adjusted 
based upon symptoms. The programming is initially performed each month after the 
pump is implanted; once a patient has reached a stable dose, then the pump is 
checked and refilled every two to three months. How can I expect to feel after having an intrathecal baclofen pump implanted? Implanting 
a pump is a surgical procedure, and many patients experience some soreness 
around the surgical site after the pump is implanted. The pump is typically 
located in the abdomen, and some patients find that clothing that rubs over the 
area is uncomfortable. Some surgeons may fill the pump during the implantation, 
so that it starts working right away, while others wait a short time after the 
surgery is completed prior to filling the reservoir with medication. Once 
medication is flowing, benefits may be identified in six to eight hours.
 
RISKS:  As with 
any surgery, there is a risk of infection around the area of the pump or tubing. 
If this is seen, the pump and tubing may need to be removed to allow the 
infection to clear. The pump must be assessed and refilled regularly; 
abruptly stopping the baclofen can be dangerous. Patients who have an intrathecal baclofen pump shouldn't drink alcohol, as this can increase the risk 
of side effects such as sleepiness. Exposure to heat, such as from a hot tub or 
heating pad, can increase the flow of medication, which could lead to an 
overdose. Certain types of
 MRI should be avoided, as this could cause problems 
with the pump. How much does a pump cost? Does insurance cover a intrathecal baclofen 
pump? Intrathecal baclofen pump therapy is approved by the FDA; as such, most 
insurance companies pay for this procedure and follow-up care. However, every 
plan is different, and the amount of coverage may vary.
</first>
</file1>