<file1>
<first>15 Birth Control Options (Types and Side Effect)

ABOUT: What is birth control, and how does it work? Birth control works to prevent
 pregnancy in different ways. Hormonal birth control methods work by preventing ovulation, so that a woman is temporarily
 infertile . Barrier methods of birth control prevents the man&amp;#39;s sperm from reaching an egg. Barrier methods include
 diaphragms, condoms, and cervical caps. Spermicide is a chemical that destroys sperm to prevent them from reaching the egg. Birth control methods such as intrauterine devices work by preventing a fertilized egg from implanting in the uterus and causing a pregnancy.
 How long does it take for birth control to begin working? Can you get pregnant on birth control? There is no form of birth control that is 100% effective, so it is possible to get
 pregnant while using most types of birth control. However, many types of birth control, when used correctly, are highly effective in preventing pregnancy. For example, the birth control pill is over 99% effective in preventing pregnancy when taken correctly. For all forms of birth control it is important to have a basic understanding how they work and how to use them correctly.
 What are the different types of birth control available? Types of birth control methods include options that prevent sperm from reaching an egg, known as barrier methods, methods that prevent ovulation, and methods that prevent implantation of a fertilized egg into the uterus. Permanent methods (surgical sterilization) are also available for those who no longer desire to have children. Types of birth control include: Hormonal birth control methods include: Barrier birth control methods include: Natural birth control methods include the use of: Other types of birth control options include: Surgical sterilization methods for birth control include: Hormonal birth control (birth control pills) types and side effects Hormonal options of birth control involve the use of hormones to prevent ovulation in a woman. Although oral contraceptive pills are the most widely used hormonal method, other options are available including the vaginal ring, hormone patches applied to the skin, and injections of progestin (birth control shot). Heart attacks ,
 blood clots , and
 strokes are potential and serious complications of
 oral contraceptives . Cigarette smoking increases the risk of these complications. This risk is greatest in women over 35 who are heavy
 smokers (&gt;15 cigarettes/day). Your health-care professional l usually will recommend that you
 quit smoking if you use birth control pills.
 Barrier methods of birth control (including condoms) types and side effects Barrier options prevent fertilization of the egg by a sperm cell. These either prevent contact between egg and sperm via a physical block or kill sperm cells before they are able to fertilize an egg. Examples of physical barrier contraceptives include the diaphragm, condoms, and the
 cervical cap or shield. Contraceptive sponges contain a spermicide cream to kill sperm cells, and other forms of spermicides are available as well. Spermicides may be used in combination with barrier methods for greater effectiveness. Side effects of barrier methods of birth control can include: An increased risk for developing
 urinary tract infections (
 UTIs ) if using a diaphragm and spermicide. Leaving a diaphragm or cervical cap in for longer than 24 hours increases your risk for
 toxic shock syndrome . Some people may have
 allergies to the chemicals used in spermicide creams or other spermicide products. They may develop irritation of the vagina or penis. One of the advantages to the use of barrier methods is that they can decrease the risk of
 sexually transmitted diseases (especially properly used condoms). None of them eliminates this risk.
 Surgical sterilization (tubal ligation or vasectomy) side effects and risks Surgical sterilization is a form of permanent birth control that is available for both women (tubal ligation) and men (vasectomy). Sterilization implants (a small coil is inserted into the fallopian tubes to block them) are a more recent type of permanent birth control that is available for women that allows women to avoid the surgical procedure associated with tubal ligation. Although women who have had tubal ligation do not have side effects after recovering from the procedure, any surgery itself carries a small risk of infection or bleeding as well as complications from the anesthetic agents. Likewise, the vasectomy procedure is associated with small risks from the procedure as well as some swelling and
 pain in the days following the procedure. For a time period post vasectomy a man can still be
 fertile and it is usually recommended that a barrier method or other birth control method is used for 10-12 weeks or 15 to 20 ejaculations post procedure.
 Natural birth control methods Natural methods involve tracking a woman&amp;#39;s
 menstrual cycle to try to determine when ovulation is most likely to occur, and avoiding sexual intercourse (or using barrier contraceptives) during that time. There are different ways to detect ovulation, including the basal body temperature method (ovulation causes a slight increase in basal body temperature) and the use of home ovulation test kits. Checking and recording the consistency of cervical mucus is another way to help determine when ovulation occurs. These methods tend to be the least successful methods as they require discipline in recording and tracking and understanding of the results.
 Emergency contraception types and side effects Emergency contraception is a medication or device used to prevent pregnancy after unprotected intercourse has occurred. Emergency hormonal contraceptives are sometimes known as "morning after" pills. These
 drugs prevent pregnancy if taken within 72 hours after intercourse. This is also known as emergency contraception. Insertion of a copper intrauterine device (IUD) is also an effective method of emergency contraception. Side effects of emergency contraception or "morning after" pills can include nausea , vomiting , headache , tiredness , dizziness , breast tenderness, and lower
 abdominal pain .
 IUDs (intrauterine devices) side effects IUDs or intrauterine devices are implantable devices that create an environment in the lining tissues of the womb that is unfavorable for implantation of a fertilized egg. Side effects of IUDs depend on the type of IUD being used. Copper-containing IUDs may worsen menstrual bleeding and cramps. Puncture or perforation of the uterus is a rare complication of all IUDs. IUDs that contain hormones may cause similar side effects to hormonal contraceptives, like
 headaches , breast tenderness, or
 acne .
</first>
</file1>