<file1>
<first>Chiggers (Bites) Symptoms, Pictures, Home Remedies, Medicine, and Cure

ABOUT: What do chiggers look like (pictures)? Can you see them? Chiggers are barely visible to the naked eye (their length is less than 1/150th of an inch). A magnifying glass may be needed to see them. They are red in color and may be best appreciated when clustered in groups on the skin. The juvenile forms have six legs, although the (harmless) adult mites have eight legs.
 How do chiggers burrow under the skin? Chigger mites infest human skin via areas of contact with vegetation, such as pant cuffs or shirtsleeves and collars. They migrate on the skin in search of an optimal feeding area. A common myth about chiggers is that they burrow into and remain inside the skin. This is not true. Chiggers insert their feeding structures into the skin and inject enzymes that cause destruction of host tissue. Hardening of the surrounding skin results in the formation of a feeding tube called a stylostome. Chigger larvae then feed upon the destroyed tissue. If they are not disturbed (which is rarely the case because they cause substantial itching) they may feed through the stylostome for a few days. The chigger&amp;#39;s mouth and feeding structures are delicate and are best able to penetrate the skin at areas of
 wrinkles , folds, or other areas of skin that are thin. Most bites occur around the ankles, the crotch and groin areas, behind the knees, and in the armpits. Barriers to migration on the skin such as belts may be one reason that chigger bites also commonly occur at the waist or at other areas where their migration is prevented by compression from clothing. The location of chigger bites contrasts with that of mosquito bites, which are usually in exposed areas of skin where mosquitoes can land.
 
SYMPTOMS:  A chigger bite itself is not noticeable. After the chigger has begun to inject digestive enzymes into the skin (usually after about 1-3 hours), symptoms and signs typically begin. What home remedies and OTC medications ease itching and pain from chigger bites? Many home remedies for chigger bites are based upon the incorrect belief that chiggers burrow into and remain in the skin. Nail polish, alcohol, and bleach have been applied to the bites to attempt to get rid of the chiggers by "suffocating" or killing the chiggers. However, because the chiggers are not present in the skin, these methods are not effective. Home remedies to help relieve the itching associated with chigger bites may help some people. These can include Taking a cool shower or applying cool compresses Sitting in a cool bath Using bath products that contain colloidal oatmeal Using certain
 over-the-counter (OTC) medications Treatment for chigger bites is directed toward relieving the itching and inflammation.
 Calamine lotion and
 corticosteroid creams may be used to control itching. Oral
 antihistamines , such as
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ), may also be used for symptom relief. Chigger bites themselves do not produce any long-term complications. However, because of the intense itching, prolonged scratching may lead to skin wounds that may become infected by bacteria. Chiggers in North America are not known to carry any diseases, unlike some other arthropods.
 
PREVENTION: </first>
</file1>