<file1>
<first>Cough (Chronic, Persistent Cough in Adults and Children)

ABOUT: What is chronic (persistent) cough? Chronic cough is a cough that persists over time. Chronic cough is not a disease in itself, but rather a symptom of an underlying condition. Chronic cough is a common problem and the reason for many doctor visits.
 
CAUSES:  Some common causes and risk factors for chronic cough include
 asthma ,
 allergic rhinitis , sinus problems (for example
 sinus infection ),
 esophageal reflux of stomach contents, medications such as
 ACE inhibitors , and whooping cough. In rare cases, chronic cough may be the result of inhaling foreign objects into the
 lungs (usually in children). It is important to see a doctor who may order a
 chest X-ray if a chronic cough is present. Common causes of chronic cough include: Cigarette smoking is the most common cause of a constant, chronic cough. Asthma is a disease of the airways, resulting in difficulty
 breathing or
 wheezing often characterized by abnormal breathing tests. Some asthma sufferers have chronic cough as their only symptom. They may even have normal lung functions tests. This is often referred to as cough-variant asthma.
 Asthma symptoms can be aggravated by
 cold air, exposure to air pollutants,
 pollen , smoke, or perfumes. Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) refers to
 acid reflux , or backward flow, of stomach acid and other contents into the
 esophagus . If stomach acid moves backward up the esophagus, reflexes result in spasm of the airways that can cause
 shortness of breath and coughing. In some instances, acid reflux can be so severe that substances can be inhaled (aspirated) into the lungs and cause similar symptoms as well as damage to lung tissue. In some individuals, no sensation of heartburn is felt and their only symptom may be chronic cough. Sinus problems and postnasal drip also are causes of chronic cough with mucus. This condition can be difficult to detect. Sometimes
 CT scan of the sinuses is necessary for diagnosis. Affected individuals often complain of a "tickle in their throat" and frequent throat clearing. Infections such as
 bronchitis or
 pneumonia can cause acute cough or a chronic cough. These infections can be caused by
 viruses , bacteria, or fungus. Viral infections do not respond to antibiotics. The
 common cold and the
 flu often produce a
 dry cough . Viral
 upper respiratory tract infections often result in a prolonged cough even after the infection has cleared in people with asthma.
 Acute bronchitis and chronic
 bronchitis are common causes of
 coughing up blood (hemoptysis). A particular strain of
 bacterial
 pneumonia , called
 Mycoplasma , may cause a chronic cough with
 fatigue ,
 weakness , shortness of breath, and sputum production. This infection is sometimes referred to as "
 walking pneumonia ," and commonly affects young and healthy people. Whooping cough (
 pertussis ) is an acute, highly
 contagious respiratory tract infection caused by the bacterium
 Bordetella pertussis . It can cause violent, rapid, constant coughing (often a high-piched cough with a “whoop” sound at the end) and it can be life-threatening in young children. Whooping cough commonly affects infants and young children, but can be prevented by immunization with pertussis
 vaccine . In adults, whooping cough can be a cause of chronic cough. Chronic
 cough in children is uncommon. Foreign material obstructing the airways of the lungs, asthma, and
 allergies need to be evaluated by a pediatrician. Certain medications , like ACE inhibitors (
 enalapril [
 Vasotec ],
 captopril [
 Capoten ] etc.) used in treating
 high blood pressure can cause chronic cough. Less common cause s of chronic cough include
 allergies , tumors,
 sarcoidosis ,
 congestive heart failure , or other lung diseases such as chronic obstructive disease (
 COPD ) or emphysema. Lung diseases also can cause coughing up blood. If chronic cough persists, it is important to be evaluated by a doctor. The health-care professional will consider the possibility of asthma, postnasal drip, esophageal reflux, drug side effects,
 interstitial lung disease ,
 lung cancer , or other unusual infections.
 
SYMPTOMS:  A chronic cough may be accompanied by other cold symptoms, including: Sore throat Postnasal drip Runny or stuffy nose Hoarseness Heartburn A bad taste in the mouth Phlegm See a doctor immediately if you have a chronic cough and experience the following serious symptoms: Wheezing or difficulty breathing Fever Chest pain Coughing up blood or yellow or green phlegm Coughing so hard it makes you vomit You have a cough with unexplained
 weight loss What are the different types of chronic coughs (dry, wet)? There are several different types of chronic (or persistent) cough. Examples include: 
CAUSES:  The treatment of chronic cough is directed at the cause. Symptoms may be relieved with
 over-the-counter (OTC) cough medicines containing
 guaifenesin and/or dextromethorphan (these can be found as
 cough syrups in tablet form). The following are treatments for chronic cough caused by medications, conditions, or diseases. Asthma: Inhaled
 bronchodilators and inhaled steroids are given to decrease inflammation of the airways, and reduce wheezing. In some cases, short-term oral steroids are prescribed to relieve chronic cough. Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD): Treatment for chronic cough of GERD includes avoiding foods that increase reflux, avoiding meals before lying down, elevating the head while sleeping, and taking medication such as
 famotidine (
 Pepcid ),
 cimetidine (
 Tagamet ),
 ranitidine (
 Zantac )
 omeprazole (
 Prilosec , Prilosec OTC),
 lansoprazole (
 Prevacid , Prevacid 24-Hour),
 rabeprazole (
 Aciphex ),
 pantoprazole (
 Protonix ),
 esomeprazole (
 Nexium ) to decrease stomach acidity. Sinus problems and postnasal drip: Use of decongestants such as pseudoephedrine (
 Sudafed ) or
 antihistamines such as
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) may improve symptoms of postnasal drip or
 runny nose , which can lead to a persistent, nagging, cough. Inhaled nasal steroids are very effective in treating allergic rhinitis (hay
 fever ), a common cause of cough. Additionally, other nasal inhalers like ipratropium bromide (
 Atrovent ) can relieve postnasal drip. Antibiotics may be prescribed if the cause is determined to be
 sinusitis . In severe cases of chronic cough a health-care professional may prescribe
 codeine or other similar narcotic medications, which are effective as cough suppressants.
 
CAUSES:  Infections: Bacterial pneumonia and
 bronchitis are typically treated with antibiotics such as cephalosporins,
 azithromycin (
 Zithromax ), and other antibiotics. If the pneumonia is close to the chest wall inflammation of the surface of the lung can cause
 pain , known as
 pleurisy and
 pain relievers (analgesics) can be helpful. Cough suppressants are used with caution in these situations because clearing the lung of the infected mucus by coughing helps clear the infection. Most bronchitis in adults is caused by viral infections. Therefore, treatment is much the same as that of the
 common cold including rest, fluids, pain relievers, and humidification. Some people find expectorant cough medicines containing guaifenesin helpful in alleviating their discomfort. Sometimes it is hard to differentiate a viral bronchitis from a bacterial bronchitis, and antibiotics are prescribed. In some cases, asthmatics can produce green mucus that looks infected. Your doctor can have the mucus examined to determine if an infection is present. Medications: Patients with chronic cough who are taking
 blood pressure medicines called ACE inhibitors (angiotensin converting enzyme), for example, enalapril (Vasotec), captopril (Capoten),
 lisinopril (
 Zestril ,
 Prinivil ), etc. should talk to their doctor about switching medications. Patients should not stop taking medicine on their own because a marked elevation in blood pressure can result from discontinuation. Discuss any possible medicaion changes with your doctor. A newer generation of ACE inhibitor like medicines called
 ARBs (angiotensin receptor blockers, for example,
 valsartan [
 Diovan ],
 losartan [
 Cozaar ], etc.) can be alternatives that have less potential to cause chronic coughing. Many other
 drugs are available to manage blood pressure.
 10 home remedies for chronic cough in children and adults Chronic cough in adults can sometimes be treated with home remedies. Consult your doctor for the home remedies that might be best for you, and talk to your doctor before taking any herbal
 supplements or natural remedies for chronic cough as some may interact with medications you take. 5 chronic cough in children and adults prevention tips Which types of doctors treat chronic coughs? A primary care provider (PCP) such as a family practitioner or internist may initially diagnose and treat a persistent cough. If cough is severe, a person may be seen in a hospital&amp;#39;s emergency department by an
 emergency medicine specialist. People suffering from constant cough may be referred to different specialists depending on the underlying cause. A pulmonologist is a lung specialist who treats diseases of the airways. An allergist is an
 allergy specialist who may treat chronic cough due to allergies. Gastroenterologists specialize in diseases of the digestive tract and can treat chronic cough due to conditions such as gastroesophageal reflux disorder (GERD). Cardiologists specialize in diseases of the heart and circulatory system and may treat persistent cough that can be a secondary symptom of
 heart disease .
</first>
</file1>