<file1>
<first>Primary Biliary Cirrhosis (PBC)
Primary biliary cirrhosis (PBC) definition Primary biliary
 cirrhosis (PBC) is a progressive disease of the
 liver caused 
by a buildup of bile within the liver (cholestasis) that results in damage to 
the small bile ducts that drain bile from the liver. Over time, this pressure 
build-up destroys the bile ducts leading to liver cell damage. As the disease 
progresses and enough liver cells die, 
cirrhosis and liver failure occur. Bile is manufactured in the liver and then transported through the bile ducts 
to the gallbladder and intestine where it helps digest
 fats and fat soluble
 vitamins (A,D,E,K). When bile cannot be drained from the liver, it causes 
inflammation that leads to cell death.
 Scar tissue gradually replaces the areas 
of damaged liver and then the body cannot perform necessary functions. 
CAUSES:  The cause of PBC is unknown. It is most likely an autoimmune disease, where 
the body's immune system attacks its own cells. In this disease, the bile ducts 
are under attack and are destroyed. 
RISKS:  There may be a 
 genetic component to the development of PBC since a 
 person 
with the disease is likely to have a family member also afflicted. Women are nine times more likely than men to develop PBC. It most often 
develops in the middle age between the ages of 40 to 60. The disease is seen more often in white, northern Europeans, compared 
to African-Americans.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Up to a quarter of patients with primary biliary cirrhosis are asymptomatic, 
meaning they do not have symptoms at the time of diagnosis and the disease is 
found incidentally because of 
abnormal
 liver blood tests . The most common initial symptoms are
 fatigue or a sense of being abnormally 
tired and, skin that itches. Because of the intense
 itching and 
scratching, the skin may become darkened and discolored in some areas. The 
person may also complain of
 dry mouth and 
eyes. Because there may be liver inflammation, some people may experience right 
upper quadrant
 abdominal pain , where the liver is located. Should the liver damage progress, the symptoms of cirrhosis may develop. 
These include muscle wasting,
 ascites (swelling of the abdomen due to fluid 
accumulation),
 leg swelling ,
 jaundice (yellow coloration of the skin), 
and
 confusion .
 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of primary biliary cirrhosis is considered when the doctor suspects that there might be liver inflammation based upon the history and physical examination. Initially there may be few symptoms like
 itching or
 fatigue to help guide further testing The diagnosis may be made incidentally when abnormal liver functions be found on routine blood tests drawn for another reason.
 Liver function tests include AST (aspartate aminotransferase), ALT (alanine aminotransferase), GGT (gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase), alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin. Blood levels tend to become elevated in
 liver disease and they may rise in specific patterns depending upon the underlying cause of inflammation. Once the diagnosis is suspected, a blood test to check for antimitochondrial antibody (AMA) is usually done. This is positive in over 90% of patients with PBC. Other blood tests may be considered including a
 complete blood count (
 CBC ) and
 cholesterol levels . Imaging of the abdomen by
 ultrasound ,
 CT scan or
 MRI is often considered to look for structural changes in the liver and to search for tumors. A
 liver biopsy , where a thin needle is inserted through the skin to take a piece of liver tissue, may help confirm the diagnosis. This tissue is examined under a microscope by a pathologist to look for changes consistent with PBC. It is also useful to help stage the disease, deciding its severity at the time of diagnosis.
 
TREATMENT:  The only "cure" for primary biliary cirrhosis is
 liver transplant , but it is 
only considered as a treatment option if other less aggressive treatments have 
failed and the patient develops liver failure. Ursodiol (Actigal) or ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA) is the first line treatment 
for PBC. It helps the liver transport bile into the gallbladder and intestine, 
in an attempt to prevent cholestasis. Depending upon the severity of the disease, immune suppression medications 
may be prescribed, including
 methotrexate (
 Rheumatrex ,
 Trexall ),
 cyclosporine and
 prednisone . Itching may be intense and difficult to control.
 Antihistamines like
 diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) may be helpful but other
 drugs may be considered 
including
 cholestyramine (
 Questran ,
 Questran Light ), which helps bind bile and decrease the itching 
associated with elevated bilirubin levels in the blood. Complications of PBC will need to be cared for. These include cirrhosis,
 portal hypertension , gastrointestinal bleeding,
 osteoporosis , and vitamin 
deficiencies.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  The complications of primary biliary cirrhosis develop as the ability of the liver to function decreases. Cirrhosis describes liver scarring and failure. The liver is responsible for helping to digest food, producing proteins, blood clotting factors, and enzymes that help digest food. Some complications include the following: Ascites: Fluid collection within the abdomen that occurs because the liver cannot produce enough albumin, a protein that helps keep fluid within the blood vessels. Ascites fluid is prone to infection and a condition called spontaneous bacterial peritonitis (peritoneum=sac that contains the abdominal organs + itis=inflammation) Edema : Swelling of the legs may occur, again because of decreased albumin levels in the body Easy bruising or bleeding: The liver is responsible for producing blood clotting factors. Without an adequate supply, there is an increased risk of bleeding. Patients may have a low platelet count because of an enlarged spleen causing easy bruising. Hepatic encephalopathy : The liver also helps remove waste products from the bloodstream. Ammonia is the chemical waste product of protein
 metabolism and the body requires a healthy liver to metabolize it. If ammonia levels rise, confusion and lethargy (
 encephalopathy ) may occur. P
 ortal hypertension: An increase in pressure within the liver can cause blood flow issues leading to portal
 hypertension . This may backup blood flow from other organs, causing
 splenomegaly , an
 enlarged spleen , and varices, swollen veins, especially in the
 esophagus and stomach that can predispose to bleeding. Osteoporosis: PBC is also complicated by
 osteoporosis , difficulty in absorbing nutrients, such as fat-soluble vitamin D and calcium, from the intestine. Cancer:  Some studies show patients with PBC are at an increased risk for hepatocellular
 carcinoma .
 
PREVENTION:  Since the cause of the disease is not known, it is not possible to prevent 
PBC. However, medications may be able to slow the progression of the disease and 
control the symptoms. Should a person develop PBC, all attempts should be made to prevent further 
potential damage. This may include limiting alcohol intake, avoiding the use of 
medications that contain
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol , Panadol), and
 cholesterol lowering agents. What is the prognosis for someone with primary biliary cirrhosis? PBC is a progressive disease that can be controlled but not cured. The prognosis depends upon a variety of factors including whether the patient has symptoms (especially
 fatigue ), liver function test abnormalities, and whether the patient has undergone treatment with medication or has required liver transplantation. Advances in treatment have extended the life expectancy in the past many years. The average survival from diagnosis for a patient with PBC who is asymptomatic is 16 years, while that of patients with symptoms is 7 1/2 years.
</first>
</file1>