<file1>
<first>Club Drugs
How Are Club Drugs Abused? GHB and Rohypnol are available in odorless, colorless, and tasteless forms 
that are frequently combined with alcohol and other
 beverages . Both drugs have 
been used to commit sexual assaults (also known as "
 date rape ," "drug
 rape ," 
"acquaintance rape," or "drug-assisted" assault) due to their ability to sedate 
and incapacitate unsuspecting victims, preventing them from resisting sexual 
assault. GHB is usually ingested orally, either in liquid or powder form, while 
Rohypnol is typically taken orally in pill form. Recent reports, however, have 
shown that Rohypnol is being ground up and snorted. Both GHB and Rohypnol are also abused for their intoxicating effects, similar 
to other CNS depressants. GHB also has anabolic effects (it stimulates protein synthesis) and has been 
used by bodybuilders to aid in fat reduction and muscle building. Ketamine is usually snorted or injected intramuscularly. How Do Club Drugs Affect the Brain? GHB acts on at least two sites in the brain: the GABAB 
receptor and a specific GHB binding site. At high doses, GHB's sedative effects 
may result in
 sleep ,
 coma , or death. Rohypnol, like other
 benzodiazepines , acts at the GABAA receptor. It can 
produce anterograde
 amnesia , in which individuals may not remember events they 
experienced while under the influence of the drug. Ketamine is a dissociative anesthetic, so called because it distorts 
perceptions of sight and sound and produces feelings of detachment from the 
environment and self. Ketamine acts on a type of glutamate receptor (NMDA 
receptor) to produce its effects, which are similar to those of the drug PCP. 
Low-dose intoxication results in impaired attention, learning ability, and 
memory. At higher doses, ketamine can cause dreamlike states and
 hallucinations ; 
and at higher doses still, ketamine can cause
 delirium and amnesia.
 Addictive Potential Repeated use of GHB may lead to withdrawal effects, including
 insomnia ,
 anxiety ,
 tremors , and
 sweating . Severe withdrawal reactions have been reported 
among patients presenting from an overdose of GHB or related compounds, 
especially if other drugs or
 alcohol are involved. Like other benzodiazepines, chronic use of Rohypnol can produce tolerance, 
physical dependence, and
 addiction . There have been reports of people binging on ketamine, a behavior that is 
similar to that seen in some
 cocaine - or 
 amphetamine-dependent individuals. 
Ketamine users can develop signs of tolerance and cravings for the drug. What Other Adverse Effects Do Club Drugs Have on Health? Uncertainties about 
the sources, chemicals, and possible contaminants used to manufacture many club 
drugs make it extremely difficult to determine toxicity and associated medical 
consequences. Nonetheless, we do know that: Coma and
 seizures can occur following use of GHB. Combined use with other 
drugs such as alcohol can result in
 nausea and
 breathing difficulties. GHB and 
two of its precursors, gamma butyrolactone (GBL) and 1,4 butanediol (BD), have 
been involved in poisonings, overdoses, date rapes, and deaths. Rohypnol may be lethal when mixed with alcohol and/or other CNS depressants. Ketamine, in high doses, can cause impaired motor function, 
 high blood 
pressure, and potentially fatal respiratory problems.
 What Treatment Options Exist? There is very little information available in the scientific literature 
about treatment for persons who abuse or are dependent upon club drugs. There are no GHB detection tests for use in emergency rooms, and as many 
 clinicians are unfamiliar with the drug, many GHB incidents likely go 
 undetected. According to case reports, however, patients who abuse GHB 
 appear to present both a mixed picture of severe problems upon admission and 
 a good response to treatment, which often involves residential services. Treatment for Rohypnol follows accepted protocols for any 
 benzodiazepine, which may consist of a 3- to 5-day inpatient detoxification 
 program with 24-hour intensive medical monitoring and management of 
 withdrawal symptoms, since withdrawal from benzodiazepines can be 
 life-threatening. Patients with a ketamine overdose are managed through supportive care for 
acute symptoms, with special attention to cardiac and respiratory functions. How Widespread Is Club Drug Abuse? Monitoring the Future (MTF) Survey* MTF has reported consistently low levels of abuse of these club drugs since 
they were added to the survey. For GHB and ketamine, this occurred in 2000; for 
Rohypnol, 1996. According to results of the 2009 MTF survey, 0.7 percent of 
8th-grade and 1.1 percent of 12th-grade students reported past-year** use of 
GHB, a statistically significant decrease from peak-year use of 1.2 percent in 
2000 for 8th-graders and 2.0 percent for 12th-graders in 2004. GHB use among 
10th-grade students was reported at 1.0 percent, an increase from 2008 (0.5 
percent), and statistically unchanged from peak use of 1.4 percent in 2002 and 
2003. Past-year use of ketamine was reported by 1.0 percent of 8th-graders, 1.3 
percent of 10th-graders, and 1.7 percent of 12th-graders in 2009. These 
percentages also represent significant decreases from peak years: 2000 for 
8th-graders (at 1.6 percent) and 2002 for 10th- and 12th-graders (at 2.2 and 2.6 
percent, respectively). For Rohypnol, 0.4 percent of 8th- and 10th-graders, and 1.0 percent of 
12th-graders reported past-year use, also down from peak use in 1996 for 
8th-graders (1.0 percent), 1997 for 10th-graders (1.3 percent), and 2002 and 
2004 for 12th-graders (1.6 percent).
 Other Information Sources For more information about club drugs, visit www.clubdrugs.gov, 
www.teens.drugabuse.gov, and www.backtoschool.drugabuse.gov; or call NIDA at 
877-643-2644. For street terms searchable by drug name, street term, cost and 
quantities, drug trade, and drug use, visit http://www.whitehousedrugpolicy.gov/streetterms/default.asp.
</first>
</file1>