<file1>
<first>Cluster Headache Causes, Symptoms, Pain Relief, and Cures
What is a cluster headache? What does the pain feel like? Cluster headache is
 pain that occurs along one side of the head. It&amp;#39;s frequently described as
 pain that occurs around, behind, or above the eye and along the temple in cyclic patterns or clusters. The pain of a cluster
 headache is very severe. Many patients describe a “drilling” type of sensation. 
CAUSES:  The specific cause and anatomic origination of cluster
 headaches isn&amp;#39;t known.
 MRI studies suggest dilation of the ophthalmic artery during an acute cluster
 headache , while PET scans reveal activity within the cavernous sinus. However, many patients with other
 headache types also have revealed abnormalities in similar regions, so these tests aren&amp;#39;t definitive. There is some evidence that the hypothalamus may be involved in the recurrence cycle of cluster
 headaches . Activation of the trigeminal
 ganglion can cause many changes associated with cluster
 headache , but the trigger for activation of this region hasn&amp;#39;t been identified. Do women get more cluster headaces than men do? Males are two to four times more likely to develop cluster headache than females; however, the overall frequency is quite low, with a prevalence rate of about 1 per 1,000. Because of the rarity of the condition, limited information is available. Although the majority of people are adults, cluster headache has been reported in children as young as 6 years of age. What
triggerscluster headaches? Many patients report their
 headaches begin while sleeping. Additionally, alcohol can trigger cluster headaches in patients who are in the midst of a cycle. Histamines and
 nitroglycerin can trigger cluster headaches in patients. Seasonal variation has been described, although this is inconsistent for many patients. Some patients have clusters precipitated by environmental changes or changes in
 stress or activity levels. Hormonal factors, or
 menstruation , do not seem to trigger cluster headache. Other risk factors include
 smoking and a family history of the problem. 
SYMPTOMS:  Cluster headache is always unilateral, or one-sided. However, some people may experience some variability of the side on which their headache occurs. Most people with cluster headaches describe their pain as occurring around or behind the eye. Pain may radiate along the forehead, into the jaw or along the gum line and into the
 teeth , or across the cheek of the affected side. Infrequently, pain may extend into the ear, neck, or shoulder. In addition to head pain, many people with cluster headaches have symptoms and signs that may include: 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of cluster headache is typically made after the history of headaches has been explored and a physical examination is completed. Cluster headaches are unique in their presentation, and often the history is sufficient to make the diagnosis. While no imaging study or specific blood test can confirm the diagnosis of cluster headache, an MRI or
 CT scan of the brain may be ordered to confirm that there are no other contributing factors that may mimic cluster headache symptoms. In some cases, ophthalmologic evaluation is needed to exclude problems within the eye itself that may be causing symptoms. Which medications are used the treatment of pain management, prevention, and other symptoms of cluster headaches? The treatment of cluster headache can be divided into two distinct categories -- relief of the acute headache and prevention of future headaches. Oxygen deliverey: Delivering oxygen by a face mask has been shown to help a majority of people within a short period of time. However, this can be unwieldy, and most people are unable or unwilling to transport oxygen canisters if they need to travel. Injectable
 sumatriptan (
 Imitrex ,
 Alsuma , Samavel DosePro) has been shown to be beneficial in many of patients with cluster headache. This treatment is contraindicated in patients with cardiac disease or untreated
 hypertension . Nasal spray or oral versions of this medication have been less effective than the injectable. Dihydroergotamine , given intravenously, can be extremely effective in treating a cluster headache, but can be difficult to administer acutely and cannot be used if a patient has used sumatriptan in the preceding 24 hours. Intranasal
 lidocaine has been suggested as a treatment option, but must be administered in a specific manner and is ineffective if not given correctly. Steroids can be extremely effective to decrease a headache cycle. Steroids should not be used frequently, and are for short-term use only as long-term use can lead to significant complications. Verapamil (
 Calan , Varelan),
 lithium (
 Lithobid , Eskalith),
 valproic acid (
 Depakote ,
 Stavzor ),
 topiramate (
 Topamax , Quedxy, Topiragen, Trokendi XR), and
 melatonin can all be of benefit in reducing the frequency and severity of cluster cycles. Surgery for intractable cases has been suggested. Radiofrequency lesioning of the trigeminal ganglion can decrease cluster headache frequency, but is associated with significant side effects and nerve loss. Gamma knife lesioning and
 deep brain stimulation are being studied as possible options with less risk of permanent nerve change. What is the prognosis for cluster headaches? Are they life threatening, can they be cured? Over time, cluster headache seems to diminish in frequency, but this may take many years. Cluster headache can go into remission for an extended period of time and then recur. As such, discussion with your physician regarding need for continuation of treatment is warranted. Cluster headache does not appear to be associated with other neurological illness, such as Alzheimer&amp;#39;s
 dementia , Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, or
 multiple sclerosis (
 MS ); however, many individuals with
 multiple sclerosis are known to experience severe headaches. 
PREVENTION:  Once cluster headaches have been accurately diagnosed, long-term treatment can be beneficial to decrease or prevent future cycles. However, as the specific underlying cause isn&amp;#39;t known, it may take some time to control the headache cycles.</first>
</file1>