<file1>
<first>Colic

ABOUT: Colic is self-limited and episodic. Estimates indicate that colic affects 5%-40% of infants worldwide and accounts for 10%-20% of health care provider visits during the early weeks of an infant&amp;#39;s life. Overfeeding, undiluted juices,
 food allergies , and emotional
 stress can aggravate colic. It is important for a doctor to evaluate a baby with new
 abdominal pain and crying in order to exclude other more serious conditions. Don&amp;#39;t give medications or other treatments to an infant unless they&amp;#39;ve been approved by the child&amp;#39;s medical practitioner. What is colic? 
CAUSES:  Physicians have recognized infantile colic for a long time. In 1954, Dr. Morris Wessel, a well-known New Haven pediatrician, defined an infant with colic as "one who, otherwise healthy and well-fed, had paroxysms of irritability, fussing, or crying without an obvious cause lasting for a total of three hours a day and occurring on more than three days in any one week for a period of three weeks." The only modification (Rome IV criteria) of this original "Rule of Three&amp;#39;s" is the notation that colic duration is now "one or more weeks." It is also important to remember that not all fussy
 babies suffer from colic. Most infants normally cry two to three hours per day, but the crying spreads out during the 24-hour period.
 
SYMPTOMS:  The crying or fussing most frequently begins suddenly and often after a feeding. The cry is loud, high pitched, and continuous, and the spells last from one to four hours. The baby&amp;#39;s face often gets flushed or red. The belly is sometimes distended or prominent, the legs alternating between flexed and extended straight out; the
 feet are often cold and the hands clenched. The episodes, while they can occur at any time of the day or night, typically begin in the late afternoon or early evening, just when parents or caregivers are most exhausted. There are some babies who are more prone to infantile colic than others. If one or both parents were colicky, their baby is more at risk. Infantile colic typically begins at about 2 to 3 weeks of age, reaches its peak at 2 months, begins to subside by 3 months, and is gone by 3½ to 4 months of age. But the frustrating fact remains that although many babies experience colic and much research has been done on the topic, there is no one proven cause of colic. Some studies found no discernible cause for one-quarter of those babies who suffered from colicky episodes. This reality is very frustrating for most parents. There are factors that may worsen the colic symptoms amongst all colicky babies: What
remediescan help babies with colic? This is a very common problem (up to 40% of all babies suffer from colic). Discuss any concerns with the child&amp;#39;s pediatrician and talk to other parents or relatives who have had similar experiences. Also keep in mind that colic generally occurs in big, healthy, active, vigorous babies who are great eaters and who grow very well. Sickly, poor-feeding, unhealthy babies or babies with significant underlying problems may well be cranky, miserable, and unhappy; however, these infants tend to be this way most of the time, whereas the baby with colic generally has episodes at a very predictable ("set your clock by the beginning and end") time of the day. Here are some suggestions: What can the doctor do to help a colicky baby? 
TREATMENT:  It is critically important to consult the baby&amp;#39;s doctor at the very beginning of the suspected colic symptoms. While there are no tests that doctors can perform where the results come back "colic," it is very important to exclude several other causes of crying or sudden-onset screaming in a newborn. Remember that other less serious causes of crying include anything that causes discomfort. Check if the infant is hungry, too cold or too warm, over-tired or suffering from food intolerance (gassy, overly
 loose stool that may be a sign of lactose or milk protein intolerance). Other more serious medical conditions to consider include intestinal blockage or obstruction, abdominal infection, a
 hernia , a scratch of the baby&amp;#39;s eye, an
 ear infection , a
 bladder infection , hair or fiber wrapped around fingers or toes, and others. Once the baby receives a clean bill of health, an understanding, supportive doctor is worth his/her weight in gold! Should a colicky baby&amp;#39;s symptoms ever suddenly change, the doctor will reassess the situation and look for unrelated problems that can arise in any baby. As discussed above, the doctor may recommend an
 over-the-counter anti-gas bubble medicine for the baby (for example, simethicone or Mylicon Drops) or even a
 probiotic . Babies take these medications orally. When it seems that there are as many home remedies or "cures" for colic as there are grandparents, always call the baby&amp;#39;s doctor first. Finally, remember that after the three or four months, the colic resolves; there are no long-term problems associated with colic.
</first>
</file1>