<file1>
<first>Braxton-Hicks Contractions (False Labor)  Symptoms, Frequency, and Causes

ABOUT: Braxton-Hicks contractions have been referred to as "
 false labor " and are contractions of the uterus that occur predominantly in the
 third trimester of
 pregnancy . Braxton-Hicks contractions are typically less painful than those of
 true labor are. Unlike
 true labor , Braxton-Hicks contractions are unpredictable, do not occur at regular intervals, and do not become more intense over time. Dehydration and physical activity may trigger Braxton-Hicks contractions. Changing positions may alleviate uncomfortable Braxton-Hicks contractions. What are Braxton Hicks contractions? Braxton-Hicks contractions are contractions of the uterus that occur during the third trimester of pregnancy. They are perfectly normal and have been said to represent contractions that occur as the uterus is preparing to give birth. In some women, they occur as early as the
 second trimester . Sometimes, Braxton-Hicks contractions have been referred to as "false
 labor ." In contrast to the contractions of
 true labor , Braxton-Hicks contractions do not occur at regular intervals, do not get stronger over time, and do not last longer over time. They do not occur at predictable intervals, and they may disappear altogether for a time. They tend to become more frequent toward the end of pregnancy. Common events can sometimes trigger Braxton-Hicks contractions, for example: Braxton-Hicks contractions are named after an English doctor, John
 Braxton Hicks , who first described them in 1872.
 What do Braxton Hicks contractions feel like? Braxton-Hicks contractions are not typically as painful as those of true
 labor contractions may be. Some women describe them as a tightening sensation across the lower abdomen. They may feel similar to
 menstrual cramps in some women. The abdomen may become firm to the touch. They do not occur at regular intervals. Which home remedies help relieve Braxton Hicks contraction uncomfortableness and pain? There are measures that can be taken to bring about relief if Braxton-Hicks contractions are uncomfortable: When should I call my doctor about Braxton Hicks contractions? Call your doctor or
 midwife if you haven&amp;#39;t reached 37 weeks and the contractions are increasing in frequency, are more painful or you have any of the signs of preterm
 labor : Increasing
 vaginal discharge ,
 vaginal bleeding , or
 spotting ; Increasing
 low back pain or pelvic pressure; More than four contractions an hour; Menstrual-like cramping or
 abdominal pain .
</first>
</file1>