<file1>
<first>Canker Sores (Causes, Home Remedies, Treatment, and Prevention)
What are canker sores? Canker sores are among the most common types of oral lesions, affecting about 20% of people. Women get canker sores more often than men. Canker sore susceptibility may be inherited, and the condition can run in families. What are canker sores types, and what do they look like? Canker sores are not the same as
 cold sores (
 fever blisters ), which are an infection caused by the
 herpes virus and are
 contagious .
 Canker sores are not contagious, and are categorized into three types: 
CAUSES:  The cause of most canker sores is not well understood, and multiple factors may cause sores to appear. Some possible causes of canker sores include the following: Injury to the mouth may cause simple canker sores. Injury could be from vigorous tooth brushing, dental work,
 braces or
 dentures , or a sports accident. Acidic foods, including citrus fruits, may trigger a canker sore or make it worse. Food sensitivities or
 allergies (anything from highly acidic foods to
 chocolate and coffee) Diets low in
 vitamins B12, zinc, folate (
 folic acid ), or iron Toothpaste containing sodium lauryl sulfate Allergy to certain bacteria in the mouth Hormones Emotional
 stress Smoking Gastrointestinal tract diseases such as
 Celiac disease or
 Crohn&amp;#39;s disease Autoimmune disorders such as
 systemic lupus erythematosus or
 Behçet&amp;#39;s disease Other immune system
 weakness such as a
 cold or the
 flu ,
 HIV/AIDS , or an organ transplant Systemic conditions such as Crohn&amp;#39;s disease or nutritional deficiencies Oral cancer Certain
 drugs may cause canker sores, including:
 Aspirin Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (
 NSAIDs ) Beta-blockers Oral
 nicotine Chemotherapy medicines Immunosuppressants Penicillamine Sulfa drugs Phenytoin Anticholinergic bronchodilators Platelet aggregation inhibitors Vasodilators Protease inhibitors Antibiotics Antiretrovirals Antihypertensives Are canker sores the same thing as cold sores (fever blisters)? No, canker sores are not the same thing as
 fever blisters (
 cold sores ). Canker sores occur inside the mouth and are not contagious . Fever
 blisters are infections caused by the herpes simplex virus (HSV), they mostly occur on the lips and outside of the mouth, and they are very contagious. 
SYMPTOMS:  Canker sores are painful sores inside the mouth. They may occur on the tongue, the lining of the cheeks, the gums, the inside of the lips, or the soft palate on the back of the roof of your mouth. Common symptoms of canker sores include the following: A burning, tingling, or prickling sensation, up to 24 hours before the sore appears Crater-like ulcers that are white, gray, or yellow in color, with a red border Sores are usually painful Difficulty speaking, eating, or swallowing Less common symptoms that can also indicate a more serious underlying infection include: Fever Swollen lymph nodes Sluggishness Weight loss Thrush infection in your mouth or throat Contact your doctor or dentist if your canker sores are Larger than usual Spreading Lasting more than three weeks Causing severe pain even after taking over-the-counter pain medication Causing difficulty drinking enough fluids to stay hydrated Accompanied by fever What natural or home remedies cure canker sores? In most cases, canker sores do not require any treatment, and there is nothing specific you need to do to get rid of a canker sore because it usually will heal on its own. Home remedies can be used to help relieve pain and inflammation of canker sores. If a you already have a canker sore, there are home remedies that can be used to help relieve the pain or irritation caused by the sore and to speed healing: Consult a health care professional before using any home remedy as many have not been scientifically tested or proven effective. What topical prescription and over-the-counter (OTC)
medicationscure canker sores? Topical gels or ointments are used for canker sores to relieve pain, decrease inflammation, and prevent infection. Topical pain medications : Gels such as benzocaine (Orajel, Orabase) and
 lidocaine (an anesthetic) are used directly on the canker sore to relieve pain or discomfort. Canker sore patches (Canker Cover) provide pain relief while covering and protecting the sore as it heals. These types of medications can be found over the counter.
 Topical anti-inflammatory medications : Steroid medications such as triamcinolone acetonide or fluocinonide can be used topically to decrease inflammation from canker sores. These medications usually require a prescription and should be used exactly as your doctor or other health care professional has instructed. Topical antibiotics : These medications may be prescribed by your doctor or dentist if there is a possibility of the canker sore becoming infected with bacteria. Redness, crusting, pus discharge, or fever are signs of infection. 
TREATMENT:  Several mouthwash solutions may be used to treat canker sore symptoms, and include: Diphenhydramine suspension (Benadryl Allergy liquid) is available over the counter and can be used as a mouth rinse because it has topical anesthetic effects on the tissue of the mouth and the canker sore. Put the suspension in your mouth, swish it around for 30 seconds to one minute, and spit it out. Do not swallow the rinse. Anti-inflammatory steroid mouth rinses may be prescribed to help reduce inflammation of the sores. Tetracycline antibiotic rinses may be prescribed and have been shown to relieve the pain and promote healing of canker sores. Do not use tetracycline if you are
 pregnant , people
 allergic to tetracycline, or if the person with the canker sore is a child under 16 years of age. What oral medications are available to cure canker sores? Several oral medications may help relieve symptoms of canker sores. Over-the-counter pain medications such as
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ),
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ), or
 naproxen (
 Aleve ) can be used to help with discomfort from canker sores. Zinc lozenges or
 vitamins B and C may also help relieve symptoms of canker sores. What should a person do if they get recurrent or chronic canker sores?</first>
</file1>