<file1>
<first>Neck Lift
How a Neck Lift Is Done Typically, the procedure will last two to three hours. Of course, if you are having a neck lift in conjunction with liposuction,
 facelift , brow lift, or other surgeries, the time will vary accordingly. Your exact procedure will depend on your desired results and your own personal circumstances. In order to undergo a neck lift, you must be in good general health, both physically and mentally. What do you dislike about your neck? Be honest with yourself! You're putting a lot of time and effort into researching the surgery, so make sure you get the results you want. You also should write down your thoughts on what you'd like to correct and have that with you at the time of your pre-operative consultation. Here are some of the most common concerns: Turkey wattle neck Excess fat Too much skin Turkey Wattle; Weakened or Loose Neck Muscles If you have weakened or loose neck muscles, this may cause the "turkey wattle" or appearance of neck "bands." To correct this, your surgeon may recommend platysmaplasty surgery. The surgeon makes incisions under your chin and/or behind your ears to access the platysma (neck muscle) and manipulate it accordingly. Sometimes, that may even mean removing some muscle. Your surgeon may also use permanent
 sutures to hold the tissue in place. There are new less invasive procedures, where your surgeon may be able to make smaller incisions and use an endoscope (small camera attached to a thin tube) to complete your surgery. Make sure you ask your surgeon for all your options during your consultation. You and your surgeon will discuss what type of anesthesia to use, depending on your level of comfort. If you want to remain asleep during the procedure, you should request general anesthesia. Otherwise, your surgeon can use local anesthesia with sedation. It's up to you, however, to make that determination. Instead of surgery or in addition to it,
 Botox injections can relax parts of the platysma that are responsible for the "band" appearance or look of fullness. The injections are completed on an outpatient basis and typically can be completed within 15 minutes.
 Excess fat in the neck area During liposuction, your surgeon will make a small incision below the chin and remove the excess fat. If you are undergoing multiple procedures during your neck lift, it is very common for
 plastic surgeons to begin with liposuction.If this is the only procedure you'll need, you should plan to spend up to an hour undergoing the operation. You will be able to determine this with your doctor during your pre-operative consultation. Your incisions will be stitched and bandaged. It's very important to follow your doctor's instructions on properly caring for the
 stitches and bandage in the days following surgery. Too much skin in the neck area Just like the platysmaplasty, your surgeon will make similar incisions for a cervicoplasty, trimming parts of the skin and lifting it into place. It will be secured with tissue glue or stitches. The cervicoplasty can be completed in about two to four hours, depending on the complexity of your procedure. Again, your anesthesia will depend on your own personal comfort level. Your surgeon will fit you with a compression bandage that you will have to wear for at least one week, unless instructed otherwise. It's important to follow his or her instructions to ensure proper recovery. How should I prepare for a neck lift? During your consultation, your surgeon will instruct you on what medications to avoid prior to your surgery. Certain medications and
 vitamins thin your blood and can cause increased bleeding. If you are a smoker, you will need to quit at least two weeks before the surgery and two weeks after. You cannot just plan to cut down. You must not smoke for this time period to ensure proper healing. Also, this is no time for a
 diet : make sure that you eat properly because this will help your body heal. Make sure you wear loose, comfortable clothing on the day of surgery. You should especially plan to wear a button-down blouse or shirt that does not have to be pulled over your neck or head. You should plan to take at least one week off from work to recover. However, your doctor can determine this based on your personal situation. If you are having platysmaplasty, cervicoplasty, or a combination of any of the procedures we've discussed here, you should plan on having a home recovery area set up before you undergo surgery. Ice packs Gauze and towels Thermometer Supply of comfortable, loose clothing (preferably button down shirts or blouses that do not have to be pulled over your neck and head) Petroleum jelly and antibacterial ointment for incision sites Telephone within reaching distance of where you'll be lying or sitting most of the time Supply of pillows which will allow you to keep your head in a comfortable position Someone who can stay with you at least the first 24 hours after surgery
 What is the expected recovery from a neck lift? Recovery takes time and it's important that you're patient with the process. Most people can return to work in 10-14 days. If you participate in other sports or are physically active, you will have to wait at least three weeks, if not longer, to resume those activities. Don't rush! It's not worth it. You've put a lot of time and energy into making this happen, so make it worthwhile. 
COMPLCATIONS:  You will have swelling and bruising that can last for several days. You may feel tightness or tingling, and different sensations including burning or pulling. You also will experience numbness. These are all very normal in the first few weeks following surgery and should not be cause for concern. As with any surgery, you run the risk of infection. Please keep a watchful eye on your temperature. At the first sign of a
 fever , contact your doctor. If you have unusual discharge from the incision site, such as pus, contact your doctor immediately. Although it's very rare, you could have an
 allergic reaction to the anesthesia. That's why it's very important to disclose any drug
 allergies to your doctor in a pre-operative consultation. Does insurance cover this procedure? Insurance carriers are all different, but one thing is the same: They typically agree NOT to cover elective,
 cosmetic surgery . If your procedures will in any way correct a medical condition, it's important that you express this to your insurance carrier. Your surgeon can write a letter detailing your case. Also, it's important to realize that cosmetic or
 plastic surgery can affect future coverage under certain insurance carriers. It can also affect your premiums. Make sure you ask your insurance carrier about how your future coverage or premiums will be affected should you undergo any of these procedures. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Plastic Surgery
 Edited by  Cynthia Haines , MD, April 2005.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2003
</first>
</file1>