<file1>
<first>Cryptococcus(Cryptococcosis)
What is
Cryptococcus? Cryptococcus is a type of fungus that is found in the soil worldwide, 
usually in association with bird droppings. The major species of
 Cryptococcus that causes illness in human is
 Cryptococcus neoformans . Another less common 
species that can also cause disease in humans,
 Cryptococcus gattii , has been 
isolated from eucalyptus trees in tropical and sub-tropical regions. Since 1999,
 C. gattii has also been found in regions of the Pacific Northwest, particularly 
Victoria Island in British Columbia, and Oregon and Washington in the United 
States. Who gets cryptococcosis? Cryptococcosis is disease due to a species of the fungus
 Cryptococcus .
 C. 
neoformans typically infects immunocompromised persons. Most people in the 
United States who develop cryptococcal infections are
 HIV -positive. However, 
occasionally persons with no apparent immune system problems develop 
cryptococcosis. Infections with
 C. gattii have also occurred in healthy persons 
without compromised immune systems. How is
Cryptococcusspread? Inhalation of airborne fungi. Cryptococcosis is not known to be spread from 
person to person. 
SYMPTOMS:  Cryptococcal infection may cause a
 pneumonia -like illness, with shortness of 
breath,
 coughing and
 fever . Skin lesions may also occur. Another common form of 
cryptococcosis is central nervous system infection, such as
 meningoencephalitis . 
People with cryptococcal meningoencephalitis are usually immunocompromised. 
Symptoms may include
 fever ,
 headache , or change in mental status.
 How soon do symptoms appear? Incubation times vary for infection due to
 Cryptococcus species. Symptoms 
from
 C. gattii infection are estimated to begin anywhere from 2-11 months after 
exposure. The incubation time for
 C. neoformans is not known. If I have symptoms, should I see my doctor? Yes, it is very important to seek immediate medical evaluation. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis can be made by microscopic examination and/or culture of tissue 
or body fluids such as blood, cerebrospinal fluid and sputum. The cryptococcal 
antigen test is a rapid test that can be performed on blood and/or on 
cerebrospinal fluid to make the diagnosis. How are cryptococcal infections treated? Treatment of meningoencephalitis and other severe infections is usually 
initiated with an amphotericin B formulation, with or without
 flucytosine .
 Fluconazole is used for maintenance therapy in
 HIV -infected patients with 
cryptococcal meningoencephalitis, and may be used for patients with milder forms 
of infection not involving the central nervous system. 
PREVENTION:  C. neoformans is commonly spread by bird droppings, especially pigeon 
droppings. People who have weakened immune systems should avoid areas 
contaminated by bird droppings, and should avoid contact with birds. There are 
no formal recommendations for the
 prevention of
 C. gattii infection.
</first>
</file1>