<file1>
<first>Caregiving
What is a caregiver? Caregivers are people who take care of other adults, most often parents or spouses, who are ill or disabled. The people who receive care usually need help with basic daily tasks. Caregivers help with many things such as: Grocery shopping House cleaning Cooking Shopping Paying bills Giving medicine Toileting Bathing Dressing Eating Usually caregivers take care of elderly people. Less often, caregivers are grandparents who are raising their grandchildren. The terms informal caregiver and family caregiver refer to people who are not paid to provide care. As the American population ages, the number of caregivers and the demands placed on them will grow. Who are our nation's caregivers? About one in four American families or 22.4 million households care for 
someone over the age of 50. The number of American households involved in 
caregiving may reach 39 million by 2007. About 75% of caregivers are women. Two-thirds of caregivers in the United 
States have jobs in addition to caring for another person. Most caregivers are 
middle-aged: 35-64 years old. What is caregiver stress? Caregiver
 stress is the emotional strain of caregiving. Studies show that 
 caregiving takes a toll on physical and emotional health. Caregivers are 
 more likely to suffer from
 depression than their peers. Limited research 
 suggests that caregivers may also be more likely to have health problems 
 like
 diabetes and
 heart disease than non-caregivers. Caring for another person takes a lot of time, effort, and work. Plus, most 
caregivers juggle caregiving with full-time jobs and
 parenting . In the process, 
caregivers put their own needs aside. Caregivers often report that it is 
difficult to look after their own health in terms of
 exercise ,
 nutrition , and 
doctor's visits. So, caregivers often end up feeling angry, anxious, isolated, 
and sad. Caregivers for people with
 Alzheimer's disease (AD) or other kinds of
 dementia are particularly vulnerable to burnout. Research shows that most
 dementia caregivers suffer from
 depression and
 stress . Also, studies show that 
the more hours spent on caregiving, the greater the risk of
 anxiety and
 depression . Women caregivers are particularly prone to feeling stress and overwhelmed. 
Studies show that female caregivers have more emotional and physical health 
problems, employment-related problems, and financial strain than male 
caregivers. Other research shows that people who care for their spouses are more 
prone to caregiving-related stress than those who care for other family members. It is important to note that caring for another person can also create 
positive emotional change. Aside from feeling stress, many caregivers say their 
role has had many positive effects on their lives. For example, caregivers 
report that caregiving has given them a sense of purpose. They say that their 
role makes them feel useful, capable and that they are making a difference in 
the life of a loved one.
 How can I tell if caregiving is putting too much stress on me? If you have any of the following symptoms, caregiving may be putting too much 
strain on you: Sleeping problems —sleeping too much or too little Change in eating habits—resulting in
 weight gain or loss Feeling tired or without energy most of the time Loss of interest in activities you used to enjoy such as going out with 
friends,
 walking , or reading Easily irritated, angered, or saddened Frequent
 headaches , stomach
 aches , or other physical problems 
PREVENTION:  Take care of yourself. In the process, you'll become a better caregiver. 
 Take the following steps to make
 your health a priority: Find out about community caregiving resources. Ask for and accept help. Stay in touch with friends and family. Social activities can help you feel connected 
and may reduce stress. Find time for
 exercise most days of the week. Prioritize, make lists and establish a daily routine. Look to faith-based groups for support 
and help. Join a support group for caregivers in your situation (like caring for 
a person with dementia). Many support groups can be found in the community or on 
the Internet. See your doctor for a checkup. Talk to her about symptoms of
 depression or sickness you may be having. Try to get enough
 sleep and rest. Eat a healthy
 diet rich in fruits, vegetables, and whole grains and low in saturated 
fat. Ask your doctor about taking a multivitamin. Take one day at a time. Caregivers who work outside the home should consider taking some time off. If 
you are feeling overwhelmed, taking a break from your job may help you get back 
on track. Employees covered under the federal Family and Medical Leave Act may 
be able to take up to 12 weeks of unpaid leave per year to care for relatives. 
Ask your human resources office about options for unpaid leave.
 What is respite care? The term respite care means care that gives the regular caregiver some time 
off. Respite care gives family caregivers a much-needed break. In the process, 
respite care reduces caregiver stress. Respite care may be provided by: Home health care workers Adult day-care centers Short-term
 nursing homes Assisted living homes Respite care is essential to family caregivers. Studies 
show that respite care helps caregivers keep their loved ones at home for longer 
periods of time. What is the National Family Caregiver Support Program (NFCSP)? The National Family Caregiver Support Program (NFCSP) is a federally-funded 
 program through the Older Americans Act. The NFCSP helps states provide 
 services that assist family caregivers. To be eligible for the NFCS, 
 caregivers must: Care for adults aged 60 years and older, or Be grandparents or relatives 
caring for a child under the age of 18. Each state offers different amounts and 
types of services. These include: Information about available services Help accessing support services Individual counseling and organization of support groups Caregiver training Respite care Limited supplemental services to 
  complement the care provided by caregivers. How can I find out about caregiving resources in my 
 community? A number of resources can help direct you to the caregiver services you 
 need. These agencies will be able to tell you: What kind of services are available in your community If these services are 
right for you If you are eligible for these services Whom to contact and hours 
of operation People who need help caring for an older person should contact their local 
Area Agency on
 Aging (AAA). AAAs are usually listed in the government sections 
of the telephone directory under "
 Aging " or "Social Services." A listing of 
state and area agencies on aging is also available online at:
 http://www.aoa.gov/eldfam/How_To_Find/Agencies/Agencies.asp The National Eldercare Locator, a toll-free service of the Administration on 
Aging, is another good resource. They can be reached by telephone at 
1-800-677-1116 or online at
 www.eldercare.gov . The Eldercare Locator can help 
find your local or state AAA. Operators are available Monday through Friday, 
9:00 a.m. to 8:00 p.m., Eastern Time. When contacting the Eldercare Locator, 
callers should have the address, zip code, and county of residence for the 
person needing assistance.
 What kind of caregiver services can I find in my community? There are many kinds of community care services such as: Transportation Meals Adult day care Home care Cleaning and yard work services Home modification Senior centers Hospice care Support groups Legal and financial 
counseling What kind of home care is available? There are two kinds of home care: home health care and non-medical home care 
 services. Both types help sick and disabled people live independently in 
 their homes for as long as possible. Caregivers and doctors decide what 
 services are necessary and most helpful. Home health care includes health-related services such as: Medicine assistance Nursing services Physical therapy Non-medical home care services include: Housekeeping Cooking Companionship How will I pay for home health care? Medicare, Medicaid and some private insurance companies will cover the cost of limited home care. Coverage varies from state to state. Other times, you will have to pay out of pocket for these services. The cost of home care depends on what types of services are used. Non-medical workers like housekeepers are much less expensive than nurses or physical therapists. Also, some home care agencies are cheaper than others. Who is eligible for Medicare home health care services? To get Medicare home health care, a person must meet all of the following four 
 conditions: A doctor must decide that the person needs medical 
  care in the home and make a plan for care at home. The person must need at least one of the following: 
  sporadic (and not full time) skilled nursing care, physical therapy, speech language pathology services, or continue to need occupational therapy. The person must be homebound. This means that he or 
  she is normally unable to leave home. When the person leaves home, it must be infrequent, for a 
  short time, or to get medical care, or to attend religious services. The home health agency caring for the person must be 
  approved by the Medicare program. To find out if a person is eligible for Medicare home health care services, call the Regional Home Health Intermediary at 1-800-MEDICARE or visit the Medicare Web site at:
 www.medicare.gov and select "Helpful Contacts."
 Will Medicaid help pay for home health care? To qualify for Medicaid, a person must have a low income and few other 
 assets. Medicaid coverage differs from state to state. In all states, 
 Medicaid pays for basic home health care and medical equipment. In some 
 cases, Medicaid will pay for a homemaker, personal care, and other services 
 not covered by Medicare. For more information on Medicaid coverage of home health care in your state, 
call your state medical assistance office. For state telephone numbers, call 
1-800-MEDICARE. For more information For more information on caregivers, call the National
 Women's Health Information Center at (800) 994-9662 or contact the following organizations: Administration for Children and Families
 Phone Number: (202) 401-9215
 Internet Address:
 http://www.acf.dhhs.gov Administration on Aging
 Phone Number: (202) 619-0724
 Internet Address:
 http://www.aoa.gov Alzheimer's Association
 Phone Number: (800) 272-3900
 Internet Address:
 http://www.alz.org Family Caregiver Alliance
 Phone Number: (415) 434-3388
 Internet Address:
 http://www.caregiver.org National Adult Day Services Association, Inc.
 Phone Number: (800) 558-5301
 Internet Address:
 http://www.nadsa.org National Association of Area Agencies on Aging
 Phone Number: 202-872-0888
 Internet Address:
 http://www.n4a.org National Family Caregivers Association
 Phone Number: (800) 896-3650
 Internet Address:
 http://www.nfcacares.org National Family Caregivers Support Program
 Phone Number: (202) 619-0724
 Internet Address:
 http://www.aoa.gov/caregivers The National Respite Locator Service
 Phone Numbers: (800) 773-5433
 Internet Address:
 http://www.respitelocator.org/index.htm SOURCE:
 www.4woman.gov</first>
</file1>