<file1>
<first>Caring for Teeth With Braces or Retainers
Special Brushing &amp; Flossing Instructions To floss your teeth, feed the short end of the floss through the space
between the main arch wire and the upper portion of the tooth closest to the
gum. Use a gentle sawing motion to work the floss on each side of the two teeth
the floss is between. Be careful not to pull with too much force around the
arch wire. Begin brushing your teeth by using a regular soft
 toothbrush . Brush
down from the top and then up from the bottom on each tooth with braces. Next,
brush your teeth with a proxabrush or "Christmas tree" brush. This
brush is specially designed for cleaning between two braces. Insert the brush
down from the top and then up from the bottom between two braces. Use several
strokes in each direction before moving on to the next space between two
braces. Repeat the procedure until all teeth have been cleaned. Foods to Avoid While Wearing Braces Most of the foods you like can still be eaten if you cut them into small
pieces that can be easily chewed. There are certain foods, however, that can
break or loosen your braces and should be avoided, such as: In addition to foods, do not chew ice or bubble gum. Caring for Retainers Every time you brush your teeth, brush your retainer as well. Once a day or
at least once a week, disinfect your retainer by soaking it in a
 denture cleanser, such as Efferdent or Polident or other brand name solutions. Add the
cleanser to a cup full of
 warm -- but never
 hot -- water . Thoroughly rinse the
retainer with plain water before placing it back in your mouth.
 Playing Sports While Wearing Braces You can continue to participate in any sport you choose. When playing sports
where there is a possibility of getting hit in the mouth, a specially designed
mouthguard will need to be worn. The mouthguard, made of durable
 plastic , is
designed to fit comfortably over your braces and will protect the soft tissues
inside your mouth. What to Do if a Bracket or Wire Breaks Broken braces, loose bands or protruding wires can cause problems but rarely
require emergency treatment. However, do call your orthodontist to set up an
office visit to fix the problem. If you suffer a more severe mouth or facial
injury, seek immediate help. Here's some tips to get you through some of the
more common problems until you are able to see your orthodontist: Loose brackets. Apply a small piece of orthodontic wax to
temporarily reattach loose brackets or place wax over the bracket to provide a
cushion between the bracket and your gums and other soft tissues of your mouth.
Your orthodontist usually provides orthodontic wax to you when you first get
your braces. Loose bands. These will need to be replaced or recemented into
place. Save the band and schedule an appointment for the repair. Protruding or broken wire. Use an eraser end of a pencil to move the
wire to a less bothersome position. If you can't move it out of the way, apply
a small amount of orthodontic wax over the protruding end. Do not attempt to
cut the wire because you might accidentally swallow it or inhale it into your
 lungs . If a mouth sore develops from the wire poking the inside of your mouth,
rinse your mouth with warm salt water or an antiseptic rinse. An
over-the-counter dental anesthetic can also be applied to numb the area. Loose spacers. These will need to be repositioned or replaced if they
slip or fall out completely.
 Other Problems Because braces brush up against the inside surface of your mouth, you may be
more prone to developing
 canker sores . If a
 canker sore develops, your
orthodontist or dentist may prescribe a corticosteroid ointment or a
prescription or nonprescription
 pain -reliever solution to reduce the
 pain and
irritation and help heal the sore. Reviewed by the doctors at 
The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry. Reviewed by Jay H. Rosoff, DDS, on March 1, 2007
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson, MD, 
on May 1, 2005.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005
</first>
</file1>