<file1>
<first>Dental Health: Caring for Your Dentures
Can I Make Adjustments or Repairs to My Dentures? One or more follow-up appointments are generally needed soon after you
receive your denture so that your
 oral health care provider can make any
necessary adjustments. Never attempt to adjust or repair your dentures
yourself. Never bend any part of the clasp or metal attachments yourself; doing
so can weaken the metal structure. "Do-it-yourself" repair kits can
permanently damage your dentures and over-the-counter glues may contain harmful
chemicals. Dentures that don't fit properly can cause irritation and sores in your
mouth and on your gums. Be sure to contact your oral health care provider if
your denture breaks, cracks, chips or if one of the teeth becomes loose.
Oftentimes, he or she can make the necessary adjustment or repair on the same
day. For some complicated repairs, your denture may have to be sent to a
special dental laboratory. Will My Dentures Need to Be Replaced? Over time, dentures will need to be relined, rebased or remade due to normal
wear, natural age-related changes to your face, jaw bones and gums, or if the
dentures become loose. To reline or rebase a denture, the dentist or
prosthodontist refits the denture base or makes a new denture base and reuses
the existing teeth. Generally, complete dentures should be used for 5 to 7
years before a replacement is necessary.
 How Should I Care for My Mouth and Gums? Even with full dentures, it is important to brush your gums, tongue and palate with a soft-bristled brush every morning before you put in your dentures. This removes plaque and stimulates circulation in the mouth. Pay special attention to cleaning teeth that fit under the denture&amp;#39;s metal clasps. Plaque that becomes trapped under the clasps will increase the risk of
 tooth decay . If you wear a partial denture, be sure to remove it before you brush your natural teeth. Clean, rest, and
 massage the gums regularly. Rinsing your mouth daily with lukewarm salt water will help clean your gums. Eat a balanced
 diet so that proper
 nutrition and a healthy mouth can be maintained. How Often Should I See the Dentist? Your dentist or prosthodontist will advise you about how often you need to
visit, but every 6 months should be the norm. Regular dental visits are
important so that your denture and mouth can be examined for proper denture
fit, to look for signs of oral diseases including
 cancer , and to have your
teeth professionally cleaned. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry. Reviewed by Jay H. Rosoff, DDS, on March 1, 2007
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson Mathis, MD, on May 2, 2005
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005</first>
</file1>