<file1>
<first>Carotid Artery Disease
What is carotid artery disease? The carotid arteries provide blood supply to the head. There are two common 
carotid arteries, located on each side of the neck, that divide into the 
internal and external carotid arteries. The external carotid artery provides 
blood supply to the
 scalp , face, and neck while the internal carotid artery 
supplies blood to the brain. Narrowing of the internal carotid artery may decrease blood supply to half of 
the brain that it supplies. This narrowing called
 atherosclerosis (atheroma = 
lump of plaque + sclerosis = hardening) occurs because of the accumulation of 
plaque on the inside of the artery wall. Plaque begins as a soft, waxy 
collection of
 cholesterol and
 triglycerides but over time begins to harden and 
calcify. Often it occurs where increased
 blood pressure and blood turbulence 
irritates the inner lining of the artery and this often occurs where the 
internal and external carotid arteries split (bifurcation). As the carotid artery begins to further narrow, the pressure within the 
artery continues to increase. This may cause the plaque to rupture, causing
 blood clots to form. A large clot may completely block (occlude) the artery or 
smaller clots and bits of plaque may travel into smaller arteries within the 
brain and cause disruption of blood supply to parts of brain tissue. It is only when a
 stroke or
 transient ischemic attack occurs, or a bruit 
(blowing or whistling sound) is found on physical examination by your doctor, 
that the diagnosis of carotid artery disease is usually made. Otherwise, the 
narrowing carotid artery does not cause symptoms. 
CAUSES:  Carotid artery disease occurs because of damage to the inner lining of the 
artery. This is a gradual process that is associated with
 smoking , high blood 
pressure, high
 cholesterol levels , and poorly controlled
 diabetes . These all may 
cause minor damage to the inner walls of an artery, and during the healing 
process, inflammation may occur and plaque may begin to form. Over time, the area of plaque may grow and narrow the lumen of the artery, 
the channel where blood flows. It becomes a vicious circle as the narrower lumen 
increases pressure within the artery and blood turbulence, which leads to more 
arterial wall damage and more plaque formation. 
RISKS:  The risk of narrowing carotid arteries is the same as the risk for those diseases associated with narrowing of arteries anywhere else in the body, including
 heart attack ,
 stroke , and
 peripheral artery disease . Those at risk include individuals who smoke and those with
 high blood pressure (
 hypertension ),
 high cholesterol , poorly controlled
 diabetes , family history of atherosclerosis, and advanced age. Metabolic syndrome also increases the risk for carotid artery disease. It is a grouping of many of the above listed diseases and to make the diagnosis, three of five of the following need to be present: high blood pressure , high blood sugar , high
 triglycerides (one of the types of fat in the blood), low
 HDL levels (another type of fat), and/or large waistline, a sign of abdominal
 obesity . 
SYMPTOMS:  Carotid artery disease in itself has no symptoms. It is only when blood flow to parts of the brain is decreased that the diagnosis is made. Decreased blood supply to the brain may result in either a
 TIA (transient ischemic attack) or
 stroke (CVA, or
 cerebrovascular accident ). A transient ischemic attack is a stroke-like group of symptoms that resolves on its own and should be considered a warning sign that a stroke is imminent. Symptoms for a TIA may include: weakness and/or numbness on one side of the body including the face, difficulty with speech , loss of vision, loss of balance, or confusion . While the symptoms tend to resolve on their own in a few minutes, they may last up to 24 hours. Signs and symptoms of a stroke are similar to a TIA but the effects are permanent without successful treatment. Since there is no way of knowing whether the symptoms will resolve, any of these symptoms should be considered a medical emergency and the patient or family should call 911 to activate the emergency medical services. Individuals who are having
 stroke symptoms may be candidates for treatment with clot busting
 drugs or thrombolytics, but the treatment must be initiated within 3 to 4 hours from the first onset of these symptoms.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  When a person has a TIA or stroke a doctor may take a history to evaluate the 
source of the bleed. The carotid 
arteries may be evaluated as a potential cause of the TIA or stroke. This is an important part of the diagnosis 
and treatment of a transient ischemic attack, since the TIA is a warning sign a 
stroke may be imminent. Finding a treatable cause and minimizing risk of a 
future stroke is an important component of patient treatment. Ultrasound is the most common screening test to determine whether carotid 
artery stenosis (narrowing) is present. Sound waves are used to understand the 
anatomy of the artery to see whether narrowing is present. Adding Doppler 
technology, the amount of blood flow and its velocity can be measured. Should ultrasound detect carotid artery disease, the next step is to better 
show the anatomy of the arteries that supply the brain.
 Angiography is a procedure used to identify any structural abnormalities within the large 
and small arteries that supply blood to the brain. Historically, angiography was performed with a 
catheter threaded into the artery and having dye injected to outline the blood 
vessels. In some patients, the artery anatomy can be seen using 
CT (computerized 
tomography) or MR (magnetic resonance) angiograms. In both CT ad MR 
angiographies, dye is injected into an arm vein, instead of an artery. 
TREATMENT:  The treatment for carotid artery disease needs to be individualized for each 
patient and situation. Discuss your options with your doctor. Possible 
treatments include: If the carotid artery is less than 50% narrowed, medical treatment is 
recommended. This includes stepwise 
antiplatelet therapy. Platelets are blood 
cells that help clot blood and in patients who have had symptomatic carotid 
artery disease, meaning that they have experienced a TIA, and decreasing 
platelet stickiness may be helpful in minimizing future stroke events. The first 
line medication is to treat the disease is
 aspirin . If the patient was already taking an aspirin and 
still experienced a TIA, the next line medication may be
 dipyridamole /aspirin 
combination (
 Aggrenox ) or clopidogrel (
 Plavix ).
 Surgery for carotid artery disease Surgery is a potential option for patients with more significant carotid artery disease. Two options exist, 1) carotid endarterectomy, and 2) carotid
 angioplasty with stenting. Surgery is recommended for symptomatic patients who have carotid artery narrowing greater than 70%. Surgery may or may not be of benefit for symptomatic patients whose narrowing is between 50% and 69%. Some patients decide to be screened by ultrasound for carotid artery disease even though they have no symptoms. Surgery is a controversial treatment option for asymptomatic patients who have narrowing greater than 60%. Surgery is not recommended for patients: who have completely blocked arteries because the body may have developed collateral circulation that bypasses the blockage. who have already suffered an irreversible stroke because there is no benefit to restoring blood supply to an area of the brain that has already died. 
COMPLCATIONS:  Brain cells cannot be replaced and do not regenerate. Loss of blood supply to 
the brain will quickly cause brain cells to die. The eventual result of carotid 
artery disease is transient ischemic attack and stroke. The narrower the artery, 
the more likely a stroke will occur. However, it is impossible to say with 
certainty which individual will or will not develop stroke symptoms.
 
PREVENTION:  Prevention is the cornerstone for treating carotid artery disease. Like any 
other blood vessel in the body, carotid arteries are at risk for narrowing in 
individuals who smoke, have
 high blood pressure ,
 high cholesterol , have
 diabetes or 
have a history of heart attack or stroke. Living a healthy life-style includes eating a well-balanced
 diet , maintaining an 
appropriate weight for your height, and exercising routinely. Smoking increases the risk for carotid artery disease and stopping
 smoking is 
beneficial, even at an older age. Lifelong control of high blood pressure, cholesterol, and blood sugars will 
decrease the risk of developing carotid artery disease. What is the prognosis for carotid artery disease? Many individuals have some narrowing of their carotid arteries and have no 
symptoms. There are benefits and risks for both medical and surgical management of 
carotid artery disease. The decision as to which treatment is offered depends 
upon the age of the patient, their neurologic status, their other underlying 
medical conditions, and the degree of carotid artery narrowing. The purpose of treatment is to reduce the risk of stroke. In patients whose 
treatment recommendation includes
 antiplatelet medications associated with blood 
pressure, cholesterol, and diabetes control, the risk of stroke after 2 years 
may be as low as 11%. For patients who qualify for surgery, their risk can fall 
to 2%-5%, but there are associated surgery risks including stroke, cranial nerve
 paralysis with
 hoarseness and
 difficulty swallowing , and restenosis or 
renarrowing of the artery. The doctor needs to discuss the benefits and risks of treatment to tailor the 
recommendations to the individual patient&amp;#39;s needs.
</first>
</file1>