<file1>
<first>Celiac Disease

ABOUT: In people with
 celiac disease , inflammation occurs in the small intestinal mucosa when it is exposed to gluten in the
 diet . Celiac disease is thought to be an autoimmune disorder and may have a familial or genetic component. The symptoms usually involve the
 digestive system and cause:
 abdominal discomfort, bloating , nausea , and loose bowel movements. However, there is a wide spectrum of symptoms that may occur. Because the intestine becomes inflamed, it may also lose its ability to absorb nutrients from the
 diet , leading to other associated illnesses. Treatment of celiac disease is following a strict
 gluten free diet . Celiac disease is also known by other names including
 celiac sprue , non-tropical sprue, and gluten enteropathy. What is celiac disease? 
CAUSES:  Gluten is a protein found in wheat, barley, and rye. In some people who are exposed to gluten in their diet, an enzyme called tissue transglutaminase changes the gluten into a chemical that causes an immune response, leading to inflammation of the lining of the small intestine. The normal fingerl-like projections (villi) that make up the lining of the intestine are blunted and destroyed, preventing the normal absorption of nutrients from the diet. This malabsorption of
 vitamins ,
 minerals , and other nutrients may lead to damage to other organs in the body, such as the
 liver , bone, and brain&amp;#39; that depend on those nutrients to develop and function normally. In children, the lack of effective
 nutrition because of malnutrition may cause abnormal growth and development. There seems to be a genetic predisposition to developing celiac disease, however not all people with a family history of celiac disease develop the condition. There may be another reason, yet discovered as to why the autoimmune response occurs. In addition to family history, celiac disease seems to be more common in people with
 type 1 diabetes ,
 microscopic colitis , Sjögren&amp;#39;s syndrome and autoimmune
 thyroid disease . 
SYMPTOMS:  Diarrhea and
 weight loss because of malabsorption are the classic symptoms of celiac disease, but they occur in less than one-half of people with the disease. The symptoms vary widely in presentation and intensity. Often the symptoms are not related to the bowel function, but instead are due to the consequences of chronic malabsorption of
 vitamins and minerals, for example, people who complain of
 weakness ,
 fatigue , joint pain, and are
 anemic  (low blood cell count) because they cannot absorb iron in the diet. Other symptoms of celiac disease may include: Headache Fatigue and weakness Joint pain Numbness and tingling (paresthesia) of the hands and
 feet Osteoporosis due to decreased absorption of calcium and
 vitamin D Skin
 rash Abdominal pain GERD and
 heartburn Infants and children may have even less specific symptoms including
 diarrhea ,
 constipation , weight loss, failure to thrive, and developmental delays. 
DIAGNOSIS:  The diagnosis of celiac disease is often delayed and it may take several months or years for the patient and the doctor to think of it as the cause of its many non-specific symptoms. History and physical examination may give direction as to the diagnosis, but commonly it take many visits with the patient complaining of recurrent
 abdominal pain , non-specific joint aches, or demonstrating chronic
 anemia that does not respond to iron treatment, to raise the suspicion that celiac disease is a possibility. When the diagnosis is suspected, there is a two-step screening process to make the diagnosis: It is important that the patient eats a regular diet for many weeks before the testing procedures. If the patient has already started a
 gluten free diet , it may cause the tests to be falsely negative. Once the diagnosis is made, screening for
 osteoporosis may be appropriate. Since it is often familial, once one person in the family is diagnosed with celiac disease, it is reasonable to have other close family members screened. 
TREATMENT:  Currently, the only treatment for celiac disease and the inflammation of the small intestine caused by gluten protein exposure is a life-long
 gluten free diet. Latent or potential celiac disease describes those people suspected of having the disease with a positive antibody blood test, but whose small bowel biopsy is normal. Currently, there is no indication to begin treatment with a gluten free diet, however, repeat biopsy might be considered if signs and symptoms develop or if symptoms of malabsorption are present. Individuals may be screened for celiac disease and have both a positive antibody blood test and a positive small intestine biopsy, and yet have no symptoms. This is considered silent celiac disease and the recommendation is to perform further testing looking for malabsorption complications such as
 anemia and
 osteoporosis . A gluten free diet may be indicated if these tests are positive. While a gluten free diet tends to resolve symptoms in most individuals, in a small group of patients, the gluten free diet fails to control the symptoms including
 abdominal pain and malabsorption. These patients are considered refractory to diet treatment. It is important that other types of bowel disease, including Crohn&amp;#39;s disease are first excluded before making this diagnosis. If diet therapy fails to resolve symptoms, refractory celiac disease is often treated with the same medications used in other autoimmune disorders to decrease inflammation. These medications include
 corticosteroids (
 prednisone ),
 azathioprine (Imurarn, Azasan) and
 cyclosporine . What is a
gluten-free dietfor celiac disease? Gluten is a complex protein found in wheat, barley, and rye grains. A gluten free diet excludes exposure to any of the foods that have this protein in its ingredients. It is easy to understand that regular wheat bread or pizza dough has gluten in it. However, it is less easy to realize that wheat flour is often used in many processed foods and in
 recipes for many foods that are prepared in a restaurant. Moreover, for it to be considered completely gluten free, processed foods should be prepared in a kitchen or factory that has no cross contamination with grains containing gluten. The Federal Drug Administration has published new guidelines that define gluten free food as having less than 20 parts per million of gluten . Regulations regarding food-labeling criteria require food to meet this standard to be labeled "gluten free." It is important to read the labels for all foods products. Aside from a gluten free designation, there may be
 food allergy statements that discuss the factory or kitchen where the product was manufactured. Many
 restaurants have gluten free menus or can accommodate the gluten free dietary needs of their customers, but it is important for the person to ask the server, manager, or cook directly about whether it contains gluten. What other medical problems are associated with celiac disease? Celiac disease is thought to be an autoimmune disorder, meaning that the body develops antibodies against its own tissues. Researchers believe that other diseases may be related, and may affect organs such as the thyroid (autoimmune
 thyroiditis ), the liver (
 primary biliary cirrhosis ), and colon (microscopic
 colitis ). Other diseases may include
 type 1 diabetes and
 dermatitis herpetiformis, a skin
 rash that has similar antibodies as celiac disease, but that are found in the skin. Growth failure, delayed
 puberty ,
 miscarriage and
 infertility may be associated with celiac disease. 
COMPLCATIONS:  The inability to properly absorb vitamins, minerals, and nutrients from the diet can affect many organs in the body. Since the diagnosis of celiac disease is often delayed, there can be significant issues with
 iron deficiency anemia ,
 osteoporosis because of decreased levels of calcium and
 vitamin D , and poor growth and development. Aside from the other associated autoimmune disorders that might also be present, celiac disease is associated with an increased incidence of
 lymphoma and small intestine
 cancer . This risk is reduced in patients who maintain a strict gluten free diet.</first>
</file1>