<file1>
<first>Childhood Immunization (Vaccination) Schedule
Why do we need vaccines? None of us wants to see our children get sick. If we could, we would protect them from any illness, no matter how
 small, even the sniffles. Now suppose you could make your child safe from some of the most deadly diseases in history. Suppose that at the same time you could also help protect your neighbors&amp;#39; children and other children around the country from the same diseases. Finally, you could actually help to rid the world of some of these diseases that have been crippling and killing children for centuries. You can do all of these things with one of the easiest and yet most powerful health tools ever developed. You can make sure you immunize your children. How do vaccines work? When you receive a
 vaccine , it helps your body to create antibodies. Antibodies are the body&amp;#39;s defenses that fight off any foreign substances (germs). Although your body can create antibodies on its own, many of the vaccine-preventable diseases cause severe illness and even death before your body can produce enough antibodies. Vaccines work best when given at certain ages. For example, health care professionals do not usually administer the
 measles vaccine until a child is at least 1 year old. If a child receives the
 measles vaccine earlier than that, it may not work as well. On the other hand, the DTaP vaccine should be given over a period of time in a series of properly spaced doses. More information about the specific diseases your child is vaccinated against is listed later in this article. Following is a description of the routine childhood immunization schedule. The U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) publishes the schedule each year.
 What are the recommended childhood vaccines, and at what ages they should be given? If first dose given before 15 years: If first does given after 15 years: What should you do if your child misses a shot? For most
 vaccines , it is never too late to catch up on missed shots. Children who missed their first shots at 2 months of age can start later. Children who have received some of their shots and then fallen behind schedule can catch up without having to start over. If you have children who were not immunized when they were infants, or who have gotten behind schedule, contact your doctor or the health department clinic. They will help you get your children up to date on their immunizations. (NOTE: Don&amp;#39;t postpone your child&amp;#39;s immunizations just because you know he or she can catch up later. Every month a child goes without scheduled immunizations is a month that the child is unprotected from vaccine-preventable diseases.) A combination vaccine is more than one vaccine contained in a single shot. Doctors and parents both like them because they allow a child to get several vaccines at once without having to get as many injections. Several combination vaccines are already in use (for example, MMR, MMRV, DTaP, Hib/HepB, DTaP/IPV/HepB, DtaP/IPV/Hib, and DtaP/IPV). More are under development. Rarely, a child should wait before getting certain vaccines or should not get them at all. Tell your doctor or nurse if any of these apply to your child on a day when an immunization visit is scheduled. What are the vaccine-preventable diseases? This vaccine protects against infection with the
 Haemophilus influenzae type b bacteria. These bacteria cause
 meningitis (an inflammation of the covering membranes that surround the brain) and may cause
 brain damage . Also these bacteria can infect the blood, joints, bones, muscles, throat, and the cover surrounding the heart. This is especially dangerous for
 babies . Before the vaccine era, this was an extremely common cause of acquired
 brain injury in children and infants. The Hib vaccine does
 not protect against the
 influenza virus and does not protect against the
 flu . The D in DTaP stands for
 diphtheria . Corynebacterium diphtheriae is a bacterium that attacks the throat, mouth, and nose. This is a very
 contagious disease (easy to get), but occurrences have been rare since the vaccine was created. Diphtheria can form a gray web that may completely cover the windpipe and cause someone to stop
 breathing . Also, if this disease is not treated right away, it could cause
 pneumonia ,
 heart failure , or
 paralysis . The T in DTaP stands for
 tetanus . Tetanus is an infection caused by a type of bacteria found in dirt, gravel, and rusty metal. It usually enters the body through a cut. Infection with tetanus bacteria causes the muscles to spasm (move suddenly). If tetanus attacks the jaw muscles, it causes
 lockjaw , which is the inability to open and close your mouth. Tetanus can also cause the breathing muscles to spasm, with potentially fatal consequences. The P in DTaP stands for
 pertussis . Bordetella
 pertussis is the type of bacteria that causes
 whooping cough . It infects the airways and destroys the cells responsible for clearing mucus and other debris. This results in an infection associated with a severe prolonged
 cough and typical "whoop." The
 cough can last for more than two months and typically causes severe illness in the very young and very old. Recently recommendations were added to administer boosters to adolescents. Infants who develop pertussis are at moderate risk for the development of
 seizures . A virus causes
 polio . It can cause paralysis of the legs and chest, making
 walking and breathing difficult or impossible. The first symptoms of polio are
 fever ,
 sore throat ,
 headache , and a
 stiff neck . Polio is very rare in the United States since the vaccine became available; however, it is still somewhat common in other countries. The first M in MMR stands for measles. Measles is a highly contagious (easy to get) virus that causes a high
 fever , cough, and a spotty
 rash all over the body. It may also cause
 ear infections and
 pneumonia . The second M in MMR stands for
 mumps . Mumps is a virus which causes painful, swollen salivary glands, which are located in front of the ears (where sideburns are located), as well as a fever and a
 headache . Mumps also may cause serious problems, including
 meningitis or
 hearing loss . It can cause inflammation of the testicles (orchitis) in males. The R in MMR stands for
 rubella . A virus causes
 rubella , also known as
 German measles . It is most dangerous for women who are
 pregnant . Rubella can cause a mother to have a
 miscarriage or deliver a baby with
 heart disease ,
 blindness ,
 hearing loss , or learning problems. Rubella is a mild disease in children. Hepatitis B is a virus that causes inflammation of the
 liver . Signs and symptoms are extreme
 tiredness and
 jaundice (moderate yellowing of the whites of the eyes and skin). It may cause the liver to stop working and has been associated with lifelong infection, liver failure,
 liver cancer , and even death. Varicella is the virus that causes
 chickenpox . It causes an
 itchy rash and a fever. You can catch it from someone who already has it if you touch an open
 blister on that person&amp;#39;s skin or if that person sneezes or
 coughs around you. Varicella infection, though usually believed to be mild, also causes
 pneumonia (lung infections) and
 encephalitis (brain infections). Streptococcus pneumoniae is a bacterium which causes
 ear infections , pneumonia (lung infection),
 sepsis (blood infection), and meningitis. It is very dangerous to the very young and very old. Hepatitis A is a virus similar to
 hepatitis B . Transmission occurs by coming in contact with contaminated food or drink. Contamination of foods may occur from food handlers not following proper hygiene procedures. Early symptoms of the disease are nonspecific and may include fever,
 diarrhea , and
 abdominal pain . It causes acute
 liver disease . It can affect anyone at any age, and in the United States, it can occur as isolated cases or even in epidemics. Neisseria meningitidis is a bacterium that causes meningitis (brain infection), sepsis (blood infection), and other infections. It is very dangerous infection and can cause
 seizures and death. Often outbreaks occur in epidemics. Rotavirus is a virus that causes severe
 diarrhea in very young infants. It causes over 55,000 hospitalizations each year in the United States and over 400,000 deaths worldwide. Children with this virus develop
 vomiting and watery
 diarrhea , which causes them to become dehydrated. Human papillomaviruses cause
 genital warts in men and women and
 cervical cancer in women (the
 cancer diagnosed by regular Pap testing). Annually, over 11,000 women develop
 invasive cervical cancer . Influenza is a virus that causes severe respiratory illness. There are two major types, influenza A and influenza B. Each year, a new influenza vaccine is required because of the virus&amp;#39; tendency to mutate (change). The flu, as the disease is called, causes the most severe illness in the very young and the very old. For more information about
 vaccinations , please visit the MedicineNet Immunizations (Vaccinations) Center and
 http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines . The Food and Drug Administration (www.fda.gov) and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (www.cdc.gov) kindly provided portions of the above information.
</first>
</file1>