<file1>
<first>Vaginal Douche (Douching) Safety, Methods, and Effectiveness
What is vaginal douching? Douching is the practice of washing or flushing the vagina with water or other fluids. Vaginal douches are available as prepackaged mixes, most commonly involving water mixed with vinegar, baking soda, or
 iodine . Douches are available at pharmacies and supermarkets. Is vaginal douching necessary? Does it prevent sexually trasnmitted diseases (STDs)? The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG) recommends that women avoid the practice of vaginal douching. Most physicians also do not recommend douching. Douching can disrupt the balance of bacteria in the vagina and can alter the normal pH of the vagina. Changes in the composition of the bacteria that normally reside within the vagina can lead to an increased risk of vaginal infections such as yeast infections. Douching can also cause the spread of harmful bacteria further up into the reproductive tract if an infection is already present in the vagina. Women who
 douche state that they do so because they believe it offers health benefits, such as cleaning the vagina, rinsing away blood after menstrual periods, avoiding odor, and preventing
 pregnancy or infections. However, these beliefs are false, and douching is not necessary to “clean” the vagina. Douching also does not protect against pregnancy or against sexually-transmitted diseases (
 STDs ).
 Can douching be harmful? Yes, in some women, douching can lead to the spread of an infection or even the development of an infection by altering the balance of normal bacteria that are present in the vagina, as discussed previously. The risk of both
 bacterial vaginosis and sexually-transmitted diseases may be increased by douching. Douching can also cause vaginal irritation. What is the best way to clean the vagina? The vagina produces mucus, which acts as a natural cleansing agent to wash away blood, semen, and
 vaginal discharge . Washing the outside of the vagina with mild soap and water with regular bathing is sufficient for good hygiene. Can douching help relieve vaginal discharge, odor, pain, itching, or burning? An abnormal
 vaginal odor , discharge, or discomfort can signal the presence of an infection, so douching to relieve the symptom would only avoid the underlying problem and might even make the infection worse. If you have abnormal
 vaginal odor or discharge,
 pain , burning, or
 itching , it&amp;#39;s important to see your health-care professional for diagnosis and treatment. Douching before the doctor&amp;#39;s visit can make it more difficult to diagnose the problem and recommend the right therapy.
 
PREVENTION:  No, douching after sex does not prevent pregnancy and should never be used as a method of
 birth control . Can douching after sex prevent sexually-transmitted diseases (STDs)? Douching after sex or at any time has no effect in preventing
 STDs . Can douching affect fertility or pregnancy? Some studies have shown that women who douche regularly take longer to become
 pregnant when
 trying to conceive than women who do not douche. Other research has shown that douching may damage the Fallopian tubes and lead to an increased risk of
 ectopic pregnancy (pregnancy outside the uterus). In pregnant women, douching was shown in one study to increase the risk of preterm birth by a factor of 1.9.
</first>
</file1>