<file1>
<first>Drug Allergy (Medication Allergy)
Drug allergy definition Allergic reactions are the hyper-immune response of our immune system to foreign (antigenic) substances. When certain foreign substances are introduced to the body, the immune system is triggered. (The immune system protects us from substances that may harm the body.) A hyper-immune response may result in
 allergic reaction symptoms. Medications are foreign substances and some of their components may trigger the immune systems of some people. What are the
signs and symptomsof an allergy to drug (medication) allergy? Drug allergic reactions are similar to allergic reactions resulting from food and other substances that we ingest. A person&amp;#39;s genetic make-up helps determine what they are allergic to, and the severity of their
 allergies . Allergic reactions, including drug allergy reactions, can be mild, moderate or even deadly. Mild drug allergy reactions include:
 Itching Rash Hives More serious reactions involve swelling of lips, tongue that can cause difficulty breathing (anaphylaxis) that can lead to death. Other signs and symptoms of drug allergies include: Dizziness Diarrhea Nausea Vomiting Abdominal cramps Seizure Low blood pressure Fainting Drug allergies may occur at any time during drug treatment. This means that the allergic reaction may occur after the first exposure to the drug or when the drug is taken again in the future. Allergic reactions are different from common side effects of many
 drugs such as a
 headache or upset stomach. To what types of drugs are people most allergic? Any drug or a component in a drug can cause an allergic reaction. Drugs that most commonly cause allergic reactions include: Penicillin and related drugs Sulfa drugs Insulin Iodine Other drugs that may cause an allergic reaction include: Chemotherapy drugs Drugs that suppress the immune system such as
 rituximab (
 Rituxan ) and
 abatacept (
 Orencia ) HIV medications Sometimes the allergic symptoms are caused by a component or substances used for packaging or administering the drug that triggers the
 allergy . Components of drugs that commonly cause allergies include: Dyes Egg proteins Peanuts Latex (in the packaging of drugs) Is there a test for drug (medication) allergies? Most times drug allergies are identified based on the time proximity of the 
reaction to administration of the drug and patient history. If the drug is 
stopped and the symptoms also stop; then the logical conclusion is that the drug 
caused the allergic reaction. Skin testing can also be used to verify that the 
drug is causing the
 allergy . If it is a drug that the patient needs and there 
are no other alternatives, careful skin testing can be done to determine if the 
person is truly allergic to the drug. What is the
treatmentfor a drug 
(medication) allergy? The first step is to stop the drug you suspect is causing the signs and 
symptoms. For skin reactions such as rashes and
 itching antihistamine creams (for example
 Benadryl ) or steroid creams (for example, hydrocortisone) are used.
 Oral antihistamines and steroids are used for more bothersome symptoms. Antihistamines injections and or steroids are given for serious allergic reactions. For life threatening anaphylactic reactions which involve difficulty breathing, epinephrine is given usually intramuscularly. In situations where a drug is needed and there are no alternatives an allergist can attempt to desensitize the individual by gradually giving very small amounts of the drug and increasing the amount over a time. What should I do if I have an allergic reaction to a drug? Contact your doctor if you develop a
 rash , itching, hives or any symptom related to drug allergy. If your 
lip or tongue swells or if you have
 shortness of breath go the emergency room immediately.
 Do not drive yourself, call 911.</first>
</file1>