<file1>
<first>Duodenal Diverticulum
What is a duodenal diverticulum? A duodenal
 diverticulum (the plural of which is
 diverticula ) is a pouch attached to the duodenum, the second part of the small intestine just past the stomach. There are two types of duodenal diverticula. The common type which is present in some individuals, is one that sticks out from the duodenum, similar to the more common colonic diverticula. This is referred to as an "extramural" diverticulum. Extramural diverticula may vary in size from a few millimeters to a few centimeters. They usually are located in the area around the Papilla of Vater where the bile and pancreatic ducts enter the duodenum. A second, rare type of diverticulum is referred to as an "intramural" diverticulum. It does not protrude from the duodenum. Rather, it protrudes into the duodenal lumen (the hollow inside of the duodenum through which digesting food flows). Both types of diverticula, extramural and intramural, communicate with the lumen of the duodenum so that contents of the duodenum can enter the diverticulum. 
CAUSES:  The cause of extramural diverticula is not definitively known; however, they are believed to be acquired (not present from birth) due to a herniation (protrusion) of the duodenum through a defect in the muscle of the wall of the duodenum, perhaps in an area where arteries pass through the intestinal muscle to nourish the lining of the intestine.
 
CAUSES:  Extramural diverticula usually cause no symptoms. Occasionally, they may 
 rupture (just like 
colonic diverticula) and lead to a pocket of inflammation adjacent to the 
duodenum with or without infection. This may result in all the signs and 
symptoms of intra-abdominal inflammation including
 pain ,
 fever , and abdominal 
tenderness. If the diverticulum is very close to the Ampulla of Vater, 
patients more frequently develop
 gallstones , particularly in the bile duct, and 
may develop all of the complications of gallstones: biliary colic (the typical
 pain of obstruction of the bile ducts), cholecystitis (inflammation of the 
gallbladder), and cholangitis (inflammation of the bile ducts due to the spread 
of bacteria into the ducts from the duodenum). Pancreatitis also may occur. These 
complications are believed to be due to interference by the diverticula with the 
normal function of the bile and pancreatic ducts. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Extramural duodenal diverticula are most commonly 
diagnosed by barium 
X-rays 
of the upper gastrointestinal tract. They also may be diagnosed at the time of
 endoscopy or, less 
frequently, with
 ultrasonography . Finally, they also may show up by chance in 
computerized tomographic 
(CT) scans or
 magnetic resonance imaging (
 MRI ) studies 
of the abdomen.
 How is a duodenal diverticulum treated? If treatment is necessary, extramural diverticula can be 
surgically removed from the outside of the duodenum. The diverticula also may be 
inverted into the lumen of the duodenum and removed through an incision in the wall of the 
duodenum. (Sometimes, the diverticulum is inverted but left attached to the wall 
of the duodenum and protruding into the duodenum.) What about intramural diverticula? The cause of intramural diverticula is not clear; however, they are believed to be congenital, that is, present from birth, and may occur as a developmental abnormality of the intestine in the fetus. Intramural duodenal diverticula most commonly cause obstruction of the duodenum when the diverticulum fills with ingested material. They are commonly diagnosed by barium X-ray studies of the upper gastrointestinal tract, but also are seen with upper gastrointestinal endoscopy. Intramural diverticula are surgically removed through an incision in the wall of the duodenum, although there are reports of treatment using non-surgical, endoscopic means to incise or open up the diverticula so that material does not collect within them.
</first>
</file1>