<file1>
<first>Dental Bonding
Introduction Dental bonding is a procedure in which a tooth-colored resin material (a durable
 plastic material) is applied and hardened with a special light, which ultimately "bonds" the material to the tooth to restore or improve an individual's smile. For What Conditions Is Dental Bonding Considered? Dental bonding is an option that can be considered: to repair decayed
 teeth (composite resins are used to fill
 cavities ) to repair chipped or cracked teeth

 to improve the appearance of discolored teeth

 to close spaces between teeth to make teeth look longer to change the shape of teeth as a cosmetic alternative to amalgam
 fillings to protect a portion of the tooth's root that has been exposed when gums recede What's the Procedure for Having a Tooth Bonded? Preparation. Little advance preparation is needed for dental bonding. Anesthesia is often not necessary unless the bonding is being used to fill a decayed tooth. Your dentist will use a shade guide to select a composite resin color that will closely match the color of your tooth. The bonding process. Next, the surface of the tooth will be roughened and a conditioning liquid applied. These procedures help the bonding material adhere to the tooth. The tooth-colored, puttylike resin is then applied, molded and smoothed to the desired shape. An ultraviolet light or laser is then used to harden the material. After the material is hardened, your dentist will further trim and shape it, and polish it to match the sheen of the rest of the tooth surface. Time-to-completion. The procedure takes about 30 to 60 minutes per tooth to complete. What are the Advantages and Disadvantages of Dental Bonding? Advantages: Bonding is among the easiest and least expensive of cosmetic dental procedures. Unlike  veneers  and  crowns , which are customized tooth coverings that must be manufactured in a laboratory, bonding usually can be done in one office visit unless several teeth are involved. Another advantage, compared with veneers and crowns, is that the least amount of tooth enamel is removed. Also, unless dental bonding is being performed to fill a  cavity , anesthesia is usually not required. Disadvantages: Although the material used in dental bonding is somewhat stain resistant, it does not resist stains as well as crowns. Another disadvantage is that the bonding materials do not last as long nor are as strong as other restorative procedures, such as crowns, veneers, or  fillings . Additionally, bonding materials can chip and break off the tooth.

 Because of some of the limitations of bonding, some dentists view bonding as best suited for small cosmetic changes, for temporary correction of cosmetic defects, and for correction of teeth in areas of very low bite pressure (for example, front teeth). Consult with your dentist about the best cosmetic approach for your particular problem. Do Bonded Teeth Require any Special Care? No. Simply follow good oral hygiene practices. Brush your teeth at least twice a day, floss at least once a day and see your dentist for regular professional check-ups and cleanings. Because bonding material can chip, it is important to avoid such habits as biting fingernails; chewing on pens, ice or other hard food objects; or using your bonded teeth as an opener. If you do notice any sharp edges on a bonded tooth or if your tooth feels odd when you bite down, call your dentist. How Long Does Bonding Material Last? The lifespan of bonding materials depends on how much bonding was done and your oral habits. Typically, however, bonding material lasts from 3 years up to about 10 years before needing to be touched up or replaced.
 How Much Does Dental Bonding Cost? Costs may vary depending on where you live. Generally, bonding can range in cost from $100 to $400 per tooth. Check with your dental insurance company to find out if the cost of crowns might be fully or partially covered. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry.
 Edited by  Michael W. Smith, MD, April 2003, WebMD.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2003
</first>
</file1>