<file1>
<first>Laser Use in Dentistry
Introduction Lasers have been used in dentistry since 1994 to treat a number of dental
problems. But, despite FDA approval, no laser system has received the American
Dental Association's Seal of Acceptance. That seal assures dentists that the
product or device meets ADA standards of safety and efficacy, among other
things. The ADA, however, states that it is cautiously optimistic about the
role of laser technology in the field of dentistry. These lasers are different
from the
 cold lasers used in phototherapy for the relief of
 headaches ,
 pain ,
and inflammation. Still, some dentists are using lasers to treat: Tooth decay. Lasers are used to remove decay within a tooth and prepare the surrounding enamel for receipt of the  filling. 
  Lasers are also used to "cure" or harden a filling. Gum disease. Lasers are used to reshape gums and remove bacteria during
 root canal procedures. Biopsy or lesion removal. Lasers can be used to remove a small piece
of tissue (called a biopsy) so that it can be examined for
 cancer . Laser are
also used to remove lesions in the mouth; and relieve the
 pain of
 canker sores . Teeth whitening. Lasers are used to speed up the in-office
 teeth whitening procedures. A peroxide
bleaching solution, applied to the tooth surface, is "activated" by
laser energy, which speeds up of the whitening process.
 How Do Lasers Work? All lasers work by delivering energy in the form of light. When used for
surgical procedures, the laser acts as a cutting instrument or a vaporizer of
tissue that it comes in contact with. When used for "curing" a filling,
the laser helps to strengthen the bond between the filling and the tooth. When
used in
 teeth whitening procedures, the laser acts as a heat source and
enhances the effect of tooth beaching agents. What Are the Pros and Cons of Using a Laser? Pros Compared to the traditional dental drill, lasers: May cause less pain in some instances, therefore, reducing the need for anesthesia May reduce
 anxiety in patients uncomfortable with the use of the dental drill Minimize bleeding and swelling during soft tissue treatments May preserve more healthy tooth during cavity removal Cons The disadvantages of lasers are that: Lasers can't be used on
 teeth with
 fillings already in place. Lasers can't be used in many commonly performed dental procedures. For
example, lasers can't be used to fill
 cavities located between teeth, around
old fillings, and large cavities that need to be prepared for a
 crown . In
addition, lasers cannot be used to remove defective crowns or silver fillings,
or prepare teeth for
 bridges . Traditional drills may still be needed to shape the filling, adjust the bite, and polish the filling even when a laser is used. Lasers do not eliminate the need for anesthesia. Laser treatment tends to be more expensive since the cost of the laser is
much higher than a dental drill. Lasers can cost between $39,000 and $45,000
compared to about $600 for a standard drill. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry. Reviewed by Jay H. Rosoff, DDS, on March 1, 2007
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson, MD, 
on May 1, 2005.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005
</first>
</file1>