<file1>
<first>Dental Health: Sealants
What Is Dental Sealants? Sealants are a thin,
 plastic coating painted on the chewing surfaces of
 teeth -- usually the back teeth (the premolars, and
 molars) -- to prevent
 tooth decay . The painted on liquid sealant quickly bonds into the depressions and grooves of the teeth forming a protective shield over the enamel of each tooth. Although thorough brushing and flossing can remove food particles and plaque from smooth surfaces of teeth, they cannot always get into all the nooks and crannies of the back teeth to remove the food and plaque. Sealants protect these vulnerable areas from tooth decay by "sealing out" plaque and food. Who Should Get Sealants? Because of the likelihood of developing decay in the depressions and grooves
of the premolars and molars, children and teenagers are obvious candidates for
sealants. However, adults without decay or
 fillings in their molars can also
benefit from sealants. Typically, children should get sealants on their permanent molars and
premolars as soon as these teeth come in. In this way, the dental sealants can
protect the teeth through the cavity-prone years of ages 6 to 14. In some cases, dental sealants may also be appropriate for baby teeth, such
as when a child's baby teeth have deep depressions and grooves. Because baby
teeth play such an important role in holding the correct spacing for permanent
teeth, it is important to keep these teeth healthy so they are not lost too
early. How Are Sealants Applied? Applying the sealant is a simple and painless process. It takes only a few
minutes for your dentist or hygienist to apply the sealant to seal each tooth.
The application steps are as follows: How Long Do Sealants Last? Sealants can protect the teeth from decay for up to 10 years, but they need
to be checked for chipping or wearing at regular dental check-ups. Your dentist
can replace sealants as necessary. Does Insurance Cover the Cost of Sealants? Many insurance companies cover the cost of sealants. Check with your dental
insurance carrier to determine if sealants are covered under your plan. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland
Clinic Department of Dentistry. Edited by 
   Charlotte E. Grayson Mathis, MD, on  May 1, 2005
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005
</first>
</file1>