<file1>
<first>Dental Health: Dental X-Rays: When to Get Them
What Types of Problems Can X-Rays Detect? In adults, X-ray films can be used to: Show areas of decay that may not be visible with an oral examination,
especially small areas of decay between teeth Identify decay occurring beneath an existing filling Reveal bone loss that accompanies
 gum disease Reveal changes in the bone or in the
 root canal resulting from
infection Assist in the preparation of tooth implants,
 braces ,
 dentures , or other
dental procedures Reveal abscesses (an infection at the root of a tooth or between the gum
and a tooth) Reveal other developmental abnormalities, such as cysts and some types of
tumors In children, dental X-ray films are used to: Watch for decay Determine if there is enough space in the mouth to fit all incoming
teeth Determine if primary teeth are being lost quickly enough to allow permanent
teeth to erupt properly Check for the development of
 wisdom teeth and identify if the teeth are impacted (unable to emerge
through the gums)
 How Often Should Teeth Be X-Rayed? The frequency of getting X-rays often depends on your medical and dental
history and current condition. Some people may need X-rays as often as every
six months; others with no recent dental or gum disease and who visit their
dentist regularly may get X-rays only every couple of years. If you are a new
patient, your dentist may take X-rays as part of the initial examination and to
establish a baseline record from which to compare changes that may occur over
time. Some general guidelines your dentist may follow regarding the frequency of
 dental X-rays is as follows: People who fall into the high risk category who may need X-ray films taken
more frequently include: Children . Children generally need more X-rays than adults
because their teeth and jaws are still developing and because their teeth are
more likely to be affected by
 tooth decay . Adults with extensive restorative work, such as
 fillings to look for decay beneath existing fillings or in new locations. People who drink a lot of sugary
 beverages to look for
tooth decay (since the sugary environment creates a perfect situation for
 cavities to develop). People with periodontal (gum) disease to monitor bone
loss. People who have
 dry mouth whether due to medications (such
as
 antidepressants , antianxiety
 drugs ,
 antihistamines , and others) or disease
states (such as
 Sjogren's syndrome , damaged salivary glands,
 radiation treatment to head and neck).
 Dry mouth conditions can lead to the development of cavities. Smokers to monitor bone loss resulting from periodontal disease (smokers are at increased risk of periodontal
disease).
 How Safe Are X-Rays? Exposure to all sources of
 radiation -- including the sun,
 minerals in the
soil, appliances in your home, and dental
 X-rays -- can damage the body's
tissues and cells and can lead to the development of
 cancer in some instances.
Fortunately, the dose of radiation you are exposed to during the taking of
dental X-rays is extremely small. Advances in dentistry over the years have lead to a number of measures that
will minimize the risks associated with X-rays. However, even with the
advancements in safety, the effects of radiation are added together over a
lifetime. So every little bit of radiation you receive from all sources
counts. If you are concerned about radiation exposure due to X-rays, talk to your
dentist about how often X-rays are needed and why they are being taken. While
some people need X-rays taken more frequently, current guidelines require that
X-rays be given only when needed for clinical diagnosis. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic Department of Dentistry.
 Reviewed by Jay H. Rosoff, DDS, on March 1, 2007
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson Mathis, MD, on May 1, 2005
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2005
</first>
</file1>