<file1>
<first>Micropigmentation (Permanent Make-Up)
Who's A Candidate For Micropigmentation? Do you want to improve the appearance of thin eyebrows or lips? Do you 
have an uneven hairline or
 allergies to make-up that create a problem? 
Micropigmentation may be a viable solution. It's not going to provide a perfect 
world, but it can help enhance certain features. How Do I Find A Specialist Who 
Performs This Procedure? Do your homework. This is not school, but it is your 
appearance. You should make sure to find a doctor or specialist who has 
experience in this procedure. Be warned. There are a lot of people out there 
performing these services who do not have your best interests in mind. When you 
visit the office, you should examine the area for cleanliness and 
professionalism. A dedicated, involved specialist should be able to answer any 
and all of your questions. Make sure you feel comfortable communicating with 
your doctor or specialist and that you feel open to ask anything that's on your 
mind. You should have a consultation with your chosen doctor before the 
procedure, during which time you discuss your expectations with the doctor or 
specialist. At this time, he or she also will determine if you should receive 
anesthesia (usually local). During the consultation, he or she may take a 
medical history. It's important that you are completely honest. Additionally, 
you should be honest for why you want micropigmentation so your doctor or 
specialist understands all of your concerns. He or she will evaluate your skin 
for tone, texture and complexion in order to best match your natural colors with 
the proper pigment. He or she also may take photos. How Is Micropigmentation 
Done? Typically, micropigmentation can be performed in an office setting. The 
procedure will be performed with a pen-like instrument or standard
 tattoo gun. 
Your doctor or specialist will wear medical gloves when performing the 
procedure. The procedure itself will take a short amount of time, perhaps 20 
minutes to a half hour at most. If you are receiving anesthesia, you will be 
required to arrive earlier in order to let the anesthesia take effect. After the 
procedure, your specialist or doctor will provide you with an antiseptic to 
cleanse the treated region.
 What Should I Expect After the Procedure? You will 
be sent home the same day. You should expect swelling in the treated region. 
Your doctor or specialist will instruct you on how often you should ice the area 
and what type of ointment you can apply to the area. If you are having the 
procedure performed in your eye region, you should plan to have someone drive 
you to the office and home again.You may experience tearing, which is normal. The pigmentation typically will appear darker in the weeks following the 
procedure, but will fade over time. Follow your doctor's instructions on what to 
avoid (such as peroxide) or sunlight. Either of these can damage your new look. After the Procedure, Contact Your Doctor Immediately If: You experience excessive swelling You develop a
 fever or
 rash The area feels excessively 
hot or
 burns Follow Up Care Your new look requires maintenance. Some people have 
to undergo two or more treatments. Make sure you understand exactly how many 
treatments you will need. As the pigment fades over the years, you also may have 
to undergo additional treatments to maintain the look. Does Insurance Cover It? No. This is an elective, cosmetic procedure that you will have to pay for on 
your own. Reviewed by the doctors at The Cleveland Clinic, Department of
 Plastic Surgery .
 Edited by Charlotte E. Grayson, MD, Sept. 2003.
 Portions of this page ©
 The Cleveland Clinic 2000-2003.</first>
</file1>