<file1>
<first>Diabetes Insipidus
Diabetes insipidus facts* Diabetes insipidus is not related to
 diabetes mellitus (type 1 and
 type 2 diabetes ). Diabetes insipidus is caused by problems related to the antidiuretic hormone (ADH) or its receptor and causes
 frequent urination . There are four types of diabetes insipidus; 1) central diabetes insipidus, 2) nephrogenic diabetes insipidus, 3) dipsogenic diabetes insipidus, and 4)
 gestational diabetes insipidus. The most common symptom of diabetes insipidus is frequent urination. The diagnosis for diabetes insipidus is based on a series of tests (for example,
 urinalysis and fluid deprivation test). The
 treatment for diabetes insipidus depends on the type of diabetes insipidus. Diabetes can lead to chronic
 kidney disease . Diabetes is the most common cause of
 kidney failure in the US. What is diabetes insipidus, and what are the symptoms of the condition? Diabetes insipidus (DI) is a rare disease that causes frequent urination. The large volume of urine is diluted, mostly water. To make up for lost water, a person with 
diabetes insipidus may feel the need to drink large amounts and is likely to urinate frequently, even at night, which can disrupt
 sleep and, on occasion, cause
 bedwetting . Because of the excretion of abnormally large volumes of dilute urine, people with 
diabetes insipidus may quickly become 
dehydrated if they do not drink enough water. Children with 
diabetes insipidus may be irritable or listless and may have
 fever ,
 vomiting , or
 diarrhea . Milder forms of 
diabetes insipidus can be managed by drinking enough water, usually between 2 and 2.5 liters a day. 
Diabetes insipidus severe enough to endanger a person's health is rare.
 What is the difference between diabetes insipidus and diabetes mellitus Diabetes insipidus should not be confused with diabetes mellitus (DM), which results from
 insulin deficiency or resistance leading to high
 blood glucose , also called
 blood sugar . 
Diabetes insipidus and diabetes mellitus are unrelated, although they can have similar signs and symptoms, like excessive
 thirst and excessive urination. Diabetes mellitus is far more common than diabetes insipidus and receives more news coverage. 
Diabetes mellitus has two main forms,
 type 1 diabetes and
 type 2 diabetes . 
Diabetes insipidus is a different form of illness altogether. How is fluid in the body normally regulated? The body has a complex system for balancing the volume and composition of body fluids. The kidneys remove extra body fluids from the bloodstream. These fluids are stored in the bladder as urine. If the fluid regulation system is working properly, the kidneys make less urine to conserve fluid when water intake is decreased or water is lost, for example, through
 sweating or
 diarrhea . The kidneys also make less urine at night when the body's metabolic processes are slower. To keep the volume and composition of body fluids balanced, the rate of fluid intake is governed by thirst, and the rate of excretion is governed by the production of antidiuretic hormone (ADH), also called vasopressin. This hormone is made in the hypothalamus, a small gland located in the brain. ADH is stored in the nearby
 pituitary gland and released into the bloodstream when necessary. When ADH reaches the kidneys, it directs them to concentrate the urine by reabsorbing some of the filtered water to the bloodstream and therefore make less urine. 
Diabetes insipidus occurs when this precise system for regulating the kidneys' handling of fluids is disrupted.
 What are the types of diabetes insipidus? Central Diabetes Insipidus The most common form of serious diabetes insipidus, central diabetes insipidus, results from damage to the pituitary gland, which disrupts the normal storage and release of ADH. Damage to the pituitary gland can be caused by different diseases as well as by 
head injuries, neurosurgery, or 
genetic disorders. To treat the ADH deficiency that results from any kind of damage to the hypothalamus or pituitary, a synthetic hormone called desmopressin can be taken by an injection, a nasal spray, or a pill. While taking desmopressin, a person should drink fluids only when thirsty and not at other times. The drug prevents water excretion, and water can build up now that the kidneys are making less urine and are less responsive to changes in body fluids. Nephrogenic Diabetes Insipidus Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus results when the kidneys are unable to respond to ADH. The kidneys' ability to respond to ADH can be impaired by
 drugs -like
 lithium , for example-and by chronic disorders including
 polycystic kidney disease ,
 sickle cell disease , kidney failure, partial blockage of the ureters, and inherited genetic disorders. Sometimes the cause of nephrogenic 
diabetes insipidus is never discovered. Desmopressin will not work for this form of diabetes insipidus. Instead, a person with nephrogenic 
diabetes insipidus may be given
 hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ) or
 indomethacin . HCTZ is sometimes combined with another drug called
 amiloride . The combination of HCTZ and amiloride is sold under the brand name Moduretic. Again, with this combination of drugs, one should drink fluids only when thirsty and not at other times. Dipsogenic Diabetes insipidus Dipsogenic diabetes insipidus is caused by a defect in or damage to the thirst mechanism, which is located in the hypothalamus. This defect results in an abnormal increase in thirst and fluid intake that suppresses ADH secretion and increases urine output. Desmopressin or other drugs should not be used to treat dipsogenic 
diabetes insipidus because they may decrease urine output but not thirst and fluid intake. This fluid overload can lead to water intoxication, a condition that lowers the
 concentration of sodium in the blood and can seriously damage the brain. Scientists have not yet found an effective treatment for dipsogenic 
diabetes insipidus. Gestational Diabetes Insipidus Gestational diabetes insipidus occurs only 
during
 pregnancy and results when an enzyme made by the placenta destroys ADH in the mother. The placenta is the system of blood vessels and other tissue that develops with the fetus. The placenta allows exchange of nutrients and waste products between mother and fetus. Most cases of gestational diabetes insipidus can be treated with desmopressin. In rare cases, however, an abnormality in the thirst mechanism causes gestational 
diabetes insipidus, and desmopressin should not be used.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Because diabetes mellitus is more common and because diabetes mellitus and 
diabetes insipidus have similar symptoms, a health care provider may suspect that a patient with 
diabetes insipidus has diabetes mellitus. But testing should make the diagnosis clear. A doctor must determine which type of diabetes insipidus is involved before proper treatment can begin. Diagnosis is based on a series of tests, including urinalysis and a fluid deprivation test. Urinalysis is the physical and chemical examination of urine. The urine of a person with 
diabetes insipidus will be less concentrated. Therefore, the salt and waste concentrations are low and the amount of water excreted is high. A physician evaluates the concentration of urine by measuring how many particles are in a kilogram of water or by comparing the weight of the urine with an equal volume of distilled water. A fluid deprivation test helps determine whether diabetes insipidus is caused by one of the following: excessive intake of fluid a defect in ADH production a defect in the kidneys' response to ADH This test measures changes in body weight, urine output, and urine composition when fluids are withheld. Sometimes measuring blood levels of ADH during this test is also necessary. In some patients, a
 magnetic resonance imaging (
 MRI ) of the brain may be necessary as well. For more information about diabetes insipidus The Diabetes Insipidus Foundation, Inc.
 Patient Support and Information
 Mary Evans-Lee
 3742 Woodland Drive
 Columbus, GA 31907
 Phone: 706-323-7576
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: www.diabetesinsipidus.org The Diabetes Insipidus and Related Disorders Network
 535 Echo Court
 Saline, MI 48176-1270
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: web.archive.org/web/20021201133912/members.aol.com/ruudh/dipage1.htm?mtbrand=AOL_US National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD)
 55 Kenosia Avenue
 P.O. Box 1968
 Danbury, CT 06813-1968
 Phone: 1-800-999-6673 (voicemail) or 203-744-0100
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: www.rarediseases.org Nephrogenic Diabetes Insipidus Foundation
 Main Street
 P.O. Box 1390
 Eastsound, WA 98245
 Phone: 1-888-376-6343
 Fax: 1-888-376-6356
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: www.ndif.org
</first>
</file1>