<file1>
<first>Diabetes: Caring for Your Diabetes at Special Times
Introduction Diabetes is part of your life. You can learn how to take 
care of yourself and your
 diabetes when you're sick, when you're at work or 
school, when you travel, when you're thinking about having a baby or are
 pregnant , or when there's an 
emergency or natural disaster. When You're Sick Having a
 cold , the
 flu , or an infection can raise your
 blood glucose levels. 
You can have serious health problems leading to a
 coma if your blood
 glucose levels are very high. Be prepared for illness. Make a plan ahead of time for sick days. Ask your 
health care team how often to check your blood glucose levels
 whether you should check for 
ketones in your blood or urine
 whether you should change your usual dose of 
your
 diabetes medicines
 what to eat and drink
 when to call your health care 
provider Your health care team may recommend the following: Check your blood glucose level at least four times a day and write down 
 the results in your record book. Keep your results handy so you can report 
 results to your health care team.
 Keep taking your diabetes medicines, even if you're not able to eat.
 Drink at least 1 cup, or 8 ounces, of water or other calorie-free,
 caffeine -free liquid every hour while you're awake.
 If you can't eat your 
usual food, try eating or drinking any of the following:
 juice
 saltine 
crackers
 dry toast
 soup
 broth or bouillon
 popsicles or sherbet
 regular—not
 sugar -free—gelatin
 milk
 yogurt
 regular—not
 sugar -free—soda Your health care provider may say you should call right away if your blood glucose levels are above 240 even though you've taken your 
diabetes medicines
 your urine or blood ketone levels are 
above normal
 you vomit more than once
 you have
 diarrhea for more than 6 
hours
 you have trouble
 breathing you have a high
 fever you can't think clearly or you feel 
sleepier than usual You should call your health care provider if you have questions about taking 
care of yourself.
 When You're at School or Work Take care of your diabetes when you're at school or at work: Follow your meal plan.
 Take your medicines and check 
your blood glucose as usual.
 Tell your teachers, friends, or close co-workers 
about the signs of
 low blood glucose . You may need their help if your blood 
glucose drops too low.
 Keep snacks nearby and carry some with you at all times 
to treat low blood glucose.
 Tell your company nurse or school nurse that you have diabetes. When You're Away From Home These tips can help you take care of yourself when you're away from home: Follow your meal plan as much as possible when you eat out. Always carry a 
snack with you in case you have to wait to be served.
 Limit your drinking of beer, wine, or other alcoholic
 beverages . Ask your 
diabetes educator how much alcohol you can safely drink. Eat something when you 
drink to prevent low blood glucose.
 If you're taking a long trip by car, check your blood glucose before driving. 
Stop and check your blood glucose every 2 hours. Always carry snacks like fruit, 
crackers, juice, or soft
 drinks in the car in case your blood glucose drops too 
low.
 Bring food for meals and snacks with you if you're traveling by plane.
 Carry your diabetes medicines and your blood testing supplies with you. Never 
put them in your checked baggage.
 Ask your health care team how to adjust your medicines, 
especially your
 insulin , if you're traveling across time zones.
 Take comfortable, well-fitting shoes on vacation. You'll probably be
 walking more than usual, so you should take good care of your
 feet .
 If you're going to be away for a long time, ask your 
doctor for a written prescription for your diabetes medicines and the name of a doctor in the place 
you're going to visit.
 Don't count on buying extra supplies when you're traveling, especially if 
you're going to another country. Different countries use different kinds of 
diabetes medicines.
 When There's an Emergency or Natural Disaster Everyone with diabetes should be prepared for emergencies and natural 
disasters, such as power outages or hurricanes. Always have your 
disaster kit 
ready. Include everything you need to take care of your diabetes, such as a blood glucose meter, lancets, and testing strips
 your diabetes medicines
 a list of your prescription numbers
 if you take insulin—some insulin, syringes, and an insulated bag to keep 
insulin cool
 if you take insulin or if recommended by your doctor—a
 glucagon kit
 glucose tablets and other foods or drinks to treat low blood glucose
 antibiotic cream or ointment
 a copy of your medical information, including a list 
of your conditions, medicines, and recent lab test results
 phone numbers for the American Red Cross and other disaster relief 
organizations You also might want to include some nonperishable food, such as canned or 
dried food, along with bottled water. Check and update your kit at least twice a year. When You're Planning a Pregnancy Keeping your blood glucose near normal before and during
 pregnancy helps 
protect both you and your baby. Even before you become pregnant, your blood 
glucose should be close to the normal range. Your health care team can work with you to get your blood glucose under 
control before you try to get pregnant. If you're already pregnant, see your 
doctor right away. It's not too late to bring your blood glucose close to normal 
so that you'll stay healthy during the rest of your pregnancy. Your insulin needs may change when you're pregnant. Your doctor may want you 
to take more insulin and check your blood glucose more often. If you take 
diabetes pills, you'll take insulin instead when you're pregnant. If you plan to have a baby, work with your health care team to get your blood glucose as close to the 
normal range as possible before you get pregnant
 see a doctor who has experience in taking care of pregnant women with 
diabetes
 don't smoke, drink alcohol, or use harmful
 drugs follow the meal plan you get from your dietitian or diabetes educator to 
make sure you and your unborn baby have a healthy
 diet Be sure to have your eyes, heart and blood vessels,
 blood pressure , and kidneys checked. Your doctor should also check for nerve 
 damage. Pregnancy can 
make some health problems worse.
 People Who Can Help You Your doctor. You may see your regular doctor for diabetes care or someone who 
has special training in caring for people with diabetes. A doctor with special 
training in diabetes is called an endocrinologist or diabetologist. You'll talk with your doctor about what kind of 
medicines you need and how much you should take. You'll also agree on a target 
blood glucose range and blood pressure and
 cholesterol targets. Your doctor will do tests to be sure 
your blood glucose, blood pressure, and cholesterol are staying on track and 
you're staying healthy. Ask your doctor if you should take
 aspirin every day to 
help prevent
 heart disease . Your diabetes educator. A diabetes educator may be a nurse, a dietitian, or 
another kind of health care worker. Diabetes educators teach you about 
 meal 
planning, diabetes medicines, physical activity, how to check your blood 
glucose, and how to fit diabetes care into your everyday life. Be sure to ask 
questions if you don't understand something.
 Your family and friends. Taking care of your diabetes is a daily job. You may 
need help or support from your family or friends. You may want to bring a family 
member or close friend with you when you visit your doctor or diabetes educator. 
Taking good care of your diabetes can be a family affair!
 A counselor or mental health worker. You might feel sad 
about having diabetes or get tired of taking care of yourself. Or you might be having problems because 
of work, school, or family. If diabetes makes you feel sad or angry, or if you 
have other problems that worry you, you can talk with a counselor or mental 
health worker. Your doctor or diabetes educator can help you find a counselor.
 Other Helpful Tips to Control Your Diabetes Follow your meal plan.
 Don't skip meals, especially if you've already taken 
your insulin, because your blood glucose may go too low.
 See your doctor before starting a physical activity program.
 Check your blood glucose before, during, and after exercising. Don't
 exercise when your blood 
 glucose is high and you have ketones in your blood or urine.
 Don't
 exercise right before you go to
 sleep because it could cause low blood 
glucose during the night. Keep a daily record of your blood glucose numbers
 the times of the day you took your insulin
 the amount and type of insulin you took
 whether you had ketones in your urine Other tips Tell your doctor if you have low blood glucose often, especially at the same 
time of the day or night several times in a row.
 Tell your doctor if you've passed out from low blood glucose.
 Ask your doctor about glucagon. Glucagon is a medicine that raises blood 
glucose. If you pass out from low blood glucose, someone should call 911 and 
give you a glucagon shot.
 Take your insulin, even if you are sick and have been throwing up. Ask your 
doctor about how to adjust your insulin dose based on your blood glucose test 
results. When you travel take a special insulated bag to carry your insulin to keep it from freezing 
or getting too hot
 bring extra supplies for taking insulin and testing your blood glucose in 
case of loss or breakage
 ask your doctor for a letter saying that you have diabetes and need to 
carry supplies for taking insulin and testing blood glucose SOURCE: National Diabetes Clearinghouse; NIDDK; "Taking Care of Your Diabetes at Special Times."
</first>
</file1>