<file1>
<first>Low Cholesterol Diet

ABOUT: A high blood
 cholesterol levels is also referred to as hypercholesterolemia, and is found in the blood circulation of humans. Cholesterol is a fatty substance that is an important part of the outer lining of cells in the body of animals. Because cholesterol is a fat (medically referred to as
 lipid ), elevated blood cholesterol is sometimes referred to as
 hyperlipidemia . Cholesterol in the blood originates from dietary intake and
 liver production. Dietary cholesterol comes primarily from animal sources including meat, poultry, fish, and dairy products. Organ meats such as liver are especially high in cholesterol. LDL (low density lipoprotein) cholesterol is called "bad" cholesterol because elevated levels of
 LDL cholesterol are associated with an increased risk of
 stroke ,
 peripheral artery disease , or coronary
 heart disease (
 atherosclerotic cardiovascular disease , ASCVD). HDL (high density lipoprotein) cholesterol is called the "good" cholesterol because
 HDL cholesterol particles prevent atherosclerosis by extracting cholesterol from artery walls and disposing of them through liver metabolism. High levels of LDL cholesterol and low levels of
 HDL cholesterol are risk factors for narrowing of the arteries in the body (atherosclerosis). Research has shown that lowering LDL cholesterol reduces the risk of
 heart attacks ,
 strokes , and peripheral artery disease. The National Institute of Health, the American Heart Association, and the American College of Cardiology publish guidelines to help physicians and patients with this risk reduction for
 heart attack ,
 stroke , and peripheral artery disease. Factors that affect blood cholesterol levels include
 diet , body weight,
 exercise , age and gender,
 diabetes , heredity, and underlying medical conditions. Guidelines recommend that cholesterol screening occur every 5 years after age 20. Should elevated cholesterol levels be found, testing may need to occur more frequently. People with cardiovascular disease,
 type 2 diabetes , LDL cholesterol levels greater 190 mg/dL, and those with a 10-year
 heart disease risk of greater than 7.5% would benefit from moderate- to high-intensity statin drug therapy. Cholesterol-lowering statin medications decrease the risk of
 heart disease . What is cholesterol? Cholesterol is a chemical compound that is naturally produced by the body and is structurally a combination of fat (lipid) and steroid. Cholesterol is a building block for cell membranes and for hormones, for example, estrogen and testosterone. The liver produces about 80% of the body&amp;#39;s cholesterol, while the rest comes from our
 diet . The main sources of dietary cholesterol are meat, poultry, fish, and dairy products. Organ meats, such as liver, are especially high in cholesterol content, while foods of plant origin contain no cholesterol. After a meal, dietary cholesterol is absorbed from the intestine and stored in the liver. The liver is able to regulate cholesterol levels in the bloodstream and can secrete cholesterol if the body needs it.
 What are "normal" cholesterol blood levels? There are no established "normal" blood levels for total and LDL cholesterol. In most other blood tests in medicine, normal ranges can be set by taking measurements from large number of healthy subjects. The normal range of LDL cholesterol among "healthy" adults (adults with no known coronary heart disease) in the United States may be too high. The atherosclerosis process may be quietly progressing in many healthy children and adults with average LDL cholesterol blood levels, putting them at risk of developing coronary heart disease in the future. What are HDL cholesterol (good) vs. LDL cholesterol (bad)? What do they do? LDL cholesterol (low-density lipoprotein) is called "bad" cholesterol, because elevated levels of LDL cholesterol are associated with an increased risk of coronary heart disease,
 stroke , and peripheral artery disease. LDL lipoprotein deposits cholesterol along the inside of artery walls, causing the formation of a hard, thick substance called cholesterol plaque. Over time, cholesterol plaque causes thickening of the artery walls and narrowing of the lumen of the arteries, a process called atherosclerosis, which decreases blood flow through the narrowed plaque-filled vessel. Narrowing of blood vessels in the heart may lead to
 angina  (a type of chest pain) or heart attack. Narrowing of blood vessels in the brain this may cause a
 transient ischemic attack (
 TIA ) or
 stroke . Narrowing of the arteries throughout the body (peripheral artery disease) can lead to signs and symptoms of
 pain , including in the intestine (mesenteric ischemia) and in the legs with
 walking (
 claudication ). HDL cholesterol (high-density lipoprotein) is called the "good cholesterol" because HDL cholesterol particles prevent atherosclerosis by extracting cholesterol from the artery walls and disposing of them through the liver. High levels of LDL cholesterol and low levels of HDL cholesterol (high LDL/HDL ratios) are risk factors for atherosclerosis and
 heart attacks Low levels of LDL cholesterol and high levels of HDL cholesterol (low LDL/HDL ratios) are desirable and protect against heart disease and stroke. Very low and very high HDL cholesterol levels can run in families. Families with low HDL cholesterol levels have a higher incidence of
 heart attacks than the general population, while families with high HDL cholesterol levels tend to live longer with a lower frequency of heart attacks. Like LDL cholesterol, lifestyle factors, and other conditions influence HDL cholesterol levels. HDL cholesterol levels tend to be lower in persons who smoke cigarettes or have
 type 2 diabetes and in those who are
 overweight or inactive. HDL cholesterol is higher in people who are lean,
 exercise regularly, and do not smoke cigarettes. Estrogen increases a person&amp;#39;s HDL cholesterol, which explains why women generally have higher HDL levels than men do. The combination of low levels of total and LDL cholesterol and high levels of HDL cholesterol is favorable. Total cholesterol is the sum of LDL (low-density) cholesterol, HDL (high -ensity) cholesterol, VLDL (very low-density) cholesterol, and IDL (intermediate density) cholesterol. The liver manufactures and secretes LDL cholesterol into the blood. It also removes LDL cholesterol from the blood by active LDL receptors on the surface of its cells. A decrease in the number of liver cell LDL receptors is associated with high LDL cholesterol blood levels. Both
 heredity and diet have a significant influence on a person&amp;#39;s LDL, HDL, and total cholesterol levels. For example, familial hypercholesterolemia (an
 inherited form of very
 high cholesterol in the blood) is a disorder in which patients have a diminished number or nonexistent LDL receptors on the surface of liver cells. People with this disorder also tend to develop atherosclerosis and heart attacks during early adulthood. Diets that are high in saturated fats and cholesterol raise the levels of LDL cholesterol in the blood.
 Fats are classified as saturated or unsaturated (according to their chemical structure). Saturated fats are derived primarily from meat and dairy products and can raise blood cholesterol levels. Some vegetable oils made from coconut, palm, and cocoa are high in saturated fats.
 What are the
cholesterol guidelines to prevent heart attack and stroke The American College of Cardiology and American Heart Association have guidelines to help health-care professionals counsel patients on how to decrease the risk of suffering a heart attack or stroke. Since it takes years for cholesterol plaque to narrow arteries enough to cause blood flow problems, there is opportunity to intervene early to stop the progression of this narrowing. In addition to controlling cholesterol, the guidelines
 stress lifelong control of
 high blood pressure and
 diabetes , and the new guidelines
 stress : W
 eight control Diet Exercise Mandatory
 smoking cessation The previous goal of maintaining "normal" cholesterol levels has been replaced by an approach that suggests more people may benefit from cholesterol-lowering statin medications, and not just those with
 high cholesterol levels. These four groups include patients: The goal for statin therapy is to decrease the LDL blood levels. In patients&amp;#39; prescribed high intensity statin therapy, the goal is to lower LDL levels by 50%. For those who have medium intensity statin therapy, the goal is a LDL reduction of 30% to 50%.
 What are LDL/HDL and total/HDL
ranges and ratios? The
 total cholesterol to HDL cholesterol ratio (total chol/HDL) is a number helpful in estimating the risk of developing atherosclerosis. The number is obtained by dividing total cholesterol by HDL cholesterol. (High ratios indicate a higher risk of heart attacks, whereas low ratios indicate a lower risk). High total cholesterol and low HDL cholesterol increases the ratio and is undesirable. Conversely, high HDL cholesterol and low total cholesterol lowers the ratio and is desirable. Ideally, one should strive for ratios of 2 or 3 (less than 4). How can levels of HDL cholesterol be increased? The first step in increasing HDL cholesterol levels (and decreasing LDL/HDL ratios) is by implementing and maintaining therapeutic life style changes. Regular
 aerobic exercise , loss of excess weight (fat), and
 smoking cessation will increase HDL cholesterol levels. Regular alcohol consumption in moderation (such as one drink a day) will also raise HDL cholesterol. Because of other adverse health consequences of excessive alcohol consumption, alcohol is not recommended as a standard treatment for low HDL cholesterol. How can high LDL or "bad" cholesterol levels be lowered? “It must be emphasized that lifestyle modification (i.e., adhering to a heart healthy
 diet , regular exercise habits, avoidance of tobacco products, and maintenance of a healthy weight) remains a critical component of health promotion and ASCVD risk reduction, both prior to and in concert with the use of cholesterol-lowering drug therapies.”
 - 2013 ACC/AHA Guideline on the Treatment of Blood Cholesterol to Reduce Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Risk in Adults Therapeutic lifestyle changes to lower LDL cholesterol can help lower and maintain levels naturally. This may involve:
 Excess
 weight loss Getting regular exercise Eating a heart healthy diet low in saturated fat and cholesterol Medications to lower cholesterol : Medications are prescribed when lifestyle changes cannot reduce the LDL cholesterol to desired levels. The most effective and widely used medications to lower LDL cholesterol are called
 statins . Research has shown that only these statin
 drugs have a proven benefit to decrease the risk of heart attack and stroke. Other medications prescribed to lower cholesterol profiles include
 fibrates such as
 gemfibrozil (
 Lopid ), resins such as
 cholestyramine (
 Questran ), and
 ezetimibe (
 Zetia ). Newer medications, PCSK9 protein antibodies, Alirocumab (Praluent) and evolocumab (Repatha) are potentially useful in treating certain patients where diet and statins have failed to adequately lower LDL level.
 14 foods that help lower cholesterol levels A healthy diet that minimizes cholesterol intake is a good first step in using food to decrease cholesterol levels in the blood. Extra lean meats, skim milk, and vegetable-based "butter-like" substitutes may help decrease LDL levels in the bloodstream. In addition to diet, exercise, and
 weight loss , there are foods that may help in lowering and rebalancing the cholesterol -- increasing HDL (the good) and decreasing LDL (the bad). Increasing soluble
 fiber in the diet helps decrease both total cholesterol and LDL cholesterol. Sources include: Nuts are healthy. Nuts that may be helpful in lowering cholesterol levels include: However, nuts are high in calories and should be eaten in moderation. Avoid nuts covered with salt or
 sugar . What
medicationslower cholesterol, lipids, and triglycerides? Lipid-altering medications are used to lower blood levels of undesirable
 lipids such as LDL cholesterol and
 triglycerides and increase blood levels of desirable lipids such as HDL cholesterol. Several classes of medications are available in the United States, including HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors (statins), nicotinic acid, fibric acid derivatives, and medications that decrease intestinal cholesterol absorption (
 bile acid sequestrants and cholesterol absorption inhibitors). Some of these medications are primarily useful in lowering LDL cholesterol, others in lowering
 triglycerides , and some in elevating HDL cholesterol. Medications also can be combined to more aggressively lower LDL, as well as lower LDL and increase HDL at the same time. Newer medications, alirocumab (Praluent) and evolocumab (Repatha) have been approved to help lower LDL levels in certain pateints where diet and other statin medications have not worked adequately. Note: Dosing guidelines change. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) issued a guideline concerning the potential dangers of taking the 80 mg dose of
 simvastatin (
 Zocor ). Is lowering LDL cholesterol enough? The reduction of LDL cholesterol is only part of the battle against atherosclerosis. Individuals who have normal or only mildly elevated LDL cholesterol levels can still develop atherosclerosis and heart attacks even in the absence of other risk factors such as
 cigarette smoking ,
 high blood pressure , and diabetes. 
PREVENTION:  The benefits of lowering LDL cholesterol are: Reduces or stops the formation of new cholesterol plaques on the artery walls Reduces existing cholesterol plaques on the artery walls and widening the arteries Prevents the rupture of cholesterol plaques, which initiates
 blood clot formation and blocks blood vessels causing heart attack or stroke Decreases the risk of heart attacks Decreases the risk of strokes Decreases the risk of peripheral artery disease The same measures that decrease narrowing in coronary arteries also may benefit the large arteries in the neck and brain (carotid and cerebral arteries) as well as the femoral arteries that supply blood to the legs and the arteries that supply blood to the intestine. What are triglycerides and VLDL? Triglyceride is a fatty substance that is composed of three fatty acids. Like cholesterol, triglyceride in the blood comes either from the diet or the liver. In addition, like cholesterol, triglyceride cannot dissolve and circulate in the blood without combining with a lipoprotein. The liver removes triglyceride from the blood and it synthesizes and packages triglyceride into VLDL (very low-density lipoprotein) particles and releases them back into the blood circulation.
 
CAUSES:  High triglyceride blood levels (hypertriglyceridemia) may be genetic or they may be acquired. Examples of inherited hypertriglyceridemia disorders include mixed hypertriglyceridemia, familial hypertriglyceridemia, and familial dysbetalipoproteinemia. Hypertriglyceridemia can often be caused by nongenetic factors such as obesity, excessive alcohol intake,
 diabetes mellitus ,
 kidney disease , and estrogen-containing medications such as
 birth control pills . Do high triglyceride levels cause atherosclerosis? Whether elevated
 triglyceride levels in the blood lead to atherosclerosis and heart attacks is controversial. While abnormally high
 triglyceride levels may be a risk factor for atherosclerosis, it is difficult to conclusively prove that elevated triglyceride by itself can cause atherosclerosis. Elevated triglyceride levels are often associated with other conditions that increase the risk of atherosclerosis including
 obesity ; low levels of HDL cholesterol;
 insulin resistance ; poorly-controlled diabetes; and small, dense LDL cholesterol particles.
 How can elevated blood triglyceride levels be treated? Diet is the first step in treating hypertriglyceridemia. A low-fat diet, regular aerobic exercise, loss of excess weight, reduction of alcohol consumption, and stopping
 cigarette smoking may be enough to control triglyceride levels in the blood. In patients with diabetes, meticulous control of elevated blood glucose is also important. This can be monitored by measuring the hemoblobin A1c levels in the blood. When medications are necessary, fibrates (such as gemfibrozil [Lopid]), nicotinic acid, and statin medications can be used. Lopid not only decreases triglyceride levels but also increases HDL cholesterol levels and LDL cholesterol particle size. Nicotinic acid lowers triglyceride levels and increases HDL cholesterol levels and the size of LDL cholesterol particles. Statins are effective for decreasing triglyceride and LDL cholesterol levels and, to a lesser extent, elevating HDL cholesterol levels.
</first>
</file1>