<file1>
<first>Diabetic Diet: Foods That Raise Your Blood Sugar Levels

ABOUT: There is no single diabetes diet, meal plan, or diet that is 
 diabetes-friendly that 
can serve as a correct meal plan for all patients with
 diabetes (type 2, gestational, or
 type 
 1 diabetes ). Glycemic index , carbohydrate counting, 
the MyPlate method, and the TLC diet plan are all methods for determining healthy 
 eating habits for
 diabetes management . The exact type and times of meals on a 
diabetic meal plan depend upon a person's age and gender, how much exercise you 
 get and your activity level, and the need to gain, lose, or maintain optimal weight. Table
 sugar and alcohol are acceptable in moderation for many 
 patients 
 with
 diabetes . Most diabetic meal plans allow the 
person with
 diabetes to eat  the same foods as the rest of the family, with 
attention to portion size and timing of meals and snacks. Eating a high-fiber diet can help improve 
blood
 cholesterol and blood sugar levels in 
 patients with
 type 2 diabetes . Glycemic index is a way to classify 
carbohydrates in terms of the amount that they raise blood sugar. High glycemic 
index foods raise blood sugar more than lower index foods. Some patients with type 2 use supplements as complementary medicine to 
 treat their disease. However, there is limited evidence on the effectiveness 
 of supplements in treating the disease. What is a diabetic diet? A diabetes meal plan (diabetes diet) is a nutritional guide for people with 
diabetes that helps them decide when to consume meals and snacks as well as what 
type of foods to eat. There is no one predetermined diabetes diet that works for 
all people with diabetes. The goal of any diabetic meal plan is to achieve and 
maintain good control over the disease, including control of blood glucose and
 blood lipid levels as well as 
to maintaining a healthy weight and
 good nutrition . Health care professionals and nutritionists can offer advice to help you create 
the best meal plan to manage your diabetes. Nutritionists can help you find
 recipes and
 cooking tips to help with meal planning and preparation. Are there diabetic diet guidelines? There is no single diabetic diet that is appropriate for all people with 
type 2, gestational, or type 1 diabetes just as there is no single medication regimen that is appropriate for 
everyone with this disease. Dietary choices depends upon many factors including your age and 
gender, overall
 exercise and activity level, any medications you may be taking 
(including
 insulin or others), and whether 
or not you are trying to
 lose weight , among other factors. Some meal planning tools and guidelines include: The plate method (
 MyPlate ) Glycemic index Counting carbohydrates Most doctors and health care professionals agree that patients with diabetes can 
eat most of the same foods and meals as the 
rest of the family with some added attention to timing of meals and portion 
sizes. As in any healthy diet, it is best to consume a variety of foods. There 
are numerous recipes and apps if you need ideas for healthy foods to eat. Healthy eating includes eating a wide variety of foods including: Vegetables Whole grains Fruits Non-fat dairy products Beans Lean meats, poultry, and fish One example of a diabetic meal plan for people who also have elevated
 cholesterol levels is known as the TLC (Therapeutic Lifestyle Changes) plan. 
This meal plan is designed to help you manage your disease and by lowering your cholesterol level and 
helping you lose 
weight. The TLC diet is defined as follows: Limit fat to 25%-35% of total daily 
calories, getting no more than 7% of your daily calories from saturated fat, 10% 
or less from
 polyunsaturated fats , and up to 20% from monounsaturated fats (like 
plant oils or nuts). Carbohydrates should account for no more than 50%-60% of 
your daily calories. Try to eat 20-30 grams of fiber each 
day. Allow 15%-20% of your daily calories 
for protein. Limit cholesterol to 200 milligrams 
per day.
 How many carbs, fats, and proteins can I eat on a healthy diabetic meal plan? The number of carbohydrates (carbs), fats, and proteins in your plan will 
depend upon the ideal number of calories you should consume each day. Your age, 
gender, the amount of exercise you get, and your activity level affect the number of calories you need to eat in 
order to gain, lose, or maintain a healthy weight. A high-fiber diet has been shown to improve blood sugar and cholesterol 
levels in people with
 type 2 diabetes . Fiber can be found in many foods, 
especially whole grains, beans, vegetables, nuts, and fruits. Can I have sugar on a diabetic meal plan? Most doctors and other medical or health care professional believe that people on a diabetic diet can have small amounts of 
sugar, so long as they are part of a healthy and balanced
 nutrition strategy. Table sugar 
does not raise blood glucose more than starches. Can I have alcohol on a diabetic diet? It may be OK for some people with diabetes to drink alcohol in 
moderation. It is best to drink alcohol when your blood sugar levels are under 
good control, and it is important to remember that wine and mixed
 drinks contain 
sugar, and alcohol has a lot of calories. Your doctor or health care 
professional can tell you if alcohol 
can be a safe part of your meal plan. What foods raise blood sugar levels? The extent to which carbohydrates raise blood sugar levels is known as their 
glycemic index.
 High glycemic index foods raise glucose levels faster and to 
a greater degree than
 low glycemic index foods . High glycemic index foods include: White bread, bagels Short-grain white rice Corn flakes or puffed rice cereal Russet potatoes Saltine crackers, pretzels, rice cakes Pumpkin Melons Pineapple Popcorn What foods help maintain good blood sugar levels? These foods can fill you up without dramatic rises in blood 
glucose levels, for example: 100% stone-ground whole wheat or 
pumpernickel bread Rolled or steel-cut oatmeal Converted rice, barley, bulgur Sweet potato,
 corn , yam, lima/butter 
beans, peas, legumes and lentils Many fruits Non-starchy vegetables (these contain fewer carbohydrates than starchy 
 vegetables) Proteins and fiber can also help you feel full without raising blood sugar 
levels as much as carbohydrates.
</first>
</file1>