<file1>
<first>Ulcerative Colitis Diet Plan
What is ulcerative colitis? Ulcerative colitis (UC) is a chronic condition that causes inflammation of the
 large intestine (colon) and the rectum and sores (ulcers) on the inner lining of the large intestine.
 Ulcerative colitis is thought to be an autoimmune disease, that is, one where the body attacks itself. It is a type of
 inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). It is not the same as
 Crohn&amp;#39;s disease , another type of IBD, which can affect any part of the gastrointestinal tract, whereas
 ulcerative colitis only affects the colon and rectum. It is also not the same as
 irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), which affects how the colon functions and does not cause inflammation. Ulcerative colitis is estimated to affect nearly 907,000 Americans, and it affects males slightly more often than females. The disease is most commonly diagnosed between the ages of 15 and 40. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of ulcerative colitis include feeling an 
urgent need to take a bowel movement, fatigue , abdominal pain and cramping, diarrhea , loss of appetite , weight loss , rectal bleeding and anemia (low red 
blood cell count). 
CAUSES:  The cause of ulcerative colitis is unknown but it is believed to be caused by 
a combination of several factors including an overactive immune system, 
genetics, and the environment. Overactive immune system: It is believed that in ulcerative colitis, the 
immune system is triggered to mistakenly attack the inner lining of the large 
intestine, causing inflammation and symptoms of ulcerative colitis. Genetics: Ulcerative colitis 
can run in families. The genetic link is not entirely clear but studies show 
that up to 20% of people with ulcerative colitis have a close family member with the disease. Environment: Certain environmental factors including taking certain medications 
 (nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs or
 NSAIDs , antibiotics, and oral 
contraceptives), and eating a high fat
 diet may slightly increase the risk of 
developing ulcerative colitis. Physical or e
 motional stress , and certain foods do not cause ulcerative 
colitis, however, they may trigger symptoms in a person who has ulcerative 
colitis.
 What is an ulcerative colitis diet? A person with ulcerative colitis may find they need to modify their
 diet to 
help manage their symptoms. There is not a single diet or meal plan that fits 
everyone with ulcerative colitis, and diets are individualized for each patient. Depending on 
symptoms different types of diets may be recommended, such as: A high-calorie diet: Many people with ulcerative colitis
 lose weight and can 
develop signs of malnutrition. A high calorie diet may prevent these problems. A 
lactose-free diet: People with ulcerative colitis may also have
 lactose intolerance . A low-fat 
diet: Ulcerative colitis may interfere with fat absorption and eating fatty 
foods may trigger symptoms. This is often recommended during an ulcerative 
 colitis flare. A 
low-fiber diet  (
 low-residue 
 diet ): This can help reduce the frequency of bowel movements and 
abdominal cramps. A low-salt diet: This diet is used when patients are on 
corticosteroid therapy to help reduce water retention. A low FODMAP diet: FODMAP 
stands for Fermentable Oligo-Di-Monosaccha-rides and Polyols, which are types of 
sugars found in certain carbohydrates and sugar alcohols. This diet is used in 
people who have intolerance to FODMAPS. A
 gluten-free diet : People with ulcerative colitis may 
also be sensitive to gluten. Attention to
 nutrition is important for patients with ulcerative colitis, as 
the symptoms of
 diarrhea and bleeding can lead to
 dehydration , electrolyte 
imbalance, and loss of nutrients. It may be necessary to take
 nutritional supplements if your symptoms do not allow you to eat a nutritionally balanced 
diet. Talk to your health-care professional about what supplements to take. Many people with 
ulcerative colitis find it easiest to eat smaller, more frequent meals rather 
than a few large ones. This can also help increase the
 nutrition absorbed from 
the foods you eat.
 19 trigger foods to avoid with an ulcerative colitis diet plan Dietary choices do not cause ulcerative colitis, but certain foods can 
trigger and worsen symptoms. Learning to identify trigger foods can help reduce 
the frequency and severity of ulcerative colitis symptoms. Not all people with ulcerative 
colitis have the same 
triggers, but a list of some of the most common include: What foods help manage and soothe ulcerative colitis flares? Avoiding foods that trigger ulcerative colitis symptoms is one way to help 
manage symptoms through diet. Another is knowing what foods to eat that may help 
relieve flares. Following is a list of foods that may help soothe ulcerative 
colitis flares: Salmon and albacore tuna contain
 omega-3 fatty acids , which can help reduce inflammation during a flare and may 
help you to stay in remission. Other sources of omega-3s include mackerel, 
herring, sardines,
 flaxseed oil , ground flaxseed, and walnuts. Some people may 
be unable to eat whole nuts and flaxseeds during a flare, but they may be 
tolerated if ground up. Lean meats and poultry are recommended 
following flares of ulcerative because proteins are often lost. Increasing your 
protein intake can help replenish the nutrients lost during a flare. Eggs are another great source of 
protein, and are often well-tolerated even during flares. Some eggs are 
fortified with
 omega-3 fatty acids , which can help 
 reduce inflammation. Soy-based protein can be substituted 
for animal protein in vegetarians and vegans. Other good sources of non-animal 
proteins include legumes and whole grains. Probiotics , usually found in yogurt, 
kefir, sauerkraut, and miso, are good bacteria that can aid in
 digestion . Choose 
yogurts that are low in added sugars, as sugar can aggravate ulcerative colitis 
symptoms. Avocados are an excellent source of 
protein and
 healthy fats . They are calorie dense, but because they are about 70% 
water, they are easily digested. Unsweetened applesauce is bland and may 
be tolerated after an ulcerative colitis flare, though some people may find it 
difficult to tolerate during a flare-up. Instant oatmeal contains refined grains 
and is often easier than steel cut or old-fashioned oatmeal because it has a 
little less fiber. Squash is a healthy choice that is 
usually well-tolerated during an ulcerative colitis flare. It&amp;#39;s full of fiber,
 vitamin C , and beta carotene. Any variety of squash (butternut, zucchini, 
spaghetti, acorn, winter, and summer) are best tolerated cooked. Raw squash may 
aggravate ulcerative colitis symptoms during a flare. Juice and smoothies can be tolerated by 
some during a flare, and can help you maintain good nutrition. Carrot juice is 
chock full of
 vitamin A and antioxidants and many 
 people with ulcerative colitis find it easy to 
tolerate. Plantains , which are a variety of 
banana, can help aid digestion.
 How can I track foods that cause flare-ups and trigger symptoms of my 
ulcerative colitis? The Crohn&amp;#39;s and Colitis Foundation of America recommends people with 
ulcerative colitis to keep a food journal to keep track of what they eat. Note 
what you eat and drink, and how you feel afterwards, noting any symptoms that 
arise. Start to keep a list of any foods you suspect may trigger or aggravate 
your ulcerative
 colitis symptoms . A food diary will also help you figure out if 
you are getting adequate nutrition, and can help your doctor or dietician 
determine the right diet for you to manage your symptoms and prevent flares. The Crohn&amp;#39;s and Colitis Foundation of America also has an interactive food 
tracking tool. It is available online or as a mobile app.
 www.ccfa.org/gibuddy What other things trigger ulcerative colitis symptoms and flare-ups? In addition to foods that trigger ulcerative colitis flare-ups, there are 
certain environmental risk factors that may also trigger flares. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, or NSAIDs (
 aspirin ,
 ibuprofen [Advil, Motrin, Nuprin],
 naproxen [Naproxen]) may cause colitis or worsen the condition. NSAIDs increase the 
occurrence of
 bloody diarrhea ,
 weight loss ,
 iron deficiency anemia , and
 abdominal pain . Where you live may predispose you to a higher incidence of 
ulcerative colitis. Ulcerative colitis is found more commonly in developed countries, urban 
areas, and northern climates. The highest rates for ulcerative colitis are reported in the 
United States, Denmark, and Iceland. Stress does not cause ulcerative colitis 
but it can make symptoms worse.
 Stress management techniques can be important in 
managing your ulcerative colitis symptoms. Not taking medications or improper dosing of 
medications that are used to treat ulcerative colitis can bring on a flare. 
Medications for ulcerative colitis must be taken regularly, even when you feel well. Take 
medications as prescribed. Do not skip doses, cut doses, or increase doses. Antibiotics may cause diarrhea in some people. If you have an infection, tell 
your doctor to figure out the right antibiotic for you. You may also take a 
probiotic along with the antibiotic to help prevent diarrhea. Which specialties of health-care professionals prescribe an ulcerative 
colitis diet? A gastroenterologist is a specialist in disorders of the digestive tract and 
can prescribe a diet for ulcerative colitis. In addition, dietitians and 
nutritionists who are familiar with the disorder may also help create a diet and 
meal plan to manage ulcerative colitis.
</first>
</file1>