<file1>
<first>Diffuse Idiopathic Skeletal Hyperostosis (DISH or Forestier's Disease)
Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) facts DISH is characterized by unique, flowing calcification along the sides of the contiguous vertebrae of the spine. Symptoms of DISH include intermittent pains and
 stiffness in the areas of the bony changes of the spine and inflamed tendons. DISH is diagnosed when the characteristic flowing calcifications are detected with images of the spine, such as in plain film X-ray methods. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications (
 NSAIDs ) can be helpful in both relieving
 pain and inflammation of DISH. What is diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis? Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) is considered a form of
 degenerative arthritis or
 osteoarthritis . However, DISH is characterized by unique, flowing calcification along the sides of the contiguous vertebrae of the spine. And, very unlike typical degenerative
 arthritis , it&amp;#39;s also commonly associated with inflammation (tendinitis) and calcification of tendons at their attachments points to bone. This can lead to the formation of
 bone spurs , such as
 heel spurs . In fact, heel spurs are common among individuals with DISH. DISH has also been called Forestier&amp;#39;s disease. 
CAUSES:  It is not known what causes DISH. DISH is associated with the
 metabolic syndrome and is more frequent in people with
 diabetes mellitus .
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of DISH include intermittent pains in the areas of the bony changes of the spine and inflamed tendons. Stiffness and dull
 pain , particularly in the upper and lower back, are common. Sometimes pains in these areas can be sharp with certain body movements, such as twisting or bending over. DISH is only slowly progressive. Calcifications between the vertebrae occur over many years. This calcification can lead to limitation of motion of the involved areas of the spine. 
DIAGNOSIS:  DISH is diagnosed when the characteristic flowing calcifications are detected with images of the spine, such as in plain film X-ray methods. 
TREATMENT:  Because areas of the spine and tendons can become inflamed, anti-inflammatory medications (NSAIDs), such as
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ,
 Motrin ) and
 naproxen (
 Aleve ), can be helpful in both relieving pain and inflammation of DISH. It is hoped that by minimizing inflammation in these areas, further calcification of tendons and ligaments of the spine leading to calcific bony outgrowths (
 osteophytes ) will be prevented. What is the outlook (prognosis) for patients with diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis? DISH often causes no symptoms, and the long-term outlook is generally good. DISH can lead to limitation of range of motion of the spine. There is no associated threat to any internal organs with this disorder. Rarely, large bone spurs can form in front of the spinal vertebrae of the neck. These spurs occasionally interfere with the passage of food through the upper
 esophagus (swallowing tube).
 
PREVENTION:  There is no prevention of DISH.
</first>
</file1>