<file1>
<first>Earthquake Kit Supplies and Emergency Preparedness
Being prepared for an earthquake While California has been the state most 
 prone to serious earthquakes in recent years, there are many other fault 
 zones in other areas of the United States. For example, geologists and 
 seismologists have predicted a 97 percent chance of a major earthquake in 
 the New Madrid seismic zone of the central United States (including 
 Arkansas, Missouri, Tennessee, and Kentucky) between now and the year 2035. 
 While earthquakes with the power of the one that hit the greater Los Angeles 
 area in January 1994 are fairly rare, less severe earthquakes can interrupt 
 your normal living patterns and cause substantial injury. During a major earthquake, you may hear a roaring or rumbling sound that 
 gradually grows louder. You may feel a rolling sensation that starts out 
 gently and, within a second or two, grows violent. Or, you may first be jarred by a violent jolt. A second or two later, you may 
feel shaking and find it difficult to stand up or move from one room to another. The real key to surviving an earthquake and reducing your risk of injury lies 
in planning, preparing, and practicing what you and your family will do if it 
happens. Earthquake practice drills By planning and practicing what to do if an 
earthquake strikes, you and your family can learn to react correctly and 
automatically when the shaking begins. During an earthquake, most deaths and 
injuries are caused by collapsing building materials and heavy falling objects, 
such as bookcases, cabinets, and heating units. Learn the safe spots in each 
room of your home. If you have children, get the entire family to practice going 
to these locations. Participating in an earthquake drill will help children 
understand what to do in case you are not with them during an earthquake. Make sure you and your child also understand the school's emergency 
procedures for disasters. This will help you coordinate where, when, and how to 
reunite with your child after an earthquake. During your earthquake drill: Get under a sturdy table or desk and hold on to it.
 If you're not near a table or desk, cover your face and head with your 
arms; and
 stand or crouch in a strongly supported doorway, or
 brace yourself in an inside corner of the house or building.
 Stay clear of windows or glass that could shatter or objects that could 
fall on you.
 Remember: If inside, stay inside. Many people are injured at entrances of 
buildings by falling debris.
 Earthquake evacuation plans If an earthquake occurs, you may 
need to evacuate a damaged area afterward. By planning and practicing for 
evacuation, you will be better prepared to respond appropriately and efficiently 
to signs of danger or to directions by civil authorities. Take a few minutes with your family to discuss a home evacuation plan. 
Sketch a floor plan of your home; walk through each room and discuss evacuation 
details.
 Plan a second way to exit from each room or area, if possible. If you need 
special equipment, such as a rope ladder, mark where it is located.
 Mark where your emergency food, water,
 first aid kits, and fire extinguishers are located.
 Mark where the utility switches or valves are located so that they can be 
turned off, if possible.
 Indicate the location of your family's emergency outdoor meeting place. How to establish 
priorities and personal documentation paperwork Establish Priorities Take time before an earthquake strikes to write an emergency priority list, 
including: important items to be hand-carried by you
 other items, in order of importance to you and your family
 items to be removed by car or truck if one is available
 things to do if time permits, such as locking doors and windows, turning 
off the utilities, etc. Write Down Important Information Make a list of important information and put it in a secure location. Include 
on your list: important telephone numbers, such as police, fire, paramedics, and medical 
centers
 the names, addresses, and telephone numbers of your insurance agents, 
including policy types and numbers
 the telephone numbers of the electric,
 gas , and water companies
 the names and telephone numbers of neighbors
 the name and telephone number of your landlord or property manager
 important medical information, such as
 allergies , regular medications, etc.
 the vehicle identification number, year, model, and license number of your 
automobile, boat, RV, etc.
 your bank's or credit union's telephone number, account types, and numbers
 radio and television broadcast stations to tune to for emergency broadcast 
information Gather and Store Important Documents in a Fire-Proof Safe Birth certificates
 Ownership certificates (automobiles, boats, etc.)
 Social Security cards
 Insurance policies
 Wills
 Household inventory, including:
 list of contents
 photographs of contents of every room
 photographs of items of high value, such as jewelry, paintings, collectors' 
items Indoor Safety There are actions you can take, even while an earthquake is happening, that 
will reduce your chances of being hurt. Lights may be out, and hallways, stairs, 
and room exits may be blocked by fallen furniture, ceiling tiles, and other 
debris. Planning for these situations will help you to take action quickly. If an earthquake strikes, you may be able to take cover under a heavy desk or 
table. It can provide you with air space if the building collapses. If you get 
under a table and it moves, try to move with it.
 Inner walls or door frames are the least likely to collapse and may also 
shield against falling objects. If other cover is not available, go to an inner 
corner or doorway, away from windows or glass panels.
 Stay away from glass and hanging objects, and bookcases, china cabinets, or 
other large furniture that could fall. Watch for falling objects, such as bricks 
from fireplaces and chimneys, light fixtures, wall hangings, high shelves, and 
cabinets with doors that could swing open.
 Grab something to shield your head and face from falling debris and broken 
glass.
 If the lights go out, use a battery-operated flashlight. Don't use candles, 
matches, or lighters during or after the earthquake. If there is a gas leak, an 
explosion could result.
 If you are in the kitchen, quickly turn off the stove and take cover at the 
first sign of shaking. High-Rise Buildings Get under a desk and stay away from windows and outside walls. Stay in the 
building. The electricity may go out, and the sprinkler systems may come on.
 DO 
NOT use the elevators. If you are in a crowded public place, do not rush for the doorways. Others 
will have the same idea. Move away from display shelves containing objects that 
may fall. If you can, take cover and grab something to shield your head and face 
from falling debris and glass. Crowded Indoor Public Places If you are in a crowded public place, do not rush for the doorways. Others 
will have the same idea. Move away from display shelves containing objects that 
may fall. If you can, take cover and grab something to shield your head and face 
from falling debris and glass.
 Outdoor Safety If outdoors, move away from buildings and utility wires. The greatest danger 
from falling debris is just outside doorways and close to outer walls. Once in 
the open, stay there until the shaking stops. Automobiles If you are in a moving automobile, stop as quickly and safely as possible and 
move over to the shoulder or curb, away from utility poles, overhead wires, and 
under- or overpasses. Stay in the vehicle, set the parking brake, and turn on 
the radio for emergency broadcast information. A car may jiggle violently on its 
springs, but it is a good place to stay until the shaking stops. If you are in a 
life-threatening situation, you may be able to reach someone with either a 
cellular or an emergency roadside assistance phone. When you drive on, watch for hazards created by the earthquake, such as 
breaks in the pavement, downed utility poles and wires, a fallen overpasses and
 bridges . Emergency supplies for earthquake preparedness Stock up now on emergency supplies that can be used after an earthquake. 
These supplies should include a
 first aid kit, survival kits for the home, 
automobile, and workplace, and emergency water and food. Store enough supplies 
to last at least 3 days. First aid kit Store your first aid supplies in a tool box or fishing tackle box so they 
will be easy to carry and protected from water. Inspect your kit regularly and 
keep it freshly stocked. NOTE: Important medical information and most 
prescriptions can be stored in the refrigerator, which also provides excellent 
protection from fires. Drugs/Medications Hydrogen peroxide to wash and disinfect wounds
 Antibiotic ointment
 Individually wrapped alcohol swabs
 Aspirin and non-aspirin tablets
 Prescriptions and any long-term medications (keep these current)
 Diarrhea medicine
 Eye drops Dressings Bandage strips
 Ace bandages
 Rolled gauze
 Cotton-tipped swabs
 Adhesive tape roll Other First Aid Supplies First aid book
 Scissors
 Tweezers
 Thermometer
 Bar soap
 Tissues
 Sunscreen Paper cups
 Pocket knife
 Small
 plastic bags
 Safety pins
 Needle and thread
 Instant
 cold packs for
 sprains Sanitary napkins
 Splinting materials
 Survival kit for your home Assemble a survival kit for your home with the following items: Tools and supplies ax, shovel, broom
 screwdriver, pliers, hammer, adjustable wrench
 rope for towing or rescue
 plastic sheeting and tape Items for safety and comfort sturdy shoes that can provide protection from broken glass, nails, and 
other debris
 gloves (heavy and durable for cleaning up debris)
 candles
 waterproof matches
 change of clothing
 knife
 garden hose (for siphoning and firefighting)
 tent
 recreational supplies for children and adults
 blankets or sleeping bags
 portable radio, flashlight, and extra batteries
 essential medications and
 eyeglasses fire extinguisher -- multipurpose, dry chemical type
 food and water for pets
 toilet tissue
 cash Survival kit for your automobile Assemble a survival kit for your automobile with the following items. Storing 
some of these supplies in a small bag or backpack will make them more convenient 
to carry if you need to walk. Blankets
 Bottled water
 Change of clothes
 Coins for telephone calls
 Fire extinguisher -- multipurpose, dry chemical type
 First aid kit and manual
 Emergency signal device (light sticks, battery-type flasher, reflector, 
etc.)
 Flashlight with fresh batteries
 Food (nonperishable --
 nutrition bars, trail mix, etc.)
 Gloves
 Local map and compass
 Rope for towing, rescue, etc.
 Paper and pencils
 Premoistened towelettes
 Prescription medicines
 Battery-operated radio with fresh batteries
 Small mirror for signaling
 Toilet tissue
 Tools (pliers, adjustable wrench, screwdriver, etc.)
 Whistle for signaling
 Jumper cables
 Duct tape
 Survival kit for your workplace Assemble a survival kit for the workplace with the following supplies: Food (nonperishable --
 nutrition bars, trail mix, etc.)
 Bottled water
 Jacket or sweatshirt
 Pair of sturdy shoes
 Flashlight with fresh batteries
 Battery-operated radio with fresh batteries
 Essential medications
 Blanket
 Small first aid kit
 Extra pair of eyeglasses and/or contact
 lens solution
 Whistle or other signaling device Emergency Water Storage And Purification Following are recommendations for storing and purifying water supplies. The minimum drinking water supply is 1 gallon per 
person per day. You will also need water for food preparation, bathing, brushing
 teeth , and dish washing. Store a 3-5 day supply of water (at least 5 gallons for 
each person).
 Water should be stored in sturdy plastic bottles with tight-fitting lids. 
Rinsed chlorine bleach bottles work well for water storage. Plastic containers 
for juice and milk do not work as well because they tend to crack and leak more 
readily. All containers should be labeled.
 Stored water should be changed every 6 months.
 Avoid placing water containers in areas where toxic substances, such as 
gasoline and pesticides, are present. Vapors may penetrate the plastic over 
time. Do not store water containers in direct sunlight. Select a place with a 
fairly constant, cool temperature. Safe Water Sources In The Home If you do not have enough water stored, there are sources in your home that 
may provide safe, clean water for drinking purposes. Water drained from the water heater faucet, if the water heater has not been 
damaged.
 Water dipped from the tank of the toilet (not the bowl). The water in the 
bowl can be used for pets. Do not use water that has been chemically treated or 
"blue" water.
 Melted ice cubes.
 Canned fruit, vegetable juice, and liquids from other canned goods.
 Water from
 swimming pools and spas can be used for personal hygiene, 
cleaning, and related uses, but not for drinking.
 Unsafe Water Sources Never use water from the sources listed below for drinking. Radiators
 Hot water boilers (home heating system)
 Water beds (fungicides added to the water or chemicals in the vinyl may make 
water unsafe for use) NOTE: Remember that carbonated
 beverages do not meet drinking water 
requirements.
 Caffeinated drinks and alcohol dehydrate the body, which increases 
the need for drinking water. Water for Drinking and Cooking Safe drinking water includes bottled, boiled, or treated water. Your state, 
local, or tribal health department can make specific recommendations for boiling 
or treating drinking water in your area. Here are some general rules concerning 
water for drinking and cooking. Remember: Do not use contaminated water to wash dishes, brush your teeth, wash and 
prepare food, or make ice.
 If you use bottled water, make sure the seal has not been broken. Otherwise, 
water should be boiled or treated before use. Drink only bottled, boiled, or 
treated water until your supply is tested and found safe.
 Boiling water kills harmful bacteria and parasites. Bringing water to a 
rolling
 boil for 1 minute will kill most organisms.
 If you can't boil water, you can treat water with chlorine tablets,
 iodine tablets, or unscented household chlorine bleach (5.25% sodium hypochlorite). If 
you use chlorine tablets or iodine tablets, follow the directions that come with 
the tablets. If you use household chlorine bleach, add 1/8 teaspoon (~0.75 
milliliter [mL]) of bleach per gallon of water if the water is clear. For cloudy 
water, add 1/4 teaspoon (~1.50 mL) of bleach per gallon. Mix the solution 
thoroughly and let it stand for about 30 minutes before using it. Treating water 
with chlorine tablets, iodine tablets, or liquid bleach will not kill many 
parasitic organisms. Boiling is the best way to kill these organisms. Containers for water should be rinsed with a bleach solution before using and 
reusing. Use water storage tanks and other types of containers with caution. For 
example, fire truck storage tanks, as well as previously used cans or bottles, 
can be contaminated with microbes or chemicals.
 Emergency Food Keep foods that:
 have a long storage life
 require little or no cooking, water, or refrigeration, in case utilities are 
disrupted
 meet the needs of
 babies or other family members who are on
 special diets meet pets' needs
 are not very salty or spicy, as these foods increase the need for drinking 
water, which may be in short supply How To Store Emergency Food A disaster can easily disrupt the food supply at any time, so plan to have at 
least a 3-day supply of food on hand.
 When storing food, it is not necessary to buy dehydrated or other types of 
emergency food. Canned foods and dry mixes will remain fresh for about 2 years.
 Certain storage conditions can enhance the shelf life of canned or dried 
foods. The ideal location is a cool, dry, dark place. The best temperature is 40 
to 60°F. Keep foods away from ranges or refrigerator exhausts. Heat causes many 
foods to spoil more quickly.
 Keep food away from petroleum products, such as gasoline, oil, paints, and 
solvents. Some food products absorb their smell.
 Protect food from rodents and insects. Items stored in boxes or in paper 
cartons will keep longer if they are heavily wrapped or stored in airtight 
containers. Date all food items. Use and replace food before it loses freshness. How To Use Emergency Food Use perishable food in your refrigerator or freezer before using food in your 
emergency supplies.
 Discard cooked, unrefrigerated foods after 2 hours at room temperature, 
regardless of appearance.
 Eat only foods that have a normal color, texture, and odor.
 Discard cans that bulge at the ends or that are leaking. Preparing Food Preparing food after an earthquake may be complicated by damage to your home 
and loss of electricity, gas, and water. The following items will help you to 
prepare meals safely: Cooking utensils
 Knives, forks, and spoons
 Paper plates, cups, and towels
 A manual can- and bottle-opener
 Heavy-duty aluminum foil
 Gas or charcoal grill; camp stove
 Fuel for cooking, such as charcoal. (CAUTION: Never burn charcoal indoors. 
The fumes are deadly when concentrated indoors.) NOTE: Do not use your fireplace for cooking until the chimney has been 
inspected for cracks and damage. Sparks may escape into your attic through an 
undetected crack and start a fire.
</first>
</file1>