<file1>
<first>Essential Mixed Cryoglobulinemia
What is cryoglobulinemia? Cryoglobulinemia is a medical condition that is caused by proteins called cryoglobulins, which are present in the blood. Cryoglobulins are abnormal proteins that by definition have the unusual property of precipitating from the serum when it is chilled in the laboratory and then dissolves back into the serum upon rewarming. Cryoglobulins may or may not cause disease. Cryoglobulins can accompany another condition (such as
 dermatomyositis ,
 multiple myeloma , viral infections, or
 lymphoma ) or be an isolated condition themselves, called cryoglobulinemia. What conditions are associated with cryoglobulinemia? Cryoglobulins in the blood (cryoglobulinemia) can cause a variety of problems throughout the body. These include complications resulting from abnormal "thickness" of the blood (such as
 stroke or
 blood clots in the eyes leading to
 blindness ) and inflammation of blood vessels, referred to as
 vasculitis . Vasculitis of arteries can result in blockage of blood flow, leading to damage to the organ(s) supplied by the affected blood vessels, such as in the skin, kidneys, or elsewhere. It can also cause bleeding when the blood vessels leak. What is essential mixed cryoglobulinemia? When the cryoglobulin proteins are a mixture of various antibody types, and forming for unknown reasons (essential), the conditions is referred to as essential mixed cryoglobulinemia. Essential mixed cryoglobulinemia is characterized by joint pains and swelling (
 arthritis ), enlargement of the spleen, skin vasculitis with purplish patches, and nerve and
 kidney disease . This can lead to recurrent
 pain in the abdomen,
 heart attack , and bleeding in the
 lungs .
 Weight loss can occur as well as poor appetite. Essential mixed cryoglobulinemia is sometimes associated with
 hepatitis C virus infection.
 What is the prognosis (outlook) for patients with essential mixed
cryoglobulinemia? The prognosis and natural history of the illness is not predictable. Kidney damage can be serious and 
some reports state that permanent failure of the kidney occurs in approximately 10% of patients. Death can occur, usually from serious
 heart disease , infection, or
 brain hemorrhage . How is essential mixed cryoglobulinemia treated? Essential mixed cryoglobulinemia is treated with combinations of medications which reduce inflammation and suppress the immune system. Medications used include nonsteroid antiinflammatory
 drugs (
 ibuprofen ,
 aspirin , and others), steroids (
 prednisone ,
 prednisolone ),
 cyclophosphamide (
 Cytoxan ),
 chlorambucil (
 Leukeran ), and
 azathioprine (Imuran). Plasmapheresis (
 hemapheresis ), a procedure whereby the blood&amp;#39;s serum is filtered to remove the cryoglobulins, is also performed for severe symptoms. Studies have demonstrated some benefit of using
 interferon -alpha for those patients with evidence of
 hepatitis C virus, particularly those with mild disease or in those with remission of manifestations after immune suppression treatment.
</first>
</file1>