<file1>
<first>Estimating Breast Cancer Risk: Questions and Answers
1. Who develops breast cancer? Breast cancer is the most frequently diagnosed non-
 skin cancer in American 
women. An estimated 213,000 American women will be diagnosed with
 breast cancer in 2006. The risk of
 breast cancer increases as women get older. Over the years, 
researchers have identified certain characteristics, usually called risk 
factors, which influence a woman's chance of getting the disease. Still, many 
women who develop breast
 cancer have no known risk factors other than growing 
older, and many women with known risk factors do not develop breast
 cancer . 2. What is the Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool? The Breast
 Cancer Risk Assessment Tool is a computer program that was 
developed by scientists at the National Cancer Institute and the National 
Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP) to assist health care 
providers in discussing breast cancer risk with their female patients. The tool 
allows a health professional to project a woman's individual estimate of breast 
cancer risk over a 5-year period of time and over her lifetime and compares the 
woman's risk calculation with the average risk for a woman of the same age. The 
Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool can be found at:
 http://www.cancer.gov/bcrisktool . 3. 
RISKS:  The risk factors included in the tool are: Personal history of breast abnormalities . Two breast tissue
 abnormalities -- ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) and lobular
 carcinoma in situ
 (LCIS) -- are associated with increased risk for developing invasive breast cancer. Age . The 
risk of developing breast cancer increases with age. The majority of breast 
cancer cases occur in women older than age 50. Age at menarche (first menstrual 
period). Women who had their first
 menstrual period before age 12 have a 
slightly increased risk of breast cancer. Age at first live birth . Risk depends 
on age at first live birth and family history of breast cancer, as shown in the 
following table of relative risks. For women with 0 or 1 affected relative, risks increase with age at first 
live birth. For women with 2 or more first degree relatives, risks decrease with 
age at first live birth. Adapted from Table 1, Gail MH, Brinton LA, Byar DP, Corle DK, Green SB, 
Shairer C, Mulvihill JJ: Projecting individualized probabilities of developing 
breast cancer for white females who are being examined annually. J Natl Cancer 
Inst 81(24):1879-86, 1989. [PubMed Abstract] Breast cancer among first-degree relatives (sisters, mother, daughters) . 
Having one or more first-degree blood relatives who have been diagnosed with 
breast cancer increases a woman's chances of developing the disease. Breast 
biopsies . Women who have had breast biopsies have an increased risk of breast 
cancer, especially if the biopsy showed a change in breast tissue, known as 
atypical hyperplasia. These women are at increased risk because of whatever 
prompted the biopsies, not because of the biopsies themselves. Race . White women 
have greater risk of developing breast cancer than Black women (although Black 
women diagnosed with breast cancer are more likely to die of the disease).
 4. 
RISKS:  Other risk factors for 
breast cancer have been identified or proposed but are not included in the 
Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool for several reasons: because evidence that 
these factors contribute to breast cancer risk is not conclusive, because 
researchers cannot determine whether these factors add useful information to 
factors already in the model, or because data on other risk factors was not 
available in the research data used to develop the model. Such risk factors 
include: age at
 menopause , use of
 birth control pills , high
 body mass index , a 
high-fat
 diet , alcohol,
 radiation exposure, and environmental pollutants. 
Recently published research indicates that breast tissue density, measured from 
mammograms, can add useful information, but risk models with breast tissue 
density measurement still need to be validated with additional independent 
studies. Research also indicates that other risk factors, such as use of hormone 
therapy, might improve the tool. 5. Is the Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool useful for all women? The Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool was developed for women in the United 
States population age 35 years or older. It should not be used for women with a 
previous diagnosis of breast cancer, women exposed to breast radiation for 
treatment of Hodgkin
 lymphoma , or women who reside in, or recently migrated 
from, regions with low breast cancer risk, such as rural China or Japan. More 
accurate methods to project risk may be available for women with certain rare 
identified mutations, such as alterations in the breast cancer susceptibility 
genes
 BRCA1 and
 BRCA2 . The Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool was developed and 
has been validated in populations consisting mainly of non-Hispanic white women. 
More research is needed to validate or refine the model for other racial and 
ethnic groups.
 6. 
RISKS:  Two studies in the September 6, 2006, issue of the Journal of the National 
Cancer Institute identified breast density as an important risk factor.* In one, 
a study of 11,638 women diagnosed with breast cancer, researchers identified 
different sets of risk factors in pre- and post-menopausal women. For 
pre-menopausal women, the risk factors included age, breast density, family 
history of breast cancer, and prior cancer diagnosis. For post-menopausal women, 
the risk factors included ethnicity, body mass index, age at
 natural menopause , 
use of
 hormone therapy , and a prior false-positive
 mammogram , in addition to all 
the risk factors for pre-menopausal women. The two separate models in this study 
for predicting breast cancer in pre- and post-menopausal women may be 
particularly helpful in identifying women at high risk for breast cancer. The other study adds breast density and weight to the Gail model, a model 
that is the basis for the Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool (see Question 2). 
As before, the new model can be used to project risk over 5, 10, 20 and 30 year 
intervals. The new model predicted higher risks than the previous model in women 
with high breast density, and previous analyses indicated that the new model had 
modestly higher accuracy. Independent validation studies are needed before this 
model should be used for counseling, and before making a permanent change to the 
Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool. 7. Are there ways to decrease the chance of developing breast cancer? Launched in April 1992, the
 Breast Cancer Prevention Trial (BCPT) was 
designed to see whether the drug
 tamoxifen could prevent breast cancer in women 
with an increased risk. Data reported in 1998 showed that both pre- and 
post-menopausal women taking tamoxifen had 49 percent fewer diagnosed cases of 
breast cancer. These results were also the first clear indication that a 
chemopreventive agent could be effective in preventing cancer in a high-risk 
population. For women over 50, tamoxifen was associated with serious side 
effects, such as
 endometrial cancer and
 blood clots . (http://www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/factsheet/
 Prevention /breast-cancer) Starting in 1999,
 postmenopausal women ages 35 or older at increased risk for 
breast cancer participated in the Study of Tamoxifen and
 Raloxifene (STAR). The 
study compared tamoxifen with raloxifene, an
 osteoporosis drug. The initial 
results of the trial were announced on April 17, 2006 (see
 http://www.cancer.gov/newscenter/pressreleases/STARresultsApr172006 ), 
and showed that the drug raloxifene works as well as tamoxifen in reducing 
breast cancer risk for postmenopausal women at increased risk of the disease. In 
STAR, both
 drugs reduced the risk of developing invasive breast cancer by about 
50 percent. In addition, within the study, women who were prospectively and 
randomly assigned to take raloxifene daily, and who were followed for an average 
of about four years, had 36 percent fewer uterine cancers and 29 percent fewer 
blood clots than the women who were assigned to take tamoxifen. Uterine cancers, 
especially endometrial cancers, are a rare but serious side effect of tamoxifen. 
Both tamoxifen and raloxifene are known to increase a woman's risk of blood 
clots. Data from STAR continues to be analyzed. (
 http://www.cancer.gov/newscenter/pressreleases/STARresultsQandA )
 8. 
RISKS:  Both breast
 cancer prevention studies, BCPT and STAR, explored ways of 
reducing the risk of developing breast cancer; their findings have increased our 
knowledge of risk. Both trials involved women who have not had breast cancer, 
but were at high risk of developing it. BCPT used the Breast Cancer Risk 
Assessment Tool to determine eligible participants by projecting each woman's 
individualized estimate of breast cancer risk. The projections were accurate; 
thus the BCPT results validated the Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool. STAR 
researchers used the Breast Cancer Risk Assessment Tool for determining 
eligibility for enrollment. All STAR participants had to have an increased risk 
of breast cancer equivalent to or greater than that of an average 60- to 
64-year-old woman. 9. What else can a woman do about breast cancer? NCI recommends that women in their 40s and older get screening mammograms 
every one to two years. Women who are at higher than average risk of breast 
cancer should talk with their health care providers about whether to have 
mammograms before age 40 and how often to have them. Women also can take an 
active part in the early detection of breast cancer by having regular clinical 
breast exams (breast exams performed by health professionals). Advances in screening have provided new tools for detection. In September of 
2005, preliminary results from a large clinical trial of digital vs. film
 mammography found no difference in detecting breast cancer for the general 
populations of women in the trial. However, the Digital Mammographic Imaging 
Screening Trial (DMIST) found that women with dense breasts, who are pre- or 
perimenopausal (women who had a
 last menstrual period within 12 months of their 
mammograms), or who are younger than age 50, may benefit from having a digital 
rather than a regular film mammogram. More information about DMIST can be found 
at
 http://www.cancer.gov/newscenter/pressreleases/DMISTQandA . Source: U.S. National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute,
 http://www.cancer.gov</first>
</file1>