<file1>
<first>Breast Self-Exam
Breast self-exam
facts A breast self-exam is a woman's 
examination of her breasts for any changes or abnormalities. Although some women prefer to do breast 
self-exams, their value in detecting early cancers and in saving lives from
 breast cancer is controversial. For this reason, many medical organizations do 
not specifically recommend that women do breast self-exams. Mammography is the best way to detect 
early breast cancers. Breast self-exam is an option for women 
who choose to perform this exam. Breast self-exam involves looking for 
both changes in appearance and changes in feel of the breasts. Any changes noticed on breast self-exam 
should be discussed with a doctor. Most
 breast lumps are benign (are not 
cancerous). What is a breast self-exam? A breast self-exam is a woman's examination of her own breasts. Breast 
self-exams were formerly encouraged to help women detect
 breast cancer , but 
experts and medical organizations do not agree about whether this is necessary 
or helps save lives. Many women feel comfortable doing breast self-exams as a 
way to monitor their own health. Is a breast self-exam
necessary? As mentioned, agencies that issue health practice guidelines do not agree on 
whether doing breast self-exams are helpful in terms of
 cancer detection or 
saving lives from
 cancer . The best way to detect
 breast cancer is by having 
regular mammograms combined with a breast examination by a health care 
professional. According to the American
 Cancer Society, breast self exam is an option for 
women starting in their 20s, but women should be informed about the limitations 
as well as the benefits of this practice. According to the ACS, "Research has 
shown that BSE plays a small role in finding breast cancer compared with finding 
a
 breast lump by chance or simply being aware of what is normal for each woman."
 How should one do a breast self-exam? If you choose to do breast self-exams, your doctor can help show you the best 
technique. Many women find it convenient to do the exam while bathing or 
showering. The best time to do the exam is 3 to 5 days after the start of the
 menstrual period , since the breasts are not as tender or lumpy at this time of 
the cycle. Women who no longer have menstrual periods should do the exam about 
the same time each month. Part of a breast self-exam involves examination of the appearance of the 
breasts in a mirror. For this step, it is best to stand in front of a mirror and 
examine your breasts in different positions: with your arms relaxed by your 
side, with your hands pressed down on your hips, leaning forward with chest 
muscles tightened, and with hands behind the head and chest muscles tightened. 
Turning from side to side may be helpful to view all angles. Look for any 
changes like sores on the skin, dimpling or puckering of the skin, or changes in 
skin color. Look for discharge or changes in the skin of the
 nipple areas, as 
well. Don't forget to examine the skin underneath the breasts. Next, use the flat part of the fingers to feel your breasts, following an up 
and down or circular motion until you have examined all breast tissue from 
collarbone to the lower border of the breasts. Examine the armpit areas too 
since these may contain breast tissue. Look for lumps or irregularities in 
density or any changes since your last exam. Feel beneath the nipple for any 
changes. It's best to do this both standing (with your hand on your hip; use the 
opposite hand to do the exam) and while lying down. What if I find a lump or abnormality on my breast self-exam? See your doctor if you find any abnormality or unexplained change in your 
breasts. Most breast lumps are benign (non-cancerous), but it is important to 
have your doctor evaluate any changes you observe during the breast self-exam.
</first>
</file1>