<file1>
<first>Black Eye

ABOUT: A black eye often results from injury to the face or the head, and is 
caused when blood and other fluids collect in the space around the eye. Swelling 
and dark discoloration result in a "black eye." Most black eyes are relatively minor injuries. Many heal on their own in a 
few days, but they may signify a more serious injury. The most common cause of a black eye is a blow to the eye, nose, or 
forehead. Pain and swelling are the most common signs and symptoms of a black eye. Call a doctor if the injured individual has changes in vision, severe
 pain , or swelling that 
does not go away, the swelling around the eyes is not related to an injury, 
 there are signs of infection (for example,
 fever , warmth, redness, pus-like drainage), if 
 the person has behavioral changes, forgetfulness or lethargy,
 nausea ,
 vomiting and/or
 dizziness , loss of vision (especially
 double vision ), or an inability to 
move the eye itself (i.e., unable to look in different directions). Home remedies for black eye include rest and ice applied early after the 
injury help to decrease swelling and pain. Do not use raw meat on an eye injury, 
 this creates potential for infection. Avoid a black eye with basic injury
 prevention . Wear the appropriate 
protective gear for any athletic or work-related activity. Complications include traumatic
 iritis and
 uveitis , 
hyphema,
 glaucoma , orbital floor fracture (blowout fracture), and retinal 
 detachment. Black eye introduction A black eye often results from 
injury to the face or the head, and is caused 
when blood and other fluids collect in the space around the eye. Swelling and 
dark discoloration result in a "black eye" – sometimes called a "shiner." Most black eyes are relatively minor injuries. Many heal on their own in a 
few days, but they may signify a more serious injury. Despite the name, "black eye," the eye itself is not 
usually injured. The tissues around the eye may be significantly discolored and 
swollen without any injury to the eye itself, like a 
bruise (ecchymosis) around the eye. The skin around the eye is very loose, with mostly fat underneath it and fluid 
accumulates easily in this area. The skin around the eye is one of the first 
places to swell when the facial area is injured. Depending on the location and 
type of injury, one or both eyes may be affected. Injuries to the eyebrow, nose, and 
forehead area often result in black eyes because gravity pulls the blood and 
inflammatory fluid into the soft tissues under and around the eyes. As a black eye heals, the swelling around the eye decreases, and the bruise 
gradually fades away. The bruising will usually start out a very dark purple, 
and as it fades, it may change to light purple, then greenish, then yellow 
before disappearing.
 
CAUSES:  The most common cause of a black eye is a blow to the eye, nose, or forehead. 
Depending on where the blow lands, one or both eyes may be affected. A blow to the nose often causes both eyes to swell 
because the swelling from the nasal injury causes fluid to collect in the loose tissues of the eyelids. Other causes of black eye include: surgical procedures to the face, such as a
 facelift , jaw 
surgery, or nose 
surgery; a certain type of
 head injury , called a 
 basilar skull fracture, 
 causes both eyes to swell and blacken; this condition is typically described 
 as "raccoon eyes." Other causes of swelling around the eye include (these conditions do not 
necessarily make the skin turn black and blue around the eye): allergic reactions, bites, cellulitis (
 skin infection around the eye), angioedema (swelling, usually around both eyes), and dental infections.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Edema (swelling) and pain are the most common signs and symptoms of a black eye, 
and may be accompanied by discoloration caused by bruising. Initially, the swelling and discoloration may be mild. The area around the eye often starts 
off slightly reddened, and then progresses to a darker shade and swelling 
increases. Some blurry vision or difficulty opening the eye may occur, but more 
serious visual problems are less common. Over the course of a few days, the area 
becomes lighter and the swelling decreases. Signs of a more serious injury are
 double vision , loss 
of sight, or inability to move the eye.
 Loss of consciousness , blood or clear 
fluid coming out of the nose or the ears, blood on the surface of the eye 
itself, or persistent
 headache can also indicate a severe injury. When should I call the doctor for a black eye? Most black eyes are minor injuries that heal on their own in a few days with ice and OTC pain medications. Depending on the mechanism of injury and accompanying symptoms, an ophthalmologist might have to examine the injured eye to make sure that no significant injury to the eye has occurred. Call a doctor if the patient: experiences changes in vision; has severe pain or swelling that does not go away; has swelling around the eyes that is not related to an injury; has signs of infection (for example,
 fever , warmth, redness, pus-like drainage), has behavioral changes,  has forgetfulness or lethargy, or nausea ,
 vomiting and/or
 dizziness . Patients should consult a health care practitioner any time they are unsure about treatment or concerned about symptoms. Some conditions require immediate medical care. Call 9-1-1 or get to an emergency department immediately in the following situations: the patient experiences changes in or loss of vision (especially double vision); an inability to move the eye itself (i.e., unable to look in different directions); any injury in which an object may have pierced the eye or may be inside the eyeball; if there is obvious blood in the eye itself; if there is deformity to the eye; fluid leaking from the eyeball; there are any lacerations (
 cuts ) to the eye area, face, or head; the patient has signs of a serious head or facial injury; if the black eye is accompanied by broken bones or
 teeth ; loss of consciousness; changes in behavior; nausea, vomiting and/or dizziness; inability to walk; blood or clear fluids coming out of the nose or the ears; patients who take blood thinners, such as
 warfarin (
 Coumadin ), or those with a history of bleeding problems such as
 hemophilia ; swelling after a bee sting near the eye; or from a suspected infection of the eye.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  For most black eyes, a doctor will perform a physical exam and will ask about the injury and look for any associated injuries or symptoms. The physician will shine a light into the patient&amp;#39;s eyes to look at the pupils and inside the eye itself for any injury, and to check for foreign bodies or abrasions on the eye. They will test the motion of the patient&amp;#39;s eye (following the doctor&amp;#39;s finger with his/her eyes), and examine the facial bones around the eye. Depending on what is found, the doctor may perform additional testing. An X-ray or a
 CT scan may be performed if the doctor suspects a fracture to the bones of the face or around the eye (the orbit) or that something is inside the eye. If there are any special concerns, the doctor may refer the patient to a specialist, such as an ophthalmologist (a medical doctor who specializes in
 eye care and surgery), for follow-up care. 
TREATMENT:  Home remedies Home remedies for black eye include rest and ice applied early after the injury help to decrease swelling and pain. Ice helps decrease swelling by constricting blood vessels, by decreasing fluid accumulation, and by cooling and numbing the area. Apply ice for 20 minutes every hour, for the first 24 hours (a package of frozen vegetables such as peas or corn can be used as it will conform to the shape of the face better than ice cubes). To avoid potential
 cold injury to the site, wrap the ice or frozen object in a cloth or use a commercial ice pack. Do not use raw meat on a black eye as putting potentially bacteria-laden meat on a mucous membrane or an open skin injury can be dangerous. For simple, uncomplicated black eyes, the treatment prescribed by health care professionals is similar to home treatment: ice; pain medications such as
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ) or
 ibuprofen (
 Advil ,
 Motrin ) (avoid taking
 aspirin (unless prescribed by your doctor or cardiologist for your heart] because this may increase bleeding); rest; and protection of the injured area. Avoid possibly injurious activities until after the eye has healed. For more complicated injuries, the patient may be referred to an appropriate specialist; such as an ophthalmologist, who can treat the patient&amp;#39;s injuries to the eye itself, or an otorhinolaryngologist (ear, nose, and throat [ENT]), or an oral/maxillofacial surgeon for fractures to the face.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  Black eye in itself usually is a minor condition that 
resolves on its own. Severe injuries, especially forceful blunt
 trauma to the eye area may result in 
complications. Traumatic 
uveitis and 
iritis (iritis is a type of
 uveitis ) results from blunt trauma to 
the eye. A black eye may be the first sign of this condition. Iritis generally 
affects only one eye. Signs and symptoms of uveitis (and iritis) may include: reddened eye (especially 
around the
 iris , the colored part of the eyeball); pain that increases with exposure to bright light; a small or irregularly shaped pupil; floating spots before the eyes; or blurred 
vision. Any of these symptoms 
should be brought to the attention of a physician. Hyphema is an accumulation of blood in the front 
(anterior) chamber of the 
eye following injury and can cause damage to the interior tissues of the eye. 
The amount of blood may be too small to see with the naked eye, or the entire 
front of the eye may fill with blood. Glaucoma may also result from blunt trauma to the eye, 
and can occur immediately or years later. The force of the trauma can cause 
bleeding inside the eye which leads to an increase in eye pressure, and damages 
the
 optic nerve . Delayed onset
 glaucoma (angle recession glaucoma) can occur as
 scar tissue from 
the injury builds in the eye. Orbital floor fracture (blowout fracture) may also occur 
as a result of the forceful blunt trauma to the eye. The force of the blow 
pushes the eyeball further into the eye socket, fracturing the very thin walls 
of bone that make up the eye socket. This can lead to pinching (entrapment) of 
the optic nerve and 
the muscles that move the eye. Loss of vision or double vision can result and 
must be treated emergently. Retinal detachment can result in permanent
 vision loss . 
Trauma to the eye can lift or pull the
 retina from its normal position, lining the back of the 
eyeball. Symptoms include partial or total loss of vision or flashing lights or 
spots in the field of vision and must be treated immediately. 
PREVENTION:  Black eye injury can be avoided with basic injury prevention. Check the home for items that might cause a fall, such as throw rugs or 
objects on the floor (such as toys). Wear the appropriate protective gear for any athletic or work-related 
activity. Wear goggles or other eye protection when working, doing yard work, 
or other hobbies and sports that may be injurious to the eyes. Wear seat belts while driving and wear helmets when riding a motorcycle.
</first>
</file1>