<file1>
<first>E. coli0157:H7 Infection Early Symptoms, Treatment, and Prevention
E. colidefinition and facts Serotype
 E. coli 0157:H7 is a bacterium that can produce
 bloody diarrhea due to toxins, especially Shiga (Vero) toxins that it produces, the toxin is secreted when the bacterium infects the human intestine. Other non-
 E. coli s0157 serotypes like 0145 or 0104:H4 can act like 0157:H7 if they acquire the ability to produce Shiga (Vero) toxin. Some of the early symptoms of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infection may include
 fever ,
 nausea ,
 vomiting , and bloody
 diarrhea Some of the later symptoms of
 E. coli infection are
 nosebleeds ,
 shortness of breath ,
 seizures , and excessive bleeding. E. coli infection is
 contagious and can be spread from person to person by fecal contamination. E. coli 0157:H7 is notorious because it can cause additional complications in children and the elderly;
 renal failure ,
 anemia , and
 dehydration especially for children (termed HUS or
 hemolytic uremic syndrome ) and spontaneous bleeding, organ failure, and mental changes in the elderly (termed TTP or thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura). Some of these patients develop permanent disabilities or die. E. coli 0157:H7 infections that produce late and/or severe symptoms may require a team of specialists to treat the patient Diagnosis is definitively made when
 E. coli 0157:H7 is isolated, usually from the patient&amp;#39;s
 stool , and identified as serotype 0157 with immunologic tests. Most
 E. coli 0157:H7 infections resolve spontaneously and require no treatment. However, supportive treatment is required quickly required if the patient becomes dehydrated,
 anemic , or develops HUS or TTP. The majority of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infections have excellent outcomes. If complications develop such as severe
 dehydration ,
 anemia , HUS or TTP, the outcomes can decline from good to poor quickly. Infection with
 E. coli 0157:H7 usually comes from eating contaminated food (
 food poisoning ).
 Prevention of infection consists of eating cooked foods, especially hamburger, and drinking treated or pasteurized fluids. Avoiding touching or eating any food that may be contaminated with any animal or human waste will help prevent the infection. There is no
 E. coli 0157:H7
 vaccine available for humans.
 What are
E. coli0157:H7 bacteria? Escherichia coli (
 E. coli ) is a bacterium (Enterobacteriaceae family) that can survive in an environment with or without air (facultative anaerobe) and, depending on the environment, may or may not produce thin hair-like structures (flagella or pili) that allow the bacteria to move and to attach to human cells. These bacteria commonly live in the
 intestines of people and in warm blood animals worldwide and do not cause problems. Some
 strains (serotypes) cause diseases that range from
 urinary tract infections to life-threatening, bloody
 diarrhea . It is a gram-negative rod-shaped bacterium. E coli O157:H7 is the predominant serotype of
 E. coli that form one group of
 EEC . This EEC group is termed enterohemorrhagic
 E. coli or EHEC. Unfortunately, other terms in the medical literature describe this group (VTEC or Vero toxin-producing
 E. coli and
 STEC or Shiga toxin-producing
 E. coli ). Research suggests that only a small number of
 E. coli 0157:H7 are needed to cause infection (ingestion of about 10–100 organisms) instead of the thousands to millions needed for infections by other
 E. coli serotypes. Infection is aided by adhesive receptors (pili or fimbriae) that attach the bacteria to human intestinal cells. Most of the problems caused by the bacteria are due to two Shiga toxins, termed Stx 1 and Stx 2 termed Vero toxins. (Toxins are chemicals that are produced by the bacterium and damage human cells.) These toxins, for example, (for example, &lt;/i&gt;E. coli Shiga&lt;/i&gt; toxin), are almost identical to toxins produced by another related bacterium,
 Shigella spp. that causes dysentery (
 Shigellosis ), and can damage and kill intestinal cells. Shigellosis occasionally causes anemia, damage to platelets, and death of cells in other organs, especially the kidneys. E. coli 0157:H7 is a major health problem. It is estimated to cause infection in more than 70,000 individuals a year in the United States, and the U. S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) suggests
 E. coli 0157:H7 is responsible for the majority of
 E. coli outbreaks in the U.S. It has been reported to cause both large as well as small outbreaks. E. coli 0157:H7 diarrheal illness was first recognized when CDC personnel isolated
 E. coli O157:H7 from patients in two separate outbreaks in Oregon and Michigan. The illnesses were associated with eating hamburgers at the
 restaurants of a national chain; some patients experienced hemorrhagic
 colitis (inflammation and bleeding of the colon). Thus, hemorrhagic colitis due to
 E. coli 0157:H7 is commonly referred to as
 hamburger disease . Since that time,
 E. coli 0157:H7 also has been associated with contaminated water, foods, and unpasteurized or incorrectly pasteurized (heat-treated) dairy products. In 2015 an outbreak of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infection occurred in Montana from Costco contaminated rotisserie chicken salad, and resulted in recalls of products from Taylor farms containing celery. In 2017, an outbreak of this strain was linked to Healthy Brand
 Soy nut Butter. The CDC found 32 people from 12 states infected with the bacteria, 12 of which required hospitalization, and nine developed hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS). Twenty-six of the 32 patients infected were younger than 18. The product was recalled, and fortunately, there were no deaths. A widespread outbreak of E. coli 0157:H7 began in April 2018. The source was traced by the CDC to Romaine lettuce and other lettuce produce and distributed from Yuma, Arizona. The bacterial strain is aggressive. Of the 121 identified patients, 1 death and 52 hospitalizations along with 14 people who developed HUS have occurred. The 121 patients have been found in 25 states with the most diagnosed in California and Pennsylvania. The CDC strongly recommends that if you cannot identify where your Romaine lettuce originated, you should not eat it. Restaurants and retailers are advised not to serve or sell romaine lettuce from the Yuma Arizona growing region.
 8 early signs and symptomsof
E. coli0157:H7 infection The early or initial symptoms of
 E. coli O157:H7 infections usually appear about three to five (though occasionally in as few as one day or as many as 10 days) after a person ingests the bacteria; the symptoms include: These symptoms can be seen in infected children and adults.
 17 later symptoms of signs and symptoms of
E. coliinfections The majority of people (especially normal adults) that are infected resolve the infection without antibiotics (self-limiting) in about five to seven days. However, some people (about 10% of people infected and especially children under the age of 5 and the elderly) develop more severe signs and symptoms, and these people usually require hospitalization and aggressive treatment. These patients develop the usual early symptoms listed above, but do not resolve the infection. They develop symptoms that last longer (at least a week) and, if not treated promptly, the infection may lead to disability or death. Later or late symptoms of
 E. coli infections may include: These symptoms or complications fall into three main categories: For most people (about 90%), the infection clears and a good outcome or and prognosis is good. However, if any of the previously mentioned complications occur, the prognosis may range from good to poor. The variable prognosis depends on the severity of the complication, the rapidity of diagnosis and treatment, the response of the individual to adequate treatment and the overall health of the individual. Children and the elderly are at higher risk for adverse outcomes. Strains of
 E. coli 0157:H7 mainly are known to produce gastrointestinal symptoms, Only a few reports of such strains causing
 E. coli urinary tract infections . How do you  get an
E. coli0157:H7 infection (how is it spread)? Most commonly,
 E. coli 0157:H7 comes from eating raw or undercooked ground beef (for example, hamburger) or from drinking raw milk. The bacteria are found in animal feces, particularly cattle feces, and contact with the feces can lead to contamination of many types of food and fluids. In 2010, the FDA recalled several productions of beef, including beef placed in pet food. Less commonly,
 E. coli 0157:H7 can be transmitted from one person to another, usually by direct physical contact. However, a major outbreak in 2018 came from contaminated Romaine lettuce grown in Yuma, Arizona.
 How long can
E. colibacteria live outside of the body? Studies suggest that
 E. coli survival outside of the body of humans and animals depends on environmental variables such as moisture, nutrients like iron and temperature. Some studies suggest
 E. coli survival times may vary from about 12 hours to 2 months or more. Is
E. coli0157:H7
contagious? E. coli 0857:H7 is an infection, and is contagious. It can be spread from person to person by contamination with feces of food or water then is eaten. What causes
E. coliinfection? There are over 700 strains (serotypes) of
 E. coli . Most of the strains of
 E. coli are normal inhabitants of the small intestine and colon and do not cause disease in the intestines. (They are non-pathogenic.) Nevertheless, non-pathogenic
 E. coli can cause disease if they spread outside of the intestines, for example, into the urinary tract (where they cause bladder or kidney infections), or into the blood stream (
 sepsis or
 E. coli in the blood). Other
 E. coli strains (enterovirulent
 E. coli strains or EEC) cause "poisoning" or diarrhea even though they usually remain within the intestine by producing toxins or intestinal inflammation. Four to six groups
 E. coli serotypes comprise EEC.. (Some researchers combine groups.) Their names are derived from descriptions of the characteristics that separate them from the other groups. EHEC (enterohemorrhagic
 E. coli ) ETEC (enterotoxigenic
 E. coli ) EPEC (enteropathogenic
 E. coli ) EIEC (enteroinvasive
 E. coli ) EAEC (enteroadherent
 E. coli ) EAggEC (enteroaggregative
 E. coli ) E. coli were first isolated by T. Escherich in 1885 and were named after him. The over 700 serotypes are identified by small antigenic changes in their surface "O" antigens (lipopolysaccharides or molecules on the bacterial surface of gram-negative bacteria), for example
 E. coli 0157 or
 E. coli 055. These serotypes are identified by immunological tests using antibodies to the antigens. "H" protein antigens (different types of flagella that make the bacteria motile) further distinguish
 E. coli strains. Consequently, a particular
 E. coli strain can be identified as H, followed by a number, and this identifier is added to the "0" name; for example,
 E. coli 0157:H7. Although this name designation seems complicated, researchers and clinicians use these antigenic identifiers to track specific
 E. coli strains that cause outbreaks of disease. As discussed previously,
 E. coli strain,
 E. coli 0157:H7 is notorious for its potential to cause complicated disease in humans; the remainder of this article will focus on this
 E. coli strain. However, it is important to remember other types of
 E. coli produce similar if not identical problems and they too, will be addressed in this article; the newest serotype causing problems is
 E. coli 0145.
 Is there a test for
E. coli? The diagnosis of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infection begins with an accurate history, physical exam, and an analysis of a sample of stool from the patient. A presumptive diagnosis is frequently made if the patient has symptoms of bloody diarrhea and a history of being exposed to persons, foods, or liquids known to be a source of an
 E. coli 0157:H7 outbreak. Because other disease-causing bacteria (for example,
 Shigella and
 Salmonella ) can give patients similar initial symptoms and test negative on bacterial screeing tests like the oxidase test; a definite diagnosis is based on culture of
 E. coli 0157:H7 from the patient&amp;#39;s sample of stool on special culturing plates that then are tested with antiserum (antibodies) that react only with
 E. coli O157H7. Not all clinics or hospitals have the diagnostic antiserum, so the testing may take a few days. In addition to taking a stool sample test, in 2009 the CDC recommended that all patients being screened for community-acquired diarrheal infections have their stool samples analyzed with antisera for Shiga toxins, toxins produced by
 E. coli 0157:H7 , and a few other bacteria, for example,
 E. coli 0104:H4 . This approach may result in faster diagnosis of I infections. Urine samples can be tested, but
 E. coli 0157:H7 infrequently causes urinar tract infections (
 UTIs ) Its renal involvement is mainly due to toxins produced by the bacteria. This approach may result in faster diagnosis of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infections. Urine samples can be tested, but
 E. coli 0157:H7 infrequently causes UTIs. Blood tests such as a
 complete blood count (
 CBC ), and blood levels of
 electrolytes , platelets, blood urea nitrogen (BUN), and
 creatinine (blood tests that measure function of the kidney) are performed periodically to look for the development of HUS or TTP.
 What is the treatment for
E. coli0157:H7? Treatment for
 E. coli 0157:H7 depends on the severity of the disease. Patients, especially healthy adults, often require no treatment for
 E. coli O157:H7 since many infections are self-limited. Moreover, for the acute diarrheal illness, antibiotics have not proven useful. In fact, some studies have shown that antibiotics may increase the chances of developing HUS (up to 17-fold). This effect is thought to occur because the antibiotic damages the bacteria, causing them to release even more toxin. Most investigators suggest antibiotic use only if a patient is septic, that is, there is evidence that the bacterium has spread to parts of the body other than the intestine. In addition, use of
 atropine and diphenoxylate (
 Lomotil ),
 drugs that are commonly used to control diarrhea, also may increase symptoms and trigger complications. In summary, mild infections are treated with the following: Rest Fluid intake Rarely, antibiotics Treatment for severe symptoms of infection and its complications may include: What are the complications of infection with
E. coli0157:H7? Although these conditions have been presented in the symptoms section, they are presented here again because they are actual complications that can occur after the initial disease begins. Patients without these complications usually have excellent outcomes (a good prognosis). Individuals who develop the following complications have outcomes that range from good to poor, depending on their overall health and how quickly they are diagnosed, treated, and respond to treatment.
 Meningitis and/or
 pneumonia are potential complications that may occur when individuals with a weakened immune system (when
 pregnant , in infants or elderly) become infected. The incubation period between exposure to EHEC bacteria, including
 E. coli O157:H7, and the onset of symptoms is usually three to four days but may be longer in some individuals. Symptoms of EHEC infection include severe
 abdominal pain and abdominal tenderness, which often is associated with bloody diarrhea. Curiously, there often is little or no fever. The diarrhea typically lasts for six to eight days. Dehydration and blood loss can lead to death in some patients if not corrected early. Hemolytic-uremic syndrome (HUS) is the most worrisome complication of EHEC infection, especially in children, because it is a serious and potentially fatal complication. "Hemolytic" refers to the breakup of
 red blood cells , which leads to anemia. There also is destruction of platelets, which leads to low blood levels of platelets (
 thrombocytopenia ), which in turn promotes abnormal bleeding. "Uremic" refers to failure of the kidneys. In addition, problems in the brain with seizures and
 coma may occur. Hemolytic-uremic syndrome most commonly affects children under the ages of 10 years and is the most common cause of acute kidney failure in infants and young children. It occurs in about 6% to 10% of hemorrhagic colitis caused by E coli 0157:H7 and usually occurs approximately 7 to 10 days after the onset of diarrhea. Early intervention usually results in better outcomes. Persons infected with
 E. coli 0157:H7, particularly the elderly, can develop a syndrome similar to HUS called thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura or TTP with clotting of blood within small blood vessels; anemia due to fragmentation of red blood cells; and a shortage of platelets (thrombocytopenia) that results in
 easy bruising , neurologic abnormalities, impaired kidney function, and fever. TTP is a serious consequence of
 E. coli 0157:H7 infection that requires early and aggressive treatment since it results in death in about 10% of all patients who develop it.
 How can
E. colibe
prevented? The CDC recommends the following to prevent infections from
 E. coli 0157:H7. Moreover, many researchers suggest that hamburgers ordered in a restaurant should be cooked through and completely so that no pink hamburger meat is visible inside. This cooking reduces the chance that
 E. coli serotypes will remain alive in the meat. All other foods involved in a recall should be put in the trash. No one should attempt to cook the recalled material and eat it, including hamburger meat. Because
 E. coli 0157:H7 is routinely found in the intestines of cattle, companies have developed a vaccine to reduce the number of these bacteria in cattle. The first vaccine for cattle was FDA approved in 2009. There is no vaccine available for
 E. coli 0157:H7 in humans. What kind of doctor(s) treat
E. coli0157:H7 infections? People who develop only acute symptoms that are mild usually do not require a physician because the illness resolves spontaneously. However, for some children, a pediatrician may be notified and/or may want to see the child. If a person develops severe symptoms, a team of doctors that may include a nephrologist (kidney specialist), a critical care specialist (pediatric or adult), a hematologist, a pulmonologist, cardiologist, and an infectious disease specialist or even a
 kidney transplant surgeon may be needed. Hospitalization also may be necessary.
 Other enterohemorrhagic
E. colistrains (for example, 0145, 026:H11, 0104:H4 and 0121) Most enterohemorrhagic
 E. coli (EHEC or STEC) infections were thought to be variants of strain 0157:H7, but this has been shown not to be the situation. Apparently, many other serotypes such as 0145 can acquire the plasmid that is responsible for the synthesis of Shiga (Vero) toxin, and thus can produce disease almost identical to disease symptoms produced by 0157:H7 in infected humans. Just like the 0157:H7 strains, these other
 E. coli serotypes can cause outbreaks of bloody diarrhea with hemorrhagic colitis that can become complicated by hemolytic uremia. In 2011, an outbreak in Germany began due to
 E. coli 0104:H4 due to contamination of sprouts. The outbreak was extensive as over 4000 people in 16 countries became infected. There is some consideration that this strain (and others) may be grouped together as a new EEC group in the future. Although EHEC strains can be transmitted person to person and on or in contaminated food, the source for the 0145 strain outbreak that has occurred in several states (California, Louisiana, Alabama, Florida, Georgia and Tennessee) was never identified by the CDC. Another strain,
 E. coli 0121, caused an outbreak in 19 states in the U.S.; it was traced to contaminated Farm Rich brand of frozen foods. These serotypes produce essentially the same type of disease as 0157:H7 and are diagnosed and treated in the same manner. Consequently, the previous sections use 0157:H7 as the prototypic EHEC so for all practical purposes, it represents all the EHEC serotypes.
</first>
</file1>