<file1>
<first>Eczema

ABOUT: Eczema is not a single health condition but a recognizable reaction pattern seen in a number of skin diseases. Atopic dermatitis , a common causes of
 eczema , is more prevalent in those with
 asthma and
 hay fever . Eczema signs and symptoms include tiny
 blisters (vesicles) that can weep and ooze, eventually producing crusted, thickened plaques of skin. It is almost always quite
 itchy . It is important to distinguish the different causes of eczema because effective treatments often differ. If eczema is produced by skin exposure to a specific substance, it can be helpful to avoid it. Keeping the skin healthy and moisturized can prevent certain kinds of eczema. What is eczema? Rather than a specific health condition, eczema is a reaction pattern that the skin produces in a number of diseases. It begins as red, raised tiny
 blisters containing a clear fluid atop red, elevated plaques. When the blisters break, the affected skin will weep and ooze. In older eczema, chronic eczema, the blisters are less prominent and the skin is thickened, elevated, and scaling. Eczema almost always is very
 itchy .
 Are there different types of eczema? 
CAUSES:  There are at least 11 distinct types of
 skin conditions that produce eczema. In order to develop a rational treatment plan, it is important to distinguish them. This is often not easy. 
SYMPTOMS:  Almost all patients with eczema complain of
 itching . Since the appearance of most types of eczema is similar, elevated plaques of red,
 bumpy skin, the distribution of the eruption can be of great help in distinguishing one type from another. For example, stasis dermatitis occurs most often on the lower leg while
 atopic dermatitis occurs in the front of the elbow and behind the knee. 
TREATMENT:  Eczema often is treated by family physicians, but since there are many causes of eczema, it may be necessary to seek help from a health specialist if things are not improving. Most dermatologists specialize in the diagnosis and treatment of all forms of eczema. 
DIAGNOSIS:  An accurate diagnosis requires an examination of the entire skin surface and a careful health history. It is important for a doctor to rule out curable conditions caused by infectious organisms. Occasionally, a sample of
 skin (biopsy) may be sent for examination in a laboratory. 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of acute eczema where there is significant weeping and oozing requires repeated cycles of application of dilute solutions of vinegar or tap water often in the form of a compress followed by evaporation. This is most often conveniently performed by placing the affected body part in front of a fan after the compress. Once the acute weeping has diminished, then topical steroid (such as triamcinolone cream) applications can be an effective treatment. In extensive disease, systemic steroids may need to be utilized either orally or by an injection (shot).
 What are
home remediesfor eczema? Mild eczema may respond to compresses composed of tepid water followed by room air evaporation. Chronic eczema can be improved by applying water followed by an emollient (moisturizing cream or lotion). Mild eczema can be effectively treated with nonprescription 1%
 hydrocortisone cream.
 Does diet affect eczema? The role of
 diet in
 atopic dermatitis is controversial. There is little compelling evidence that
 diet plays a significant role for majority of people who have eczema, no matter which type they have. Is there a cure for eczema? Each type of eczema requires a specific sort of therapy. The easiest eczemas to cure permanently are those caused by fungi and
 scabies .
 Allergic contact eczema can be cured if a specific allergenic substance can be identified and avoided. Is eczema
contagious? Eczema caused by fungi and
 scabies is transmissible to others. None of the other types of eczema are
 contagious . What is the prognosis of eczema? Most of the patients with eczema do quite well under the care of a dermatologist who has made an accurate diagnosis. Occasionally, eczema can become infected by microorganisms, such a
 staphylococci or
 herpes simplex virus. This is because the normal barrier function of the skin has been damaged by the inflammatory condition. In this situation, the infection could be contagious and require antibiotics treatment. An important signal would be the development of
 fever and pustules, plus
 pain at the site of the rash.
 
PREVENTION:  The judicious use of moisturizing creams or ointments can be an effective treatment for many people in preventing certain types of eczema.
</first>
</file1>