<file1>
<first>Electrolysis for Unwanted Hair Removal
What Causes Unwanted Hair Growth? Hair growth is the result of heredity and hormonal levels. Also, some
 drugs ,
temporary methods of
 hair removal , and some illnesses can stimulate hair
growth. Usually, hair growth is desirable. But when the hair is the wrong part
of your
 body -- a woman's upper lip or chin or bikini line, for
 example -- you may be
considering electrolysis. How Many Electrolysis Treatments Will I Need? Since many factors influence hair growth, you will need to return for
several electrolysis visits. The total number of sessions needed to remove hair permanently
from a particular area will vary from person to person. Most clients return
once a week or every other week, as necessary. But the unwanted hair will be
gone forever once the series of treatments have been completed. Each treatment
lasts between 15 minutes and one hour. Myths About Electrolysis Electrolysis is painful. The truth is, electrolysis usually does not cause
much discomfort. Modern electrolysis methods have reduced the discomfort to a
mere tingling. A topical anesthetic may be used in some cases. The electric tweezer method is permanent. The truth is, the Food and Drug
Administration and the American Medical Association recognize only electrolysis
as a permanent method of removing hair. In fact, some states prohibit those who
use the electric
 tweezer -- which can also be purchased for consumer
 use -- from claiming it provides permanent hair removal. Temporary methods of hair removal can be better. Chemical
depilatories (liquids or creams) are often used to remove body hair. These
products contain irritating chemicals, and can be time-consuming and messy.
Likewise, bleaches contain harsh chemicals and do little to disguise dark hair.
They may also discolor the skin. Waxing is another temporary method of hair
removal and is usually done in salons. A hot wax is applied to the skin and
removed once it has dried over the hair. The hair is stripped off when the wax
is removed. Waxing can be painful and costly. Home waxing kits are available,
but they can be difficult to use and messy. There are electrical electrolysis
devices available for home use that try to copy the devices used by
professionals. These devices are often unsafe for use by anyone who is not
trained in electrolysis.
 Facts About Electrolysis How Do I Choose an Electrologist? Electrologists are people who have undergone training to professionally
administer the electrolysis procedure. If you are considering undergoing
electrolysis, it is very important that you do your research before committing
to an appointment. The wrong decision can mean extra sessions and cost and
unnecessary discomfort. By following the guidelines listed below, you can take
comfort in knowing that you will be making an educated and informed decision
when choosing an electrologist. Know their qualifications.  Many states require that electrologists be
licensed or certified within the state in order to practice electrolysis. If
you live in those states, be sure the practitioner's
certificate is current and fully on display. For states that do not regulate
electrolysis, look for electrologists who have a certification from an
accredited electrology school. Ask around.  One of the best ways to find any good service is to ask friends
and family for recommendations. If you know anybody who has undergone
electrolysis, ask for his or her input. Get a consultation.  Many places will give you a free consultation. During
the consultation, be sure that any and all of your questions about the
procedure are answered. Some of the questions you can ask include: how the
procedure will feel; an estimate on the number of visits you will likely need;
the cost of each visit (this will vary from place to place, and it is best to
call around); the length of each session; how long they have been in business;
and the number of clients they have treated. Make sure they use the right technique. Make sure the practitioner uses
needle electrolysis, which is the only permanent form of hair removal. Some
places may advertise electrolysis, but in reality they use electronic tweezers
or photoepilators. These are not permanent hair removal procedures. Use common sense. When you go to your consultation, look around. Does the
place look clean? Do the workers look clean? Do they use disposable gloves or
probes? Ask to meet to person who will be performing the electrolysis for you.
Does he or she strike you as professional? If you are not personally
comfortable with somebody, do not go to him or her. Personal comfort is
essential to knowing you have made the right decision in choosing an
electrologist. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>