<file1>
<first>Emphysema, Chronic Bronchitis, and Colds
Introduction If you have
 emphysema or
 chronic bronchitis , you know how miserable it feels 
when you catch a
 cold . After all,
 breathing is difficult enough with a
chronic 
obstructive pulmonary disease (
 COPD ). Not only does catching a cold worsen your 
ability to breathe and be active, but the cold virus increases your chance of 
getting a more serious respiratory tract infection. Here's what you must know to 
stay well. What is emphysema and chronic bronchitis? Emphysema and chronic
 bronchitis are chronic (long-term) lung diseases that 
make it hard to breathe. Both diseases are chronic obstructive pulmonary 
diseases (
 COPD ), meaning they are conditions that cause a limitation in airflow. 
Emphysema and chronic
 bronchitis can occur separately or together and are 
usually the result of
 cigarette smoking . In addition, although it happens 
rarely, a genetic form of emphysema can occur early in adulthood, even if you 
never smoked. In the United States,
 COPD is vastly under diagnosed. While only 15 to 20 
percent of smokers are diagnosed with COPD, experts believe the majority of 
smokers develop some degree of airflow obstruction. Emphysema comes on gradually after years of exposure to irritants such as 
cigarette smoke. With emphysema, the tiny air sacs in the
 lungs become damaged. 
Because the tiny sacs lose their "stretch," less air gets in and out of the 
lungs. This causes you to feel short of breath. With chronic
 bronchitis , the airways that carry air to the lungs are inflamed 
and produce a lot of mucus. The mucus and inflammation cause the airways to 
narrow or become obstructed, making it difficult to breathe. Once the airways 
are irritated over a long period, the lining of the airways becomes thickened. 
This thickening of the airways results in an 
irritating
 cough , hampered airflow, 
and lung scarring. The damaged airways then become a breeding place for
 bacterial infections such as
 pneumonia .
 What happens with emphysema and chronic bronchitis and colds? A cold is a viral respiratory illness that mainly affects your nose and 
throat but in some instances can affect your airways. When you have emphysema or 
chronic bronchitis, you already have some difficulty breathing because of the 
damaged airways and lungs. Catching a respiratory virus along with COPD can 
hinder breathing even more and can cause the following changes in your symptoms: An increase in phlegm
 An increase in the thickness or stickiness of the 
 phlegm
 A change in phlegm color to yellow or green
 A presence of blood in the phlegm
 An increase in the severity of
 shortness of breath ,
 cough , or
 wheezing A general feeling of ill health
 Difficulty sleeping
 Increased
 fatigue Why should I take colds seriously with emphysema or chronic bronchitis? Catching a cold with emphysema or chronic bronchitis may also lead to 
bacterial infections such as
 pneumonia . This occurs because of the
 airway obstruction and the inability to cough out infected secretions of mucus. Sometimes, patients with COPD are hospitalized because of a respiratory 
infection and the worsening of their symptoms. Treatment may include inhaled 
medications, oxygen, and antibiotics to treat any bacterial infection. 
Antibiotics do not treat a cold. To avoid more serious problems with emphysema, chronic bronchitis, and colds, 
it's important to always alert your doctor if your cold symptoms get worse. 
Don't wait until you have more serious breathing problems to contact your 
doctor.
 Which cold treatment should I use with emphysema or chronic bronchitis? First, it is important to stay on your prescribed medications for emphysema 
and chronic bronchitis. Then, to decide how to treat cold symptoms, it's best to 
talk with your doctor. You might treat the body
 aches and
 fever associated with 
a cold with
 acetaminophen or
 ibuprofen . In addition, you should avoid
 antihistamines that thicken mucus and make it even more difficult to cough up. Most over-the-counter cold remedies are generally safe for people with 
emphysema and chronic bronchitis. However, decongestants raise
 blood pressure and some of the medications used to treat emphysema and chronic bronchitis also 
raise heart rate. So, use decongestants with caution. Again, ask your doctor 
about medications for cold symptoms. 
PREVENTION:  The following guidelines can help: Good hygiene can decrease respiratory infections such as colds. Prevent 
 the spread of a cold virus by making sure you and your family members wash 
 your hands regularly.
 Check with your doctor about a pneumonia and
 influenza vaccine. You need 
 a
 flu shot every year. One pneumonia shot is usually enough to protect you 
 from a specific type of bacterial pneumonia.
 Avoid crowds during cold and
 flu season, since colds and flu can cause 
 serious problems for people with COPD.
 Pay attention to healthy lifestyle habits by avoiding cigarette smoke 
 and air pollutants; eating a balanced, healthy
 diet ; and 
 exercising to stay 
 strong.
 Sinus infections can trigger breathing problems for those with emphysema 
 and chronic bronchitis. Be aware of your sinus symptoms and report them 
 immediately to your doctor to prevent worsening of breathing difficulties. SOURCES: American Lung Association: Need Help For Treatment Decisions with COPD? American Lung Association:
 Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) Fact Sheet. The National Heart Lung and Blood Institute: COPD: Learn to Breathe Better. Global Initiative for
 Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD): GOLD Guidelines At-A-Glance Desk Reference.
 Reviewed by Michael W. Smith, MD on December 19, 2007
 ©2007 WebMD, Inc. All rights reserved.
</first>
</file1>