<file1>
<first>Elimination Disorders in Children

ABOUT: Constipation is defined as "a group of disorders associated with persistent, 
difficult, infrequent, or seemingly incomplete defecation without evidence of a 
structural or biochemical explanation." Constipation is a relatively common 
event estimated to be responsible for 3%-5% of all visits to a pediatrician's 
office. Encopresis has been defined as "the repetitive, voluntary or involuntary, 
passage of stool in inappropriate places by 
children 4 years of age and older, 
at which time a child may be reasonably expected to have completed 
toilet 
training and to
 exercise bowel control." Most studies indicate approximately 4% 
of all children 4-17 years of age will experience encopresis. What are elimination disorders in children? There are two types of disorders of elimination that may affect children. One 
category reflects problems with stooling, relatively common
 constipation and less 
frequently occurring encopresis (also known a
 fecal incontinence or soiling). 
The other category of elimination disorders in children reflects problems with 
urination and is known as enuresis. The article will review only problems 
associated in children dealing with stooling. 
Problems with urination in 
children are reviewed elsewhere. 
CAUSES:  Most children with encopresis have underlying constipation. Why some children 
develop encopresis does not seem to reflect differences in either physiology or 
psychology. Pediatric GI specialists have noted three areas of intestinal 
maturation that may set the stage (in some children) for the onset of 
constipation and (in some, ultimately) encopresis. These areas include the 
following: Regardless of the cause, many children with constipation will ultimately pass 
either an overly large and/or hard stool, resulting in a painful experience. The 
rational step (from the child's perspective) is to avoid stooling and thus avoid 
further
 pain . Consequently, stool accumulates in the rectum and becomes 
desiccated and thus more difficult and more painful to pass. This recurrent 
cycle reinforces the child's behavior to avoid stooling at all costs. Children 
who develop encopresis may develop abnormal stretching and enlargement of the 
rectal area that reduces the reflex urge to stool. As a consequence, the impacted 
stool mass may allow "upstream" semisolid stool to leak around the "downstream" 
stool obstruction, causing soiling in clothes as well as occasional chunks of 
stool to also be passed without the child's knowledge or desire.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Pediatric gastroenterologists (GI doctors) indicate that symptoms of 
constipation generally involve six characteristics of abnormal stooling present 
in infants and toddlers for at least one month and children 4 to 18 years of age 
for two months. A minimum of two criteria must be present to fulfill the 
definition of constipation. These stooling patterns/problems include the 
following: 
SYMPTOMS:  Specialists who deal with encopretic children note that the above criteria 
for constipation are also characteristic of encopresis. In one recent study 
focusing on constipation, many of the children in the study first presented to 
their physician with a history consistent with encopresis. There are, however, 
several historical elements that are unique to encopresis. These include the 
following: 
DIAGNOSIS:  A complete evaluation of a child with constipation or encopresis involves a 
thorough history, a detailed physical examination, and may include laboratory 
testing. The child's pediatrician may generally handle the analysis of these 
elements. A pediatric GI specialist consultation may be indicated should a more 
ominous cause for the elimination disorder be discovered or if the evaluation 
produces conflicting data and thus obscures the establishment of the exact cause 
and thus management for the child's problem. The history to be explored during an evaluation of elimination disorders 
includes: (1) age and abruptness of onset, (2) frequency and character of the 
current stool pattern in comparison to that noted prior to the onset of 
symptoms, (3) relationship to ingestion of meals as well as types of food in the 
child's
 diet , (4) unusual
 weight loss or gain, (5) associated abdominal 
complaints (for example,
 abdominal pain ), (6) urological issues (many children with 
elimination disorders may also have enuresis -- involuntary loss of bladder 
control), (7) psychosocial family dynamics (for example, parental/sibling/peer response 
to the problem), and (8) gentle exploration for any possibility of sexual 
abuse -- regression,
 depression , sexually acting out, etc. The goal of a complete physical exam is to eliminate the possibility of 
anatomical or functional causes for the elimination disorder. Children affected 
by
 cerebral palsy , global hyponia (low muscle tone), mental retardation, and 
anatomical malformations (for example, spinal cord abnormalities or displacement of the 
anus) must be considered and ruled out as a cause for the child's symptoms. 
Physical examination of the abdomen will often demonstrate a large stool mass. A 
rectal exam will commonly demonstrate an enlarged rectal volume that is packed 
with stool. Absence of anal muscular tone should be a "red flag" for a potential 
neurological disorder. As noted above, appropriate anal location should be 
documented. Likewise, the physician should perform an evaluation for hidden 
spinal cord malformations (for example, tuft of hair over the lower spine). Most children with either constipation or encopresis do not need laboratory 
or radiographic evaluation unless the history and/or physical examination 
warrant further analysis (for example, an
 MRI for spinal cord malformations). Blood studies 
to evaluate
 thyroid function may be a consideration on an individualized basis. 
An abdominal X-ray may be helpful to measure the child's stool burden. For 
those children with urologic problems, a culture and
 urinalysis are reasonable 
studies. A pediatric gastroenterologist may perform a study of anal and rectal 
muscle tone (anal/rectal manometry) to assess the anal/rectal response to 
inflation with air in children who do not respond to routine therapy.
 
TREATMENT:  Successful treatment of elimination disorders includes reestablishing an 
appropriate bowel evacuation regimen and development of a program to ensure 
maintenance of such a stool elimination pattern. A program that may include the 
use of laxatives, changes in diet, toileting behavior adjustments, and close 
follow-up has been shown to provide the highest rate of success. The therapeutic 
approach is often defined by the age of the child. 
Breastfed infants are less 
likely to have stooling problems when compared with their formula-fed peers. 
Diluted prune juice (50:50 with water) will promote a softer and increased 
volume stool. Rectal stimulation with either a rectal thermometer or
 glycerin suppository may be an appropriate technique to address a stool-impacted infant. 
Mineral oil is not recommended for infants due to the possibility of 
gastroesophageal reflux (GER) and possible lung pathology if aspirated. Careful 
attention to the child's stooling pattern is worthwhile when solid foods are 
introduced into the young infant's diet. Preschoolers, grammar-school-age, and older children with elimination 
disorders are generally approached in a similar fashion. If the child is 
chronically impacted, the use of an orally administered cathartic (for example, magnesium 
citrate) will "clean out" the colon. Colonic enemas have fallen out of favor due 
to the emotional
 stress that may be associated with their use. Follow-up daily 
use of water retaining laxatives (for example,
 polyethylene glycol without
 electrolytes marketed as
 PEG -3350 or
 Miralax ) is common. This approach allows the chronically 
distended colon to gradually return to a normal volume -- thus allowing 
redevelopment of stretch receptors to respond to the local rectal/anal 
enlargement associated with stool arrival to the area. These water-retaining 
laxatives may be needed for several months before considering a gradual 
tapering. A thorough review of the child's diet is important. Avoidance of large 
amounts of constipating items is paramount. Such foods would include excessive 
milk/dairy products, starches (bread, pasta, etc.), and "fast foods," which are 
often high in saturated
 fats . Grandmother's suggestion to "eat your fruits and 
vegetables" has solid medical credence. An adequate intake of water as well as 
daily vigorous physical activity will also promote colonic health. Establishment 
of a daily routine of "toilet time" has been shown to be very helpful. Spending 
between five to 10 minutes on the toilet is a generally accepted goal. For young 
children, a reward system is often helpful. The reward should be a response for 
sitting on the toilet for the allotted time -- not the production of stool. 
Passage of a daily normal character stool without discomfort is the intended 
goal of bowel reeducation. The use of
 probiotics has received scientific study in the last few years. 
Pediatric studies are less convincing than those utilizing adult patients and 
many studies present conflicting results. There has been no documentation of a 
deleterious effect of
 probiotic usage in children or adults.
 
PREVENTION:  While there are no guarantees in this world (except death and taxes, as 
Benjamin Franklin reportedly said), there are several measures that can be taken 
to lessen the likelihood of constipation and/or encopresis. Breastfed infants 
have fewer stooling issues than their formula-fed counterparts. Careful 
monitoring of intestinal changes associated with the introduction of solid foods 
(between 4 to 6 months of age) is helpful. The process of toilet training should 
be viewed as the socially coordinated behavior of a purely biologic function. 
Forceful threats, intimidation, shaming, and extreme pressure should not be part 
of the toilet-training process. Many a toddler discovers that they, and not 
their parents, have ultimate control of when and where they will have a bowel 
movement. Forcing the issue will often only complicate matters. Frustrated 
parents should remember that very few high school seniors wear Depends to the 
senior prom. As noted above, a healthy diet emphasizing proper hydration, whole 
grains, fruits and vegetables, and an active lifestyle will promote normal stool 
production and elimination. What is the prognosis for children with elimination disorders? With parental education regarding risk factors and awareness of techniques 
maximizing their avoidance, the prognosis for children with elimination 
disorders is positive. Likewise, effective therapy has been demonstrated to be 
successful in both the short and long term, allowing reestablishment and 
maintenance of normal bowel function.
</first>
</file1>