<file1>
<first>Endometrial Cancer Prevention

PREVENTION:  Cancer prevention is action taken to lower the chance of getting
 cancer . By preventing
 cancer , the number of new cases of
 cancer in a group or population is lowered. Hopefully, this will lower the number of deaths caused by cancer. To prevent new cancers from starting, scientists look at risk factors and protective factors. Anything that increases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor; anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer protective factor. Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. For example, both
 smoking and inheriting certain genes are risk factors for some types of cancer, but only
 smoking can be avoided. Regular
 exercise and a healthy
 diet may be protective factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may lower your risk but it does not mean that you will not get cancer. Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied, including: Changing lifestyle or eating habits. Avoiding things known to cause cancer. Taking medicines to treat a
 precancerous condition or to keep cancer from starting. Endometrial cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in 
the tissues of the endometrium. The
 endometrium is the lining of the uterus. The uterus is part of the female 
reproductive system. It is a hollow, pear-shaped, muscular organ in the pelvis, 
where a fetus grows.  Cancer of the endometrium is different from cancer of the muscle of the 
uterus, which is called sarcoma of the uterus. Endometrial cancer is the most common invasive cancer of the female 
reproductive system. Endometrial cancer usually occurs in women after
 menopause , and affects more 
white women than black women. Black women diagnosed with endometrial cancer are 
more likely to have more advanced disease at diagnosis, and are more likely to 
die from endometrial cancer than white women.
 Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may help prevent 
cancer. Avoiding
 cancer risk factors such as
 smoking , being
 overweight , and lack of
 exercise may help prevent certain cancers. Increasing protective factors such as 
quitting smoking, eating a healthy
 diet , and exercising may also help prevent 
some cancers. Talk to your doctor or other health care professional about how 
you might lower your risk of cancer. The following risk factors may increase the risk of endometrial cancer: Estrogen Estrogen is a hormone made by the body. It helps the body develop and 
maintain female sex characteristics. Estrogen can affect the growth of some 
cancers, including endometrial cancer. A woman's risk of developing endometrial 
cancer is increased by being exposed to estrogen in the following ways: Estrogen-only
 hormone replacement therapy : Estrogen may be given to 
 replace the estrogen no longer produced by the ovaries in
 postmenopausal women or women whose ovaries have been removed. This is called hormone 
 replacement therapy (
 HRT ), or
 hormone therapy (HT). The use of hormone 
 replacement therapy that contains only estrogen increases the risk of 
 endometrial cancer. For this reason, estrogen therapy alone is usually 
 prescribed only for women who do not have a uterus.
 When estrogen is combined with progestin (another hormone), it is called 
 combination estrogen-progestin replacement therapy. For postmenopausal 
 women, taking estrogen in combination with progestin does not increase the 
 risk of endometrial cancer.
   Early
 menstruation : Beginning to have menstrual periods at an early age 
 increases the number of years the body is exposed to estrogen and increases 
 a woman's risk of endometrial cancer.
   Late
 menopause : Women who reach
 menopause at an older age are exposed to 
 estrogen for a longer time and have an increased risk of endometrial cancer.
   Never being
 pregnant : Because estrogen levels are lower during
 pregnancy , women who have never been pregnant are exposed to estrogen for a 
 longer time than women who have been pregnant. This increases the risk of 
 endometrial cancer. Tamoxifen Tamoxifen is one of a group of
 drugs called selective estrogen receptor 
modulators, or SERMs. Tamoxifen acts like estrogen on some tissues in the body, 
such as the uterus, but blocks the effects of estrogen on other tissues, such as 
the breast. When tamoxifen is used to prevent
 breast cancer in women who are at 
high risk for the disease, it increases the risk of endometrial cancer. This 
risk is greater in postmenopausal women. Raloxifene is a SERM that is used to prevent bone
 weakness in postmenopausal 
women. It does not have estrogen-like effects on the uterus and has not been 
shown to increase the risk of endometrial cancer. Other SERMs are being studied 
in
 clinical trials . Inherited risk Hereditary nonpolyposis colon cancer (
 HNPCC ) syndrome is an inherited 
disorder caused by changes in certain genes. Women who have HNPCC syndrome have 
a much higher risk of developing endometrial cancer than women who do not have 
HNPCC syndrome. Polycystic ovary syndrome Women who have
 polycystic ovary syndrome (a disorder of the hormones made by 
the ovaries) have an increased risk of endometrial cancer. Body fat Obesity increases the risk of endometrial cancer. This may be because obesity 
is related to other risk factors such as estrogen levels, polycystic ovary 
syndrome, lack of physical activity, and a diet that is high in saturated
 fats . It is not known if losing weight decreases the risk of endometrial cancer. The following protective factors may decrease the risk of endometrial 
cancer: Combination oral contraceptives Taking contraceptives that combine estrogen and progestin (combination oral 
contraceptives) decreases the risk of endometrial cancer. The protective effect 
of combination
 oral contraceptives increases with the length of time they are 
used, and can last for many years after oral
 contraceptive use has been stopped. Physical activity Physical activity may lower the risk of endometrial cancer. Pregnancy and breast-feeding Estrogen levels are lower during pregnancy and when breast-feeding. Being 
pregnant and/or breast-feeding may lower the risk of endometrial cancer. Diet A diet low in saturated fats and high in fruits and vegetables may lower the 
risk of endometrial cancer. The risk may also be lowered when
 soy -based foods 
are a regular part of the diet. Cancer prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to prevent 
cancer. Cancer
 prevention clinical trials are used to study ways to lower the risk of 
developing certain types of cancer. Some cancer prevention trials are conducted 
with healthy people who have not had cancer but who have an increased risk for 
cancer. Other prevention trials are conducted with people who have had cancer 
and are trying to prevent another cancer of the same type or to lower their 
chance of developing a new type of cancer. Other trials are done with healthy 
volunteers who are not known to have any risk factors for cancer. The purpose of some cancer prevention clinical trials is to find out whether 
actions people take can prevent cancer. These may include eating fruits and 
vegetables, exercising, quitting smoking, or taking certain medicines,
 vitamins ,
 minerals , or food
 supplements .
</first>
</file1>