<file1>
<first>Bowel Incontinence (Fecal Incontinence)
Bowel incontinence (fecal incontinence) definition Fecal incontinence can be defined as the unintentional loss of stool (feces) 
or
 gas (flatus). It is often due to a failure of one or more of the components 
that allow the body to control the evacuation of feces, when it is socially 
appropriate. A normal bowel movement requires a complex interaction and feedback system 
between the nerves and muscles of the rectum and anus. The anatomy of this area 
is complicated. The rectum is a reservoir for holding stool. Two sphincters or 
circular muscles separate the rectum from the anus and control when the anus 
should allow a bowel movement. The internal anal sphincter (IAS) is under 
involuntary control of the body&amp;#39;s nervous system, while the external anal 
sphincter (EAS) can be actively controlled by the indivdiual. In addition, the puborectalis muscle tugs at the junction of the rectum and anus, creating a 90 
degree angle, which makes it harder for stool to move involuntarily into the 
anus. When the rectum is full and for a normal bowel movement to occur, the IAS 
relaxes just a little. Cells in the anus can detect feces or flatus and if the 
brain says that it is an opportune social time to pass gas or have a bowel 
movement, the puborectalis muscle relaxes, straightening the path from the 
rectum to the anus. Squatting or sitting helps increase the pressure within the 
abdomen, and muscles that surround the rectum squeeze its contents, the EAS 
relaxes and a bowel movement occurs. If it is not an appropriate time to open the bowel, the puborectalis muscle 
contracts, the EAS contracts, the rectum relaxes and stool is forced back into 
the upper part of the rectum, causing the urge to have a bowel movement to be 
temporarily quieted. 
CAUSES:  Fecal incontinence occurs because of an underlying disease or illness (it is 
not considered a "disease"). There are numerous potential causes and many 
patients have more than one reason to cause loss of bowel control. Damage to muscles and nerves may occur directly at the time of 
vaginal 
childbirth or after anal or rectal surgery. Neurologic diseases such as
 stroke ,
 multiple sclerosis ,
 spinal cord injury , and
 spina bifida can be potential causes of fecal
 incontinence . Complications of
 diabetes can also cause 
peripheral nerve damage leading to incontinence. Patients with
 inflammatory bowel disease (Crohn&amp;#39;s disease,
 ulcerative colitis ) and irritable bowel disease may develop fecal incontinence. Stool seepage is different than fecal incontinence. Minor staining can occur 
in people who have
 hemorrhoids , rectal fistula, rectal prolapse and
 poor hygiene . 
Other causes include 
chronic
 diarrhea , parasite infections, and
 laxative abuse . Paradoxical
 diarrhea or overflow incontinence may occur is a a person who has
chronic
 constipation . In paradoxical
 diarrhea , stool fills the rectum, hardens and becomes impacted. 
Liquid stool leaks around the fecal mass, imitating incontinence.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Bowel incontinence refers to the inability to control the passage of small 
amount of stool, liquid or solid, or control flatus. People are sometimes reluctant to discuss their lack of bowel control 
because of the social stigma attached to it. Their initial complaint might be
 anal itching (pruritis ani), a buttock
 skin infection , or breakdown of the skin 
and ulcers. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Taking a history is very important and the health care professional will 
spend time learning about how often loss of bowel control occurs, in what 
situations and whether it is solid, liquid, or gas. Past medical and surgical 
history is important, especially obstetric history or surgery of the anus, 
including
 hemorrhoids . It could be several years before the complication of a 
surgery or childbirth lead to fecal incontinence. Dietary habits and medications 
(including over-the-counter medications and
 laxative ) will also be considered 
and evaluated. Physical examination will likely include a rectal examination to assess 
sphincter tone. In females, a
 pelvic exam will also be performed. While blood tests are not usually needed to make the diagnosis, other tests 
may be helpful in deciding the potential cause of fecal incontinence. Anal 
manometry measures the pressure within the rectum, both at rest and when the 
patient squeezes the anal sphincter. Nerve and muscle conduction studies may be 
considered.
 Ultrasound can evaluate the anal sphincters and look for muscle 
damage.
 
TREATMENT:  The treatment approach for a patient with fecal incontinence is 
individualized based upon the underlying cause. The purpose is to regulate bowel 
movements, decrease their frequency, and increase stool firmness and consistency. 
Often this involves dietary changes and the use of medications that bulk the 
stool. Increasing the strength of the muscles of the pelvic floor might be helpful. 
Kegel exercises and electrical stimulation may be recommended. Biofeedback is 
often used to help retrain the anal sphincters and have the patient appreciate 
the sensation of rectal fullness that comes just before the need to defecate. If the incontinence persists even after maximum medical therapy has been 
attempted, surgery may be an alternative. If damaged, attempts can be made to 
repair the muscles of the pelvic floor including the external anal sphincter. 
The internal anal sphincter function may be enhanced by injecting materials like 
silicone, carbon beads, or collagen. As a last resort, where all other options have failed, a
 colostomy may be 
performed, where the colon is diverted through the abdominal wall to empty into 
a removable bag. What about bowel incontinence in
children? In children, fecal incontinence (also called
 encopresis ) is often due to 
chronic
 constipation and overflow incontinence or diarrhea. By definition, there 
should be at least one inappropriate bowel movement per month for at least three 
months in a child older than age 4 years. The incontinence usually happens 
during the day and not at night. Most often, the diagnosis is made by history and physical examination by the 
health care professional and further testing is not needed. Treatment is directed at developing a more routine bowel evacuation schedule 
and may require changes in
 diet , behavior modification, and the addition of stool 
bulking agents.
 
PREVENTION:  Maintaining sphincter tone may prevent fecal incontinence. This might include 
preventing
 constipation by increasing
 fiber in the
 diet and keeping well 
hydrated and avoiding straining to promote a bowel movement. Unfortunately, many times the cause of incontinence is childbirth anal 
surgery. It may be years until the symptoms of incontinence arise. What is the prognosis for bowel incontinence? The frequency of fecal incontinence increases with age. Once it occurs, the 
patient may be able to control the symptoms with diet, medication, and
 exercise . 
Many patients may initially benefit from surgery, but that benefit gradually 
decreases over the years and incontinence may recur.
</first>
</file1>