<file1>
<first>Fish Odor Syndrome  (Trimethylaminuria)
Fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria) facts* *Fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria) facts Medically Edited by:
 Charles P. Davis, MD, PhD Fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria) is a
 genetic disease ; symptoms are 
often present from birth. Fish odor syndrome is characterized by an offensive body odor and the smell 
of rotting fish due to the excessive excretion of trimethylaminuria (TMA) in the 
urine, sweat, and breath of affected individuals. Fish odor syndrome is caused by mutations in the
 FMO3 gene. Other causes of odor body can occur as a result from an excess of proteins 
in the
 diet , or from an increase in bacteria that normally produce 
trimethylamine in the GI tract (also may make fish odor syndrome worse);
 liver disease,
 kidney disease ,
 poor hygiene ,
 gingivitis , and cases of blood-borne
 halitosis . Diagnostic tests that help differentiate fish odor syndrome 
(trimethylaminuria) from other causes of body odor are available at specialized 
laboratories. Fish odor syndrome symptoms have been seen temporarily in a small number of 
premature infants and in healthy women at the start of
 menstruation , usually in 
individuals that are heterozygous for the mutant
 FMO3 gene or due to immaturity 
of the faulty
 FMO3 gene expression (
 FMO3 expression increases with age). Fish odor syndrome treatment includes certain dietary restrictions, use of 
acid lotions and soaps to remove secreted trimethylamine on the skin, use of 
activated charcoal and copper chlorophyllin, certain antibiotics, laxatives, and 
riboflavin
 supplements .
 What is fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? Trimethylaminuria is a disorder in which the body is unable to break down 
trimethylamine, a compound derived from the
 diet that has a strong odor of 
rotting fish. What are the signs and symptoms of fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? As trimethylamine builds up in the body, it causes affected people 
to give off a fish-like odor in their sweat, urine, and 
breath. The intensity of 
this odor may vary over time. The strong body odor can interfere with many 
aspects of daily life, affecting a person's relationships, social life, and 
career. Some people with trimethylaminuria experience
 depression and social 
isolation as a result of this condition. What causes fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? Although gene mutations account for most cases of trimethylaminuria, the 
condition can also be caused by other factors. A fish-like body odor may result 
from an excess of certain proteins in the diet or from an increase in bacteria 
that normally produce trimethylamine in the
 digestive system . A few cases of the 
disorder have been identified in adults with 
liver or kidney disease. Temporary 
symptoms of this condition have been reported in a small number of premature 
infants and in some healthy women at the start of
menstruation.
 How common is fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? Trimethylaminuria is an uncommon
 genetic disorder ; its incidence is unknown. What genes are related to fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? Mutations in the
 FMO 3 gene cause trimethylaminuria. The FMO3 gene provides instructions for making an enzyme that breaks down 
nitrogen-containing compounds from the diet, including trimethylamine. This 
compound is produced by bacteria in the intestine as they help digest proteins 
from eggs, liver, legumes (such as soybeans and peas), certain kinds of fish, 
and other foods. Normally, the
 FMO3 enzyme converts fishy-smelling 
trimethylamine into another molecule that has no odor. If the enzyme is missing 
or its activity is reduced because of a mutation in the
 FMO3 gene, 
trimethylamine is not processed properly and can build up in the body. As excess 
trimethylamine is released in a person's sweat, urine, and breath, it causes the 
strong odor characteristic of trimethylaminuria. Researchers believe that
 stress and diet also play a role in triggering symptoms. How do people inherit fish odor syndrome (trimethylaminuria)? Most cases of trimethylaminuria appear to be 
inherited in an autosomal 
recessive pattern, which means both copies of the gene in each cell have 
mutations. Most often, the parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive 
condition each carry one copy of the mutated gene, but typically do not show 
signs and symptoms of the condition. Carriers of an
 FMO3 mutation, however, may 
have mild symptoms of trimethylaminuria or experience temporary episodes of 
fish-like body odor.
 Where can I find information about diagnosis, management, or treatment of 
trimethylaminuria? These resources address the diagnosis or management of trimethylaminuria and 
may include treatment providers. Gene Review:
 Trimethylaminuria Gene Tests:
 Trimethylaminuria Where can I find additional information about trimethylaminuria? You may find the following resources about trimethylaminuria helpful. These 
materials are written for the general public. MedlinePlus -
 Metabolic Disorders Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center - Information about genetic conditions and rare 
diseases Additional NIH Resources -
 National Human Genome Research Institute You may also be interested in these resources, which are designed for 
healthcare professionals and researchers. Gene Reviews 
Clinical summary Gene Tests - DNA 
tests ordered by healthcare professionals OMIM - Genetic 
disorder catalog
 What other names do people use for trimethylaminuria? Fish malodor syndrome Fish odor syndrome Stale fish syndrome TMAU TMAuria What if I still have specific questions about trimethylaminuria? Ask the Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center</first>
</file1>