<file1>
<first>Ciguatera Poisoning
What is ciguatera poisoning? Ciguatera is a type of
 food poisoning . The ciguatera toxin may be found in large reef fish, most commonly barracuda, grouper, red snapper, eel, amberjack, sea bass, and Spanish mackerel. These fish live in coral reef waters between latitudes of 35 degrees south to 35 degrees north, corresponding to the area located between the Tropic of
 Cancer and the Tropic of Capricorn. These geographic lines ring the earth north and south of the equator and make up the tropics. These areas include the Caribbean Sea, Hawaii, and coastal Central America. Ciguatera toxin tends to accumulate in predator fish, such as the Barracuda and other carnivorous reef fish because they eat other fish that consume toxin-producing algae (dinoflagellates) that live in coral reef waters. Ciguatera toxin is harmless to fish but poisonous to humans. The toxin is odorless and tasteless, and it is heat-resistant, so cooking does not destroy the toxin. Eating ciguatera-contaminated tropical or subtropical fish poisons the person who eats it. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of ciguatera poisoning generally begin six to eight hours after eating the contaminated fish. Symptoms include: nausea , vomiting , diarrhea , muscle pain , numbness, tingling, abdominal
 pain , dizziness , and vertigo . Hot and
 cold sensation may be reversed. Severe cases of ciguatera poisoning may result in tearing of the eyes,
 chills , skin
 rash ,
 itching ,
 shortness of breath ,
 drooling , and
 paralysis . Death due to heart or respiratory failure occurs in rare cases.
 
TREATMENT:  If you or someone you know has ingested a fish that you 
suspect might be contaminated with ciguatera toxin, and you or they have signs 
or symptoms, such as nausea, vomiting, pain, trouble breathing, seizure, 
 confusion, or abnormal skin color, call either an ambulance or the 
National Poison Control Center (1-800-222-1222) for guidance. The National
 Poison Control Center phone number is 1-800-222-1222. This number is routed to 
the poison control center that serves your area. Place the telephone number 
(along with police, fire, and 911 or equivalent) near your home phones. Do 
not induce vomiting or give syrup of Ipecac. Ipecac was formerly used to 
induce
 vomiting in poisoned patients where there was a chance to get the toxin 
out of the body. Several advisory bodies such as the American Association of 
  Poison Control Centers and the American Academy of
 Pediatrics have recommended 
that Ipecac NOT be used and that it should not even be kept in the household. 
For more information on this subject go to: 
http://www.poison.org/prepared/ipecac.asp Do not give activated charcoal 
at home. Allow medical personnel to decide if this treatment is appropriate. The poison control center will instruct you what to do. Maintain hydration. 
Intravenous fluids may be necessary for uncontrollable
 nausea and vomiting. There is no specific antidote for ciguatera poisoning. Diphenhydramine (
 Benadryl ) may help relieve
 itching . Give 25-50 mg every 6 hours. Alcohol, 
fish, nuts, and nut oils should be avoided after exposure to ciguatera poisoning 
because they may trigger recurrent symptoms.
 When should I see a doctor for ciguatera poisoning? Severe cases of ciguatera poisoning require hospitalization for intravenous 
fluids. If you think you may have ciguatera poisoning, seek immediate 
medical attention. A doctor should be consulted in every case about 
treatment for ciguatera poisoning, including available medications.
</first>
</file1>