<file1>
<first>Mental Health: Factitious Disorders
Types of Factitious Disorders There are four main types of factitious disorders, including: Factitious disorder with mostly psychological symptoms : As the 
 description implies, people with this disorder mimic behavior that is 
 typical of a mental illness, such as
 schizophrenia . They may appear 
 confused, make absurd statements and report
 hallucinations , the experience 
 of sensing things that are not there; for example,
 hearing voices. Ganser 
 syndrome, sometimes called prison psychosis, is a factitious disorder that 
 was first observed in prisoners. People with Ganser syndrome have short-term 
 episodes of bizarre behavior similar to that shown by people with serious 
 mental illnesses. Factitious disorder with mostly physical symptoms : People with 
 this disorder claim to have symptoms related to a physical illness, such as 
 symptoms of
 chest pain , stomach problems, or
 fever . This disorder is 
 sometimes referred to as
 Munchausen syndrome , named for Baron von 
 Munchausen, an 18th century German officer who was known for embellishing 
 the stories of his life and experiences. Factitious disorder with both psychological and physical symptoms : 
 People with this disorder produce symptoms of both physical and mental 
 illness. Factitious disorder not otherwise specified : This type includes a 
 disorder called factitious disorder by proxy (also called 
 Munchausen 
 syndrome by proxy). People with this disorder produce or fabricate symptoms 
 of illness in another person under their care. It most often occurs in 
 mothers (although it can occur in fathers) who intentionally harm their 
 children in order to receive attention.
 What Are the Symptoms of Factitious Disorders? Possible warning signs of factitious disorders include: Dramatic but inconsistent medical history Unclear symptoms that are not controllable and that become more 
  severe or change once treatment has begun Predictable relapses following improvement in the condition Extensive knowledge of hospitals and/or medical terminology, as well 
  as the textbook descriptions of illness Presence of many surgical
 scars Appearance of new or additional symptoms following negative test 
  results Presence of symptoms only when the patient is with others or being 
  observed Willingness or eagerness to have medical tests, operations, or other 
  procedures History of seeking treatment at many hospitals, clinics, and doctors 
  offices, possibly even in different cities Reluctance by the patient to allow health care professionals to meet 
  with or talk to family members, friends, and prior doctors What Causes Factitious Disorders? The exact cause of factitious disorders is not known, but researchers are 
looking at the roles of biological and psychological factors in the development 
of these disorders. Some theories suggest that a history of abuse or neglect as 
a child, or a history of frequent illnesses that required hospitalization might 
be factors in the development of the disorder. How Common Are Factitious Disorders? There are no reliable statistics regarding the number of people in 
  the U.S. who suffer from factitious disorders. Obtaining accurate 
  statistics is difficult because dishonesty is common with this 
  condition. In addition, people with factitious disorders tend to seek 
  treatment at many different health care facilities, which can lead to 
  statistics that are misleading. In general, factitious disorders are more common in men than in 
  women. However, factitious disorder by proxy tends to be more common in 
  women than in men.
 How Are Factitious Disorders Diagnosed? Diagnosing factitious disorders is very difficult because of, again, 
  the dishonesty that is involved. Doctors must rule out other possible 
  physical and mental illnesses before a diagnosis of factitious disorder 
  can be considered. If the doctor finds no physical reason for the symptoms, he or she 
  may refer the person to a psychiatrist or psychologist,
 mental health professionals who are specially trained to diagnose and treat mental 
  illnesses. Psychiatrists and psychologists use specially designed 
  interview and assessment tools to evaluate a person for a factitious 
  disorder. The doctor bases his or her diagnosis on the exclusion of 
  actual physical or mental illness, and his or her observation of the 
  person's attitude and behavior. How Are Factitious Disorders Treated? The first goal of treatment for a factitious disorder is to modify the 
person's behavior and reduce his or her misuse or overuse of medical resources. 
In the case of factitious disorder by proxy, the main goal is to ensure the 
safety and protection of any real or potential victims. Once the initial goal is 
met, treatment aims to work out any underlying psychological issues that may be 
causing the person's behavior. The primary treatment for factitious disorders is
 psychotherapy (a 
  type of counseling). Treatment likely will focus on changing the 
  thinking and behavior of the individual with the disorder 
  (cognitive-behavioral therapy). Family therapy may also be helpful in 
  teaching family members not to reward or reinforce the behavior of the 
  person with the disorder. There are no medications to treat factitious disorders themselves. 
  Medication may be used, however, to treat any related disorder -- such 
  as
 depression ,
 anxiety , or a personality disorder. The use of 
  medications must be carefully monitored in people with factitious 
  disorders due to the risk that the
 drugs may be used in a harmful way.
 What Is the Outlook for People with Factitious Disorders? People with factitious disorders are at risk for health problems (or 
  even death) associated with hurting themselves or otherwise causing 
  symptoms. In addition, they may suffer from reactions or health problems 
  related to multiple tests, procedures, and treatments; and are at high 
  risk for
 substance abuse and attempts at
 suicide . A complication of 
  factitious disorder by proxy is the abuse and potential death of the 
  victims. Because many people with factitious disorders deny they are faking 
  symptoms and will not seek or follow treatment, recovery is dependent on 
  a doctor or loved one identifying or suspecting the condition in the 
  person and encouraging them to receive proper medical care for their 
  disorder and stick with it. Some people with factitious disorders suffer one or two brief 
  episodes of symptoms and then get better. In most cases, however, the 
  factitious disorder is a chronic, or long-term, condition that can be 
  very difficult to treat. Can Factitious Disorders Be Prevented? There is no known way to prevent factitious disorders. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>