<file1>
<first>Frozen Shoulder (Adhesive Capsulitis)
Frozen shoulder (adhesive capsulitis) facts Frozen shoulder is the result of scarring, thickening, and shrinkage of the joint capsule. Any injury to the shoulder can lead to adhesive capsulitis. Frozen shoulder symptoms and signs include loss of range of shoulder movement,
 stiffness , and
 pain . A frozen shoulder is usually diagnosed during an examination. A frozen shoulder usually requires aggressive treatment. What is a frozen shoulder? A frozen shoulder is a shoulder joint with significant loss of its range of motion in all directions. The range of motion is limited not only when the patient attempts motion but also when the doctor attempts to move the joint fully while the patient relaxes. A frozen shoulder is medically referred to as adhesive capsulitis. 
CAUSES:  Frozen shoulder is the result of inflammation, scarring, thickening, and shrinkage of the capsule that surrounds the normal shoulder joint. Any shoulder injury can lead to a frozen shoulder, including tendinitis,
 bursitis , and
 rotator cuff injury (
 rotator cuff syndrome). Adhesive capsulitis occurs more frequently in patients with risk factors of
 diabetes , chronic inflammatory
 arthritis of the shoulder, or after chest or breast surgery. Long-term immobility of the shoulder joint can put people at risk to develop a frozen shoulder. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms and signs of a frozen shoulder include
 shoulder pain , stiffness, and loss of range of shoulder motion. The shoulder range of motion is limited when either the patient or an examiner attempts to move the joint. The shoulder can develop increased
 pain with use. These symptoms can make
 sleep very uncomfortable.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  A frozen shoulder is suggested during examination when the shoulder range of motion is significantly limited, with either the patient or the examiner attempting the movement. Underlying diseases involving the shoulder can be diagnosed with the history, examination, blood testing, and X-ray examination of the shoulder. If necessary, the diagnosis can be confirmed when an X-ray contrast dye is injected into the shoulder joint to demonstrate the characteristic shrunken shoulder capsule of a frozen shoulder. This X-ray test is called arthrography. The tissues of the shoulder can also be evaluated with an
 MRI scan. What conditions can mimic adhesive capsulitis? Inflammation of the shoulder joint (arthritis) or the muscles around the shoulder and
 degenerative arthritis of the shoulder joint can cause swelling, pain, or stiffness of the joint that can mimic the range of motion limitation of a frozen shoulder. Injury to individual tendons around the shoulder (tendons of the
 rotator cuff ) can limit shoulder-joint range of motion but usually not in all directions. Often during the examination of a shoulder with tendon injury (tendinitis or tendon tear), the doctor is able to move the joint with the patient relaxed beyond the range that the patient can on their own. 
TREATMENT:  The treatment of a frozen shoulder usually requires an aggressive combination of
 over-the-counter non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medication,
 cortisone injection (s) into the shoulder, and physical therapy (physiotherapy). Without aggressive treatment, adhesive capsulitis can be permanent. Diligent physical therapy is often essential for recovery. A physical therapist will administer
 ultrasound , electric stimulation, range-of-motion
 exercise maneuvers, stretching, ice packs, and eventually strengthening exercises. Physical therapy can take weeks to months for recovery, depending on the severity of the scarring of the tissues around the shoulder. It is very important for people with a frozen shoulder to avoid reinjuring the shoulder tissues during the rehabilitation period. These individuals should avoid sudden, jerking motions of or heavy lifting with the affected shoulder. Sometimes a frozen shoulders is resistant to treatment. Patients with resistant frozen shoulders can be considered for release of the
 scar tissue by arthroscopic surgery or manipulation of the scarred shoulder under anesthesia. This manipulation is performed to physically break up the
 scar tissue of the joint capsule. It carries the risk of breaking the arm bone (humerus
 fracture ). It is very important for patients that undergo manipulation to partake in an active
 exercise program for the shoulder after the procedure. It is only with continued exercise of the shoulder that mobility and function is optimized.
 What is the prognosis of a frozen shoulder? The prognosis of a frozen shoulder depends on its response to physical therapy, exercises, and treatments as described above. Again, it is essential to avoid reinjuring the shoulder tissues during the rehabilitation period. Patients with resistant frozen shoulders can be considered for release of the scar tissue by arthroscopic surgery or manipulation of the scarred shoulder under anesthesia. Without aggressive treatment, a frozen shoulder can be permanent. 
PREVENTION:  Prevention of a frozen shoulder involves avoiding injury or reinjury to the shoulder.
</first>
</file1>