<file1>
<first>Gaucher Disease

ABOUT: Gaucher disease is an inherited 
(genetic) condition that is due to a deficiency in the enzyme 
glucocerebrosidase. Gaucher disease leads to the 
accumulation of fatty substances in certain organs. Signs and symptoms of Gaucher disease 
include
 enlarged liver and spleen, fatigue , anemia , bone pain and
 fractures , and easy bruising and bleeding. Signs and symptoms vary among people with Gaucher disease. There are several types of Gaucher disease including type 1, 2, 3 
 Gaucher disease; perinatal lethal Gaucher disease, and cardiovascular 
 Gaucher disease. The most common type of Gaucher disease is type 1, and this type typically does not affect the nervous system. Type 2 Gaucher disease and perinatal 
lethal Gaucher disease are rare and severe forms of the disease. Gaucher disease is inherited in an 
autosomal recessive manner. Gaucher disease is most common in 
people of Ashkenazi Jewish descent, affecting about 1 out of every 855 people. 
In the non-Jewish population, Gaucher disease affects 1 out of every 40,000 
people. Enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) is the 
main treatment for Gaucher disease. Those with family members affected with 
Gaucher disease may want to consider
 genetic counseling and screening for the 
genetic mutation.
 What is Gaucher disease? Gaucher disease (sometimes called Gaucher&amp;#39;s disease) is an inherited 
condition that results in the abnormal accumulation of fatty substances known as 
glycolipids in different body tissues due to a deficiency of an enzyme known as glucocerebrosidase. There are several different types of the condition, 
and the signs and symptoms that arise due to the sphingolipid accumulation vary 
widely. Gaucher disease is due to a genetic defect in a gene known as GBA1. 
Gaucher disease belongs to a class of diseases called lysosomal storage 
diseases, named after a type of cell that is affected by the buildup of 
glycolipids. 
SYMPTOMS:  The main signs and symptoms of Gaucher disease are: Anemia (
 low red blood cell count ) Fatigue (tiredness) Low platelet count , 
that can lead to easy bruising  
 Enlarged spleen and liver (hepatosplenomegaly) Easy bleeding that is difficult to stop Bone pain, bone crisis (severe bone pain 
often accompanied by
 fever ), and the chance of easily broken bones People with type 1 Gaucher disease usually first notice painless enlargement 
of the spleen, anemia, or bleeding and bruising due to low platelet count. The 
enlargement of the spleen may become severe and may limit a child&amp;#39;s growth due 
to the energy required to sustain the enlarging spleen. An enlarged liver and 
abnormal
 liver function tests are also characteristic signs. Skeletal 
involvement by Gaucher disease is common and can take the form of bone pain, 
fractures of bone, and a defect of the thigh bone (femur).
 How is Gaucher disease inherited? Gaucher disease is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern, meaning that both parents must carry a copy of the defective gene in order for a child to be affected. How common is Gaucher disease? In people of Ashkenazi Jewish descent Type 1 Gaucher disease (see below) is 
more common, and affects 1 out of every 855 people. About 1 out of every 15 
people of Ashkenazi Jewish descent are thought to be carriers of the genetic 
mutation responsible for Gaucher disease. The other types of Gaucher disease do 
not occur more frequently in people of Ashkenazi Jewish heritage. In the 
non-Jewish population, Gaucher disease affects 1 out of every 40,000 people. What are the types of Gaucher disease? The most common form of the condition is type 1 Gaucher disease. About 90% of people with the condition have this type. The signs and symptoms of this type can vary in their extent of severity. The symptoms can appear in childhood or may be delayed until adulthood. The brain and spinal cord, or central nervous system (CNS), are typically not affected by the disease, so this type is sometimes referred to as non-neuronopathic, meaning that the condition does not affect nerve cells. This rare type of Gaucher disease affects the nervous system and is termed neuronopathic Gaucher disease. Signs and symptoms include seizures, eye movement problems, and
 brain damage . Type 2 Gaucher disease is very severe and typically leads to life-threatening medical problems that begin in infancy. Like Type 2 Gaucher disease, type 3 Gaucher is a neuronopathic form of Gaucher disease that affects the nervous system, but symptoms do not progress as rapidly as in Type 2. The signs and symptoms may appear in infancy or later in childhood. Perinatal lethal Gaucher disease is the most severe form of the condition. With this type, the life-threatening conditions can appear before birth. There may be excessive swelling and fluid accumulation in the fetus (hydrops fetalis) prior to birth. Other features can include severe neurological disturbances, abnormal facial features, hepatosplenomegaly, and dry or scaly skin. Most infants with this form of the condition survive only a few days after birth. This type of Gaucher disease, considered a rare subgroup of type 3 disease, primarily affects the heart, leading to calcification or hardening of the heart valves. Sometimes, symptoms and signs of other types of Gaucher disease may also be present.
 
CAUSES:  All of the types of Gaucher disease are caused by a deficiency of the enzyme 
glucocerebrosidase, leading to an abnormal buildup of fatty substances, 
glycolipids, in the body cells. Mutations in the gene known as GBA1 are the 
cause of the deficient enzyme, and over 300 different GBA1 mutations have been 
identified in people with Gaucher disease. The mutations are inherited (passed 
from parent to offspring) in an autosomal recessive manner (see above). The four 
most common mutations of GBA1 gene are N370S, L444P, 84gg and IVS2[+1]. DNA 
analysis for these 4 mutations can detect 90%-95% of the mutations associated 
with Gaucher Disease in the Ashkenazi Jewish population, and 50%-75% of the 
associated mutations in the general population. Which specialties of doctors treat Gaucher disease? Patients with Gaucher disease may be treated by a number of different medical 
specialists, depending on the type of the disease and the specific symptoms and 
signs of the condition they experience. These may include pediatricians, 
neonatologists, internists, geneticists, neurologists, orthopedists, critical 
care specialists, cardiologists, and hematologists. Most patients who are 
treated with enzyme replacement therapy will have their 
treatment plan managed by a geneticist and/or hematologist. 
DIAGNOSIS:  A blood test is used to make the diagnosis of Gaucher disease. The enzyme assay test measures the activity of the glucocerebrosidase enzyme in certain white blood cells. Having less than 15% of normal enzyme activity is diagnostic for Gaucher disease. Genetic analysis is also done to establish the specific type of mutations in the GBA1 gene. 
TREATMENT:  There is no cure for Gaucher disease, but medical treatments are available. 
Enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) is the primary form of treatment for people 
with type 1 and Gaucher disease and for the non-neurologic symptoms of type 3 
Gaucher disease. The drug is given intravenously, generally at 2-week intervals. 
There are three ERT
 drugs available, imiglucerase (
 Cerezyme ), velaglucerase alfa 
(VPRIV), and taliglucerase alfa (Elelyso). Other medications available to treat Gaucher disease include drugs that block 
the production of the sphingolipids that accumulate in cells and cause symptoms. 
These drugs are known as glucosylceramide synthase inhibitors and are taken by 
mouth. Two drugs in this class are miglustat (Zavesca) and eliglustat 
(Cerdelga). Formerly, the condition was often treated by surgical removal of the spleen 
(splenectomy). However, this is typically not necessary given the availability 
of ERT.
 What is the prognosis, or life-expectancy, for someone with Gaucher disease? The prognosis for people with type 1 or type 3 Gaucher disease who receive treatment is very good. Many people with Gaucher disease have few symptoms and can expect a normal lifespan even without treatment. One study estimated life expectancy at birth for people with type 1 Gaucher disease to be 68 years, compared with 77 years in the general population. Type 2 Gaucher disease usually results in death within the first few years of life. Should I talk to my family about Gaucher disease? As with any
 inherited disease , sharing information with family members is 
important. If Gaucher disease is identified within a family, other family 
members may wish to be tested to find out if they are carriers for the gene 
mutation. Carrier testing is simple and can be performed on a sample of blood or 
saliva. Your health-care professional can help you decide if carrier testing is 
appropriate and may refer you to a genetic counselor for more information. What help is available for patients and their families living with Gaucher 
disease? Living with Gaucher disease or any chronic illness is stressful for both 
patient and family. Getting help and support are important for achieving the 
best quality of life possible while facing the challenges and that the illness 
brings. The National Gaucher Foundation (800-504-3189) offers educational and 
support services for affected families, including a mentor program, an 
electronic pen pal program for young adults, real-life patient stories, and 
numerous educational programs. What other names are used to refer to Gaucher disease? Gaucher disease has been referred to in the medical literature by a number of different names. These include: cerebroside lipidosis syndrome Gaucher
 splenomegaly Gaucher syndrome Gaucher&amp;#39;s disease Gauchers disease GD glucocerebrosidase deficiency glucocerebrosidosis glucosyl cerebroside lipidosis glucosylceramidase deficiency glucosylceramide beta-glucosidase deficiency glucosylceramide lipidosis kerasin histiocytosis kerasin lipoidosis kerasin thesaurismosis lipoid histiocytosis (kerasin type)
</first>
</file1>