<file1>
<first>Genetic Counseling
What are genetic professionals and what do they do? Genetics professionals are health care professionals with specialized degrees 
and experience in medical genetics and counseling. Genetics professionals 
include geneticists, genetic counselors and genetics nurses. What is genetic counseling and evaluation? Genetic professionals work as members of health care teams providing 
information and support to individuals or families who have genetic disorders or 
may be at risk for inherited conditions. Genetic professionals: Assess the risk of a
 genetic disorder by researching a family's history and 
evaluating medical records.
 Weigh the medical, social and ethical decisions surrounding genetic 
testing.
 Provide support and information to help a person make a decision about 
testing.
 Interpret the results of genetic tests and medical data.
 Provide counseling or refer individuals and families to support services.
 Serve as patient advocates.
 Explain possible treatments or preventive measures.
 Discuss reproductive options. Additional Resources What is a genetics consultation? What to Expect from a Genetics Consultation How do I find a genetic professional? Your health care provider may refer you to a genetic professional. 
Universities and medical centers also often have affiliated genetic 
professionals, or can provide referrals to a genetic professional or genetics 
clinic. As more has been learned about genetics, genetic 
professionals have grown more specialized. For example, they may specialize in a 
particular disease (such as
 cancer genetics), an age group (such as 
adolescents) or a type of counseling 
(such as
 prenatal ). How do I decide whether I need to see a geneticist or other specialist? Your health care provider may refer you to a geneticist - a medical doctor or 
medical researcher - who specializes in your disease or disorder. A medical 
geneticist has completed a fellowship or has other advanced training in medical 
genetics. While a genetic counselor or 
genetic nurse may help you with testing decisions and support issues, a medical 
geneticist will make the actual diagnosis of a disease or condition. Many genetic diseases are so rare that only 
a geneticist can provide the most complete and current information about your 
condition. Along with a medical geneticist, you may also be 
referred to a physician who is a specialist in the type of disorder you have. 
For example, if a genetic test is positive for
 colon cancer , you might be referred to an oncologist. For a 
diagnosis of
 Huntington disease , you may be referred to a neurologist. These online resources can help you find a genetic professional in your 
community: ResourceLink A database of genetics counseling services, searchable by location, name, 
institution, type of practice or specialty. Hosted by the National Society of 
Genetic Counselors.
 Genetic Centers, 
 Clinics and Departments A comprehensive resource list for genetic counseling, including links to 
genetic centers and clinics, associations, and university genetics departments. 
Hosted by the University of Kansas Medical Center.
 GeneClinics A searchable directory of international genetics and
 prenatal diagnosis clinics. SOURCE: National Human Genome Research Institute, "Frequently Asked Questions About Genetic Counseling."
</first>
</file1>