<file1>
<first>Genetic Diseases (Inherited) Symptoms, Causes, Treatments, and Prognosis
What is a genetic disease? How is it defined? A genetic disease is any disease that is caused by an abnormality in an individual&amp;#39;s genome, the person&amp;#39;s entire genetic makeup. The abnormality can range from minuscule to major -- from a discrete mutation in a single base in the DNA of a single gene to a gross chromosome abnormality involving the addition or subtraction of an entire chromosome or set of chromosomes. Some genetic disorders are inherited from the parents, while other genetic diseases are caused by acquired changes or mutations in a preexisting gene or group of genes. Mutations can occur either randomly or due to some environmental exposure. What are the types of genetic inheritance? There are a number of different types of genetic inheritance including: Single gene inheritance Multifactorial inheritance Chromosome abnormalities Mitochondrial inheritance Single gene genetic inheritance Single gene inheritance, also called Mendelian or monogenetic inheritance. This type of inheritance is caused by changes or mutations that occur in the DNA sequence of a single gene. There are more than 6,000 known single-gene disorders, which occur in about 1 out of every 200 births. These disorders are known as monogenetic disorders (disorders of a single gene). Some examples of monogenetic disorders include: cystic fibrosis , sickle cell anemia , Marfan syndrome , Huntington&amp;#39;s disease, and hemochromatosis . Single-gene disorders are inherited in recognizable patterns: autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive, and X-linked. Multifactorial genetic inheritance Multifactorial inheritance, which is also called complex or polygenic inheritance. Multifactorial inheritance disorders are caused by a combination of environmental factors and mutations in multiple genes. For example, different genes that influence
 breast cancer susceptibility have been found on chromosomes 6, 11, 13, 14, 15, 17, and 22. Some common chronic diseases are multifactorial disorders. Examples of multifactorial inheritance include: heart disease , high blood pressure , Alzheimer&amp;#39;s disease, arthritis , diabetes , cancer , and obesity . Multifactorial inheritance also is associated with heritable traits such as fingerprint patterns, height, eye color, and skin color. Chromosome abnormalities Chromosomes, distinct structures made up of DNA and protein, are located in the nucleus of each cell. Because chromosomes are the carriers of the genetic material, abnormalities in chromosome number or structure can result in disease. Abnormalities in chromosomes typically occur due to a problem with cell division. For example,
 Down syndrome (sometimes referred to as "Down&amp;#39;s syndrome") or
 trisomy 21 is a common disorder that occurs when a person has three copies of chromosome 21. There are many other chromosome abnormalities including: Turner syndrome (45,X0), Klinefelter syndrome (47, XXY), and Cri du chat syndrome, or the "cry of the cat" syndrome (46, XX or XY, 5p-). Diseases may also occur because of chromosomal translocation in which portions of two chromosomes are exchanged. Mitochondrial genetic inheritance This type of genetic disorder is caused by mutations in the non-nuclear DNA of mitochondria. Mitochondria are small round or rod-like organelles that are involved in cellular
 respiration and found in the cytoplasm of plant and animal cells. Each mitochondrion may contain 5 to 10 circular pieces of DNA. Since egg cells, but not sperm cells, keep their mitochondria during
 fertilization , mitochondrial DNA is always inherited from the female parent. Examples of
 mitochondrial disease include: an eye disease called Leber&amp;#39;s hereditary optic atrophy; a type of
 epilepsy called MERRF which stands for myoclonic
 epilepsy with Ragged Red Fibers; and a form of
 dementia called MELAS for mitochondrialencephalopathy, lactic acidosis and
 stroke-like episodes . What is the human genome? The human genome is the entire "treasury of human inheritance." The sequence of the human genome obtained by the Human Genome Project, completed in April 2003, provides the first holistic view of our genetic heritage. The 46 human chromosomes (22 pairs of autosomal chromosomes and 2 sex chromosomes) between them house almost 3 billion base pairs of DNA that contains about 20,500 protein-coding genes. The coding regions make up less than 5% of the genome (the function of all the remaining DNA is not clear) and some chromosomes have a higher density of genes than others. Most genetic diseases are the direct result of a mutation in one gene. However, one of the most difficult problems ahead is to further elucidate how genes contribute to diseases that have a complex pattern of inheritance, such as in the cases of
 diabetes ,
 asthma ,
 cancer , and
 mental illness . In all these cases, no one gene has the yes/no power to say whether a person will develop the disease or not. It is likely that more than one mutation is required before the disease is manifest, and a number of genes may each make a subtle contribution to a person&amp;#39;s susceptibility to a disease; genes may also affect how a person reacts to environmental factors.</first>
</file1>