<file1>
<first>Genital Herpes in Women Symptoms, Signs, Transmission, and Treatment

ABOUT: Genital herpes is a
 sexually transmitted disease  or sexually transmitted infection (
 STD  or STI) caused by the
 herpes simplex virus (HSV). Herpes simplex virus causes genital herpes by entering the skin or mucous membranes through microscopic breaks in the skin and mucous membranes. There are 2 types of HSV:
 Herpes simplex virus-1, that typically causes
 cold sores , and Herpes simplex virus-2, that typically causes genital herpes. Either herpes simplex virus type can cause sores on the genital areas. Genital herpes is transmitted by any type of sexual contact with the genital area. With the initial (first episode) genital herpes infection, some individuals may develop symptoms that seem flu-like and include
 fever , body aches, and swollen lymph nodes . When symptoms and signs do appear, they may include painful blisters and/or ulcers in the genital area, itching, and burning or tingling sensations in the skin. Genital
 herpes symptoms come and go over the person&amp;#39;s lifetime due to reactivations of the virus. Diagnosis is usually done by recognizing the skin changes in the genital area but viral cultures, genetic amplification of herpes simplex virus genome material, and other tests may be done. There is no cure for genital herpes, but there are medications to make living with genital herpes more manageable. Antiviral medications are used to reduce the severity and frequency of genital herpes. Genital herpes symptoms and signs in women usually develop near the vagina, buttocks, and/or anus a few days after exposure to an infected person. Some natural and home remedies may help relieve and soothe symptoms severity, but provide no cure. Oral antiviral medications may be used in
 pregnancy . Check with your OB/GYN before taking any medications if you are
 pregnant . The prognosis of genital herpes is variable: there is no cure, and the recurrent outbreaks may vary in frequency and severity. Genital herpes prevention is difficult.
 Condoms may prevent the disease spread during sex, but not in areas of skin not covered by a
 condom or during oral to genital contact.
 What is genital herpes? Genital herpes is a common sexually transmitted infection (STI) caused by an infection with the herpes simplex virus (HSV). There are two types of herpes. HSV-1 is most commonly associated with
 blisters and ulcers around the mouth known as
 cold sores  (oral herpes). HSV-2 is associated with blistering lesions in genital areas that are exposed during sexual contact. However, both types of herpes simplex virus can infect the mouth or the genital areas, meaning that genital contact (oral sex) with a cold sore on the mouth can lead to genital herpes. Likewise, kissing someone with a cold sore can spread the herpes simplex virus infection. After the first outbreak of herpes, the virus travels through the nerves and resides in nerve tissue within the body. Reactivations, or repeat occurrences of the blisters, can occur throughout an individual&amp;#39;s lifetime. Among people aged 14 to 49, an estimated one out of every six people have the infection. Genital herpes is not the same thing as
 genital warts .
 Genital warts are flesh-colored growths that appear on the sexually exposed areas due to infection with certain types of
 human papillomavirus (
 HPV ). How common is genital herpes? Herpes is very common. Among people aged 14 to 49, an estimated one out of every six people (15.5% of the population) have been infected with HSV-2, the virus that is predominantly responsible for genital herpes. Estimates suggest that in the U.S., 776,000 people become infected every year. The viral infection is more common in women than in men. Spread from men to women is known to occur more readily than from women to men. According to WHO estimates, HSV-1 infects 67% of all humans under the age of 50. The majority of infected people are not aware they are infected.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Many people infected with genital herpes have mild symptoms or symptoms that are mistaken for another condition. It also is possible to be infected with the virus and have no herpes symptoms. Not every woman who is infected may be aware of the infection. When signs and symptoms are present, they consist of: Typically painful fluid-filled blisters (that may appear like "
 pimples ") around the vaginal area Blisters around the vagina, anus, or buttocks Ulcer formation after the blisters break open Blisters take 2 to 4 weeks to heal. With the first outbreak of genital herpes, a person may also experience
 flu-like symptoms including: Fever Chills Body aches Swollen lymph nodes Immediately prior to an outbreak, there may be an
 itching , burning, or tingling sensation of the skin. In women, genital herpes usually causes blistering lesions on the vulva and around the vaginal opening that progress to ulcer formation. The infection spreads to involve the cervix in most cases, leading to cervicitis (inflammation of the cervix). In some women, cervicitis may be the only sign of genital herpes infection. Infection and inflammation of the urethra accompanies the infection in some women, leading to
 pain on urination. After the initial infection, a person may or may not have outbreaks later in life.
 
CAUSES:  How does it spread? The herpes
 viruses enter the skin or mucous membrane through tiny, even microscopic, breaks in the tissue when there is skin-to-skin contact with an infected person. Because an infected person may spread the disease even when he or she does not have signs or
 symptoms of herpes , avoiding sexual contact with someone with active blisters does not guarantee protection against the infection. Even normal appearing skin can spread the infection. Clothing that touches genital skin ulcers may transmit herpes simplex virus to others that wear the clothing. The average incubation period (time until symptoms develop) after exposure is 4 days, but symptoms may develop anywhere from 2 to 12 days after you have been exposed to the virus. Individual outbreaks of herpes vary among affected people in terms of their frequency and severity. Outbreaks can be related to the function of the immune system and are typically worse in cases in which the immune system is suppressed. For example, at times of physical or emotional
 stress , during illness, or when taking certain medications, genital herpes outbreaks may be more likely. How do you get genital herpes (
transmission)? Herpes simplex virus infection is transmitted by direct person-to-person contact. Genital herpes is acquired through sexual contact of any type that involves contact with the genital areas. Genital herpes also can be caused by mouth to genital contact (oral sex) with a person who has
 cold sores or herpes infection of the mouth. Transmission of herpes from an infected male to a female partner is more likely than transmission from an infected woman to a male partner. Is there a cure for genital herpes? There is no cure for genital herpes, and once a person is infected with genital herpes, the infection persists throughout the individual&amp;#39;s life, with the potential for recurrent outbreaks. However, there are medications that can reduce the severity and frequency of outbreaks and treatments to manage the symptoms.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  In most cases in which the characteristic signs and symptoms are present, they are sufficient to establish a diagnosis of genital herpes infection. Laboratory tests, such as viral culture and nucleic acid amplification (
 polymerase chain reaction or
 PCR ) tests to detect the genetic material of the virus, are also available. Immunologic tests to identify antibodies to genital herpes are other possible tests to establish whether infection has occurred.
 
TREATMENT:  Antiviral medicines are available that can help manage the severity and duration of outbreaks, if taken immediately prior to (when there are tingling or unusual skin sensations but no blisters) or within 24 hours of a herpes outbreak. The medications typically used are acyclovir (
 Zovirax ), famciclovir (
 Famvir ), or valacyclovir (
 Valtrex ). These are all typically taken by mouth. In severe cases of viral infection, antiviral medications may be given intravenously, but this is not usually needed for herpes. Topical medications that are applied directly to the herpes sores are also available, but these are less effective than oral medications and are not generally used. All of these medications may also be given daily as suppressive therapy to decrease the number of outbreaks in people who have frequent herpes outbreaks (more than six outbreaks per year). How do doctors manage genital herpes during pregnancy? Oral antiviral medications as described above may be used during pregnancy. One serious concern with genital herpes in pregnancy is transmission of the infection to the baby during delivery. In an infant, genital herpes infection can spread through the bloodstream and have serious consequences. Cesarean delivery (
 C-section ) is performed for women who go into
 labor while there is an active outbreak of genital herpes in order to prevent infection of the baby during birth. The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists recommends that pregnant women with recurrent genital herpes be offered oral antiviral medication at or beyond 36 weeks until delivery in order to increase the chances of being able to deliver vaginally. Are home remedies or natural treatments effective for genital herpes? There are no home or natural remedies available for genital herpes, and as mentioned above, the infection cannot be cured. Home cares such as warm baths, keeping the blisters dry after washing, and wearing loose-fitting, cotton underwear may help soothe symptoms. What is the prognosis for 
a person with genital herpes? As discussed previously, there is no cure for genital herpes infection, and the infection persists for life. People vary in the number and severity of outbreaks they experience. For those with frequent outbreaks, taking antiviral medications as suppressive therapy can decrease the frequency of outbreaks. 
TREATMENT:  Genital herpes is treated by primary care providers including internal medicine and family medicine specialists, as well as pediatricians for adolescents. For women, gynecologists are often the treating physicians. In certain circumstances, other specialists may be consulted, including urologists and infectious disease specialists.
 Is there a link between genital herpes and HIV? The
 HIV virus that causes
 AIDS is not the same as the genital herpes virus. However, having the ulcers and sores of herpes makes it more likely to contract
 HIV if exposed, or to transmit
 HIV if you have been infected. The ulcers of genital herpes cause breaks in the skin that make spreading the HIV virus to a sex partner more likely during sexual contact. 
PREVENTION:  Herpes can be spread both during an outbreak and by infected people even when there is no outbreak of the condition, so prevention can be difficult. While condoms may help prevent the spread of genital herpes to sexual partners during sexual activity, the infection also can be spread from skin contact in areas not covered by a condom, or during oral to genital contact. If you are having an outbreak, thorough hand washing and not sharing clothing that has touched the herpes sores can also help prevent transmitting the virus to others.
</first>
</file1>