<file1>
<first>Rubella (German Measles)
About rubella Rubella , sometimes called German
 measles or three-day
 measles , is a
 contagious disease caused by a virus. The infection is usually mild with
 fever and
 rash . Symptoms Rubella usually causes the following symptoms in children: Rash that starts on the face and spreads to the rest of the body Low
 fever (less than 101 degrees) These symptoms last 2 or 3 days. Older children and adults may also have swollen glands and symptoms like a
 cold before the rash appears. Aching joints occur in many cases, especially among young women. About half of the people who get rubella do not have symptoms. Complications Birth defects if acquired by a
 pregnant woman: deafness,
 cataracts , heart defects, mental retardation, and
 liver and spleen damage (at least a 20% chance of damage to the fetus if a woman is infected early in
 pregnancy ). Transmission Spread by contact with an infected person, through
 coughing and
 sneezing . Prevention Rubella vaccine (contained in MMR vaccine) can prevent this disease. Does my child need this vaccine? Children should get 2 doses of MMR vaccine: The first dose at 12-15 months of age The second dose at 4-6 years of age These are the recommended ages. But children can get the second dose at any age, as long as it is at least 28 days after the first dose. As an adult, do I need this vaccine? You do NOT need the measles, mumps, rubella vaccine (MMR) if: You had blood tests that show you are immune to measles,
 mumps , and rubella. You are a man born before 1957. You are a woman born before 1957 who is sure she is not having more children, has already had rubella vaccine, or has had a positive rubella test. You already had two doses of MMR
 or one dose of MMR plus a second dose of measles vaccine. You already had one dose of MMR
 and are not at high risk of measles or mumps exposure. You SHOULD get the measles vaccine if you are not among the categories listed above, and You are a college student, trade school student, or other student beyond high school. You work in a hospital or other medical facility. You travel internationally, or are a passenger on a cruise ship. You are a woman of childbearing age.
</first>
</file1>