<file1>
<first>Herpangina

ABOUT: Herpangina is a self-limited viral infection primarily caused by a member of the Coxsackievirus family. Herpangina most often affects young children. Herpangina is associated with
 fever ,
 sore throat , and
 blisters in the back of the mouth. Generally, doctors diagnose herpangina based on clinical symptoms and characteristic physical findings alone. Laboratory tests are usually unnecessary. Treatment of herpangina aims to minimize the discomfort associated with the mouth
 blisters . Most children with herpangina recover completely after four to seven days. There is no easy way to prevent herpangina. What is herpangina? Herpangina is an acute, self-limited viral illness often seen in young children during the summer months. Affected children usually complain of
 mouth sores and
 fever . A number of
 viruses , all members of the
 Enterovirus family, cause herpangina. Coxsackievirus is the most common cause of the infection. Most children develop a high fever and complain of a
 sore throat . They then develop vesicles (blisters) or ulcers (sores) at the back of the throat and palate. Children, especially younger children, may refuse to eat or drink because of the
 pain and are at risk for developing signs and
 symptoms of dehydration . 
CAUSES:  Several common members of the Coxsackie A virus family and a number of other enteroviruses can cause herpangina. The viruses are usually spread via the "fecal-oral route" (contamination of hands and other surfaces with fecal matter) or via the "respiratory route" (air droplets from
 coughing or
 sneezing ). One can contract the illness from contact with either of these materials from an individual infected with one of these viruses. Interestingly, half of individuals infected with some of these
 Enterovirus family members remain asymptomatic (having no symptoms) which makes preventing transmission more difficult.
 Is herpangina contagious? Coxsackievirus infections are extremely
 contagious and can easily pass from child to child through contaminated surfaces, unwashed hands, and through sneezing and coughing. Typically, people infected with the virus are most contagious during the first week of illness. How long is the incubation period for herpangina? The normal course of the infection involves an incubation period (the duration between exposure to the virus and development of symptoms) lasting anywhere from one to two weeks. 
SYMPTOMS:  Typically, children with herpangina have the following: Fever Sore throat Small blisters and ulcers may cover the soft palate, uvula,
 tonsils , and posterior pharynx. The rest of the mouth is normal in appearance. The
 gingiva ("gums"), buccal mucosa (inner cheek region) and tongue are not generally involved. These blisters can last for up to a week. Enlarged lymph nodes along the neck (
 lymphadenopathy ) Rash may or may not be present. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Since herpangina is a clinical diagnosis, and the illness is self-limited, there is no real reason to perform any laboratory studies. Some children (hospitalized or immune-compromised for example) may have viral studies performed on specimens from the nose or throat. Isolating virus from these samples takes a long time, and generally, symptoms resolve long before the identification of the virus is available. It&amp;#39;s possible to measure antibodies to Coxsackievirus if desired, but that is generally unnecessary.
 
TREATMENT:  Treatment is supportive, just like for most virus infections. Fever and
 pain control with
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ) or
 ibuprofen (
 Advil /
 Motrin ) are generally the primary treatments. It is important to keep children well hydrated as well, and often young children will be resistant to drinking or eating. The aptly named "magic mouthwash" is an alternative treatment used to control the mouth pain associated with herpangina. There are various
 recipes , but most include a topical pain medication such as viscous
 lidocaine as well as some sort of additional liquids that function as a barrier. A child&amp;#39;s health care provider might prescribe one of these. It is important to remember that patients always should use these types of medications as directed by a provider, since some of the components may have serious side effects if given in too high a concentration. Remember that since a virus causes herpangina, antibiotics have no role in the treatment, nor do any antiviral medications currently available. Many young patients find that a
 diet of cold, soft items provide a special treat and lessen their symptoms (if only by a placebo effect). Ice cream, smoothies, milk shakes, yogurt and frozen yogurt may all be helpful. How long does herpangina last?What is the prognosis for herpangina? The entire duration of the illness is usually four to seven days. The prognosis is usually excellent. Very rarely, younger patients may refuse to drink or eat and will require hospitalization for intravenous fluids for hydration. It is important to manage a young child&amp;#39;s pain to prevent this from occurring. Rarely, enteroviral infections can also cause viral or aseptic
 meningitis . These patients usually recover fully. What is the difference between herpangina and hand, foot, and mouth disease? Enteroviruses cause both herpangina and
 hand, foot, and mouth (HFM) disease. Both cause oral blisters and ulcers. The locations of the blisters differ, with HFM lesions occurring at the front of the mouth and herpangina lesions occurring at the back of the mouth. Approximately 75% of children with HFM also develop skin lesions on the palms and soles (as the name implies), but children with herpangina rarely develop any typical
 rashes .
 What is the difference between herpangina and herpes simplex-1 (HSV-1)? Herpes simplex 1 (HSV-1) infections are also very common in young children. Unlike herpangina, HSV-1 infections do not have a seasonal preference.
 Gingivostomatitis is another term for HSV-1 infection. The characteristic changes in the mouth are zones of multiple small (1-2 mm) vesicles with a surrounding 1-2 mm halo of inflamed tissue. Areas involved are more varied than seen in herpangina. HSV-1 infections commonly involve the buccal mucosa (inner cheek tissue), gingiva (gums), tongue (also known as "stomatitis") and the hard and soft palate. Approximately 60% of infected people will develop lesions on the lips and adjacent skin, commonly known as "
 cold sores ." Common characteristics shared by herpangina and HSV-1 infections include moderate fever, reduced appetite,
 headache , and malaise. The typical HSV-1 infection lasts for seven to 10 days. Herpangina symptoms generally last for four to seven days. While there are no antiviral
 drugs to treat herpangina, it&amp;#39;s possible to lessen HSV-1 infection symptoms if an individual starts oral
 acyclovir immediately upon developing early symptoms. Topical preparations of acyclovir are not helpful. 
PREVENTION:  Prevention of herpangina is dependent upon good hygiene (for example, frequent hand washing with soap and water) and avoidance of individuals infected with Coxsackievirus. This is easier said than done, since as mentioned earlier, 50% of infected individuals remain asymptomatic. There is no
 vaccine . Where can people find more information about herpangina? "Non-Polio Enterovirus," CDC
 http://www.cdc.gov/non-polio-enterovirus/index.html "Viral Exanthems," Dermatology Online Journal
 http://dermatology.cdlib.org/93/reviews/viral/scott.html
</first>
</file1>