<file1>
<first>Hoarseness

ABOUT: Hoarseness is an abnormal change in the voice. The most common cause of hoarseness is 
 acute
 laryngitis . The underlying cause of hoarseness can usually be diagnosed by a 
health care professional based on the patient's history and physical exam. The treatment for hoarseness depends on the underlying cause. Hoarseness can be prevented by avoiding excessive strenuous voice use and
 smoking cessation . What is hoarseness? Hoarseness is an abnormal change in the voice caused by a variety of 
conditions. The voice may have changes in pitch and volume, ranging from a deep, 
harsh voice to a weak, raspy voice. 
CAUSES:  Hoarseness is generally caused by irritation of, or 
injury to, the vocal 
cords. The larynx (also referred 
to as the voice box), is the portion of the respiratory (
 breathing ) tract 
containing the vocal cords. The cartilaginous outer wall of the larynx is 
commonly referred to as the "Adams apple." The vocal cords are two bands of 
muscle that form a "V" inside the larynx. When we sing or 
speak, the vocal cords vibrate and produce sound. Hoarseness can be caused by a number of conditions. The 
most common cause of hoarseness is acute laryngitis (inflammation of the vocal 
cords) caused most often by an
 upper respiratory tract infection (usually viral), and less 
commonly from overuse or misuse of the voice (such as from yelling or singing). Other causes of hoarseness include: benign vocal cord nodules, cysts or polyps, gastroesophageal reflux (
 GERD ), allergies , inhalation of respiratory tract irritants, smoking , thyroid problems, trauma to the larynx/vocal cords, neurological 
conditions (such as
 Parkinson's disease and
 strokes), and cancer of the larynx .
 
SYMPTOMS:  Hoarseness typically gives the voice a raspy and harsh 
quality, though it may also cause a change in the pitch or volume of the voice. 
The rapidity of onset 
and any associated symptoms will depend on the underlying cause leading to 
hoarseness. 
DIAGNOSIS:  A health care professional will ask the patient questions 
about their hoarseness and any other associated symptoms. A physical exam will 
focus on the head and neck. Often times, a diagnosis can be made based on this 
initial assessment. In some instances, a long lighted flexible tube (fiberoptic 
scope) will be inserted into the throat to directly visualize the vocal cords if no other cause is initially 
identified. Individuals with hoarseness that lasts longer than 2 to 3 weeks should 
have a consultation with an otolaryngologist 
in order to exclude any serious causes of hoarseness. 
TREATMENT:  The treatment for hoarseness depends on the underlying 
cause, for example: Acute laryngitis caused by an upper respiratory tract infection will 
usually improve on its own as the infection clears the body. Conservative 
treatment with
 cough suppressants and humidified air can be helpful. Voice rest is also recommended
in order to avoid further irritation or injury to the vocal cords. Antibiotics 
are not indicated for most cases of acute laryngitis. Smoking cessation is 
suggested for those individuals that smoke. Individuals with hoarseness caused by vocal overuse or misuse should adhere 
to voice rest, as serious injury (such as vocal cord hemorrhage can occur to the vocal cords if the voice is 
strenuously used during episodes of acute laryngitis. Medications for gastroesophageal reflux (
 GERD ) or
 allergies can treat hoarseness if either of these is found to be the underlying 
cause. In some instances, surgery may be necessary for benign nodules or polyps, trauma to the 
larynx/vocal cords and for
 cancer of the larynx.
 
PREVENTION:  Hoarseness can be prevented in some instances, for example: Avoid situations that require 
excessive strenuous voice use, and if a person needs to project their voice, use a microphone 
 if possible. Voice therapists or singing teachers may be helpful in 
certain cases to assist individuals with vocal training and voice modification. Smoking cessation can prevent hoarseness or the 
development of
 cancer of the larynx. Individuals with hoarseness caused 
by gastroesophageal reflux (GERD) can benefit from medications and dietary 
modification (such as avoiding alcohol,
 caffeine , and spicy foods).
</first>
</file1>