<file1>
<first>HPV Infection in Men
HPV Virus (Genital Warts ) in Men Introduction Much of the information about
 HPV virus (human 
papillomavirus) centers on women, since having the virus increases their risk of 
getting
 cervical cancer . But
 HPV virus in men can cause health problems, too. So 
it's important for men to understand how to reduce the risks of HPV infection. It can increase a man's risk of getting genital cancers, although these 
cancers are not common. HPV can also cause
 genital warts in men, just as in 
women. More than half of men who are sexually active in the United States will have 
HPV at some time in their life. Often, a man will clear the virus on his own, 
with no health problems. Risks of HPV Virus in Men Some of the 30 or so types of HPV associated with 
genital cancers can lead to
 cancer of the anus or 
penis in men. Both of these
 cancer types are rare. In those with a healthy immune system, they are even 
rarer. About 1,530 men in the U.S. were diagnosed with
 cancer of the penis in 
2006, according to American
 Cancer Society estimates. About 1,910 men got a 
diagnosis of
 anal cancer . The risk of anal
 cancer is about 17 times higher in sexually active gay and 
bisexual men than in men who have sex only with women. Men who have
 HIV (human
 immunodeficiency virus) are also at higher risk of getting this cancer. Other types of HPV virus rarely cause cancer in men, but they do cause
 genital warts . At a given point in time, about 1% of sexually active men in the 
U.S. will have genital
 warts .
 Male HPV: The Symptoms The types of high-risk HPV that can cause cancer 
rarely present any symptoms in men or in women. Genital
 warts are the first 
symptom you may see with low-risk HPV
 strains that cause warts but not cancer. Tests for HPV Virus in Men To diagnose genital warts in men, the doctor will 
visually check a man's genital area to see if warts are present. Some doctors 
will apply a vinegar solution to help identify warts that aren't raised and 
visible. But the test is not foolproof. Sometimes normal skin is mistakenly 
identified as a
 wart . There is no routine test for men to check for high-risk HPV
 strains that can 
cause cancer. However, some doctors are urging anal Pap tests for gay and 
bisexual men, who are at higher risk of anal cancer caused by HPV. In an anal
 Pap test , the doctor collects cells from the anus, and then has them checked for 
abnormalities in a lab. Treatments for HPV There is no treatment for asymptomatic HPV infection. 
Instead, doctors treat the health problems that are caused by the HPV virus. When genital warts appear, a variety of treatments can be used. The patient 
can apply prescription creams at home. Or a doctor can surgically remove or 
freeze off the warts. Early treatment of warts is discouraged by some doctors because genital warts 
can go away on their own. It can also take time for all warts to appear. So a 
person who treats warts as soon as they appear may need another treatment later 
on. Anal cancer can be treated with
 radiation ,
 chemotherapy , and surgery. The 
specific treatments depend on the stage of cancer - how big the
 tumor is and how 
far the cancer has spread.
 HPV Vaccine for Men? The
 HPV vaccine Gardasil , approved for use in women in 
2006, is not yet approved for men. Studies are still being done to determine if the vaccine works in males. 
Eventually, public health experts say, boys and men may be vaccinated. How to Manage HPV in a Relationship If a man's long-term sexual partner has 
HPV, chances are good HPV transmission has already occurred and he also has it. 
HPV in men may clear from the body more easily than in women. Women, in general, 
often clear the virus in two years or less. The HPV types associated with
 cervical cancer usually do not cause health 
problems for a heterosexual man having sex with an HPV-infected woman. If a partner has HPV, it does not necessarily mean they have had sex with 
someone else recently. The virus can lay dormant in the body for years without 
causing noticeable symptoms. How to Prevent Transmission of HPV Abstinence is the only sure way to prevent 
HPV transmission. Risk of transmission can be lowered if a person has sex only 
with one person who is not infected and who is monogamous. To lower the risk of HPV transmission, men can also limit the number of sex 
partners and pick partners who have had few or no partners in the past. Condoms can provide some protection against HPV transmission. But they aren't 
100% effective, since HPV is transmitted primarily by skin-to-skin contact. The 
virus can still infect the skin uncovered by the
 condom . In a recent study of young women who had just become sexually active, those 
whose partners used a condom each time they had sex were 70% less likely to get 
an HPV infection than were women whose partners used a condom less than 5% of 
the time. WebMD Medical Reference SOURCES: Joel Palefsky, MD, professor of medicine, University of California, 
San Francisco. CDC: "HPV and Men," and "HPV Vaccine: Questions and Answers." 
American Social Health Association: "HPV: Genital Warts: Questions &amp;amp; 
Answers," and ""What Men Should Know." Diane Harper, MD, MPH, professor of 
community and family medicine and obstetrics and gynecology, Dartmouth Medical 
School, Hanover, N.H. Joan Walker, MD, gynecologic oncologist, University of 
Oklahoma Health Sciences Center, Oklahoma City. Winer R. New England Journal of 
Medicine, June 22, 2006: vol 354: pp 2645-2654. Reviewed by Louise Chang, MD on April 24, 2007 © 2007 WebMD, Inc. All rights reserved.
</first>
</file1>