<file1>
<first>Hematocrit
What is the hematocrit? The hematocrit is the proportion, by volume, of the blood that consists of
 red blood cells . The hematocrit (hct) is expressed as a percentage. For example, a hematocrit of 25% means that there are 25 milliliters of red blood cells in 100 milliliters of blood. How is the hematocrit measured? The hematocrit is typically measured from a blood sample by an automated machine that makes several other measurements of the blood at the same time. Most of these machines in fact do not directly measure the hematocrit, but instead calculate it based on the determination of the amount of
 hemoglobin and the average volume of the red blood cells. The hematocrit can also be determined by a manual method using a centrifuge. When a tube of blood is centrifuged, the
 red cells will be packed into the bottom of the tube. The proportion of red cells to the total blood volume can then be visually measured.
 What is a normal hematocrit? The normal ranges for hematocrit are depend on the age and, after adolescence, the sex of the individual. The normal ranges are: Newborns: 55% to 68% One (1) week of age: 47% to 65% One (1) month of age: 37% to 49% Three (3) months of age: 30% to 36% One (1) year of age: 29% to 41% Ten (10) years of age: 36% to 40% Adult males: 42% to 54% Adult women: 38% to 46% These values may vary slightly among different laboratories.
 What does a low hematocrit mean? A person who has a low hematocrit is referred to as being
 anemic . There are many reasons for
 anemia . Some of the more common reasons are loss of blood (traumatic injury, surgery, bleeding, and
 colon cancer ), nutritional deficiency (iron, vitamin B12, folate), bone marrow problems (replacement of bone marrow by
 cancer , suppression by
 chemotherapy drugs ,
 kidney failure ), and abnormal hemoglobin (
 sickle cell anemia ).
 What does a high hematocrit mean? Higher than normal hematocrit levels represent abnormally elevated red blood cell counts. High hematocrits can be seen in people living at high altitudes and in chronic
 smokers .
 Dehydration produces a falsely high hematocrit that disappears when proper fluid balance is restored. Some other infrequent causes of an elevated hematocrit are lung disease, certain tumors, a disorder of the bone marrow known as
 polycythemia rubra Vera, and abuse of the drug
 erythropoietin (
 Epogen ) by athletes for "blood doping" purposes.
</first>
</file1>