<file1>
<first>Hypermobility Syndrome (Joint Hypermobility Syndrome)

ABOUT: The joint hypermobility syndrome is a condition that features joints that easily move beyond the normal range expected for that particular joint. Hypermobile joints tend to be
 inherited . Symptoms of the joint hypermobility syndrome include
 pain in the knees, fingers, hips, and elbows. Often joint hypermobility causes no symptoms and requires no treatment. Treatments are customized for each individual based on their particular manifestations. What is the joint hypermobility syndrome? The joint hypermobility syndrome is a condition that features joints that easily move beyond the normal range expected for a particular joint. The joint hypermobility syndrome is considered a benign condition. It is estimated that 10%-15% of normal children have hypermobile joints or joints that can move beyond the normal range of motion. Hypermobile joints are sometimes referred to as "loose joints," and those affected are referred to as being "double jointed." 
CAUSES:  Hypermobile joints tend to be inherited in specific genes passed on by parents to their children. It is felt that these certain genes predispose to the development of hypermobile joints. As a result, there is a tendency of the condition to run in families (familial). Genes that are responsible for the production of collagen, an important protein that helps to glue tissues together, are suspected of playing a role. 
RISKS:  Joint hypermobility is also a feature of a rare, inherited, more significant medical condition called
 Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), which is characterized by
 weakness of the connective tissues of the body. Joint hypermobility is commonly seen in people with
 Down syndrome and in people with
 Marfan syndrome .
 
SYMPTOMS:  Because the joints are capable of excessive motion in people with the joint hypermobility syndrome, they are susceptible to injury. Symptoms of the joint hypermobility syndrome include
 pain in the knees, fingers, hips, and elbows. There is a higher incidence of joint dislocation and
 sprains of involved joints.
 Scoliosis (curvature of the spine) occurs more frequently in people with hypermobile joints and can lead to
 back pain . Joint hypermobility tends to decrease with
 aging as we become naturally less flexible. Signs of the syndrome are the ability to place the palms of the hands on the floor with the knees fully extended, hyperextension of the knee or elbow beyond 10 degrees, and the ability to touch the thumb to the forearm. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Joint hypermobility syndrome is diagnosed by examining affected joints and noting that they easily move beyond the normal range expected. For example, the middle of the fingers may bend backward more than usual. There is no blood test for hypermobility syndrome.
 
TREATMENT:  Often joint hypermobility causes no symptoms and requires no treatment. Many individuals with joint hypermobility syndrome improve in adulthood. Treatments are customized for each individual based on their particular manifestations.
 Joint pains can be relieved by medications for pain or inflammation. Proper physical
 fitness exercise should be designed to avoid injury to joints. Home remedies include home exercises and
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ), as needed. Sometimes physical therapy can help with rehabilitation of injured areas and can be especially helpful to prevent reinjury. 
TREATMENT:  Doctors who treat hypermobility syndrome include general-medicine doctors, family medicine doctors, and internists, as well as
 rheumatologists , orthopedists, and physical-medicine physicians. 
PREVENTION:  Because joint hypermobility syndrome is inherited, it is not preventable. Nevertheless, when joint hypermobility syndrome causes symptoms, prevention of injury and pain is possible by avoiding
 trauma and with appropriate treatments. What is the prognosis for those affected by joint hypermobility syndrome? Frequently, there are no long-term consequences of joint hypermobility syndrome. However, hypermobile joints can lead to
 joint pain . Over time, joint hypermobility can lead to degenerative cartilage and
 arthritis . Certain hypermobile joints can be at risk for injury, such sprained ligaments.
</first>
</file1>