<file1>
<first>Hypersensitivity Pneumonitis

CAUSES:  Hypersensitivity pneumonitis (HP) is an inflammation of the 
lung (usually of the very small airways) caused by the body's immune 
reaction to small air-borne 
particles.  These particles can be bacteria,
 mold , fungi, or even 
inorganic matter. What is acute hypersensitivity pneumonitis? Acute hypersensitivity pneumonitis tends to occur 4-12 hours after exposure (usually heavy exposure) to the particles. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of acute hypersensitivity pneumonitis include: Fever Chills Coughing Shortness of breath Body
 aches , malaise Chest X-ray may show diffuse small nodules in the
 lungs . Typically, the symptoms will subside hours to days after exposure (provided there are no repeated exposures). The 
abnormalities on chest X-ray abnormalities will also disappear.  The 
patient's condition can deteriorate after exposure; therefore it is imperative 
that a medical evaluation be performed to determine the best course of 
treatment.
 What is chronic hypersensitivity pneumonitis? Chronic (long-term) hypersensitivity pneumonitis causes 
 lung scarring (fibrosis). 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of chronic hypersensitivity pneumonitis include: Shortness of breath Cough Chronic disease is believed to occur after prolonged low grade exposure to the offending particles.
It is sometimes quite surprising that individuals with a passion for their 
hobbies or occupation will continue to allow exposure to lung damage (if the 
offending particles are related to the hobby or job) despite the knowledge that 
it is harmful. What are examples of hypersensitivity pneumonitis? Examples of hypersensitivity pneumonitis include: Farmer's lung disease from exposure to mold spores in hay Pigeon breeder's disease from exposure to protein particles in 
 pigeon droppings Sauna takers' disease from exposure to mold growing in wet 
 containers M
 ushroom workers' disease from exposure to moldy compost Bagassosis from exposure to moldy
 sugar cane Winemaker&amp;#39;s lung from exposure to a fungus on grapes called
 Botrytis cinerea An unusual case was published involving a case of hypersensitivity to
 Canadian goose dropping s. The individual was a physician who was exposed 
 to both indoor and outdoor antigens while living in a suburban Illinois 
 community. One can only imagine the tremendous detective work necessary to 
 make this diagnosis. A more detailed analysis is listed in the table, which includes the 
 types of compounds, bacteria, and molds known to cause hypersensitivity 
 pneumonitis. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Many people with episodes of hypersensitivity pneumonitis are probably unrecognized and undiagnosed. Some cases believed to be viral pneumonias may actually be hypersensitivity pneumonitis. The patient's history of repeated episodes of typical symptoms, hours after exposure to certain environments are important in establishing the diagnosis. Most patients with this disorder have symptoms of shortness of breath and/or
 cough . Quite often a chest 
X-ray may show a variety of abnormalities, but primarily increased lung markings.  A specialist in lung disease will primarily depend on a history of exposure either by occupation or hobby.  With the abnormal chest X-ray, a high resolution cat scan  of the chest is often reviewed.  This study shows a detailed image of the appearance of the lung tissue.  Lung function tests that examine the lung volumes and the ability for gases to move through the lungs (diffusing capacity) are then performed.  Not only are the
 CT scan and pulmonary function tests useful in diagnosis but they are also useful in following response to therapy. Blood antibody tests and skin tests against certain offending molds, bacteria, or particles are  available, but their results are usually inconclusive. Other more recent tests such as the serum KL-6 (Krebs von den Lungen-6; this test may act as a marker for activity seen in diffuse lung disease) may be used.  Infectious causes as well as collagen vascular diseases and
 cancer must be excluded as a cause of the symptoms and signs, and this may involve a biopsy.  Unfortunately the small biopsies obtained with a bronchoscope or a needle are usually inadequate. It is often necessary to perform Video Assisted Thoracoscopic Surgery (a.k.a. VATS), which is an open lung biopsy technique performed by thoracic surgeons under general anesthesia.  This procedure allows for a larger sample size and more accurate diagnosis. The interpretation of these tests is complicated, and is best performed by a doctor experienced in hypersensitivity pneumonitis, often with the help of a pathologist experienced in lung diseases.  The most accurate determination of the cause of hypersensitivity pneumonitis is almost always a detailed exposure history.  It is not uncommon, however, to be unable to find the causative agent.
 
TREATMENT:  The most important treatment of hypersensitivity pneumonitis is avoidance of repeated exposures to the offending particles. With early diagnosis and
 prevention , the prognosis is good. Prolonged, repeated exposures can lead to permanent lung damage, scarring, and  potentially significant disability.
</first>
</file1>