<file1>
<first>Pseudotumor Cerebri (Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension)
What is pseudotumor cerebri? Pseudotumor cerebri literally means "false
 brain tumor ." It is likely due to high pressure within the skull caused by the buildup or poor absorption of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF). The disorder is most common in women between the ages of 20 and 50. 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of pseudotumor cerebri include symptoms that closely mimic large brain tumors: headache , nausea , vomiting , and pulsating sounds within the head. How is pseudotumor cerebri treated? Obesity , other treatable diseases, and some medications can cause raised intracranial pressure and symptoms of pseudotumor cerebri. A thorough medical history and physical examination is needed to evaluate these factors. If a diagnosis of pseudotumor cerebri is confirmed, close, repeated ophthalmologic exams are required to monitor any changes in vision. Drugs may be used to reduce fluid buildup and to relieve pressure. Weight loss and cessation of certain drugs (including
 oral contraceptives ,
 tetracycline , and a variety of steroids) may lead to improvement. Surgery may be needed to remove pressure on the
 optic nerve . Therapeutic shunting, which involves surgically inserting a tube to drain CSF from the lower spine into the abdominal cavity, may be needed to remove excess CSF and relieve CSF pressure. What is the prognosis for patient's with pseudotumor cerebri? The disorder may cause progressive, permanent visual loss in some patients. In some cases, pseudotumor cerebri recurs. For more information about pseudotumor cerebri Intracranial Hypertension Research Foundation 6517 Buena Vista Drive
 Vancouver, WA   98661
 [email protected] http://www.IHRFoundation.org
 Tel: 360-693-4473
 Fax: 360-694-7062 National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD) P.O. Box 1968
 (55 Kenosia Avenue)
 Danbury, CT   06813-1968
 [email protected] http://www.rarediseases.org
 Tel: 203-744-0100 Voice Mail 800-999-NORD (6673)
 Fax: 203-798-2291 Pseudotumor Cerebri Support Network 8247 Riverside Drive
 Powell, OH   43065
 [email protected] http://www.pseudotumorcerebri.com
</first>
</file1>