<file1>
<first>Portal Hypertension
What is portal hypertension? The
 liver serves many purposes within the body from making carbohydrates, 
proteins and
 fats to synthesizing bile to help digest found. Because of this, 
the liver requires a significant blood supply. As opposed to other organs in the 
body, the majority of this blood supply (75%) comes from the venous system 
through the portal system. Blood vessels from the stomach, small intestine, 
pancreas, and spleen converge and form the portal vein delivering nutrients and 
chemical building blocks to the liver. Once in the liver, the portal vein and 
hepatic artery (which accounts for 25% of the liver's blood supply) come 
together to form sinusoids, spaces where the blood is filtered. From there, 
blood makes its way to the Vena cava, the largest vein in the body to return to 
the heart. Portal
 hypertension describes elevated pressure within the portal system, 
including the portal vein and the tributary veins that drain into it. The 
pressure within the portal system is not normally measured and is not an issue 
except if an illness or disease occurs that makes it difficult for blood to flow 
through the liver tissue. This damming effect increases pressure within the 
portal venous system and causes potential problems with
 liver function . It is 
the onset of symptoms associated with
 liver disease that might cause the health 
care professional to look for the presence of portal
 hypertension . 
CAUSES:  Portal
 hypertension occurs when there is an obstruction of blood flow through 
the liver and pressure rises within the portal vein. This obstruction can be 
intrahepatic (intra=within +hepatic=liver), pre-hepatic (pre=before) or post- 
hepatic (post=after). Intrahepatic causes of portal hypertension include
 cirrhosis and hepatic 
fibrosis or scarring. A wide variety of illnesses are implicated as the cause of 
portal hypertension. Examples 
include the following: Alcohol abuse , Hepatitis B and 
 C infections, Fatty liver (NASH, non-alcoholic steatohepatitis), Wilson's disease, an abnormality of 
copper
 metabolism , Hemochromatosis (
 iron overload ), excess iron buildup Cystic fibrosis Primary sclerosing cholangitis , a 
hardening of the bile ducts Biliary atresia, poorly formed bile 
ducts Parasite infections such as
 schistosomiasis Portal vein thrombosis or
 blood clots within the portal vein Congenital portal vein atresia or 
failure of the portal vein to develop Post-hepatic causes are due to obstruction of blood flow from the liver to 
the heart and can include: Hepatic vein thrombosis Inferior Vena cava thrombosis Restrictive
 pericarditis , where the 
lining of the heart stiffens and does not allow the heart to relax and expand 
when blood returns to it. Causes may include
 tuberculosis ,
 fungal infections , 
tumors, connective tissue disorders (for example,
 scleroderma ), and complications from
 radiation therapy .
 
SYMPTOMS:  When blood cannot easily flow through the liver architecture (from portal vein to sinusoids to hepatic vein to Vena cava), it tries to bypass the portal system, using the systemic venous system to return to the heart. Symptoms of portal hypertension are due to the complications of decreased blood flow through the liver, and from increased pressure within the veins where blood is shunted. Varices describe enlarged veins. Blood meant for the portal system, is diverted to and gathers in other veins as it makes its way to the heart. These varices can occur in the
 esophagus , stomach, around the umbilicus and in the anus and rectum. Esophageal and gastric varices are at risk for life threatening bleeding and can have signs and symptoms with
 vomiting blood and blood in the stool. Melena describes black, tarry stool that is the result of upper gastrointestinal bleeding. Ascites describes abnormal fluid collection within the peritoneum (the sac that contains the
 intestines within the abdominal cavity) and is due to a combination of factors, including increased pressure in the portal system and decrease protein in the body. The liver produces the body&amp;#39;s protein and portal hypertension and the underlying liver disease decreases its ability to function. Hepatic encephalopathy is another complication of
 liver disease , causing
 confusion and lethargy due to the buildup of waste products and the inability of the liver to adequately filter them. Splenomegaly or enlargement of the spleen. Because of portal hypertension, blood backs up, and this also can trap the components of blood (
 red blood cells , white blood cells and platelets) within the spleen causing
 anemia and
 thrombocytopenia (
 low platelet count in the bloodstream). Decreased white blood cell counts increase the risk of general infection. Spontaneous bacterial peritonitis is an infection within the peritoneal sac within the abdomen, and is seen as a consequence of long standing portal hypertension.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  Portal hypertension usually is diagnosed well after the process has begun in the body, and only after a complication occurs. When a patient develops 
 ascites or has gastrointestinal bleeding, the health care professional will look for potential causes, including portal hypertension. Once the diagnosis is a possibility, it can be confirmed by blood tests, X-rays, CT or
 MRI and
 endoscopy . Pressures within the portal vein are not routinely measured except in specific situations (see TIPS procedure) 
TREATMENT:  Treatment for portal hypertension is often directed at preventing complications. This includes treating the underlying cause and avoidance of alcohol. Because of the risk of further liver damage, over-the-counter medications that contain
 acetaminophen (
 Tylenol , Panadol, etc.) should also be avoided. Dietary restrictions include limiting salt to prevent further ascites fluid accumulation. Protein restriction may also be indicated, since increased protein load can overwhelm the liver&amp;#39;s ability to synthesize it and may lead to hepatic
 encephalopathy . Medications such as
 beta blockers and
 nitroglycerin may be appropriate to decrease pressure within the portal system.
 Lactulose may be prescribed as a treatment for hepatic encephalopathy. Endoscopy may be required to band or tie off varices in the esophagus to prevent catastrophic and life threatening bleeding. A TIPS procedure (
 transjugular intrahepatic portosystemic shunt ) may be an option to decrease the pressure within the portal system. An interventional radiologist attempts to place a tube that connects the portal vein with the hepatic vein. This may decrease the pressure within the liver and may also reduce pressure within the veins of the stomach and esophagus, hopefully decreasing the risk of bleeding. If portal hypertension and liver dysfunction become bad enough, liver transplantation may be necessary.
 
COMPLCATIONS:  The complications of portal hypertension are the complications of liver 
failure. These include gastrointestinal bleeding from varices, ascites and 
hepatic encephalopathy.
 Splenomegaly can also cause
 anemia , low white blood 
cell counts, and low platelet counts. 
PREVENTION:  Some liver diseases due to inborn errors of
 metabolism like copper and iron 
cannot be prevented. The same can be said with congenital anatomy problems. 
However, when liver disease is due to alcohol and
 drug abuse ,
 prevention is a 
real possibility. 
Chronic
 alcoholism can lead to cirrhosis and portal 
hypertension. IV drug abuse can be the cause of
 hepatitis B and C, resulting in 
cirrhosis. What is the prognosis for portal hypertension? Portal hypertension is a complication of an underlying liver disease. It is a 
disease that can be controlled but requires patients to be compliant with 
dietary restrictions and to abstain from alcohol and
 drugs . Survival rates can 
be quite high as long as some liver function is maintained. The worse the liver 
function, the worse the prognosis
</first>
</file1>