<file1>
<first>Childbirth Class Options
Childbirth class options introduction Many women and couples desire to take part in formal classes as part of their 
birthing plan. While a number of class formats and emphasis is available, what 
they have in common is that they all prepare a mother for giving birth. Classes 
may cover techniques for non-drug
 pain management as well as information about
 labor and delivery . Childbirth classes can also teach expectant women what to 
expect in the postpartum period. In addition, information regarding
 breastfeeding is commonly presented. While classes focused on birthing techniques commonly start around the 
seventh month of
 pregnancy , other types of classes may start in early pregnancy. 
Your health care professional can help you decide when and if a childbirth class is 
a good option for you. Classes can be held at hospitals, community centers, 
health care practitioners' offices or other settings. Video or book versions of 
classes are also available. The following is a brief overview of some of the most well-known childbirth 
class options in the United States. What is the Lamaze technique? The Lamaze technique is one of the best known methods, and one of the most 
commonly used childbirth class method in the United States. Lamaze classes are 
designed to inform women about their options for support during the birth 
process. The Lamaze program does not encourage or discourage the use of medications and medical 
interventions during the birth process. Women are presented with information 
and options to make the decision that is best for her. Some of the topics covered in Lamaze technique classes include: The progress of normal labor The delivery and postpartum period Pain relief techniques such as
 massage and relaxation methods Other kinds of support during labor Communication Breastfeeding Medical procedures that may be 
recommended Living a healthy lifestyle Lamaze classes are generally taught in small groups of up to 12 couples. 
Typically, there is at least 12 hours of instruction time.
 What is The Bradley Method? The Bradley method is also known as husband-coached childbirth. It is a 
process that prepares a woman to give birth without the use of
 pain control 
medications. It also prepares the woman's partner to be an effective birth 
coach. The method does include preparation for problems or unexpected situations 
like unplanned Cesarean section delivery. The course is taught over 12 sessions. 
Topics covered in the classes include: Healthy lifestyle choices Relaxation techniques for use during 
labor "Rehearsals" for labor Postpartum care Breastfeeding Training for the partner in coaching 
techniques Ways to avoid a Cesarean section 
(
 C-section ) What is The Alexander Technique? The Alexander Technique is a strategy for improving movement, balance, 
coordination, and flexibility. This technique is used by many individuals--not 
just
 pregnant women. In expectant women it may be used to increase the mother's 
comfort during pregnancy, increase the effectiveness of pushing, lessen any 
discomfort associated with
 nursing , and assist the overall recovery from 
childbirth. Some pregnant women choose to take weekly lessons in the technique 
throughout their pregnancy. What is HypnoBirthing? HypnoBirthing is a method that is based on self-hypnosis techniques to 
achieve a healthy and natural birth process. It is sometimes referred to as the 
Morgan method. Pre-birth
 parenting and the consciousness of the unborn baby are 
among the topics covered in the training sessions. It is commonly given in a 
series of 4 or 5 class sessions of 2 ½ to 3 hours each.
 10 questions to ask when choosing a childbirth class Asking the following questions may help women decide on a childbirth class. 
There are no right or wrong answers. Thinking about these issues may help you 
clarify your own interests and goals.</first>
</file1>