<file1>
<first>Addison's Disease
Addison's disease facts* *
 Addison's Disease Facts by John P. Cunha, DO, FACOE Addison's disease, also called adrenal insufficiency, or hypocortisolism, occurs when the adrenal glands do not produce enough of the hormone cortisol and, in some cases, the hormone aldosterone. Addison's disease is an endocrine or hormonal disorder characterized by
 weight loss , muscle
 weakness ,
 fatigue ,
 low blood pressure , and sometimes darkening of the skin. Most cases of Addison's disease are caused by autoimmune disorders. As a result, often both glucocorticoid (cortisol) and mineralocorticoid (aldosterone) hormones are lacking. Tuberculosis (
 TB ), an infection which can destroy the adrenal glands, accounts for about 20 percent of cases of primary adrenal insufficiency in developed countries. Secondary adrenal insufficiency is more common than primary adrenal insufficiency due to a lack of ACTH. Symptoms of Addison's disease begin gradually and include chronic, worsening
 fatigue , muscle weakness,
 loss of appetite , and
 weight loss . Symptoms of an addisonian crisis, or acute adrenal insufficiency, include sudden penetrating
 pain in the lower back, abdomen, or legs, severe
 vomiting and
 diarrhea ,
 dehydration ,
 low blood pressure , and
 loss of consciousness . Addison's is diagnosed with blood tests and/or a
 CT scan . Treatment of Addison's disease involves replacing, or substituting, the hormones the adrenal glands are not making. Cortisol is replaced orally with hydrocortisone tablets, and aldosterone is replaced with oral doses of a mineralocorticoid called
 fludrocortisone acetate (
 Florinef ). People with Addison's may wish to wear a descriptive warning bracelet or neck chain to alert emergency personnel. What is Addison's disease? Addison's disease is an endocrine or hormonal disorder that occurs in all age groups and afflicts men and women equally. The disease is characterized by
 weight loss , muscle weakness,
 fatigue ,
 low blood pressure , and sometimes darkening of the skin in both exposed and nonexposed parts of the body.
 How does Addison's disease occur? Addison's disease occurs when the adrenal glands do not produce enough of the hormone cortisol and, in some cases, the hormone aldosterone. The disease is also called adrenal insufficiency, or hypocortisolism. What is cortisol? Cortisol is normally produced by the adrenal glands, located just above the kidneys. It belongs to a class of hormones called glucocorticoids, which affect almost every organ and tissue in the body. Scientists think that cortisol has possibly hundreds of effects in the body. Cortisol's most important job is to help the body respond to
 stress . Among its other vital tasks, cortisol: helps maintain
 blood pressure and heart function helps slow the immune system's inflammation response helps balance the effects of
 insulin in breaking down
 sugar for energy helps regulate the
 metabolism of proteins, carbohydrates, and
 fats helps maintain proper arousal and sense of well-being How is cortisol regulated? Because cortisol is so vital to health, the amount of cortisol produced by the adrenals is precisely balanced. Like many other hormones, cortisol is regulated by the brain's hypothalamus and the
 pituitary gland , a bean-sized organ at the base of the brain. First, the hypothalamus sends "releasing hormones" to the pituitary gland. The pituitary responds by secreting hormones that regulate growth and
 thyroid and adrenal function, and sex hormones such as
 estrogen and testosterone. One of the pituitary's main functions is to secrete ACTH (adrenocorticotropin), a hormone that stimulates the adrenal glands. When the adrenals receive the pituitary's signal in the form of ACTH, they respond by producing cortisol. Completing the cycle, cortisol then signals the pituitary to lower secretion of ACTH.
 What is aldosterone? Aldosterone belongs to a class of hormones called mineralocorticoids, also produced by the adrenal glands. It helps maintain blood pressure and water and salt balance in the body by helping the kidney retain sodium and excrete potassium. When aldosterone production falls too low, the kidneys are not able to regulate salt and water balance, causing blood volume and blood pressure to drop. What causes Addison's disease? Failure to produce adequate levels of cortisol can occur for different reasons. The problem may be due to a disorder of the adrenal glands themselves (primary adrenal insufficiency) or to inadequate secretion of ACTH by the pituitary gland (secondary adrenal insufficiency). Primary adrenal insufficiency Addison's disease affects about 1 in 100,000 people. Most cases are caused by the gradual destruction of the adrenal cortex, the outer layer of the adrenal glands, by the body's own immune system. 
Up to 80 percent of reported cases of Addison's disease are caused by autoimmune disorders, in which the immune system makes antibodies that attack the body's own tissues or organs and slowly destroy them. Adrenal insufficiency occurs when at least 90 percent of the adrenal cortex has been destroyed. As a result, often both glucocorticoid (cortisol) and mineralocorticoid (aldosterone) hormones are lacking. Sometimes only the adrenal gland is affected, as in idiopathic adrenal insufficiency; sometimes other glands also are affected, as in the polyendocrine deficiency syndrome. Polyendocrine deficiency syndrome The polyendocrine deficiency syndrome is classified into two separate forms, referred to as type I and type II. Type I occurs in children, and adrenal insufficiency may be accompanied by: underactive parathyroid glands slow sexual development pernicious anemia chronic candida infections chronic active
 hepatitis hair loss (in very rare cases) Type II, often called Schmidt's syndrome, usually afflicts young adults. Features of type II may include: an
 underactive thyroid gland slow sexual development diabetes vitiligo loss of pigment on areas of the skin Scientists think that the polyendocrine deficiency syndrome is inherited because frequently more than one family member tends to have one or more endocrine deficiencies.
 Tuberculosis Tuberculosis (TB), an infection which can destroy the adrenal glands, accounts for about 20 percent of cases of primary adrenal insufficiency in developed countries. When adrenal insufficiency was first identified by Dr. Thomas Addison in 1849, TB was found at
 autopsy in 70 to 90 percent of cases. As the treatment for TB improved, however, the incidence of adrenal insufficiency due to TB of the adrenal glands has greatly decreased. Other causes Less common causes of primary adrenal insufficiency are: chronic infection, mainly
 fungal infections cancer cells spreading from other parts of the body to the adrenal glands amyloidosis surgical removal of the adrenal glands Secondary adrenal insufficiency This form of adrenal insufficiency is much more common than primary adrenal insufficiency and can be traced to a lack of ACTH. Without ACTH to stimulate the adrenals, the adrenal glands' production of cortisol drops, but not aldosterone. A temporary form of secondary adrenal insufficiency may occur when a person who has been receiving a glucocorticoid hormone such as
 prednisone for a long time abruptly stops or interrupts taking the medication. Glucocorticoid hormones, which are often used to treat inflammatory illnesses like
 rheumatoid arthritis ,
 asthma , or
 ulcerative colitis , block the release of both corticotropin-releasing hormone (CRH) and ACTH. Normally, CRH instructs the pituitary gland to release ACTH. If CRH levels drop, the pituitary is not stimulated to release ACTH, and the adrenals then fail to secrete sufficient levels of cortisol. Another cause of secondary adrenal insufficiency is the surgical removal of benign, or noncancerous, ACTH-producing tumors of the pituitary gland (Cushing's disease). In this case, the source of ACTH is suddenly removed, and replacement hormone must be taken until normal ACTH and cortisol production resumes. Less commonly, adrenal insufficiency occurs when the pituitary gland either decreases in size or stops producing ACTH. These events can result from: tumors or infections of the area loss of blood flow to the pituitary radiation for the treatment of pituitary tumors surgical removal of parts of the hypothalamus surgical removal of the pituitary gland
 What are the signs and symptoms of Addison's disease? The symptoms of adrenal insufficiency usually begin gradually. Characteristics of the disease are: chronic, worsening fatigue muscle weakness loss of appetite weight loss About 50 percent of the time, one will notice: nausea vomiting diarrhea Other symptoms include: low blood pressure that falls further when standing, causing
 dizziness or
 fainting skin changes in Addison's disease, with areas of
 hyperpigmentation , or dark tanning, covering exposed and nonexposed parts of the body; this darkening of the skin is most visible on
 scars ; skin folds; pressure points such as the elbows, knees, knuckles, and toes; lips; and mucous membranes Addison's disease can cause irritability and
 depression . Because of salt loss, a craving for salty foods also is common.
 Hypoglycemia , or
 low blood glucose , is more severe in children than in adults. In women, menstrual periods may become irregular or stop. Because the symptoms progress slowly, they are usually ignored until a stressful event like an illness or an accident causes them to become worse. This is called an addisonian crisis, or acute adrenal insufficiency. In most cases, symptoms are severe enough that patients seek medical treatment before a crisis occurs. However, in about 25 percent of patients, symptoms first appear during an addisonian crisis. Symptoms of an addisonian crisis include: sudden penetrating
 pain in the lower back, abdomen, or legs severe vomiting and
 diarrhea dehydration low blood pressure loss of consciousness Left untreated, an addisonian crisis can be fatal.
 How is Addison's disease diagnosed? In its early stages, adrenal insufficiency can be difficult to diagnose. A review of a patient's medical history based on the symptoms, especially the dark tanning of the skin, will lead a doctor to suspect Addison's disease. A diagnosis of Addison's disease is made by laboratory tests. The aim of these tests is first to determine whether levels of cortisol are insufficient and then to establish the cause. X-ray exams of the adrenal and pituitary glands also are useful in helping to establish the cause. This is the most specific test for diagnosing Addison's disease. In this test, blood cortisol, urine cortisol, or both are measured before and after a synthetic form of ACTH is given by injection. In the so-called short, or rapid, ACTH test, measurement of cortisol in blood is repeated 30 to 60 minutes after an intravenous ACTH injection. The normal response after an injection of ACTH is a rise in blood and urine cortisol levels. Patients with either form of adrenal insufficiency respond poorly or do not respond at all. When the response to the short ACTH test is abnormal, a "long" CRH stimulation test is required to determine the cause of adrenal insufficiency. In this test, synthetic CRH is injected intravenously and blood cortisol is measured before and 30, 60, 90, and 120 minutes after the injection. Patients with primary adrenal insufficiency have high ACTHs but do not produce cortisol. Patients with secondary adrenal insufficiency have deficient cortisol responses but absent or delayed ACTH responses. Absent ACTH response points to the pituitary as the cause; a delayed ACTH response points to the hypothalamus as the cause. In patients suspected of having an addisonian crisis, the doctor must begin treatment with injections of salt, fluids, and glucocorticoid hormones immediately. Although a reliable diagnosis is not possible while the patient is being treated for the crisis, measurement of blood ACTH and cortisol during the crisis and before glucocorticoids are given is enough to make the diagnosis. Once the crisis is controlled and medication has been stopped, the doctor will delay further testing for up to 1 month to obtain an accurate diagnosis. Once a diagnosis of primary adrenal insufficiency has been made, x-ray exams of the abdomen may be taken to see if the adrenals have any signs of calcium deposits. Calcium deposits may indicate TB. A tuberculin skin test also may be used. If secondary adrenal insufficiency is the cause, doctors may use different imaging tools to reveal the size and shape of the pituitary gland. The most common is the CT scan, which produces a series of x-ray pictures giving a cross-sectional image of a body part. The function of the pituitary and its ability to produce other hormones also are tested.
 How is Addison's disease treated? Treatment of Addison's disease involves replacing, or substituting, the hormones that the adrenal glands are not making. Cortisol is replaced orally with hydrocortisone tablets, a synthetic glucocorticoid, taken once or twice a day. If aldosterone is also deficient, it is replaced with oral doses of a mineralocorticoid called fludrocortisone acetate (Florinef), which is taken once a day. Patients receiving aldosterone replacement therapy are usually advised by a doctor to increase their salt intake. Because patients with secondary adrenal insufficiency normally maintain aldosterone production, they do not require aldosterone replacement therapy. The doses of each of these medications are adjusted to meet the needs of individual patients. During an addisonian crisis, low blood pressure, low
 blood glucose , and high levels of potassium can be life threatening. Standard therapy involves intravenous injections of hydrocortisone, saline (salt water), and dextrose (
 sugar ). This treatment usually brings rapid improvement. When the patient can take fluids and medications by mouth, the amount of hydrocortisone is decreased until a maintenance dose is achieved. If aldosterone is deficient, maintenance therapy also includes oral doses of fludrocortisone acetate. Surgery Patients with chronic adrenal insufficiency who need surgery with general anesthesia are treated with injections of hydrocortisone and saline. Injections begin on the evening before surgery and continue until the patient is fully awake and able to take medication by mouth. The dosage is adjusted until the maintenance dosage given before surgery is reached. Pregnancy Women with primary adrenal insufficiency who become
 pregnant are treated with standard replacement therapy. If
 nausea and vomiting in early
 pregnancy interfere with oral medication, injections of the hormone may be necessary. During delivery, treatment is similar to that of patients needing surgery; following delivery, the dose is gradually tapered and the usual maintenance doses of hydrocortisone and fludrocortisone acetate by mouth are reached by about 10 days after childbirth.
 Patient education A person who has adrenal insufficiency should always carry identification stating his or her condition in case of an emergency. The card should alert emergency personnel about the need to inject 100 mg of cortisol if its bearer is found severely injured or unable to answer questions. The card should also include the doctor's name and telephone number and the name and telephone number of the nearest relative to be notified. When traveling, a needle, syringe, and an injectable form of cortisol should be carried for emergencies. A person with Addison's disease also should know how to increase medication during periods of
 stress or mild upper respiratory infections. Immediate medical attention is needed when severe infections, vomiting, or diarrhea occur. These conditions can precipitate an addisonian crisis. A patient who is vomiting may require injections of hydrocortisone. People with medical problems may wish to wear a descriptive warning bracelet or neck chain to alert emergency personnel. A number of companies manufacture medical identification products. For more information The following articles about Addison's disease can be found in medical libraries, some college and university libraries, and through interlibrary loan in most public libraries. Stewart PM. The adrenal cortex. In: Larsen P, ed. Williams Textbook of Endocrinology. 10th ed. Philadelphia: Saunders; 2003: 491-551. Chrousos GP. Glucocorticoid therapy. In: Felig P, Frohman L, eds. Endocrinology and
 Metabolism . 4th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill; 2001: 609-632. Miller W, Chrousos GP. The adrenal cortex. In: Felig P, Frohman L, eds. Endocrinology and Metabolism. 4th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill; 2001: 387-524. Ten S, New M, Maclaren N. Clinical Review 130: Addison's disease 2001. Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism. 2001;86(7):2909-2922. Williams GH, Dluhy, RC. Disorders of the adrenal cortex. In: Braunwald E, ed. Harrison's Principles of Internal Medicine. 15th ed. New York: McGraw-Hill Professional; 2001: 2084-2105. The following organizations might also be able to assist with certain types of information: American Autoimmune Related Diseases Association National Office
 22100 Gratiot Avenue
 East Detroit, MI 48021
 Phone: 586-776-3900
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: www.aarda.org National Adrenal Disease Foundation
 505 Northern Boulevard, Suite 200
 Great Neck, NY 11021
 Phone: 516-487-4992
 Fax: 516-829-5710
 Internet: www.nadf.us/ National Endocrine and Metabolic Diseases Information Service
 6 Information Way
 Bethesda, MD 20892-3569
 Phone: 1-888-828-0904
 Fax: 1-703-738-4929
 Email:
 [email protected] Internet: http://endocrine.niddk.nih.gov/
</first>
</file1>