<file1>
<first>Hypoparathyroidism
Hypoparathyroidism facts* *
ABOUT: by John P. Cunha, DO, FACOEP Hypoparathyroidism is a condition in which the body doesn't make enough parathyroid hormone (PTH), a hormone that regulates the amount of calcium and phosphorus in your body's bones and blood. Hypoparathyroidism is very rare. It is different from
 hyperparathyroidism , a much more common condition in which the body makes too much PTH. The most common cause of hypoparathyroidism is injury to the parathyroid glands, such as during head and neck surgery. In other cases, it is present at birth or may be associated with an autoimmune disease. Symptoms of hypoparathyroidism may include tingling in the lips, fingers, and toes; dry hair,
 brittle nails , and dry, coarse skin;
 muscle cramps and
 pain in the face, hands, legs, and
 feet ;
 cataracts ; dental problems;
 memory loss ,
 headaches , and
 muscle spasms . Calcium carbonate and
 vitamin D supplements are the only currently approved treatment. What is hypoparathyroidism? Hypoparathyroidism is a condition in which the body doesn't make enough parathyroid hormone (PTH). This hormone regulates the amount of calcium and phosphorus in your body's bones and blood. Decreased levels of PTH lead to low levels of calcium and high levels of phosphorus in the blood. This imbalance can lead to problems with bones, muscles, skin, and nerve endings. 
CAUSES:  The most common cause of hypoparathyroidism is injury to the parathyroid glands, such as during head and neck surgery. Parathyroid glands are small endocrine glands that are located in the neck behind the
 thyroid gland. It other cases, hypoparathyroidism is present at birth or may be associated with an autoimmune disease that affects the parathyroids along with other glands in the body, such as the
 thyroid , ovaries, or adrenal glands. Hypoparathyroidism is very rare. It is different from hyperparathyroidism, a much more common condition in which the body makes too much PTH.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of hypoparathyroidism may include: Tingling in the lips, fingers, and toes Dry hair, brittle nails, and dry, coarse skin Muscle cramps and
 pain in the face, hands, legs, and feet Cataracts on the eyes Malformations of the
 teeth , including weakened tooth enamel and misshapen roots of the teeth Loss of memory Headaches Severe muscle spasms (also called tetany) and convulsions How is hypoparathyroidism treated? The goal of treatment for hypoparathyroidism is to restore the body's calcium and phosphorus to normal levels. Calcium carbonate and
 vitamin D supplements are the only currently approved treatment. However, NIH studies have shown the investigational drug PTH to work well as an alternative therapy. If hypoparathyroidism is diagnosed and treated early, outcomes are usual good and the body grows normally. If hypoparathyroidism is left untreated, complications can include a blocked
 airway due to severe muscle spasms, stunted growth, malformed teeth, development of
 cataracts , and calcium deposits in the brain.
</first>
</file1>