<file1>
<first>Low Blood Pressure (Hypotension)
Low blood pressure (hypotension) definition and facts What is low blood pressure?  What do the numbers mean (chart with ranges)? Blood pressure is the force exerted by circulating blood on the walls of blood vessels. It constitutes one of the critically important signs of life or vital signs, which include heart rate,
 breathing , and temperature. Blood pressure is generated by the heart pumping blood into the arteries modified by the response of the arteries to the flow of blood. An individual&amp;#39;s blood pressure is expressed as
 systolic/diastolic blood pressure, for example, 120/80. The systolic blood pressure (the top number) represents the pressure in the arteries as the muscle of the heart contracts and pumps blood into them. The diastolic blood pressure (the bottom number) represents the pressure in the arteries as the muscle of the heart relaxes following its contraction. Blood pressure always is higher when the heart is pumping (squeezing) than when it is relaxing. The range of systolic blood pressure for most healthy adults falls between 90 and 120 millimeters of mercury (mm Hg). Normal diastolic blood pressure ranges between 60 and 80 mm Hg. Current guidelines define normal blood pressure range as lower than 120/80. Blood pressures over 130/80 are considered high.
 High blood pressure increases the risk of damaging the arteries, which leads to the development of: Heart disease Kidney disease Hardening of the arteries (atherosclerosis or
 arteriosclerosis ) Eye damage Stroke Low blood pressure (
 hypotension ) is pressure so low it causes symptoms or signs due to the low flow of blood through the arteries and veins. When the flow of blood is too low to deliver enough oxygen and nutrients to vital organs such as the brain, heart, and kidney, the organs do not function normally and may be temporarily or permanently damaged. Unlike
 high blood pressure , low blood pressure is defined primarily by signs and symptoms of low blood flow and not by a specific blood pressure number. Some individuals routinely may have blood pressure numbers of 90/50 with no symptoms and therefore do not have low blood pressure. However, others who normally have higher blood pressures may develop symptoms of low blood pressure if their blood pressure drops to 100/60. During
 pregnancy , blood pressure tends to decrease. Normal blood pressure during pregnancy may be lower than 100/60. Your OB/GYN or
 Midwife should monitor your bood pressure if you are
 pregnant . How does blood pressure work? During relaxation of the heart (diastole), the
 left ventricle of the heart fills with blood returning from the
 lungs . The left ventricle then contracts and pumps blood into the arteries (systole). The blood pressure in the arteries during contraction of the ventricle (systolic pressure) is higher because blood is being actively ejected into the arteries. It is lower during relaxation of the ventricle (diastolic pressure) when no blood is being ejected into the arteries. The pulse we feel when we place our fingers over an artery is caused by the contraction of the left ventricle and the ejection of blood. Blood pressure is determined by two factors: 1) The amount of blood pumped by the left ventricle of the heart into the arteries, and 2) the resistance to the flow of blood caused by the walls of the arterioles (smaller arteries). Generally, blood pressure tends to be higher if more blood is pumped into the arteries or if the arterioles are narrow and/or stiff. Narrow and/or stiff arterioles, by resisting the flow of blood, increase blood pressure. Arterioles may become narrower when the muscles surrounding them contract. Arterioles may become stiff and narrow when older patients develop atherosclerosis. Blood pressure tends to be lower if less blood is being pumped into the arteries or if the arterioles are larger and more flexible and, therefore, have less resistance to the flow of blood. The body has mechanisms to alter or maintain blood pressure and blood flow. There are sensors that detect blood pressure in the walls of the arteries and send signals to the heart, the arterioles, the veins, and the kidneys that cause them to make changes that lower or increase blood pressure. Several ways in which blood pressure can be adjusted by adjusting the amount of blood pumped by the heart into the arteries (cardiac output), the amount of blood contained in the veins, the arteriolar resistance, and the volume of blood. The heart can speed up and contract more frequently and it can eject more blood with each contraction (more forcefully). Both of these responses increase the flow of blood into the arteries and increase blood pressure. The veins can expand and narrow. When veins expand, more blood can be stored in the veins and less blood returns to the heart for pumping into the arteries. As a result, the heart pumps less blood, and blood pressure is lower. On the other hand, when veins narrow, less blood is stored in the veins, more blood returns to the heart for pumping into the arteries, and blood pressure is higher. The arterioles can expand and narrow. Expanded arterioles create less resistance to the flow of blood and decrease blood pressure, while narrowed arterioles create more resistance and raise blood pressure. The kidney can respond to changes in blood pressure by increasing or decreasing the amount of urine that is produced. Urine is primarily water that is removed from the blood. When the kidney makes more urine, the amount (volume) of blood that fills the arteries and veins decreases, and this lowers blood pressure. If the kidneys make less urine, the amount of blood that fills the arteries and veins increases and this increases blood pressure. Compared with the other mechanisms for adjusting blood pressure, changes in the production of urine affect blood pressure slowly over hours and days. (The other mechanisms are effective in seconds.) For example, low blood volume due to bleeding (such as a bleeding ulcer in the stomach or from a severe laceration from an injury) can cause low blood pressure. The body quickly responds to the low blood volume and pressure by the following adjustments, which all increase blood pressure: The heart rate increases and the forcefulness of the heart&amp;#39;s contractions increase, pumping more blood through the heart. Veins narrow to return more blood to the heart for pumping. Blood flow to the kidneys decreases to reduce the formation of urine and thereby increases the volume of blood in the arteries and veins. Arterioles narrow to increase resistance to blood flow. These adaptive responses will keep the blood pressure in the normal range unless blood loss becomes so severe that the responses are overwhelmed. Is low blood pressure dangerous? People who have lower blood pressures have a lower risk of
 stroke , kidney disease, and
 heart disease . Athletes, people who
 exercise regularly, people who maintain ideal body weight, and nonsmokers tend to have lower blood pressures. Low blood pressure is desirable as long as it is not low enough to cause symptoms and damage to the organs in the body. 
SYMPTOMS:  When blood pressure is not sufficient to deliver enough blood to the organs of the body, the organs do not work properly and can be temporarily or permanently damaged. Symptoms of low blood pressure caused by conditions or diseases depend upon the specific cause of the low blood pressure. For example, if insufficient blood flows to the brain, brain cells do not receive enough oxygen and nutrients, and a person can feel lightheaded, dizzy, or even faint. The most common symptoms of low blood pressure include: Lightheadedness Dizziness Fainting (
 syncope ) Symptoms of low blood pressure due to conditions or diseases include: Orthostatic hypotension symptoms: Going from a sitting or lying position to a standing position often brings out symptoms of low blood pressure. This occurs because standing causes blood to "settle" in the veins of the lower body, and this can lower the blood pressure. If the blood pressure is already low, standing can make the low pressure worse, to the point of causing symptoms. The development of lightheadedness, dizziness, or fainting upon standing caused by low blood pressure is called orthostatic hypotension. Normal individuals are able to compensate rapidly for the low pressure created by standing with the responses discussed previously and do not develop orthostatic hypotension. Heart disease: Chest pain (a symptom of
 angina ) or even a
 heart attack may occur when there is insufficient blood pressure to deliver blood to the coronary arteries (the arteries that supply blood to the heart&amp;#39;s muscle). Kidney disease: When insufficient blood is delivered to the kidneys, the kidneys fail to eliminate wastes from the body, for example, urea (BUN and
 creatinine ), and increases in their levels in the blood occur. Shock is a life-threatening condition where persistently low blood pressure causes organs such as kidney,
 liver , heart, lung, and brain to fail rapidly. 
CAUSES:  Conditions that reduce the volume of blood or that reduce cardiac output (the amount of blood pumped by the heart) and medications are frequent reasons for low blood pressure. Dehydration, bleeding, and inflammation Heart disease Several common reasons for bradycardia include: 1) sick sinus syndrome, 2)
 heart block , and 3) drug toxicity. Many of these conditions occur in the elderly. An abnormally fast heart rate (tachycardia) also can cause low blood pressure. The most common example of tachycardia causing low blood pressure is
 atrial fibrillation (
 Afib ).
 Atrial fibrillation is a disorder of the heart characterized by rapid and irregular electrical discharges from the muscle of the heart causing the ventricles to contract irregularly and (usually) rapidly. The rapidly contracting ventricles do not have enough time to fill maximally with blood before each contraction, and the amount of blood that is pumped decreases in spite of the faster heart rate. Other abnormally rapid heart rhythms such as ventricular tachycardia also can produce low blood pressure, and sometimes life-threatening shock. Medications Medications that cause low blood pressure Medications such as
 calcium channel blockers , beta blockers, and digoxin (Lanoxin) can slow the rate at which the heart contracts. Some elderly people are extremely sensitive to these medications since they are more likely to have diseased hearts and electrical conduction tissues. In some individuals, the heart rate can become dangerously slow even with small doses of these medications. Medications used in treating high blood pressure (such as angiotensin converting enzyme or
 ACE inhibitors , angiotensin receptor blockers, beta blockers, calcium channel blockers, and alpha blockers) can excessively lower blood pressure and result in symptomatic low blood pressure especially among the elderly. Water pills (diuretics) such as
 hydrochlorothiazide (
 HydroDIURIL ) and
 furosemide (
 Lasix ) can decrease blood volume by causing excessive urination. Medications used for treating
 depression , such as
 amitriptyline (
 Elavil ); Parkinson&amp;#39;s disease, such as
 levodopa-carbidopa (
 Sinemet ); and
 erectile dysfunction (
 impotence ), such as
 sildenafil (
 Viagra ),
 vardenafil (
 Levitra ), and
 tadalafil (
 Cialis ) when used in combination with
 nitroglycerin , can cause low blood pressure. Alcohol and narcotics also can cause low blood pressure. Other causes of low blood pressure How do I know if I have low blood pressure? In some people, particularly relatively healthy ones, symptoms of weakness, dizziness, and fainting raise the suspicion of low blood pressure. In others, an event often associated with low blood pressure, for example a heart attack, has occurred to cause the symptoms. Measuring blood pressure in both the lying (supine) and standing positions usually is the first step in diagnosing low blood pressure. In patients with symptomatic low blood pressure, there often is a marked drop in blood pressure upon standing, and patients may even develop orthostatic symptoms. The heart rate often increases. The goal is to identify the cause of the low blood pressure. Sometimes the causes are readily apparent (such as loss of blood due to trauma, or sudden shock after receiving X-ray dyes containing iodine). At other times, the cause may be identified by testing: CBC (complete blood count) may reveal
 anemia from blood loss or elevated white blood cells due to infection. Blood electrolyte measurements may show
 dehydration and mineral depletion,
 renal failure (kidney failure), or acidosis (excess acid in the blood). Cortisol levels can be measured to diagnose adrenal insufficiency and Addison&amp;#39;s disease. Blood and urine cultures can be performed to diagnose septicemia and bladder infections, respectively. Radiology studies, such as chest
 X-rays , abdominal ultrasounds, and
 computerized tomography (CT or CAT) scans may detect
 pneumonia , heart failure, gallstones, pancreatitis, and
 diverticulitis . Electrocardiograms (EKG) can detect abnormally slow or rapid heartbeats, pericarditis, and heart muscle damage from either previous heart attacks or a reduced supply of blood to the heart muscle that has not yet caused a heart attack. Holter monitor recordings are used to diagnose intermittent episodes of
 abnormal heart rhythms . If abnormal rhythms occur intermittently, a standard
 EKG performed at the time of a visit to the doctor&amp;#39;s office may not show the abnormal rhythm. A Holter monitor is a continuous recording of the heart&amp;#39;s rhythm for 24 hours that often is used diagnose intermittent episodes of bradycardia or tachycardia (aslow or fast heart rate). Patient-activated event recorder: If the episodes of bradycardia or tachycardia are infrequent, a 24-hour Holter recording may not capture these sporadic episodes. In this situation, a patient can wear a patient-activated event recorder for up to 4 weeks. The patient presses a button to start the recording when he or she senses the onset of an abnormal heart rhythm or symptoms possibly caused by low blood pressure. The doctor then analyzes the recordings later to identify the abnormal episodes. Echocardiograms are examinations of the structures and motion of the heart using
 ultrasound . Echocardiograms can detect
 pericardial fluid due to pericarditis, the extent of heart muscle damage from heart attacks, diseases of the heart valves, and rare tumors of the heart. Ultrasound examinations of the leg veins and CT scans of the chest can detect
 deep vein thrombosis and
 pulmonary embolism . Tilt-table tests are used to evaluate patients suspected of having postural hypotension or syncope due to abnormal function of the autonomic nerves. During a
 tilt-table test , the patient lies on an examination table with an intravenous infusion administered while the heart rate and blood pressure are monitored. The table then is tilted upright for 15 minutes to 45 minutes. Heart rate and blood pressure are monitored every few minutes. The purpose of the test is to try to reproduce postural hypotension. Sometimes a doctor may administer epinephrine (
 Adrenalin ,
 Isuprel ) intravenously to induce postural hypotension. 
TREATMENT:  Low blood pressure readings in healthy people without symptoms or organ damage need no treatment. A doctor should evalute all patients with symptoms that are possibly due to low blood pressure. Patients who have had a major drop in blood pressure from their usual levels even without the development of symptoms also should be evaluated. The doctor needs to identify the cause of the low blood pressure; remedies will depend on the cause. For example, if a medication is causing the low blood pressure, the dose of medication may have to be reduced or the medication stopped.
 Do not adjust medication dose on your own, and do not stop taking any medication without first consulting your doctor. Dehydration is treated with fluids and
 minerals (
 electrolytes ). Mild dehydration without nausea and vomiting can be treated with oral fluids and electrolytes. Moderate to severe dehydration usually is treated in a hospital or emergency room with intravenous fluids and electrolytes. Blood loss can be treated by treating the cause of the bleeding, and with intravenous fluids and blood transfusions. Continuous and severe bleeding needs to be treated immediately. Septic shock is a medical emergency and is treated with intravenous fluids and antibiotics. Blood pressure medications or diuretics are adjusted, changed, or stopped by the doctor if they are causing
 low blood pressure symptoms . Bradycardia may be due to a medication. The doctor may reduce, change, or stop the medication. Bradycardia due to sick sinus syndrome or heart block is treated with an
 implantable pacemaker . Tachycardia is treated depending on the nature of the tachycardia.
 Atrial fibrillation can be treated with oral medications, electrical
 cardioversion , or a catheterization procedure called pulmonary vein isolation. Ventricular tachycardia can be controlled with medications or with an implantable
 defibrillator . Pulmonary embolism and deep vein thrombosis is treated with blood thinners, initially with types of
 heparin . Later, oral
 warfarin (
 Coumadin ) or other oral medications are substituted for heparin. Pericardial fluid from pericarditis can be removed by a procedure called pericardiocentesis. Postural hypotension can be treated with changes in
 diet such as increasing water and salt intake,* increasing intake of
 caffeinated beverages (because
 caffeine constricts blood vessels), using compression stockings to compress the leg veins and reduce the pooling of blood in the leg veins, and in some patients, the use of a medication called
 midodrine (
 ProAmatine ). The problem with midodrine is that while it increases blood pressure in the upright position, the supine blood pressure may become too high, thus increasing the risk of strokes. Mayo Clinic researchers found that a medication used to treat muscle weakness in
 myasthenia gravis called
 pyridostigmine (
 Mestinon ) increases upright blood pressure but not supine blood pressure. Pyridostigmine, an anticholinesterase medication, works on the autonomic nervous system, especially when a person is standing up. Side effects include minor abdominal cramping or increased frequency of bowel movements. Postprandial hypotension refers to low blood pressure occurring after meals.
 Ibuprofen (
 Motrin ) or
 indomethacin (
 Indocin ) may be beneficial. Vasovagal syncope can be treated with several types of drugs such as beta blockers, for example, propanolol (
 Inderal ,
 Inderal LA ) and selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors such as
 fluoxetine (
 Prozac ),
 escitalopram oxalate (
 Lexapro ),
 paroxetine (
 Paxil ),
 sertraline (
 Zoloft ),
 citalopram (
 Celexa ), and
 fluvoxamine (
 Luvox ).
 Fludrocortisone (
 Florinef ) (a drug that prevents dehydration by causing the kidney(s) to retain water) also may be used. A
 pacemaker can also be helpful when a patient fails drug therapy. Natural remedies have not been proven. Some herbs reported to raise blood pressure include
 ginger , rosemary, aniseed, cinnamon, and pepper. Do not take any herbs without first consulting your doctor. *Note: Increasing salt intake can lead to heart failure in patients with existing heart disease and should not be undertaken without consulting a doctor.</first>
</file1>