<file1>
<first>Tension Headache Symptoms, Signs, Relief, Causes, and Treatment

ABOUT: Tension
 headache is the most common type of
 headache . Although the precise cause of tension
 headache is unknown, there are factors that seem to contribute to tension
 headaches , such as
 stress , impaired
 sleep , or skipping meals. Different conditions may contribute to tension
 headaches such as vision problems or
 eye strain , overexertion, muscle
 strains caused by poor posture have all been associated with development of tension
 headache . While certain foods (processed or aged foods,
 chocolate , and red wine) can trigger
 migraine headache , in some cases head and neck movement or physical exertion might trigger a
 migraine ; this is not typical of tension headache. Some individuals have both
 migraine and tension headache; additionally, tension headache can trigger migraine
 pain , and may be relieved by migraine medications.
 Symptoms of migraine include
 light and sound sensitivity, nausea or vomiting , and (often one-sided) throbbing head
 pain which worsens with exertion Both tension
 headaches and
 migraines are diagnosed by physical examination and headache history of the patient. Treatments for tension headaches can include OTC and prescription pain relievers,
 exercise (including formal physical therapy),
 stress management and relaxation techniques, and alternative therapies.
 What is a tension headache? Headache -- a condition so common it&amp;#39;s the punch line for a number of jokes, but when you&amp;#39;re experiencing a headache, it&amp;#39;s no laughing matter. When most people discuss headache, they&amp;#39;re typically referring to the most frequently experienced type of headache, a tension headache (also known as tension-type or
 stress headache). Almost half of adults experienced a headache in the past year; fortunately, for the majority of those individuals, the headache was mild, short-lived, and likely fell into the category of tension headache. Children and
 teens can experience tension headache; with a significant percentage of children having experienced tension headache by age 15. Females are often diagnosed with tension headaches (more often, about twice as often) than males.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Most tension headaches occur infrequently, and are usually short-lived (resolves within minutes to a few hours). In rare cases the headache may last for many days. A tension headaches that occur more than 15 days each month are referred to as chronic tension headaches. Tension headaches are not associated with
 nausea or
 vomiting , and do not have symptoms like flashing lights, blind spots, or numbness or
 weakness of the arms or legs which precede the headache. These symptoms can help distinguish tension headaches from other types of headaches (for example, migraine headaches).
 
CAUSES:  The exact cause of tension headache isn&amp;#39;t known; and many factors probably play a role in why people develop headache. These factors may include: lack of
 sleep , skipping meals, or increased stress (leading to a frequent description of these headaches as stress headaches). Underlying diseases or conditions may frequently cause a headache, for example: eye strain, muscular tension caused by poor posture, over exertion, or anxiety . In children, headache may be seen as a response to changes in school or home situations such as: a new sibling, testing at school, or social isolation. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Tension headaches are diagnosed based on the patient&amp;#39;s reported history of the headache and physical examination. There is no test to specifically confirm tension headache. Because the physical examination in patients with tension headache is generally normal, additional testing such as
 CT scan or
 MRI scan usually isn&amp;#39;t required. Some basic blood work may be done to confirm that no underlying abnormality is present. Treatment for tension headaches include prescription medications,
 over-the-counter (OTC) pain relievers, combination
 drugs containing
 aspirin ,
 acetaminophen ,
 caffeine , and stress management.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Alternative treatments or therapies: Alternative therapies such as a hot compress or an ice pack may provide substantial benefit for some individuals. Hydrate: Sometimes headaches can be triggered by mild
 dehydration or lack of food; if so, drinking some non-
 caffeinated fluids or eating something may help. Flaxseed: People who eat
 flaxseed , which is rich in
 omega-3 fatty acids , may experience a decrease in headaches. This is thought to be related to the anti-inflammatory properties of the
 omega-3 fatty acids . Peppermint or lavender oil: Inhaling the scent of
 peppermint oil or lavender oil may help decrease headache pain (
 lavender oil should not be consumed orally ). Scalp massage: A
 scalp massage is easily done and may provide significant relief; concentrating efforts over the temporal regions or the occipital area (the back of the scalp) may lead to the best response. Whole-body massage: Whole body massage may provide relief. Stress management: If stress seems to be a trigger, learning stress-management techniques or relaxation techniques can provide substantial benefit. Exercise: Exercise , whether regular aerobic activities or specific movements to improve posture, has been shown to be quite effective in decreasing the frequency of tension headaches.
 
TREATMENT:  Many people treat tension headache on their own, using OTC (over-the-counter) medications like acetaminophen (
 Tylenol ),
 ibuprofen (
 Motrin ), or combination medications containing acetaminophen, aspirin, and
 caffeine (Excedrin). While these medications can be effective and when taken as directed are safe for most people, overuse can lead to headaches which are more frequent and severe. This can occur if these agents are used more than 2 days each week routinely. If tension headache occurs during
 pregnancy , the patient should contact her physician about medications that are safe to use. Products which contain aspirin should not be given to children due to the risk of Reye&amp;#39;s syndrome. Chronic use of acetaminophen, or use of acetaminophen in large amounts may lead to
 liver toxicity (current recommended maximal dose is 3 grams per 24 hours), and a number of medications are combined with acetaminophen so patients should discuss all OTC drugs they are taking with their doctors. If a diagnosis of chronic tension headache is made or suspected, prescription medications may be used in an effort to lessen the frequency and decrease the severity of the headaches. Medications used include antidepressants and antiseizure drugs. A doctor can help determine which medicine is best for you.
 What stress management techniques can help reduce headache pain, other symptoms, and the frequency of tension headaches? For people who experience recurrent tension headache,
 stress management techniques have been an effective way of helping to decrease headache frequency and severity. This can include regular exercise, deep
 breathing techniques, and relaxation training. Other non-medicinal approaches can include massage therapy, heat, ice, or
 acupuncture . Learning to identify stressful situations which trigger headache and taking steps to avoid these is also a useful strategy for many individuals. 
PREVENTION:  Often, the best defense is a good offense and this approach is frequently effective when trying to prevent tension headache. Identifying
 headache triggers and then attempting to avoid or modify those triggers can be a successful strategy to decrease or even eliminate a tension headache. Some people find that scheduled exercise and eating on a regular basis is beneficial. Learning and practicing relaxation techniques, including deep breathing exercises, directed relaxation of specific muscles, or meditation, can also be effective. See your doctor if any of the following situations occur: If a person experiences regular headaches or if they have changed in severity, location or frequency If a person experiences a headache that is very different from his or her usual headaches If previously helpful treatments are no longer effective If someone is experiencing "The worst headache of my life" they need to be evaluated emergently.
</first>
</file1>