<file1>
<first>Your Child's Headache
Introduction Kids get
 headaches and migraines, too! Many adults with
 headaches started having them as kids -- in fact, 20% of adult
 headache sufferers say their
 headaches started before age 10, and 50% report their headaches started before age 20. How Common Are Headaches in Children and Adolescents? Headaches are very common in children and adolescents. In one study, 56% of boys and 74% of girls between the ages of 12 and 17 reported having had a
 headache within the past month. By age 15, 5% of all children and adolescents have had migraines and 15% have had tension headaches. Many parents worry that their child&amp;#39;s
 headache is the sign of a
 brain tumor or serious medical condition, but most headaches in children and adolescents are not the result of a serious illness. What Types of Headaches Do Children and Adolescents Get? Children get the same types of headaches adults do, including: tension headaches, migraines, and sinus headaches. What Causes Headaches in Children and Adolescents? Children get headaches for many of the same reasons adults get headaches. But, most headaches in children are usually due to an illness, infection,
 cold , or
 fever . Other conditions that can cause headaches include
 sinusitis (inflammation of the sinuses),
 pharyngitis (inflammation or infection of the throat), or
 otitis (
 ear infection ). The exact causes of migraines are unknown, although they are related to changes in the brain as well as to genetic causes. For many years, scientists believed that migraines were linked to the expanding (dilation) and constriction (narrowing) of blood vessels on the brain&amp;#39;s surface. However, it is now believed that migraines are caused by inherited abnormalities in certain areas of the brain. Most children and adolescents (90%) who have migraines have other family members with migraines. When both parents have a history of migraines, there is a 70% chance that the child will also develop migraines. If only one parent has a history of migraines, the risk drops to 25%-50%. Children and adolescents with migraines may also inherit the tendency to be affected by certain
 migraine triggers , such as
 fatigue , bright lights, and changes in weather. Some
 migraine triggers can be identified such as
 stress ,
 anxiety ,
 depression , a change in routine or
 sleep pattern, bright light, loud noises, or certain foods, food additives, and
 beverages . Too much physical activity or too much sun can trigger a
 migraine in some children or adolescents as well. Common causes of tension headaches include striving for academic excellence as well as emotional
 stress related to family, school, or friends. Other causes of tension headaches include eyestrain and neck or back strain due to poor posture.
 Depression may also be a reason your child is having headaches. When tension headaches worsen over time and occur along with other neurological symptoms such as loss of vision, speech problems, or muscle
 weakness , they can be the sign of a more serious problem, such as: Hydrocephalus (abnormal build-up of fluid in the brain) Infection of the brain including:
 Meningitis (an infection or inflammation of the membrane that covers the brain and spinal cord) Encephalitis (inflammation of the brain) Abscess Hemorrhage (bleeding within the brain) Tumor Blood clots Head
 trauma If you suspect any of the above listed conditions, immediately take your child to his or her doctor for evaluation.
 How Are Headaches Evaluated and Diagnosed in Children and Adolescents? The good news for pediatric and adolescent
 headache sufferers is that once a correct headache diagnosis is made, an effective treatment plan can be started. If your child has headache symptoms, the first step is to take your child to his or her doctor. The doctor will perform a complete physical exam and a headache evaluation. During the headache evaluation, your child&amp;#39;s headache history and description of the headaches will be evaluated. You and your child will be asked to describe the headache symptoms and characteristics as completely as possible. A headache evaluation may include a
 CT scan or
 MRI if a structural disorder of the central nervous system is suspected. Both of these tests produce cross-sectional images of the brain that can reveal abnormal areas or problems. If your child&amp;#39;s headache symptoms become worse or become more frequent despite treatment, ask your child&amp;#39;s doctor for a referral to a specialist. Children should be referred to a pediatric neurologist, and adolescents should be referred to a headache specialist. Your child&amp;#39;s doctor should be able to provide the names of headache specialists. How Are Headaches Treated in Children and Adolescents? The good news for pediatric and adolescent headache sufferers is that once a correct headache diagnosis is made, an effective treatment plan can be started. If your child has headache symptoms, the first step is to take your child to his or her doctor. The doctor will perform a complete physical exam and a headache evaluation. During the headache evaluation, your child&amp;#39;s headache history and description of the headaches will be evaluated. You and your child will be asked to describe the headache symptoms and characteristics as completely as possible. A headache evaluation may include a CT scan or MRI if a structural disorder of the central nervous system is suspected. Both of these tests produce cross-sectional images of the brain that can reveal abnormal areas or problems. If your child&amp;#39;s headache symptoms become worse or become more frequent despite treatment, ask your child&amp;#39;s doctor for a referral to a specialist. Children should be referred to a pediatric neurologist, and adolescents should be referred to a headache specialist. Your child&amp;#39;s doctor should be able to provide the names of headache specialists. The proper treatment will depend on several factors, including the type and frequency of the headache, its cause and the age of the child. Treatment may include education,
 stress management , biofeedback and medications. Headache education includes identifying and recording what triggers your child&amp;#39;s headache, such as lack of
 sleep , not eating at regular times, eating certain foods or additives,
 caffeine , environment, or stress. Helping your child keep a headache diary can help you and your child record this information. Avoiding
 headache triggers is an important step in successfully treating the headaches. Stress management: To successfully treat tension headaches, it is important for kids and their parents to identify what causes or triggers the headaches. Then they can learn ways to cope or remove the stressful activities or events. Biofeedback: Biofeedback equipment includes sensors connected to the body to monitor your child&amp;#39;s involuntary physical responses to headaches, such as
 breathing , pulse, heart rate, temperature, muscle tension, and brain activity. By learning to recognize these physical reactions and how the body responds in stressful situations, biofeedback can help your child learn how to release and control tension that causes headaches. Medications: There are three categories of headache medications for children, including symptomatic relief and abortive and preventive medications. Many of the
 drugs used to treat adult headaches are used in smaller doses to treat headaches in children and adolescents. But, aspirinshould not be used to treat headaches in children under age 15.
 Aspirin can cause Reye&amp;#39;s syndrome, a rare, but fatal condition, young kids can get.
 What Happens After My Child Starts Headache Treatment? Do Children Outgrow Headaches? Headaches may improve as your child gets older. The headaches may disappear and then return later in life. By junior high school, many boys who have migraines outgrow them, but in girls, migraine frequency increases with age because of hormone changes. Migraines are three times more likely to occur in adolescent girls than in boys. WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>