<file1>
<first>Heart Failure

ABOUT: The definition of heart failure is when the heart cannot pump efficiently enough for blood to circulate oxygen-rich blood throughout the body. When the heart becomes weak or when it becomes thickened and stiff, the heart muscle cannot keep up with its workload. Signs and symptoms of heart failure include
 shortness of breath , fatigue , lightheadedness , exercise intolerance, coughing (or
 chronic cough ), wheezing , pounding or racing heart, excessive
 tiredness , loss of appetite , nausea , confusion , problems thinking, swelling in the ankles, and rarely,
 chest pain Symptoms are usually worse at night when lying flat. Risk factors for heart failure include
 high blood pressure , prior
 heart attack ,
 obesity ,
 smoking ,
 alcohol abuse , vitamin deficiencies,
 sleep apnea , heavy metal toxicity, eating an unhealthy
 diet (including animal fat and salt), and being sedentary. The cause of heart failure is a weakened or thickened cardiac muscle. When risk factors for heart failure are present, there usually is inflammatory stress, which further damages the cardiac muscle, depleting cells of energy and antioxidants. There are four stages of heart failure, used to classify the severity of symptoms. Heart failure treatment includes lifestyle and
 diet changes, taking medications, and sometimes implanting devices.
 Heart transplant may be needed in some cases. Medications can help reduce the symptoms of
 congestive heart failure (CHF) and improve heart muscle function. Commonly prescribed medications for heart failure include beta-blockers, diuretics (water pills), ACE (angiotensin converting enzyme) inhibitors, and
 ARBs (angiotensin receptor blockers). The prognosis for heart failure is highly variable. If lifestyle changes are not made, or medications are not taken, or the underlying causes are not correctable, heart failure can become a progressive and ultimately fatal condition. Heart failure can be prevented and reversed by making healthier choices such as addressing
 stress , being active, eating well, getting enough nutrients, treating
 sleep apnea , and taking medications as prescribed.
 What is heart failure? The term heart failure can be frightening, but in reality, it just means that 
the heart is not pumping as well as it could be. When the heart muscle is weak, 
blood cannot be pumped efficiently enough to get oxygen to all of the cells. 
Sometimes the heart becomes dilated and weak. Other times it may be stiff and 
thickened. Over time, the heart cannot keep up with its workload. When this 
happens, there isn't enough oxygenated blood reaching the brain and muscles, and 
fluid begins to backup in the
 lungs and other tissues. The lack of oxygen 
causes the main symptoms of heart failure such as
 fatigue , shortness of breath, 
and difficulty completing tasks that require exertion. What are the different types of heart failure? The heart has four chambers through which blood pumps. Newly oxygenated blood is pumped from the lungs to the
 left atrium and
 left ventricle and out through the
 aorta to circulate through the rest of the body. After the oxygen has been used, the blood returns through the veins to the
 right atrium and right ventricle into the lungs to be re-oxygenated. Systolic heart failure (left-sided heart failure): When the heart loses strength on the left side (left ventricle) and cannot pump the blood into circulation, it is called systolic heart failure or left-sided heart failure. When this occurs, the heart becomes dilated and weak. The strength of the heart muscle can be measured with an
 echocardiogram that measures the ejection fraction. An ejection fraction of 70% is normal. The term congestive heart failure, or CHF, refers to the accumulation of fluid in the tissues. Fluid can accumulate in the legs causing swelling (
 edema ), into the lungs causing
 pulmonary edema , or into the abdomen where it is called
 ascites . A type of heart failure termed
 acute decompensated heart failure is an emergency . Diastolic heart failure (right-sided heart failure): The second type of heart failure is diastolic heart failure, characterized by the bottom chambers of the heart becoming thicker and stiffer. When this happens, the left ventricle cannot fill with sufficient blood, and not enough blood is pumped into circulation, even if the pumping action is still strong. This is why diastolic heart failure is sometimes referred to as heart failure with preserved ejection fraction (PEF), or right-sided heart failure. If the signs and symptoms of heart failure are present and the ejection fractions is greater than 50%, diastolic heart failure may be considered, especially if an echocardiogram shows the heart muscle is thickening.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of heart failure include: Symptoms are usually worse at night when lying flat. Symptoms are very 
similar for systolic and diastolic heart failure. Your doctor may need further 
testing to see which type you have. 
RISKS:  The most common risk factors for heart failure include: Coronary 
 artery disease Previous heart attack Heart valve problems Cardiomyopathy Other major risk factors include: High blood pressure Genetics (
 congenital heart defects ) Infections (especially viral 
infections) Obesity Less well recognized risk factors of heart failure include: Sleep apnea Nutrient deficiencies An unhealthy diet (low in antioxidant vegetables and high in animal
 fats ) Stress Lack of exercise All of these also contribute to coronary artery 
disease, which is a major risk factor for heart failure.
 
CAUSES:  The cause of heart failure is a weakened or thickened cardiac muscle. For 
example, in chronic
 high blood pressure (hypertension), the heart must pump 
extra forcefully against the additional
 blood pressure . First it becomes 
enlarged and thickened. But over time, the heart weakens, scarring (fibrosis) 
develops, and it becomes less efficient at pumping. It can become larger 
(dilated) and weak or thickened and stiff. When the risk factors for heart 
failure are present, there usually is inflammatory stress, which further damages 
the cardiac muscle depleting cells of energy and antioxidants. What are heart failure stages or classifications? While doctors define heart failure in stages or classifications, it 
represents a progression of heart muscle weakness. Sometimes people refer to 
this process as chronic heart failure but technically that term isn't correct. The New York Heart Association (NYHA) puts the stages of heart failure into 
four classifications: Class I: no limitations in activity. 
Normal activities can be performed. Class II: mild limitations and mild 
symptoms with activity; no symptoms at rest Class III: noticeable limitations in 
activity; only comfortable at rest Class IV: symptoms occur at any level 
of activity and uncomfortable even resting The American Heart Association along with the American College of Cardiology 
grades heart failure in four stages, and takes into account that heart failure 
can be present even before symptoms appear: Stage A: No heart failure, but at high 
risk due to another medical condition that can lead to heart failure, such as 
high blood pressure,
 diabetes , obesity, or
 coronary artery disease . Stage B: The heart has been damaged by 
 the patient&amp;#39;s other medical condition(s) or other factors, but no symptoms 
 are present yet. Stage C : The heart is damaged and the patient is experiencing heart failure symptoms. Stage D: The patient has severe heart failure 
that requires specialized care, despite receiving treatment (end-stage). 
DIAGNOSIS:  Heart failure can be diagnosed by physical exam, reported symptoms, or chest 
X-ray. An echocardiogram test can identify a low ejection fraction or a 
thickened, stiff heart muscle. Echocardiograms may be used to distinguish 
between systolic and diastolic types of heart failure. Blood tests such as BNP 
(beta naturetic peptide) suggest heart failure. Algorithms and guidelines exist 
to score and weigh signs and symptoms to help make the diagnosis.
 
TREATMENT:  Heart failure treatment options include making healthier decisions about 
lifestyle and diet, taking medications, and sometimes implanting devices. Heart 
transplant is sometimes considered for certain individuals. In acute or decompensated heart failure, the person may need hospitalization or even 
intravenous medications to help recover. What diet and lifestyle management techniques help heart failure? Many lifestyle and diet factors can improve, or even reverse, congestive heart failure. Cardiac rehabilitation programs can teach people how to make lifestyle changes, as can integrative cardiology clinics. Some of the lifestyle factors that make a difference include: Manage stress by doing mind-body practices such as
 Tai Chi ,
 yoga , Qi Gong, and meditation Quit smoking or using tobacco Eliminate alcohol Eat a healthy Mediterranean, vegetarian, or vegan diet Be physically active and become stronger Get enough restful sleep Manage and treat sleep apnea Take
 dietary supplements including CoQ10, L-carnitine, Crataegus (hawthorne), magnesium, and
 fish oil Avoiding salt and excess fluids Talk to your doctor before taking any herbs or
 supplements .
 
TREATMENT:  Medications help reduce the symptoms of congestive heart failure (CHF) and 
can actually improve heart muscle function. There are several main classes of 
medications that are used for treating a weak heart muscle. Your physician will 
choose medications based on your symptoms and whether your heart needs to be 
strengthened or relaxed. The types of medications commonly prescribed for heart 
failure include: Beta-blockers: carvedilol (
 Coreg ),
 bisoprolol (
 Zebeta ),
 metoprolol (
 Lopressor , Toprol), nebivolol (Bystolic),
 acebutolol (
 Sectral ),
 atenolol (
 Tenormin ),
 betaxolol (Kerlone), carteolol 
(Cartrol), esmolol (Brevibloc), penbutolol (Levatol),
 nadolol (Corgard), 
pindolol (Visken),
 propranolol (
 Inderal , InnoPran),
 timolol (
 Blocadren ),
 labetalol (
 Trandate ,
 Normodyne ) Diuretics (water pills):
 Thiazide diuretics :
 hydrochlorothiazide (
 Microzide ,
 Hydrodiuril ), chlorothiazide (Diuril),
 metolazone (Mykrox,
 Zaroxolyn , Diulo), 
methyclothiazide (Enduron),
 indapamide (Lozol), chlorothalidone (Hygrotron) Loop diuretics: furosemide (
 Lasix ),
 bumetanide (Bumex), 
torasemide (
 Demadex ), ethacrynate (
 Edecrin ) Potassium sparing diuretics: spironolactone (
 Aldactone ),
 triamterene (
 Dyrenium ),
 eplerenone (
 Inspra ),
 amiloride hydrochloride ACE (angiotensin converting enzyme) 
inhibitors: lisinopril (
 Prinivil ,
 Zestril ),
 benazepril (
 Lotensin ), and
 captopril (
 Capoten ),
 enalapril /enalaprilat (
 Vasotec oral and injectable), fosinopril 
(
 Monopril ),
 moexipril (
 Univasc ),
 perindopril (
 Aceon ),
 quinapril (
 Accupril ),
 ramipril (
 Altace ),
 trandolapril (
 Mavik ) ARBs (angiotensin receptor blockers): candesartan (
 Atacand ),
 irbesartan (
 Avapro ), olmesartan (Benicar),
 losartan (
 Cozaar ),
 valsartan (
 Diovan ),
 telmisartan (
 Micardis ), eprosartan (Teveten)
 
TREATMENT:  In severe heart failure, devices can help the heart pump better. Left 
Ventricular Assist Devices (
 LVAD ) are implanted mechanical pumps that are most 
commonly used when people are waiting for heart transplants. When medications and lifestyle haven't stopped the progression of heart 
failure, surgical transplantation of a donor heart can be lifesaving. Other 
surgical procedures can sometimes be performed earlier to address the risk factors 
and causes of
 heart disease such as
 coronary artery bypass , percutaneous 
coronary intervention, or
 angioplasty to open the blockages of coronary atherosclerosis. Which specialties of doctors treat heart failure? You may initially see your primary care provider (PCP) such as a family 
practitioner or internist, and in a sudden or severe situation you may be seen 
by an
 emergency medicine specialist in a hospital's emergency department. You will be referred to a cardiologist, a specialist in disorders of the 
heart. You also may see some sub-specialties of cardiology, including a cardiac electrophysiologist, who specializes in electrical and heart rhythm problems, or 
a cardiothoracic surgeon if surgery is needed. 
COMPLCATIONS:  The complications of heart failure include severe fatigue and weakness, 
inability to complete activities of daily living, kidney damage, and progressive 
heart failure that could ultimately require heart transplant.
 What is the prognosis and life expectancy for a person with heart failure? The course of heart failure is highly variable. People who address their risk 
factors and make lifestyle changes may never progress. However, if changes are 
not made, if medications are not taken, or if the underlying causes are not 
correctable, heart failure can become a progressive and eventually fatal 
condition. This means that the heart muscle will continue to get weaker and have 
more difficulty keeping up with the workload. Fortunately, many 
treatment options exist for heart failure. 
PREVENTION:  The best way to prevent heart failure is to never have a heart attack, but if you do, there still are treatments. The Lyon Heart study demonstrated that a
 Mediterranean diet can prevent heart failure among people who have had a heart attack. Following other healthy lifestyle recommendations such as not
 smoking , not abusing alcohol, eating a plant-based diet, eating a diet that is antioxidant rich, eating an anti-inflammatory diet such as a Mediterranean diet, and being physically active every day may also help prevent heart failure. Treating early signs of heart failure and risk factors such as high blood pressure, being overweight or obese, and hardening of the arteries (atherosclerosis) are also strategies to prevent congestive heart failure.  Stress raises blood pressure, worsens
 diabetes , and causes coronary artery disease. Learning stress resiliency techniques such as Transcendental Meditation, Yoga, or meditation can reduce the risk of many types of cardiovascular disease.
</first>
</file1>