<file1>
<first>Heart Disease: Dilated Cardiomyopathy
What Is Dilated Cardiomyopathy? Dilated
 cardiomyopathy (DCM) is a condition in which the heart&amp;#39;s ability to pump blood is decreased because the heart&amp;#39;s main pumping chamber, the
 left ventricle , is enlarged and weakened. In some cases, it prevents the heart from relaxing and filling with blood as it should. Over time, it can affect the other heart chambers. What Are the
Symptomsof DCM? Many people with dilated cardiomyopathy have no symptoms or only minor symptoms, and live a normal life. Other people develop symptoms, which may progress and worsen as heart function worsens. Symptoms of DCM can occur at any age and may include: Heart failure symptoms (
 shortness of breath and
 fatigue ). Swelling of the lower extremities. Fatigue (feeling overly tired). Weight gain . Fainting (caused by conditions such as irregular heart rhythms, abnormal responses of the blood vessels during
 exercise , or no cause may be found). Palpitations (fluttering in the chest due to
 abnormal heart rhythms ). Dizziness or
 lightheadedness . Blood clots can form in the dilated left ventricle as a result of pooling of the blood. If a
 blood clot breaks off, it can lodge in an artery and disrupt blood flow to the brain, causing
 stroke . A clot can also block blood flow to the organs in the abdomen or legs. Chest pain or pressure. Sudden death.
 What Causes DCM? DCM can be inherited, but it is primarily caused by a variety of other factors, including: Severe
 coronary artery disease Alcoholism Thyroid disease Diabetes Viral infections of the heart Heart valve abnormalities Drugs that are toxic (or cause damage) to the heart It can also occur in women after childbirth (postpartum cardiomyopathy). How Is DCM Diagnosed? DCM is diagnosed based on medical history (your symptoms and family history), physical exam, blood tests,
 electrocardiogram (
 ECG or
 EKG ),
 chest X-ray ,
 echocardiogram ,
 exercise stress test ,
 cardiac catheterization ,
 CT scan , and
 MRI . Another test rarely done to determine the cause of a cardiomyopathy is a
 myocardial biopsy , or heart biopsy, where a tissue sample is taken from the heart and examined under a microsope to determine the cause of the symptoms. If you have a relative with dilated cardiomyopathy, ask your doctor if you should be screened for the condition. Genetic testing may also be available to identify abnormal genes.
 What Is the Treatment for DCM? Treatment of dilated cardiomyopathy is aimed at decreasing the heart size and the substances in the bloodstream that enlarge the heart and ultimately lead to worsened symptoms: Medications: To manage heart failure, most people improve by taking drugs, such as a beta-blocker, ACE inhibitor an ARB, and/or diuretics. If you have an
 arrhythmia (irregular heart beat), your doctor may give you a medication to control your heart rate or lessen the occurrence of arrhythmias. Blood thinners may be used to prevent blood clots from occurring. Lifestyle changes: If you have heart failure, sodium should be restricted to 2,000-3,000 mg per day -- for the rest of your life. Your doctor may recommend
 aerobic exercise , but don&amp;#39;t do heavy
 weight lifting . What Surgeries Are Used to Treat DCM? People with severe DCM may need one of the following surgeries: Cardiac resynchronization by biventricular pacemaker. For some people with DCM, stimulating both the right and left ventricles with this
 pacemaker improves the heart&amp;#39;s ability to contract with more force, thereby improving symptoms and increasing the length of time you can
 exercise . This pacemaker also will help people with
 heart block or some bradycardias (slow heart rates). Implantable cardioverter defibrillators (ICD). ICDs are suggested for people at risk for life-threatening arrhythmias or sudden cardiac death. The ICD constantly monitors the heart rhythm. When it detects a very fast, abnormal heart rhythm, it &amp;#39;&amp;#39;shocks&amp;#39;&amp;#39; the
 heart muscle into returning to a normal rhythm. Surgery. Conventional surgeries for
 coronary artery disease or valvular disease may be recommended. Some people may be eligible for surgical repair of the left ventricle or placement of a cardiac assist device. Heart transplant WebMD Medical Reference</first>
</file1>