<file1>
<first>Heat Stroke Symptoms, Signs, First Aid, and Recovery

ABOUT: Heat
 stroke is a form of hyperthermia in which the body temperature is elevated dramatically. Heat
 stroke is a medical emergency and can be fatal if not promptly and properly treated. The cause of heat
 stroke is an elevation in body temperature, often accompanied by
 dehydration . Symptoms of heat
 stroke can include
 confusion , agitation, disorientation, the absence of
 sweating , and coma . Heat stroke is diagnosed by observation of the symptoms and signs in a person exposed to extreme temperatures. Heat stroke is treated by cooling the victim is a critical step in the treatment of heat stroke.
 Always notify emergency services immediately if heat stroke is suspected. The most important measures to prevent heat
 strokes are to avoid becoming dehydrated and to avoid vigorous physical activities in hot and humid weather. Infants, the elderly, athletes, and outdoor workers are the groups at greatest risk for heat stroke. Leaving infants, children, or animals in cars poses a risk for heat stroke. Even in moderate weather, the temperature inside a closed car can reach dangerous levels.
 What is heat stroke? 
RISKS:  Heat stroke is a form of hyperthermia or
 heat-related illness , an abnormally elevated body temperature with accompanying physical symptoms including changes in the nervous system function. Unlike
 heat cramps and
 heat exhaustion , two other forms of hyperthermia that are less severe,
 heat stroke is a true medical emergency that is often fatal if not properly and promptly treated. Heat stroke is also sometimes referred to as heatstroke or sun stroke. Severe hyperthermia is defined as a body temperature of 104 F (40 C) or higher. The body normally generates heat as a result of metabolism, and is usually able to dissipate the heat by
 radiation of heat through the skin or by evaporation of sweat. However, in extreme heat, high humidity, or vigorous physical exertion under the sun, the body may not be able to sufficiently dissipate the heat and the body temperature rises, sometimes up to 106 F (41.1 C) or higher. Another cause of heat stroke is
 dehydration . A dehydrated person may not be able to sweat fast enough to dissipate heat, which causes the body temperature to rise. Heat stroke is not the same as a stroke. "Stroke" is the general term used to describe decreased oxygen flow to an area of the brain. Those most susceptible (at risk) individuals to heat stroke include: Infants The elderly (often with associated heart diseases, lung diseases, kidney diseases, or who are taking medications that make them vulnerable to dehydration and heat strokes) Athletes Individuals who work outside and physically exert themselves under the sun Infants, children, or pets left in cars. Heat stroke is sometimes classified as exertional heat stroke (EHS, which is due to overexertion in hot weather) or non-exertional heat stroke (NEHS, which occurs in climactic extremes and affects the elderly, infants, and chronically ill.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Symptoms of heat stroke can sometimes mimic those of
 heart attack or other conditions. Sometimes a person experiences symptoms of heat exhaustion before progressing to heat strokes. Signs and symptoms of heat exhaustion include However, some individuals can develop symptoms of heat stroke suddenly and rapidly without warning. Different people may have different symptoms and signs of heatstroke.
 Common symptoms and signs of heat stroke include: Can infants, children, and teens suffer from heat stroke? While the elderly are at greatest risk for heat stroke, infants and children are also at risk. In particular, infants or young children who are unattended in locked a car may suffer heat-related illness quickly, since the indoor temperature of a locked car can rise to dangerous levels even in moderate weather. Rarely, infants have died of heat stroke when overly bundled in their cribs. It is critically important that parents understand the medical dangers inherent in leaving children unattended in cars in addition to the obvious safety risks. Further, cars should always be kept locked when not in use so that children may not enter them and become trapped. Among older children and
 teens , heat stroke or heat-related illness is a risk for athletes who train in hot environmental conditions. Among reported heat-related illnesses in U.S. high school athletes, the majority of cases occur in football players during the month of August.
 4 First aid treatments for heat stroke Victims of heat stroke must receive immediate treatment to avoid permanent organ damage. First and foremost, cool the victim. 
PREVENTION:  The most important measures to prevent heat strokes are to avoid becoming dehydrated and to avoid vigorous physical activities in hot and humid weather. If you have to perform physical activities in hot weather, drink plenty of fluids (such as water and sports
 drinks ), but avoid alcohol, and
 caffeine (including soft drinks and tea), which may lead to dehydration. Your body will need replenishment of
 electrolytes (such as sodium) as well as fluids if you sweat excessively or perform vigorous activity in the sunlight for prolonged periods. Take frequent breaks to hydrate yourself. Wear hats and light-colored, lightweight, loose clothes. Keep cars locked when not in use and never, ever, leave infants, children or pets unattended in a locked car.
</first>
</file1>