<file1>
<first>Hepatic Hemangioma
What is a hepatic hemangioma? Hepatic hemangiomas are thought to be present in as many as 7% of 
healthy people.  Hemangiomas are four to six times more common in 
women than in men. Female hormones may promote the formation and growth of hemangiomas.  Hemangiomas, although referred to as tumors,
are not
 malignant and do not become cancerous.  Hemangiomas are not 
unique to the
 liver and can occur almost anywhere in the body. 
SYMPTOMS:  Hemangiomas usually are small, measuring only a quarter inch in diameter, but they can be several inches in diameter or even larger. The vast majority of hemangiomas of the liver never cause
symptoms or health problems.   Most hepatic hemangiomas are discovered
incidentally at the time of testing for unrelated medical problems, 
most commonly with
 ultrasound imaging or CT (
 computerized tomography )
scanning of the abdomen.  Very large hemangiomas can cause symptoms, especially 
if they are
positioned near other organs.
 Pain ,
 nausea , or 
enlargement of the
liver can occur.  Rarely, larger hemangiomas can rupture, causing 
severe
 pain and bleeding into the abdomen that may be severe or even 
life threatening. 
DIAGNOSIS:  When a
 hemangioma is suspected, the challenge for
the health care professional, is to be sure that it is in fact a hemangioma and not 
another type of
 tumor , particularly a malignant one. With specialized 
tests,
however, doctors can  reassure patients that the tumor is with little 
doubt a hemangioma.  Such special testing may include scintigraphy 
(using a tiny amount of a
radioactive substance to identify the hemangioma), CT scanning, or
 MRI (
 magnetic resonance imaging ).  In general, a biopsy of 
suspected hemangiomas is avoided because of their benign nature and 
the potential
risk of bleeding from the biopsy. 
TREATMENT:  The vast majority of hepatic
hemangiomas require no treatment.  If a hepatic hemangioma is
large, especially if it is causing symptoms, surgical removal is an 
option.
</first>
</file1>