<file1>
<first>Hemolytic Uremic Syndrome (HUS)
Hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) facts Hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) is a condition characterized by destruction 
of
 red blood cells ,
 low platelet count , and
 kidney failure . There are two types of HUS. Typical HUS follows a diarrheal infection often caused by
 E. coli OH157:H7. Atypical HUS is not associated with an infection of the digestive tract and has a less favorable outcome. Symptoms of HUS include
 vomiting and
 diarrhea (often bloody),
 weakness , lethargy, 
and bruising (purpura). These symptoms are due to a combination of
 dehydration ,
 anemia (due to the 
 destruction of red blood cells and low platelet counts), and uremia (the inability of the kidneys to clear waste products from the 
body). Diagnosis of HUS is made by a combination of history, physical exam, and abnormal 
blood tests. There is no one test that makes the diagnosis of hemolytic uremic 
 syndrome. Treatment of HUS is supportive with intravenous fluids.
 Anemia may require blood 
transfusion and temporary
 dialysis may be necessary 
 to help treat kidney failure. What is a "syndrome?" In medicine, a syndrome is defined as a collection of symptoms (patient 
complaints), signs (findings on physical examination), and laboratory or imaging 
findings that tend to group together and be associated with a specific disease 
or illness.
 What is hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS)? Hemolytic uremic syndrome (HUS) is a disease of two body systems, the blood 
stream and the kidney.
 Hemolysis describes the destruction of red blood cells. In 
hemolytic uremic syndrome, blood within capillaries, the smallest blood vessels in the body, begins to clot abnormally. When red blood cells pass through the clogged capillaries, they are sheared apart and broken. (hemo=blood +lysis=destruction). The second failed system, kidney failure (uremia), occurs when urea and other waste products build up in the bloodstream because the 
kidneys cannot filter and dispose of them. (urea=a waste chemical + emia= in the blood). HUS is also related to another disease caused by a similar normal clotting process 
within the capillaries called thrombotic 
thrombocytic purpura (TTP). Within the 
medical literature, these two conditions are often considered together. HUS is 
more widely known, however, because it has been discussed in the press because 
of its relationship to a special type of
 E. Coli (
 Escherichia coli ) infection 
associated with
 food poisoning . HUS can be classified as typical or atypical. The typical type is associated 
with gastrointestinal (GI) signs and symptoms including
 vomiting and
 diarrhea . 
Atypical HUS is not associated with GI symptoms. 
CAUSES:  While the cause of HUS has not been established with certainty, researchers 
believe that an abnormal inflammatory reaction is stimulated in the blood stream 
causing platelets (the parts of the blood that form clots) to sludge in small 
blood vessels and form
 blood clots where they are not supposed to. This uses up 
the platelets and causes a shortage of them in the rest of the body. This 
abnormal reaction may be caused by a yet unidentified chemical that is produced 
in blood plasma (the fluid or non-cellular part of the bloodstream). The triggering events for HUS are varied and include: Enterohemorrhagic
 E. Coli is a type of bacteria that causes
 bloody diarrhea .
 E. coli is a very common type of bacteria in the body, and it is only 
the OH157:H7 type that causes the problem. It can be found in undercooked meat 
and other foods; and is one of the causes of food recalls and restaurant-related
 food poisoning outbreaks. This accounts for almost 90% of HUS in children. The 
 2011 outbreak of HUS in Germany was due to a different type of Shigela 
 toxin-producing
 E. coli called 0104:H4. Pregnancy and the early postpartum (after delivery) time period and the use 
of
 birth control pills are the more common associations with HUS. Pneumonia caused by the
 Streptococcus pneumoniae bacteria is another 
possible precipitating factor. HUS is rare complication of this common 
infection. Most often, this
 pneumonia is treated with antibiotics as an 
outpatient. However, it is the cause of 40% of atypical HUS. Medications may be also associated with HUS, including some
 chemotherapy and immunosuppression
 drugs ,
 birth control pills,
 ticlopidine (Ticlid, 
 an anti-platelet drug) and
 quinine (Quinerva, 
 Quinite) an anti-platelet drug. AIDS may be associated with HUS. Only the diarrheal form of HUS is considered to be typical HUS and is usually a disease of infants and children younger than 3 years of age. The others are classified as atypical HUS and also include the familial form of the disease in which a gene mutation affects the blood clotting mechanism.
 
SYMPTOMS:  In typical HUS,
 gastroenteritis occurs with abdominal cramping, 
vomiting and profuse bloody, watery
 diarrhea , 
as a symptom up to a week before the onset of HUS. This may cause significant
 dehydration , weakness and lethargy, as well as 
electrolyte imbalances because of 
the loss of sodium, potassium, and chloride in the 
vomit and diarrhea. These symptoms 
may resolve before the onset of anemia and the kidney failure symptoms of HUS. The anemia and uremia usually present with weakness, lethargy, and 
sleepiness.
 Seizures may occur. Purpura or small areas of bleeding in the skin may be seen because of 
low platelet counts (
 thrombocytopenia ). 
DIAGNOSIS:  The health care professional will have a suspicion of the disease based on the 
history and physical examination, especially in a small child who has had the 
typical bloody diarrhea. Abnormal laboratory tests help confirm the 
diagnosis. These abnormal findings may include: Hemolytic anemia: the red blood cell count is low and a peripheral blood 
smear, in which blood is examined under a microscope, will show that the red 
cells have been damaged and destroyed. This differentiates hemolysis (hemo=blood 
+ lysis=destruction) from anemia caused by decreased production of blood cells 
in the bone marrow. Thrombocytopenia: a low
 platelet count Uremia: Kidney function can be measured by testing the level of 
 waste products in the blood normally filtered by the kidney. BUN (blood urea 
 nitrogen) and creatinine are measures of this kidney function. When levels 
 rise, it is an indication of kidney failure or uremia in which the kidneys 
 cannot clear the waste products of
 metabolism from the body. Abnormal urine findings: Blood and protein may be found in the urine when 
normally they are not present. Stool cultures: Since
 E. coli O157:O7 is the most common 
 cause of HUS in children; attempts are made to culture the bacteria from 
 stool samples. 
 The body usually clears the bacteria from the stool within a week, so a 
 negative test does not exclude the disease. A positive test helps confirm 
 HUS and will be reported to public health authorities to try to determine 
 the source of the infection. In 2011, outbreaks in Europe were traced by 
 public health authorities to tainted sprouts. In atypical HUS, history is very important to search for other potential 
causes of the disease. Unfortunately, the case may not be found in up to half of 
cases of atypical HUS. One of the distinguishing findings between HUS and TTP is a normal neurologic 
examination. The brain function is normal in HUS.
 
TREATMENT:  Typical HUS in children tends to be self-limiting, and supportive care is often all 
that is needed. This may include intravenous fluids for rehydration and 
rebalancing of
 electrolytes like sodium and potassium, which can be lost with 
the diarrhea. Blood transfusions are only used for the most severe cases of anemia in which 
the
 hemoglobin falls below 6 or 7 g/dL (depending on age, the normal value is 
11-16). Kidney failure 
may be managed expectantly (by observation and supportive 
care), and dialysis is not often required. Adults with atypical HUS tend to become more ill and need more aggressive therapy than 
children with the condition. In addition to the supportive care discussed above, 
plasmapheresis or plasma exchange may be required. Since it is thought there is 
an abnormal chemical in the plasma stimulating the abnormal clot formation, 
removing the plasma and replacing it with donor plasma is helpful in treating 
adult HUS. Dialysis may be needed while awaiting recovery of the kidneys from 
the illness. Eculizumab (Soliris) has been approved by the FDA for the treatment of atypical HUS. It is a monoclonal antibody that decreases the blood clotting in the capillary blood vessels, decreasing the potential destruction of cells. This type of therapy decreases the body&amp;#39;s immune capabilities, and the risk of infection increases. What is the prognosis of hemolytic uremic syndrome? Typical HUS in children tends to be self-limiting, and full recovery is most 
likely. Adults do less well. Without aggressive therapy like plasmapheresis and 
dialysis, up to 25% of those affected with atypical HUS may die in the acute 
phase of the disease, and 50% may have developed long-term kidney impairment. Patients with HUS not related to a diarrheal illness have a worse prognosis 
than those whose illness is due to gastrointestinal infection. In those patients with genetically caused HUS, relapsing illness is common as 
are kidney failure requiring dialysis and death.
 
PREVENTION:  Most cases of typical HUS associated with diarrhea can be prevented by thorough washing 
and cooking of 
food products. The vast majority of cases of typical HUS are caused by poor food 
handling from the farmer to the wholesaler and grocer. Proper washing and 
cooking techniques in the kitchen is the key to
 prevention . Unfortunately, there is no way to prevent atypical HUS.
</first>
</file1>