<file1>
<first>Intussusception

ABOUT: Intussusception is the infolding (telescoping) of one segment of the 
intestine within another. Intussusception usually results in a blockage of the intestine. Intussusception occurs primarily in infants (boys more often than girls) 
but can also occur in adults and older children. The primary symptoms of intussusception include
 abdominal pain and
 vomiting . Early diagnosis and treatment of intussusception are essential to save the 
intestine and the patient. What is intussusception? Intussusception is the telescoping of one segment of intestine into another 
adjacent distal ("downstream") segment of the intestine. (The term 
"intussusception" is pronounced "in-tuh-suh-sep-shun" with the accent on the 
"in." It comes from the Latin "intus", within + "suscipere", to receive = to 
receive within). Common mispellings of intussusception include: intususception, intussuseption, intersusception. Intussusception is the most common cause of intestinal obstruction in 
children between 3 months and five years of age. It is extremely rare in children 
under 3 months of age or in older children and adults. What happens during intussusception? During intussusception, a segment of bowel (intussusceptum) telescopes into a more distal segment (intussuscipiens), and drags the associated mesentery, vessels, and nerves with it. This results in compression of the veins, followed by swelling of the region leading to obstruction and a subsequent decrease in blood flow to the affected part of the intestine. Most cases affect the ileocolic region of the intestine (where the small intestine meets the
 large intestine ). The compression of blood vessels in the involved intestine reduces the supply of blood to the affected intestine. If the blood supply is greatly reduced, the involved intestine may swell, causing an obstruction, or even die (become gangrenous) and bleed. It also may rupture and lead to abdominal infection and
 shock .
 Is intussusception an urgent problem? Intussusception is an emergency and requires immediate attention. 
RISKS:  Most cases of intussusception occur in children between 5 months and 1 year 
of age. Boys develop the condition two times more often than girls. 
Intussusception can also occur in adults and older children, although it is 
uncommon. 
CAUSES:  The causes of intussusception are not fully known. Most cases in young 
children are idiopathic, (meaning the cause is unknown), although some 
viral and
 bacterial infections of the intestine may possibly contribute to intussusception 
in infancy. Intussusception is very rare in older children and adults. In this 
population, the causes are believed to be due to 
polyps or tumors, which are 
often referred to as the "lead point" of the intussusception. 
DIAGNOSIS:  Early diagnosis and treatment of intussusception is 
essential in order to prevent injury to the intestine and the associated sequelae, including 
surgical removal of the bowel,
 sepsis , and even death.
 
SYMPTOMS:  Most describe the symptoms of intussusception as a triad of colicky
 abdominal pain , bilious
 vomiting , and "currant jelly" stool. The primary symptom of intussusception is described as intermittent crampy
 abdominal pain . This is often called "colicky
 pain ." Intussusception in an infant usually starts with the infant suddenly crying very loudly, as if in great
 pain . The infant intermittently draws the knees up to the chest while crying. This reaction is caused by the abdominal pain which recurs frequently and increases in intensity and duration. These intermittent painful episodes are believed to be caused by the telescoping of the bowel and resultant compression of blood vessels and nerves. In addition to the abdominal pain, most children will also have episodes of vomiting associated with the pain. This vomiting is usually not associated with eating and may be bilious (yellow-green colored) Some affected individuals who do not seek early medical attention may pass "currant jelly stool". This is stool that is bloody and mucousy and may be a sign that the affected bowel has lost its blood supply and that the bowel may be necrotic (non-viable). As the condition progresses, the infant becomes may become weaker and develop additional symptoms, including those associated with shock, such as paleness, lethargy, and even
 fever , though these are not an integral part of the associated "triad." Thankfully, most cases are diagnosed early.
 
DIAGNOSIS:  The history of abdominal pain and vomiting as described above, may suggest 
the diagnosis of intussusception. Additionally, the examining doctor may feel 
an abdominal "sausage-shaped" mass (the intussusception itself) or upon 
auscultation with a stethoscope, may hear diminished or absent
 bowel sounds . Lab 
tests are usually not helpful, although plain abdominal X-rays can reveal signs 
of an intestinal obstruction, including air-fluid levels, decreased
 gas , and 
unexplained masses, usually seen in the right lower quadrant of the abdomen.
 Ultrasound and 
CT scans are generally not required to make the diagnosis. A barium, water-soluble contrast or air enema is 
considered both diagnostic and therapeutic in the management of intussusception. 
This radiologic procedure 
involves the introduction of the contrast into the lower intestine. If an 
intussusception is present, it will be seen during the imaging. Often just the 
introduction of the contrast will reduce the telescoped bowel to its normal 
position and shape. In these cases there is a high risk of for 
re-intussusception in the first 24 hours following the enema, though, less 
commonly, recurrence may be seen several days and even months later. Is it necessary to operate when there is intussusception? The treatment of intussusception may or may not require 
surgery. In some cases, the intestinal obstruction can be reversed with an 
enema. The enema carries a risk of intestinal rupture and cannot be done if the 
bowel has already perforated. The procedure also requires the availability of a 
surgeon, in case 
the patient's bowel ruptures or the intussusception cannot be reduced. If the intestinal obstruction cannot be reversed by an enema, surgery 
is necessary to reverse the intussusception and relieve the obstruction. If a 
portion of the intestine has become gangrenous, it must be removed. After 
surgery, intravenous feeding and fluids are continued until normal bowel 
movements resume. Because of the risk of recurrence, patients who are 
successfully reduced by enema usually are admitted for observation during the 
first 24 hours post procedure, and have no ill effects. Recently, research has 
suggested that a select population of the children may be observed for shorter 
periods of time (6 hours) after undergoing reduction of the intussesception by 
enema, but currently, most patients stay the full 24 hours.
 What is the prognosis (outlook) for patients with intussusception? The outlook for intussusception is usually good with early diagnosis and 
treatment. Early detection and treatment are paramount.
</first>
</file1>